<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0056-0047-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GALT, John (9th edition, volume 10, page 47)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1053582">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:912577">Entail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039784">Novelle</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155691">Travelers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pt4b">Novels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n56/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GALT, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1779-1839), a
                    Scottish novelist, was born at Irvine, in Ayrshire, on May 2, 1779. He received
                    his early education at Irvine and Greenock, and read largely from one of the
                    public libraries while serving as a clerk in a mercantile office. His first
                    compositions appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Greenock Advertiser</hi> and the
                        <hi rend="italic">Scots Magazine.</hi> In 1804 he went to settle in London,
                    where he continued to work at a poem on the <hi rend="italic">Battle of
                        Largs,</hi> which was published anonymously. After unsuccessful attempts to
                    succeed in business, Galt left for the Continent, and met Byron and Sir John
                    Hobhouse at Gibraltar, with whom he had a tour in the Mediterranean. He remained
                    abroad for three years, and then returned to London. His early works are the <hi
                        rend="italic">Life and Administration of Wolsey, Voyages and Travels,
                        Letters from the Levant,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Life of Benjamin West,
                        Historical Pictures,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Wandering Jew,</hi> and a
                    volume of dramas; but he first showed his real power in <hi rend="italic">The
                        Ayrshire Legatees,</hi> which appeared in <hi rend="italic">Blackwood’s
                        Magazine</hi> in 1820. This was followed in 1821 by his masterpiece— <hi
                        rend="italic">The Annals of the Parish</hi>; and, at short intervals, <hi
                        rend="italic">Sir Andrew Wylie, The Entail, The Steam-Boat,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">The Provost</hi> were published. These arc all in his happiest
                    manner, and are unsurpassed as studies of Scottish character. His next works
                    were <hi rend="italic">Ringan Gilhaize,</hi> a story of the Covenanters; <hi
                        rend="italic">The Spaewife,</hi> which relates to the times of James I. of
                    Scotland; <hi rend="italic">Rothelan,</hi> a novel founded on the reign of
                    Edward III.; <hi rend="italic">The Omen,</hi> which was favourably criticized by
                    Sir Walter Scott; and <hi rend="italic">The Last of the Lairds,</hi> another
                    picture of Scottish life. In 1826 he visited America for the second time, in
                    connexion with the establishment of the Canada Company—an undertaking which
                    involved him in great difficulties, and ultimately proved disastrous to his
                    worldly prospects. It is pleasant to remember that, although Gait’s connexion
                    with Canada was unfortuate for himself, his youngest son, Sir Alexander Galt,
                    has had a distinguished career there, and was, for some time, finance minister
                    of the colony. In 1827 Galt founded Guelph in Upper Canada, passing on his way
                    the township of Galt on the Grand River, named after him by the Hon. William
                    Dixon. In 1829 he returned to England commercially a ruined man, and devoted
                    himself with great ardour to literary pursuits, of which the first fruit was <hi
                        rend="italic">Lawrie Todd—</hi> one of his best novels. Then came <hi
                        rend="italic">Southennaη,</hi> a tale of Scottish life in the times of Queen
                    Mary. In 1830 he was appointed editor of the <hi rend="italic">Courier</hi>
                    newspaper—a post he soon relinquished. His untiring industry was seen in the
                    publication, in rapid succession, of a <hi rend="italic">Life of Byron, Lives of
                        the Players, Bogle Corbet, Stanley Buxton, The Member, The Radical,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Eben</hi><hi rend="italic">Erskine, The Stolen Child,</hi> his
                        <hi rend="italic">Autobiography,</hi> and a collection of tales entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">Stories of the Study.</hi> In 1834 appeared his <hi
                        rend="italic">Literary Life and Miscellanies,</hi> dedicated by permission
                    to William IV., who sent the author a present of £200. As soon as this work was
                    published Galt retired to Greenock, where he lingered on in bad health till his
                    death on the 11th of April 1839.</p>
                <p>Galt, like almost all voluminous writers, was exceedingly unequal. His
                    masterpieces are <hi rend="italic">The Ayrshire Legatees, The Annals of the
                        Parish, Sir Andrew Wylie, The Entail, The Provost,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Lawrie Todd. The Ayrshire Legatees</hi> gives, in the form of
                    a number of exceedingly diverting letters, the adventures of the Rev. Dr Pringle
                    and his family in London. The letters are made the excuse for endless teaparties
                    and meetings of kirk session in the rural parish of Garnock. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Annals of the Parish</hi> are told by the Rev. Micah
                    Balwhidder, Gait’s finest character. This work is a splendid picture of the
                    old-fashioned Scottish pastor and the life of a country parish; and, in rich
                    humour, genuine pathos, and truth to nature, it is unsurpassed even by Scott.
                    Like his other Scotch novels, it is a fine specimen of the homely graces of the
                    Scottish dialect, and preserves much <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n57/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0057-0048"/> vigorous Doric phraseology fast passing out
                    of use even in country districts. In this novel Mr Galt used, for the first
                    time, the term “Utilitarian,” which has since become so intimately associated
                    with the doctrines of John Stuart Mill and his followers (see <hi rend="italic"
                        >Annals of the Parish,</hi> chap, xxxv., and a note by Air Mill in <hi
                        rend="italic">Utilitarianism,</hi> chap. it). In Aeir <hi rend="italic"
                        >Andrew</hi><hi rend="italic">Wylie</hi> the hero entered London as a poor
                    lad, but achieved remarkable success by his shrewd business qualities. The
                    character is somewhat exaggerated, but excessively amusing. <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Entail</hi> was read thrice by Byron and Scott, and is the best of
                    Gait’s longer novels. Leddy Grippy is a wonderful creation, and was considered
                    by Byron equal to any female character in literature since Shakespeare’s time.
                        <hi rend="italic">The Provost,</hi> in which Provost Pawkie tells his own
                    story, portrays inimitably the jobbery, bickerings, and selfseeking of municipal
                    dignitaries in a quaint Scottish burgh. In <hi rend="italic">Lawrie Todd</hi>
                    Galt, by giving us the Scot in America, has accomplished a feat which Sir Walter
                    never attempted. This novel exhibits more variety of style and a greater love of
                    nature than his other books. The life of a settler is depicted with unerring
                    pencil, and with an enthusiasm and imaginative power much more poetical than any
                    of the author’s professed poems.</p>
                <p>Gait’s humour is broader and more contagious than Scott’s; and his pictures of
                    the sleepy life of old Scottish towns are unrivalled in literature. He is
                    generally called an imitator of Scott; but the <hi rend="italic">Annals of the
                        Parish</hi> existed in MS. before <hi rend="italic">Waverley</hi> was
                    published. As Galt is preeminently an illustrator of west-country Scottish life,
                    his range may be said to be narrower than Scott’s; but within it he is supreme.
                    It would be difficult to overrate the immense services which Galt has rendered
                    alike to the history of the manners and to the history of the language of the
                    Scottish people.</p>
                <p>For further information about Galt, see his <hi rend="italic">Autobiography;
                        The</hi><hi rend="italic">Literary Life of John Galt</hi>; anil a
                    biographical memoir by his friend the late Dr Moir of Musselburgh, prefixed to
                        <hi rend="italic">The Annals of</hi><hi rend="italic">the Parish.</hi> (T.
                    GI.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
