<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0440-0427-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GEORGE IV</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 427</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:933481">Foxes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1093056">Regents</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1085685">Questioning</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j33z">Debt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n440/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GEORGE IV</label>. <hi rend="italic">(foeorge Augustus
                    Frederick,</hi> 1762-1830), lived long enough to strip the crown of the
                    leadership of the nation which his father had won for it. Born on August 12,
                    1762, he was noted in the years of his early manhood for good looks, for ease of
                    carriage, and graciousness of manner. He soon plunged into the whirl of sensual
                    excitement. His life was passed in the grossest profligacy. He was false as well
                    as licentious His word was never to be trusted. Not even an occasional gleam of
                    brightness lights up the dark picture of his career. If he now and then flung to
                    a dependant a kindly word which cost him nothing, no serious project of
                    well-doing ever occupied his thoughts. Politics had no attraction for him except
                    so far as changes of Government might minister to his ease, or bring him money
                    to be squandered in some new scheme of folly.</p>
                <p>Such a character was probably beyond the reach of any education. But it is
                    certain that the education which he received in the strict and formal domestic
                    circle of his parents was only fitted to repel him from the path of virtue. His
                    father became to him the type of uninteresting formality. He gladly sought the
                    society of his father’s Whig opponents, and was initiated by Fox and Sheridan in
                    the vices of the fashionable world. In 1783 he naturally supported the coalition
                    ministry which his father detested, and the coalition ministry in return
                    proposed to raise his income from £50,000 to £100,000. The king saved the
                    ministry from committing one more blunder in its career by refusing to sanction
                    the proposition. In 1786 the prince’s friends urged Pitt to increase the
                    allowance, but Pitt refused to do anything of the kind. All the world knew that
                    the money would be frittered away at the gambling table or in some other equally
                    disreputable way. Applying to the king and getting a distinct refusal, the
                    prince sold, his horses and carriages, shut up his house, and dismissed his
                    servants. As it was well known that these were not the expenses which had
                    brought him to distress, he was only laughed at for his pains. A lower depth was
                    soon reached. The prince fell in love with Mrs Fitzherbert who had been twice a
                    widow at twenty-five. She was ready to marry him, but she would yield to him on
                    no other terms. She was a Roman Catholic, and a marriage by the heir of the
                    crown with a Roman Catholic forfeited his succession by the Act of Settlement.
                    Nor, by the Royal Marriage Act, could he legally contract marriage even with a
                    Protestant without his father’s consent, unless at the end of a year after
                    formal notice had been given, and then only if parliament had not expressed its
                    disapprobation. Believing truly that he could contract no legal marriage with
                    Mrs Fitzherbert, he was quite ready to go through the form of marriage. Mrs
                    Fitzherbert, holding that the performance of the ceremony by a priest of her
                    church was of sacramental efficacy, was indifferent to the legality of the
                    proceeding. The marriage took place. Not long afterwards, in April 1787,
                    Alderman Newenham moved in the House of Commons for a grant in relief of the
                    prince. In the course of debate allusion was made to a marriage which might
                    bring in question the succession. Fox went to the prince, and was assured by him
                    that the marriage had never even formally taken place. Fox, deceived by his
                    apparent openness, came down to the House and assured the Commons that the whole
                    story was a malicious falsehood. The next day a friend of Fox’s opened his eyes
                    to the trick which had been played on him. “I see by the papers, Mr Fox,” he
                    said, “that you have denied the fact of the marriage of the prince of Wales with
                    Mrs Fitzherbert You have been misinformed. I was present at that marriage.” The
                    prince was not content with his original falsehood. He threw out hints to his
                    friends that Fox had exceeded his instructions. He led Mrs Fitzherbert to
                    believe that Foxhad uttered the denial unsuggested. “Only conceive, Maria,” he
                    said to her, “what Fox did yesterday. He went down to the House· and denied that
                    you and I were man and •wife.” The denial however cleared away for the moment
                    one cause of the prince’s unpopularity. With the consent of the Government he
                    received an addition of £10,000 to his income, £161,000 to pay his debts, and
                    £20,000 for the repairs of Carlton House. The temporary insanity of the king in
                    1788 again brought the prince’s name prominently before the public. Fox
                    maintained and Pitt denied that the prince of Wales, as the heir-apparent, had a
                    right to assume the regency independently of any parliamentary vote. Pitt, with
                    the support of both Houses, proposed to confer upon him the regency with certain
                    restrictions. The recovery of the king in February 1789 put an end to the
                    prince’s hopes. During the king’s illness he had been in the habit of amusing
                    his companions by mimicry of his unfortunate father. The disgust caused by his
                    behaviour had doubtless some part in the enthusiasm with which the king was
                    received when he went in state to St Paul’s to return thanks for his recovery.
                    In 1795 the prince married Caroline of Brunswick, because his father would not
                    pay his debts on any other terms. Her behaviour was light and flippant, and he
                    was brutal and unloving. The ill-assorted pair soon parted, and soon after the
                    birth of their only child, the Princess Charlotte, they were formally separated.
                    With great unwillingness the House of Commons voted fresh sums of money to pay
                    the prince’s debts. In 1811 the prince at last became regent in consequence of
                    his father’s definite insanity. No one doubted at that time that it was in his
                    power to change the ministry at his pleasure. He had always lived in close
                    connexion with the Whig opposition, and he now empowered Lord Grenville to form
                    a ministry. There soon arose differences of opinion between them on the answer
                    to be returned to the address of the Houses, and the prince regent then informed
                    the prime minister, Mr Perceval, that he should continue the existing ministry
                    in office. The ground alleged by him for this desertion of his friends was the
                    fear lest his father’s recovery might be rendered impossible if he should come
                    to hear of the advent of the Opposition to power. Lord Wellesley’s resignation
                    in February 1812 made the reconstruction of the ministry inevitable. As there
                    was no longer any hope of the king’s recovery, the former objection to a Whig
                    administration no longer existed. Instead of taking the course of inviting the
                    Whigs to take office, he asked them to join the existing administration. The
                    Whig leaders however refused to join, on the ground that the question of the
                    Catholic disabilities was too important to be shelved, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n441/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0441-0428"/> and that their difference of opinion with Mr
                    Perceval was too glaring to be ignored. The prince regent was excessively angry,
                    and continued Perceval in office till that minister’s assassination on May 11,
                    when he was succeeded by Lord Liverpool, after a negotiation in which the
                    proposition of entering the cabinet was again made to the Whigs aud rejected by
                    them. In the military glories of the following years the prince regent had no
                    share. When the allied sovereigns visited England in 1814, he played the part of
                    host to perfection. So great was his unpopularity at home that hisses were heard
                    in the streets as he accompanied his guests into the city. The disgust which his
                    profligate and luxurious life caused amongst a people suffering from almost
                    universal distress after the conclusion of the war rapidly increased. In 1817
                    the windows of the prince regent’s carriage were broken as he was on his way to
                    open parliament.</p>
                <p>The death of George III. on January 29, 1820, gave to his son the title of king
                    without in any way altering the position which he had now held for nine years.
                    Indirectly, however, this change brought out a manifestation of popular feeling
                    such as his father had never been subjected toeven in the early days of his
                    reign, when mobs were burning jack-boots and petticoats. The relations between
                    the new king and his wife unavoidably became the subject of public discussion.
                    In 1806 a charge against the princess of having given birth to an illegitimate
                    child had been conclusively disproved, and the old king had consequently re
                    fused to withdraw her daughter, the Princess Charlotte, from her custody. When
                    in the regency the prince was able to interfere, and prohibited his wife from
                    seeing her daughter more than once a fortnight. On this, in 1813, the princess
                    addressed to her husband a letter setting forth her complaints, and receiving no
                    answer published it in the <hi rend="italic">Morning Chronicle.</hi> The prince
                    regent then referred the letter, together with all papers relating to the
                    inquiry of 1806, to a body of twenty-three privy councillors for an opinion
                    whether it was fit that the restrictions on the intercourse between the Princess
                    Charlotte and her mothershould continue in force. All except two answered as the
                    regent wished them to answer. But if the official leaning was towards the
                    husband, the leaning of the general public was towards the wife of a man whose
                    own life had not been such as to justify him in complaining of her whom he had
                    thrust from him without a charge of any kind. Addresses of sympathy were sent up
                    to the princess from the city of London and other public bodies. The discord
                    again broke out in 1814 in consequence of the exclusion of the princess from
                    court during the visit of the allied sovereigns. In August in that year she left
                    England, and after a little time took up her abode in Italy. The accession of
                    George IV. brought matters to a crisis. He ordered that no prayer for his wife
                    as queen should be admitted into the Prayer Book. She at once challenged the
                    accusation which was implied in this omission by returning to England. On June 7
                    she arrived in London. Before she left the Continent sne had been informed that
                    proceedings would be taken against her for adultery if she landed in England.
                    Two years before, in 1818, commissioners had been sent to Milan to investigate
                    charges against her, and their report, laid before the cabinet in 1819, was made
                    the basis of the prosecution. On the day on which she arrived in London a
                    message was laid before both Houses recommending the criminating evidence to
                    parliament. A secret committee in the House of Lords after considering this
                    evidence brought in a report on which the prime minister founded a Bill of Pains
                    and Penalties to divorce the queen and to deprive her of her royal title. The
                    Bill passed the three readings with diminished majorities, and when on the third
                    reading it obtained only a majority of nine, it was abandoned by the Government.
                    The king’s unpopularity, great as it had been before, was now greater than ever.
                    Public opinion, without troubling itself to ask whether the queen was guilty or
                    not, was roused to indignation by the spectacle of such a charge being brought
                    by a husband who had thrust away his wife to fight the battle of life alone,
                    without protection or support, and who, whilst surrounding her with spies to
                    detect, perhaps to invent, her acts of infidelity, was himself living in
                    notorious adultery. In the following year (1821) she attempted to force her way
                    into Westminster Abbey to take her place at the coronation. On this occasion the
                    popular support failed her; and her death not long afterwards relieved the king
                    from further annoyance.</p>
                <p>Immediately after the death of the queen, the king set out for Ireland. He
                    remained there but a short time, and his effusive declaration that rank,
                    station, honours, were nothing compared with the exalted happiness of living in
                    the hearts of his Irish subjects gained him a momentary popularity which was
                    beyond his attainment in a country where he was better known. His reception in
                    Dublin encouraged him to attempt a visit to Edinburgh in the following year
                    (August 1822). Since Charles II. had come to play the sorry part of a
                    covenanting king in 1659 no sovereign of the country had set foot on Scottish
                    soil. Sir Walter Scott took the leading part in organizing his reception. The
                    enthusiasm with which he was received equalled, if it did not surpass, the
                    enthusiasm with which he had been received in Dublin. But the qualities which
                    enabled him to fix the fleeting sympathies of the moment were not such as would
                    enable him to exercise the influence in the government which had been
                    indubitably possessed by his father. He returned from Edinburgh to face the
                    question of the appointment of a secretary cf state which had been raised by the
                    death of Lord Londonderry, better known to the world by his earlier title of
                    Castlereagh. It was upon the question of the appointment of ministers that the
                    battle between the Whigs and the king had been fought in the reign of George
                    III. George IV. had neither the firmness nor the moral weight to hold the reins
                    which his father had grasped. He disliked Canning for having taken his wife’s
                    side very much as his father had disliked Fox for taking his own. But Lord
                    Liverpool insisted on Canning’s admission to office, and the king gave way.
                    Tacitly and without a struggle the constitutional victory of the last reign was
                    surrendered. But it was not surrendered to the same foe as that from which it
                    had been won. The coalition ministry in 1784 rested on the great landowners and
                    the proprietors of rotten boroughs. Lord Liverpool’s ministry had hitherto not
                    been very enlightened, and it supported itself to a great extent upon a narrow
                    constituency. But it did appeal to public opinion in a way that the coalition
                    did not, and what it wanted itself in popular support would be supplied by its
                    successors. What one king had gained from a clique another gave up to the
                    nation. Once more, on Lord Liverpool’s death in 1827, the same question was
                    tried with the same result. The king not only disliked Canning personally, but
                    he was opposed to Canning’s policy. Yet after some hesitation he accepted
                    Canning as prime minister; and when, after Canning’s death and the short
                    ministry of Lord Goderich, the king in 1828 authorized the duke of Wellington to
                    form a ministry, he was content to lay down the principle that the members of it
                    were not expected to be unanimous on the Catholic question. When in 1829 the
                    Wellington ministry unexpectedly proposed to introduce a Bill to remove the
                    disabilities of the Catholics, he feebly strove against the proposal and quickly
                    withdrew his opposition. The worn-out debauchee had neither the merit of
                    acquiescing in the change nor the courage to resist it.</p>
                <p>George IV. died on June 26, 1830. He had rendered to <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n442/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0442-0429"/> the constitution of his country the service of
                    tacitly aban doning a position which had been perhaps necessarily achieved by
                    his father, but which it was not desirable that the sovereigns of England should
                    permanently occupy.</p>
                <p>His only child by his wife Queen Caroline was the Princess Charlotte Augusta,
                    married in 1816 to Leopold of Saxe-Coburg, afterwards king of the Belgians. She
                    died in childbirth November 6, 1817. (s. R. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
