<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0128-0119-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GAY, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 119</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90251t">Opera</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn54">Sports</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:939255">Gays</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1140317">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1046191">Operas</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1046145">Opera</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n128/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GAY, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1688-1732), one
                    of the most eminent of the secondary English poets, was a native of Devonshire,
                    born in 1688 at Frithelstock, near Torrington, where his family had been long
                    settled. His father dying when the future poet was only about six years of age,
                    and leaving four children, the prospects of the family were unpromising; and
                    John, after receiving his education at the grammar school of Barnstaple, was put
                    apprentice to a silk mercer in London. He disliked the employment, obtained his
                    discharge, and embarked in a literary life, varied only by incessant efforts to
                    obtain the patronage of the great. How he lived up to his twenty-second year is
                    not stated. In 1710 he published his poem of <hi rend="italic">Wine,</hi> an
                    enumeration of the charms of the “enlivening grape,” written in the grave,
                    mock-heroic, and minutely descriptive style, which he afterwards displayed with
                    greater power in his <hi rend="italic">Trivia.</hi> In 1712 he was received into
                    the household of the duchess of Monmouth in the capacity of secretary. Next year
                    he published his <hi rend="italic">Rural Sports,</hi> inscribed to Pope; and
                    this seems to have led to a friendship between the poets uninterrupted and
                    sincere. The superiority of Pope was freely conceded. There could be no rivalry
                    on the part of Gay, and Pope appears to have exerted himself on every occasion
                    to serve his friend. Gay’s ambition was limited to a life of ease,
                    fine-dressing, and a luxurious table, in all of which he had marvellous success,
                    but little contentment. In the years 1713 and 1714, besides the <hi
                    rend="italic">Rural Sports,</hi> he produced a comedy, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Wife of Bath,</hi> which was acted only three nights; <hi rend="italic">The
                    Fan,</hi> a poem; and <hi rend="italic">The Shepherd’s Weeh,</hi> a series of
                    six pastorals drawn from English rustic life. Pope is believed to have incited
                    his friend to this task in order to cast ridicule on the Arcadian pastorals of
                    Ambrose Philips, who had been lavishly praised in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Guardian</hi> (ignoring the claims of Pope) as the first pastoral writer of the
                    age, and the true English Theocritus. The malicious wit was completely
                    successful, but Gay’s ludicrous pictures of the English swains and their loves
                    were found to be interesting and amusing without reference to their sarcastic
                    origin. The poem was popular, and the author’s reputation considerably advanced.
                    In this fortunate year Gay was appointed secretary to the earl of Clarendon,
                    ambassador to the court of Hanover; but the death of Queen Anne, August 1, 1714,
                    soon put an end to his hopes of permanent official employment. He then tried the
                    drama, and produced his farce of <hi rend="italic">What Tye Call it?</hi> which
                    was acted with little success in February 1714-15. In 1716 appeared his <hi
                    rend="italic">Trivia, or the Art of Walking the Streets of London,</hi> a poem
                    in three books, for which he acknowledged having received several hints from
                    Swift. It is an excellent <hi rend="italic">town</hi> poem, containing graphic
                    and humorous descriptions of the London of that period. In January 1716-17 the
                    comedy of <hi rend="italic">Three Hours after Marriage</hi> was brought on the
                    stage, and emphatically condemned. In this piece Gay was assisted by Pope and
                    Arbuthnot. Pope is distinctly visible in his allusions to Dennis the critic; and
                    it is remarkable that three such men should have produced a play so dull,
                    unnatural, and gross. Gay was taken to Aix by Mr Pulteney in 1717. Inl720he
                    collected his poems and published them by subscription, by which he is said to
                    have realized .£1000. Secretary Craggs also presented him with some South Sea
                    stock; and Gay called in his friends to advise as to the investment of his
                    riches. Erasmus Lewis, according to Johnson, advised him to intrust his money to
                    the funds, and live upon the interest; Arbuthnot bade him intrust it to
                    Providence, and live upon the principal; while Pope directed him, and was
                    seconded by Swift, to purchase an annuity. This was Pope’s own prudent system;
                    but Gay, like many others who ask advice, followed none, but took his own way.
                    He embarked all in South Sea stock; and, refusing to sell out before the bubble
                    burst, he lost the actual principal as well as the anticipated profit. The
                    calamity overwhelmed him; his life was despaired of; but his friends exerted
                    themelves to cheer and succour the desponding bard. Lord Burlington entertained
                    him for months in his princely house at Chiswick; and Pope, Arbuthnot, and the
                    other members of the circle were <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n129/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0129-0120"/> unceasing m their attentions. By the beginning of
                    1724 he had a new play ready, a tragedy called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Captives,</hi> which was patronized by the Princess (afterward Queen) Caroline
                    and the Prince of Wales. In 1726 he published his famous <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fifty-one Fables in Verse.</hi> His next work was the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Beggar's Opera,</hi> performed in 1727, written in ridicule of the Italian
                    Opera, which for a time it drove off the English stage. Swift suggested the
                    subject, and Pope is believed to have added some poignancy to the satirical
                    songs; but Gay’s own <hi rend="italic">bonhomie</hi> and voluptuous style colour
                    the whole. The play ran to the end of the season, sixty-two nights, four of
                    which were for the benefit of the author, and produced to him the handsome sum
                    of &lt;£693, 13s. 6d. The same year he sold his copyright of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Opera,</hi> with that of the <hi rend="italic">Fables,</hi> for 90
                    guineas. The success of <hi rend="italic">The Beggar's Opera</hi> induced Gay to
                    attempt a continuation of the operatic style. He wrote another piece, <hi
                    rend="italic">Polly,</hi> with no satirical design, as he states; but the lord
                    chamberlain prohibited its representation. The poet then resorted in 1729 to
                    publication by subscription; his friends were again active —the duchess of
                    Queensberry even bearding royalty in resentment of the refusal of the licence;
                    and Gay must have cleared above £1000 by what was deemed his oppression. The
                    duke of Queensberry received Gay into his house, and the duchess treated him
                    with equal respect for bis talents and character. This clever, beautiful, and
                    eccentric woman—the idol of the poets—appears nowhere to more advantage than in
                    her affectionate patronage of Gay, and her long-cherished regret for his loss.
                    The poet died, after a short illness, December 4, 1732, and the duke and duchess
                    of Queensberry honoured his remains with a splendid funeral and monument in
                    Westminster Abbey. A week before his death another opera, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Achilles,</hi> had been brought out with applause, and this, with a new volume
                    of <hi rend="italic">Fables,</hi> was published in 1733, the profits going to
                    his sisters, two widow ladies, who inherited by the poet’s death no less than
                    £6000. As late as 1743 appeared the posthumous comedy of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Distrest Wife,</hi> and the farce of <hi rend="italic">The Rehearsal at
                    Gotham</hi> in 1753. Pope and Swift—al ways ready to blame the court and
                    courtiers, though far from averse to their society—have censured Mrs Howard,
                    afterwards countess of Suffolk, for not more zealously promoting the interests
                    of Gay by her supposed influence with the king. One offer was made to the
                    poet,—the situation of gentleman·usher to the Princess Louisa, a child,—but he
                    declined it on account of his being, as he writes to Swift, so far advanced in
                    life. He was only thirty-nine; but all Gay’s friends seem to have treated the
                    offer as an indignity. When the queen’s establishment was made up in 1727, they
                    expected some more important office for their favourite associate, though it is
                    not easy to discover what appointment about the court could have been better
                    adapted to one so easy, so natural, and helpless. Mrs Howard, it is now known,
                    had very little influence with her royal master. The real power was in the hands
                    of the queen, and the philosophical Caroline was content that his Majesty (who
                    hated <hi rend="italic">bhoetry</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bhainting,</hi> and
                    looked upon poets as mechanics) should possess what mistresses he pleased,
                    provided that the state power and patronage continued with herself and Walpole.
                    But it may be safely said that no man could have acquired such a body of great
                    and accomplished friends as those which rallied round Gay and mourned his loss,
                    without the possession of many valuable and endearing qualities. His poetry is
                    neither high nor pure; but he had humour, a fine vein of fancy, and powers of
                    observation and local painting which bespeak the clo≡e poetical student and the
                    happy literary artist. <hi rend="smallcaps">(r. ca.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
