<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0433-0420-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GEORGE I (9th edition, volume 10, page 420)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm13z3g">Heirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n433/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GEORGE I</label>., king of Great Britain and Ireland <hi
                        rend="italic">(George Louis,</hi> 1660-1727), born in 1660, was heir through
                    his father Ernest Augustus to the hereditary lay bishopric of Osnabrück, and to
                    the duchy of Calenburg, which formed one portion of the Hanoverian possessions
                    of the house of Brunswick, whilst he secured the reversion of the other portion,
                    the duchy of Celle or Zell, by his marriage (1682) with the heiress, his cousin
                    Sophia Dorothea. The marriage was not a happy one. The morals of German courts
                    in the end of the 17th century took their tone from the splendid profligacy of
                    Versailles. It became the fashion for a prince to amuse himself with a mistress
                    or more frequently with many mistresses simultaneously, and he was often content
                    that the mistresses whom he favoured should be neither beautiful nor witty.
                    George Louis followed the usual course. Count Königsmark—a handsome
                    adventurer—seized the opportunity of paying court to the deserted wife. Conjugal
                    infidelity was held at Hanover to be a privilege of the male sex. Count
                    Königsmark was assassinated. Sophia Dorothea was divorced in 1694, and remained
                    in seclusion till her death in 1726. When her descendant in the fourth
                    generation attempted in England to call his wife to account for sins of which he
                    was himself notoriously guilty, free-spoken public opinion reprobated the
                    offence in no measured terms. In the Germany of the 17th century all free-spoken
                    public opinion had been crushed out by the misery of the Thirty Years’ War, and
                    it was understood that princes were to arrange their domestic life according to
                    their own pleasure.</p>
                <p>The prince’s father did much to raise the dignity of his family. By sending help
                    to the emperor when he was struggling against the French and the Turks, he
                    obtained the grant of a ninth electorate in 1692. His marriage with Sophia, the
                    youngest daughter of Elizabeth the daughter of James I. of England, was not one
                    which at first seemed likely to confer any prospect of advancement to his
                    family. But though there were many persons whose birth gave them better claims
                    than she had to the English crown, she found herself, upon the death of the duke
                    of Gloucester, the next Protestant heir after Anne. The Act of Settlement in
                    1701 secured the inheritance to herself and her descendants. Being old and
                    unambitious she rather permitted herself to be burthened with the honour than
                    thrust herself forward to meet it. Her son George took a deeper interest in the
                    matter. In his youth he had fought with determined courage in the wars of
                    William III. Succeeding to the electorate on his father’s death in 1698, he had
                    sent a welcome reinforcement of Hanoverians to fight under Marlborough at
                    Blenheim. With prudent persistence he attached himself closely to the Whigs and
                    to Marlborough, refusing Tory offers of an independent command, and receiving in
                    return for his fidelity a guarantee by the Dutch of his succession to England in
                    the Barrier treaty of 1709. In 1714 when Anne was growing old, and Bolingbroke
                    and the more reckless Tories waere coquetting with the son of James II., the W
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> ^higs invited George’s eldest son, who was
                    duke of Cambridge, to visit England in order to be on the spot in case of need.
                    Neither the elector nor his mother approved of a step which was likely to
                    alienate the queen, and which was specially distasteful to himself, as he was on
                    very bad terms with his son. Yet they did not set themselves against the strong
                    wish of the party to which they looked for support, and it is possible that
                    troubles would have arisen from any attempt to carry out the plan, if the
                    deaths, first of the electress (May 28) and then of the queen (August 1, 1714),
                    had not laid open George’s way to the succession without further effort of his
                    own.</p>
                <p>In some respects the position of the new king was not unlike that of William III.
                    a quarter of a century before. Both sovereigns were foreigners, with little
                    knowledge of English politics and little interest in English legislation. Both
                    sovereigns arrived at a time when party spirit had been running high, and when
                    the task before the ruler was to still the waves of contention. In spite of the
                    difference between an intellectually great man and an intellectually <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n434/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0434-0421"/> small one, in spite too of the difference
                    between the king who began by choosing his ministers from both parties, and the
                    king who persisted in choosing his ministers from only one, the work of
                    pacification was accomplished by George even more thoroughly than by
                    William.</p>
                <p>George I. was fortunate in arriving in England when a great military struggle had
                    come to an end. He had therefore no reason to call upon the nation to make great
                    sacrifices. All that he wanted was to secure for himself and his family a high
                    position which he hardly knew how to occupy, to fill the pockets of his German
                    attendants and his German mistresses, to get away as often as possible from the
                    uncongenial islanders whose language he was unable to speak, and to use the
                    strength of England to obtain petty advantages for his German principality. In
                    order to do this he attached himself entirely to the Whig party, though he
                    refused to place himself at the disposal of its leaders. He gave his confidence,
                    not to Somers and Wharton and Marlborough, but to Stanhope and Townshend, the
                    statesmen of the second rank. At first he seemed to be playing a dangerous game.
                    The Tories, whom he rejected, were numerically superior to their adversaries,
                    and were strong in the support of the country gentlemen and the country clergy.
                    The strength of the Whigs lay in the towns and in the higher aristocracy. Below
                    both parties lay the mass of the nation, which cared nothing for politics except
                    in special seasons of excitement, and which asked only tobe let alone. In 1715 a
                    Jacobite insurrection in the north, supported by the appearance of the
                    Pretender, the son of James II., in Scotland, was suppressed, and its
                    suppression not only gave to the Government a character of stability, but
                    displayed its adversaries in an unfavourable light as the disturbers of the
                    peace.</p>
                <p>Even this advantage, however, would have been thrown away, if the Whigs in power
                    had continued to be animated by violent party spirit. What really happened was
                    that the Tory leaders were excluded from office, but that the principles and
                    prejudices <hi rend="italic">oV</hi> the Tories were admitted to their full
                    weight in the policy of the Government. The natural result followed. The leaders
                    to whom no regard was paid continued in opposition. The rank and file who would
                    personally have gained nothing by a party victory were conciliated into
                    quiescence.</p>
                <p>This mingling of two policies was conspicuous both in the foreign and the
                    domestic actions of the reign. In the days of Queen Anne, the Whig party had
                    advocated the continuance of war with a view to the complete humiliation of the
                    king of France, whom they feared as the protector of the Pretender, and in whose
                    family connexion with the king of Spain they saw a danger for England. The Tory
                    party on the other hand had been the authors of the peace of Utrecht, and held
                    that France was sufficiently depressed. A fortunate concurrence of circumstances
                    enabled George’s ministers, by an alliance with the regent of France, the duke
                    of Orleans, to pursue at the same time the Whig policy of separating France from
                    Spain and from the cause of the Pretender, and the Tory policy of the
                    maintenance of a good understanding with their neighbour across the Channel. The
                    same eclecticism was discernible in the proceedings of the home Government. The
                    Whigs were conciliated by the repeal of the Schism Act and the Occasional
                    Conformity Act, whilst the Tories were conciliated by the maintenance of the
                    Test Act in all its vigour. The satisfaction of the masses was increased by the
                    general wellbeing of the nation.</p>
                <p>Very little of all that was thus accomplished was directly owing to George I. The
                    policy of the reign is the policy of his ministers, Stanhope and Townshend from
                    1714 to 1717 were mainly occupied with the defence of the Hanoverian settlement.
                    After the dismissal of the latter in 1717, Stanhope in conjunction with
                    Sunderland took up a more decided Whig policy. The Occasional Conformity Act and
                    the Schism Act were repealed in 1719. But the wish of the liberal Whigs to
                    modify if not to repeal the Test Act remained unsatisfied. In the following year
                    the bursting of the South Sea bubble, and the subsequent deaths of Stanhope in
                    1721 and of Sunderland in 1722, cleared the way for the accession to power of
                    Sir Robert Walpole, to wlιom and not to the king was due the conciliatory policy
                    which quieted Tory opposition by abstaining from pushing Whig principles to
                    their legitimate consequences.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless something of the honour due to Walpole must be reckoned to the
                    king’s credit. It is evident that at his accession his decisions were by no
                    means unimportant. The royal authority was still able within certain limits to
                    make its own terms. This support was so necessary to the Whigs that they made no
                    resistance when he threw aside their leaders on his arrival in England. When by
                    his personal intervention he dismissed Townshend and appointed Sunderland, he
                    had no such social and parliamentary combination to fear as that which almost
                    mastered his great-grandson in his struggle for power. If such a combination
                    arose before the end of his reign it was owing more to his omitting to fulfil
                    the duties of his station than from the necessity of the case. As he could talk
                    no English, and his ministers could talk no German, he absented himself from the
                    meetings of the cabinet, and his frequent absences from England and his want of
                    interest in English politics strengthened the cabinet in its tendency to assert
                    an independent position. Walpole at last by his skill in the management of
                    parliament rose as a subject into the almost royal position denoted by the name
                    of prime minister. In connexion with Walpole the force of wealth and station
                    established the Whig aristocracy in a point of vantage from which it was
                    afterwards difficult to dislodge them. Yet, though George had allowed the power
                    which had been exercised by William and Anne to slip through his hands, it was
                    understood to the last that if he chose to exert himself he might cease to be a
                    mere-cipher in the conduct of affairs. As late as in 1727 Bolingbroke gained
                    over one of the king’s mistresses, the-duchess of Kendal; and though her support
                    of the fallen Jacobite took no effect, Walpole was not without fear that her
                    reiterated entreaties would lead to his dismissal. The king’s death in a
                    carriage on his way to Hanover, in the night between 10th and 11th June in the
                    same year, put an end to these apprehensions.</p>
                <p>His only children were his successor George II., and Sophia Dorothea (1687-1757),
                    who married in 1706 Frederick William, crown prince (afterwards king) of
                    Prussia. She was the mother of Frederick the Great. (s. <hi rend="smallcaps">r.
                        g.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
