<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0015-0006-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GAELIC LANGUAGE AND LITERATURE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 6</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="24" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="41" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="fasttopic:1032344">Names</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:892462">Dialectic</term>
                    <term n="15" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:889519">Deer</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="22" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="23" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81q3f">Deer</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="21" ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b45x25g11">Dialects</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="21" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n15/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GAELIC LANGUAGE AND LITERATURE</label>. Until recently thet ’
                    e was doubt as to the family of languages to which the Gaelic belonged; indeed,
                    with many scholars the impression existed that it belonged to the Semitic
                    branch, and that its relations must all be traced among some one or other of its
                    varieties. This view arose very much from the neglect with which the language
                    had been treated by scientific men. Comparative philology is itself a modem
                    subject of study. Naturally, in its progress, the more prominent languages came
                    first, while the more obscure were passed over as of comparatively subordinate
                    importance. The study is one so comprehensive, and requiring so large an amount
                    of acquirement of various kinds, that it is no real reproach to modern
                    scholarship that the study of such languages as the latter should have been
                    postponed in favour of that of languages more generally known. Their turn,
                    however, gradually came, and no one can complain now that they have not received
                    the attention of very competent scholars. It is doubtful whether a higher class
                    of scholarship has been nurtured anywhere than in the study of the Celtic
                    languages, as exhibited by such men as Zeuss, Dieffenbach, Ebel, Whitley Stokes,
                    the Chevalier Nigra, Henri Gaidoz, and others who have devoted their strength to
                    their exposition. The result has been the complete establishment of the fact
                    that this class of languages belongs to the Indo-European or Aryan stock, and is
                    closely related to the classical branch of those tongues.</p>
                <p>The first who brought real scholarship to bear upon the question of the family to
                    which the Celtic dialects belonged was Dr Cowles Pritchard. His <hi
                    rend="italic">Eastern Origin of the Celtic Nations</hi> is a work of the highest
                    value, distinguished by its erudition, and the sound judgment it displays. He
                    was one of the most remarkable men whom Britain has produced in the field of
                    comparative philology. No doubt it is with the Welsh he chiefly dealt, but, in
                    discussing such questions as he had to deal with, it mattered little which of
                    the Celtic tongues was made use of. Many writers followed Dr Pritchard, and
                    there is now, as has been said, no question <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> about
                    the Aryan source of the Celtic languages. It is not that the words are to a
                    large extent analogous, but the grammatical structure and the idioms correspond
                    to such an extent that the question is put beyond a doubt; while, with the
                    exception of a few common vocables, there is little that is analogous between
                    the Celtic and the Semitic languages.</p>
                <p>The territory once occupied by the Celtic race is a question of much interest.
                    Now they are confined within well-known limits. On the European continent they
                    occupy that part of France usually called Brittany, the most westerly portion of
                    the country terminating in Cape Finisterre. They occupied this territory so
                    early as the days of Julius Caesar, although it has been said that they were
                    emigrants from Britain at a later period. The topographical terms given by
                    Caesar in describing the Roman invasion all indicate that the language of the
                    natives of Brittany used then, and for a long time before, was as much Celtic as
                    it is now. Opposite to Brittany lies British Cornwall, a region with a Celtic
                    tongue until about 100 years ago. The two Cornwalls—one in Britain and the other
                    in France—terminated, one on each side, the territory occupied by the Celt. The
                    dialect3 spoken in these stood in the closest relationship. To the north of this
                    lies the greatest of all the modem sections<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n16/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0016-0007"/> of the Cimbrian Celts. Wales, occupied by about a
                    million inhabitants, is nearly Celtic, and uses the ancient tongue of Wales,
                    Cumbria, and Strathclyde. Across the sea from Wales lies the Isle of Man, where
                    the Gaelic branch of the Celtic held sway, and does to some extent still In
                    Ireland the Gaelic also prevailed, and is still spoken by about a million
                    people. And lastly, in the Scottish Highlands about 300,000 people still use,
                    less or more, the old Gaelic tongue of Scotland. Thus Brittany, Wales, Man,
                    western Ireland, and the Scottish Highlands are now the territory of the Celtic
                    languages. That they once occupied a wider sphere is beyond a doubt. There are
                    traces of the tongue, in one form or other, to be found all along southern
                    Europe. Topography is a valuable source of evidence, and one that will be made
                    to serve purposes it has never served as yet; and it furnishes us—in Italy,
                    France, Switzerland, Spain, and Portugal—with relics which, like animal fossils
                    dug from the depths of the earth, spealL·unmistakably of what formerly existed
                    there. How far the Gaelic form of Celtic speech prevailed it is difficult to
                    say, or whether it existed alongside of the Cimbric on the continent of Europe.
                    But the name Gallia is significant as applied to France; and it is a suggestive
                    fact that, to this day, the Bretons call France Gaul, as distinguished from
                    their own country, and in like manner call the French language Gallic, as
                    distinguished from the Breton. In Scotland the Gaelic and Cimbric races long
                    dwelt together, distinct and yet nearly related. When they separated, either as
                    to race or language, is not easily settled. There are indications on the
                    Continent which rather throw doubt on the idea maintained by some writers that
                    the divergence took place after the settlement of the race in Britain, and
                    farther inquiry as to these indications is essential ere a satisfactory
                    conclusion can be reached. But within the historic period the two races existed
                    side by side in Scotland, the Cimbric occupying the region called Strathclyde,
                    with their separate government and laws, and the Gael at least occupying the
                    Dalriadic kingdom of Argyll. The people called by the Romans Picts occupied the
                    north and east of Scotland. That these were the same people with the Dalriadic
                    Scots is somewhat questionable. That they were closely related to them is beyond
                    doubt, but that they had linguistic and other peculiarities is manifest. Their
                    topography proves it, being different from that of either Ireland or Argyll,
                    and, so far as the historic relations of both are concerned, they indicate a
                    state of chronic war. For centuries there were mutual raids of Scots on Picts,
                    and Picts on Scots, until finally, under Kenneth MacAlpine, king of Dalriada,
                    the Picts were overcome in the year 813, and they and the Scots became united
                    under one monarchy. The tradition is that the Picts were annihilated,—meaning,
                    in all likelihood, their power,—and there arose one great united kingdom. The
                    united people are the ancestors of the present Scottish Highlanders, and the
                    Gaelic language has come down from them to us, influenced as to structure by the
                    dialect spoken and written by the victors.</p>
                <p>The Gaelic language, as now in use in Scotland, resembles closely in its
                    structure both the Irish and the Manx. They form one family, and yet it has its
                    own distinctive features. Irish scholars maintain that it is a modern and
                    corrupt offshoot of the Irish, and account in this way for these peculiarities.
                    They say, for example, that the absence of the present tense in the Gaelic verb
                    is a mere instance of decay, and proves the modern character of the dialect. But
                    the Welsh is no modern and corrupt form of Irish, but an ancient distinct
                    tongue, so far back as history carries us. And yet it wants the present tense,
                    indicating that this peculiarity is distinctive of some of the Celtic tongues,
                    and that what is cited as a proof of recency may in reality be a proof of
                    priority. The present tense may be called an Irish addition made to the verb in
                    the process of culture. At the same time it must be allowed that there is a
                    difficulty in proving from any literary remains existing that the present
                    Scottish form of the language is of great antiquity. All the literary relics
                    that have come down to us are written in what is usually called the Irish
                    dialect. The present tense is in universal use, as well by Scottish as by Irish
                    writers. This arose from the identity of the Irish and Scottish churches. The
                    dialect in which all theological treatises were written was one, and this
                    dialect extended from the clergy to bards, and sennachies, and medical men.
                    There is not a page of Gaelic written in any other dialect before the middle of
                    last century. But as in other countries there was both a spoken and a written
                    dialect in use, so in both Scotland and Ireland there appears to have been a
                    dialect in use among the people as their common speech, and another used by
                    their scholars,—the former varying according to locality, and the latter being
                    identical throughout. Some of the features that distinguish the Gaelic language,
                    partly in common with the other Celtic tongues, and partly not, are the
                    following :—</p>
                <p>1. The aspiration of consonants. This is accomplished by the change of <hi
                    rend="italic">m</hi> into <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> of <hi rend="italic">b</hi>
                    into <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> of <hi rend="italic">d</hi> into <hi
                    rend="italic">y,</hi> of <hi rend="italic">g</hi> into a broad <hi rend="italic"
                    >y,</hi> of <hi rend="italic">p</hi> into ∕, and s and <hi rend="italic">t</hi>
                    into <hi rend="italic">h.</hi> As appearing in the initial articulations this
                    presents a peculiar difficulty to the learner of Gaelic. He has been accustomed,
                    in learning other tongues, to observe the changes required by inflexion, and
                    other requirements of correct grammatical structure. But he has not been
                    familiar with changes in the initial letters of words. In English these letters
                    never undergo any change; but in Gaelic he meets with such changes at once. He
                    finds <hi rend="italic">mac,</hi> a son, becoming in certain circumstances <hi
                    rend="italic">vac,</hi> and he is ready to doubt whether both forms belong to
                    the same word. To make the difficulty as little formidable as possible to the
                    reader, the authors of the Gaelic orthography fell upon the method of using the
                    letter <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> which, though hardly a letter in Gaelic, and
                    never used to begin a word, is now used more than any other letter. The Irish
                    use a dot. The use of the <hi rend="italic">h</hi> serves to preserve to the
                    reader the original form of the word. Hence <hi rend="italic">mac</hi> becomes
                    by aspiration, or <hi rend="italic">adoucissement</hi> as the French call it,
                    <hi rend="italic">mhac,</hi> pronounced <hi rend="italic">vac.</hi> These
                    initial changes of certain consonants arc made for the purpose of euphony, to
                    which Gaelic makes large sacrifices, and also for the purpose of distinguishing
                    gender. An aspiration converts the feminine into the masculine, and, <hi
                    rend="italic">vice versa. An ceann</hi> is the head, masculine, <hi
                    rend="italic">a’ chos</hi> the foot, feminine. So <hi rend="italic">a chos</hi>
                    is his foot, <hi rend="italic">a cos</hi> is her foot; <hi rend="italic">a
                    chcann</hi> is his head, <hi rend="italic">a ceann</hi> is her head, the pronoun
                    undergoing no change, although its gender is indicated by the change. There are
                    other purposes served by aspiration of considerable importance. The Gaelic
                    learner makes a large acquisition when he masters the principles of aspiration,
                    and inquirers into the characters of the language will cease to blame the
                    frequency with which <hi rend="italic">k</hi> appears in Gaelic writing when
                    they come to see how important a purpose it serves.</p>
                <p>2. Another peculiarity of the Gaelic language is to be found, as already said, in
                    the want of a present tense in the verb. Tho verb “to do” is <hi rend="italic"
                    >dean,</hi> the theme of the verb being in the imperative mood. There is no
                    tense expressing simply I do, the form in use being I am doing, <hi
                    rend="italic">tha mi a' cleanamh.</hi> The Irish say <hi rend="italic"
                    >deanaim,</hi> I do, but that is not the Scottish form of the expression. In
                    this Gaelic is not only at one with several of the Celtic branches, but with
                    some of the Semitic tongues. And it has this further in common with these last,
                    that the future is used to express present time. This occurs frequently in the
                    Gaelic version of the Bible, where we have <hi rend="italic">an</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ti a chreidcas</hi><hi rend="italic">anns a’ Mhac,</hi> he that
                    will believe in the Son, for he that believeth. And yet occasionally a true
                    present tense appears in Gaelic :— <hi rend="italic">an cluinn thu sin?</hi> Do
                    you hear that? <hi rend="italic">cluinnidh,</hi> I do hear it; <hi rend="italic"
                    >am faic</hi><hi rend="italic">thu</hi><hi rend="italic">sin?</hi> Do you see
                    that? <hi rend="italic">chi,</hi><hi rend="italic">I</hi> do see it. In these
                    cases and some others there is no doubt a distinct present tense. The cases are,
                    however, few, and occur in peculiar circumstances.</p>
                <p>3. Another feature peculiar to Gaelic is that there is no real infinitive in the
                    verb. The infinitive in use is a noun which may appear either in the form of a
                    participle or an infinitive, according to the effect of the preceding
                    preposition. I am going to strike, <hi rend="italic">tha mi 'dol do
                    bhualadh,</hi> I am going to striking; I am striking, <hi rend="italic"
                    >tha</hi><hi rend="italic">mi a</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">bualadh,</hi> I am at
                    striking,—the preposition <hi rend="italic">do,</hi> to, in the one case giving
                    the noun the force of an infinitive, and the preposition <hi rend="italic"
                    >ag</hi> or <hi rend="italic">a',</hi> at, giving the same noun the force of a
                    participle. The Gaelic infinitive is thus identical with the Latin gerund, and
                    is one of the points where the classical and the Celtic tongues meet and
                    touch.</p>
                <p>In the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Celtic Literature</hi> reference is made to
                    some of those cases in which the Irish dialect of the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n17/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0017-0008"/> Celtic differs from some of the others. It is
                    unnecessary here to go over the same ground again. What is distinctive of the
                    Irish is, for the most part, distinctive of the Scottish Gaelic. The Gaelic
                    retains the hard or <hi rend="italic">k</hi> sound of c. There is not an
                    instance of a purely Gaelic word in which the <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is
                    pronounced soft. There are dialects of Gaelic, however, in which the <hi
                    rend="italic">c</hi> becomes aspirated in the middle or at the end of a word.
                    Thus <hi rend="italic">mac,</hi> a son, is pronounced <hi rend="italic"
                    >machd;</hi><hi rend="italic">veacadh,</hi> sin, is pronounced <hi rend="italic"
                    >peachdadh.</hi> This peculiarity does not exist in the counties of Sutherland
                    and Caithness, where the hard sound of <hi rend="italic">c</hi> is retained. The
                    Scottish Gaelic, in like manner, in common with Sanskrit, Latin, German, and
                    Slavonian, retains the sibilant β, where other dialects have discarded it. Many
                    words beginning in Gaelic with s have <hi rend="italic">h</hi> as the initial
                    letter in Welsh. It is worthy of observation, however, that, in the aspirated
                    form of the s used in inflexion or as indicative of gender, the s assumes the
                    sound of <hi rend="italic">h</hi> in Gaelic. In like manner, words in Gaelic, as
                    in Irish, can eud in s, <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> aud <hi rend="italic">n.</hi>
                    The instances of these are numerous. So also does the Gaelic, like Irish, retain
                    a harder form of the articulation than the British, but not io the same extent;
                    for <hi rend="italic">huvel,</hi> low, in Irish <hi rend="italic">humal,</hi> is
                    in Gaelic <hi rend="italic">umhal,</hi> approaching in this, as in many other
                    cases, nearer to the British form. So the Gaelic preserves letters where the
                    British loses them, but not to the same extent as the Irish. For when the Irish
                    has <hi rend="italic">tech,</hi> a house, and the British <hi rend="italic"
                    >ti,</hi> the Gaelic has both <hi rend="italic">teach</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >tigh,</hi> and for the most part uses the latter. In addition to this, the
                    Gaelic, like the Irish, has preserved the declension of its noun, which cannot
                    be said of the British. Four of the cases are .in constant use, the nominative,
                    the genitive, the dative, and the vocative in both numbers, the dative plural
                    alone having almost disappeared from common speech. In the singular number these
                    cases are distinctly marked— <hi rend="italic">cos,</hi> a foot, gen. <hi
                    rend="italic">coise,</hi> dat. <hi rend="italic">cois,</hi> voc. <hi
                    rend="italic">a chos.</hi> Wherever the language is well spoken these cases are
                    in daily use, and are lost only when the language is far on in the process of
                    decay.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Difference between Gaelic</hi><hi rend="italic">and
                    Irish.—</hi> The differences between the Gaelic and the Irish are considerable,
                    and, though Irish writers maintain the contrary, are not to be taken as
                    indications of the modern origin of the former. Without entering on that
                    question, we find a marked distinction in the use by the Irish of what is called
                    eclipsis,— that is, the use of other and softer articulations to eclipse the
                    harder in the beginning of a word, in some cases, as, for instance, in the
                    genitive plural of nouns. The object Aimed at would seem to be euphony, and in
                    seeking this object the Irish and the Scottish ear did not altogether
                    correspond. In Irish, the law as given by O’Donovan is that <hi rend="italic"
                    >m</hi> eclipses δ, as <hi rend="italic">ar m-bo,</hi> our cow <hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi><hi rend="italic">g</hi> eclipses <hi rend="italic">c,</hi> as <hi
                    rend="italic">ar</hi><hi rend="italic">g-ceart,</hi> our right; <hi
                    rend="italic">η</hi> eclipses <hi rend="italic">d, bh</hi> eclipses <hi
                    rend="italic">f,</hi><hi rend="italic">n</hi> eclipses <hi rend="italic"
                    >g,</hi><hi rend="italic">b</hi> eclipses <hi rend="italic">p, d</hi> eclipses
                    <hi rend="italic">t,</hi><hi rend="italic">t</hi> eclipses s. This system of
                    eclipsing runs through the nouns and verbs. It is unknown in Gaelic, if we
                    except the eclipsing of <hi rend="italic">s</hi> by <hi rend="italic">t,</hi> as
                    <hi rend="italic">an</hi><hi rend="italic">t-sùil,</hi> the eye, <hi
                    rend="italic">an t-slat,</hi> the rod, and certain words which, in some
                    districts of the Highlands, suffer eclipse. In Skye the expression for the
                    number of men is <hi rend="italic">àireamh</hi><hi rend="italic">nan
                    n-daoine,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">η</hi> eclipsing the <hi rend="italic"
                    >d.</hi> Other instances may be found along the weβt coast of Scotland. But
                    eclipsis is, for the most part, distinctive of the Irish dialect. The Gaelic is
                    further marked by a greater tendency to aspiration than the Irish. The sentence
                    <hi rend="italic">cionnas</hi><hi rend="italic">ta tu</hi> 1 how art thpu 1 in
                    Irish, is in Gaelic <hi rend="italic">cionnus tha thu</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ί</hi> the verb and the pronoun being both aspirated. Other differences might
                    be referred to, but one is prominent, the difference of accent or emphasis. The
                    tendency of the Irish is to emphasize the final syllable, that of the Gaelic to
                    emphasize the penultimate. Thus <hi rend="italic">salàch,</hi> dirty, in Irish,
                    is in Gaelic <hi rend="italic">salach∙, Ois'ιn,</hi> Ossian, is in Gaelic <hi
                    rend="italic">Oisian.</hi> This makes a striking difference in the spoken
                    tongues, and occasions one of the main difficulties Irish and Scottish Celts
                    have in understanding each others’ speech.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Advantages and Defects of Gaelic.—</hi> The Gaelic language, as
                    now existing, has its advantages and its corresponding defects. It is admirably
                    adapted for the purposes of the poet. In descriptive poetry few languages excel
                    it. There are some pieces of ancient, authentic, Ossianic poetry existing that
                    are equal in power and beauty to the compositions of any age or country. Such
                    are the description of Cuchullin’s chariot and horses, and the description of
                    the swords of the Ossianic heroes. The same is true of more modern poetic
                    compositions. Macintyre of Glenorchy’s <hi rend="italic">Beiιιn Douran</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Coire</hi><hi rend="italic">Cheathaich</hi> are fine specimens
                    of descriptive poetry—poetical in conception throughout, couched in the choicest
                    language, and with rhythm of unfailing accuracy. The same may be said of
                    Macdonald’s <hi rend="italic">Oran an t-samhraidh,</hi> or Ode to Summer, which
                    is a remarkable specimen of what the Gaelic is capable of when used for the
                    description of nature. Other lyrical compositions are also of a high order of
                    merit. Love-songs and boat-songs abound, and are in many cases full of life and
                    force; and the numerous songs expressive of clan affections and animosities
                    display the same characteristics. No language is more capable of expressing both
                    love and hate, and there seems to have been ample scope for both in the past
                    history of the Highland clans. Within certain limits then, Gaelic is the
                    language of poetry, extending from the epic of the Ossianic bards down to the
                    lyric or less aspiring efforts of lesser bards.</p>
                <p>The language is also admirably fitted for the communication of religious
                    knowledge. It is in its structure metaphorical and emotional, and renders with
                    wonderful precision and effect the statements of Scripture. The saying
                    attributed to one of the dukes of Argyll is well known, that if addressing his
                    sovereign he would choose English, if addressing the lady of his affections he
                    would choose French, but if he was addressing his God he would choose Gaelic.
                    Few of those whose calling it is to teach religious truth, and who know how to
                    handle the language with effect, have failed to feel and own that it is
                    incomparable for conveying the knowledge of the truth with power. Perhaps no
                    preachers have surpassed the Welsh in real eloquence, and yet some of the Gaelic
                    preachers have not been behind them. The language has served a great purpose in
                    the Highlands in connexion with the religious life of the people. <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi></p>
                <p>The defects of the language are to be found chiefly in the departments of
                    philosophy, science, and art. There it has either to be rejected or to be
                    supplied from foreign sources. Indeed in this field it seems to have
                    deteriorated during the course of several centuries. There are MSS. of the 14th
                    and 15th centuries in existence, in which terms are employed in connexion with
                    discussions in philosophy, theology, and medicine that could not now be
                    understood. The philosophy of Aristotle is well rendered, as are also the
                    theology of the fathers and the medical disquisitions of the Arabic writers on
                    medicine. But when modern science and philosophy, and even theology in some of
                    its departments, have to be dealt with, the lack of terms renders the task a
                    difficult one. It is here that, in the progress of education, the difficulty of
                    preserving the language lies. The effect of this want is traceable in common
                    speech, when English words have of necessity to be used in connexion with
                    objects of everyday use. Steamer, train, boiler, engine, railway, quay,
                    &lt;fcc., have just tobe introduced from the Saxon, and presented with a little
                    of the Gaelic tone in them to suit the Celtic ear. Some writers and speakers do
                    try to invent Gaelic terms to represent all these and similar objects, but
                    popular usage rejects them and prefers the foreign words.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n18/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0018-0009"/>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gaelic Literature.</hi> —The literature of the Scottish
                    Highlands may be divided into several branches. The following outline
                    comprehends more perhaps than is usually included under that term; in
                    particular, it appears necessary to give here some account of topographical and
                    personal names.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mythology.—</hi> We have first the mythology of the race.
                    Little of this now exists, and it is difficult to piece the scattered fragments
                    together. We find the mythology of the older faith or faiths interwoven in some
                    cases with the mythology of the Northmen. The mythology of the East appears at
                    some points, and we have giants, fairies, and witches, some of them firmly
                    believed in to the present day. Adamnan, in his life of Columba, refers to the
                    magi who were in the palace of the Pictish king whom the missionary sought to
                    convert. Who these were, and what was their creed, is not clearly stated, but
                    all we read of that early faith, and all that tradition brings down to us, would
                    seem to indicate that their worship was a form of sun worship. The words applied
                    to the cardinal points of the compass convey this impression, the fear shown in
                    many ways of going against the course of the sun, and certain festivals in which
                    fire was and is used, would seem to confirm it. The bodies of the dead are in
                    some cases carried sunwise round certain objects on their way to the burial
                    ground; in fact, words and practices crop up in several parts of the country
                    serving to show that the sun was worshipped. <hi rend="italic">Path,</hi> a
                    circle, is used in Gaelic to express good fortune :— <hi rend="italic">cha-n'eil
                    rath air,</hi> there is no circle on him,—he is not fortunate,—referring, no
                    doubt, to the course of the sun. There was a Gaelic mythology connected with the
                    Fingalian heroes. Whether they themselves were mythical or not is debated, but
                    there was a mythology connected with them. Fingal had a sword that never
                    required to be used twice; the Vulcan of the race could cross a glen with a
                    stride; Manannan, son of Lir, from whom the Isle of Man is named, could clothe
                    himself in a fog, and so hide himself from his enemy. The story of Diarmad and
                    the boar and the story of Fraoch and the beast are mythological, the former
                    being the Celtic story of Achilles, and the latter the Celtic version of the
                    Garden of the Hesperides. Then there were giants called <hi rend="italic">Na
                    Piantaicheaη,</hi> men of colossal mould. <hi rend="italic">Dun Fhian,</hi> the
                    giant’s castle, is a common topographical term. Here is the description (with
                    English translation) of one of these heroes :—</p>
                <p>“Tamhull mor, mac sheann Tamhuil, Cha ruigeadh a ’ rnhuir mhδr a ruinnse, Cha
                    tharadlι e mach, ’s cha thàradh e steach, ’Us ’n uair a bhitheadh e ’s a bheul
                    fodha, Bhitheadh a dhnιim a’ sgriobadh an athar.” Great Taval, son of old Taval,
                    The great sea wouldn’t reach his middle; He couldn’t get out and he couldn’t get
                    in; And when he lay down on his face, His back would be scratching the sky.</p>
                <p>Some of these tales of the giant3 attribute to them a great age. There is one
                    tale in which five generations in succession are said to exist at the same time,
                    and the youngest of them a very aged man. The traditional tales taken down by Mr
                    J. F. Campbell, from oral tradition in the Highlands are full of mythology.
                    Animals in these play an important part, and are endowed with remarkable powers.
                    How far this mythology is original, or is borrowed from the East, is an
                    interesting question. In some of the Western Isles, the Scandinavian god Odin
                    enters into the popular mythology, a relic, no doubt, of the Norse occupation of
                    the territory. Fairies, or the <hi rend="italic">daoine sιthe</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">sith-ichean,</hi> fill an important place in the mythology of the
                    Highlands. The name of these imaginary beings is derived from their supposed
                    habits. <hi rend="italic">Sith</hi> is a common name in Gaelic for a hill of a
                    peculiar form. As a diminutive it is <hi rend="italic">sιtheaιι,</hi> the word
                    used for green hillocks, which abound throughout the Highlands. These hills are
                    supposed to be the abodes of fairies, who, in consequence, are called <hi
                    rend="italic">daoine</hi><hi rend="italic">sιthe,</hi> or the men of the
                    hillocks. <hi rend="italic">Sïth,</hi> peace, has no part in forming the
                    designation, although often said to have. These beings were the very opposite of
                    peaceful in the popular belief. It is impossible here to give an account of the
                    common belief in the Highlands regarding fairies, but there is a great deal of
                    popular literature taken up with descriptions of it, and with stories regarding
                    these mischievous and meddling beings. They were fond of carrying away young
                    children, and substituting young fairies in their place, to the grief and
                    harassment of the mother. Nor did they confine their assaults to children, but
                    sometimes carried men and women to their underground abodes, where they passed
                    through extraordinary scenes. The Rev. Robert Kirke of Balquhidder wrote an
                    account of the fairies which awakened their anger, and they spirited him away to
                    fairyland. He was able to appear in the room at the baptism of a child born
                    after his removal, when it was arranged that for his deliverance a knife was to
                    be thrown over his head at a certain moment. The hour came, but through some
                    infatuation the party entrusted with the duty failed in the performance, Mr
                    Kirke was not delivered, and is believed to be in fairyland to this day. Similar
                    stories are without number, and show how widely extended the belief in fairies
                    was.</p>
                <p>Witchcraft had a large place in the popular beliefs, and has not lost
                    itιaltogether at the present day. It was supposed possible for a person endowed
                    with this power to inflict great damage upon an adversary. Milk could be
                    abstracted from the cows of a neighbour and brought to swell the produce of the
                    party abstracting it. This belief has been the source of much animosity and
                    strife among neighbours down to the present time. Clay bodies stuck over with
                    pins could be formed representing an adversary, and could be laid in a stream,
                    and as the clay wasted, the body of the man represented pined until he died.
                    This afforded ample room for the exhibition of party or personal hatred, and is
                    not altogether unknown now. The literature of witchcraft is of considerable
                    extent, and consists in tales and forms of exorcism which are very various, and
                    some of them very curious. The forms are all in rhyme, and do not display much
                    of tire genius of poetry; they are usually made up of appeals to saints and
                    apostles, with the occasional introduction of the Virgin Mary. Several of these
                    have been handed down by tradition, and are scattered through various works
                    devoted to Highland lore. Near the valley of the Spey there recently lived a
                    noted wizard, who possessed a charmed bridle which exercised a most powerful
                    influence over all forms of bewitchment. A clergyman, not far from the residence
                    of this man, was on one occasion much disturbed by the state of his cows, which
                    had suddenly ceased to give milk. The neighbours assured the minister that it
                    was witchcraft, and that he ought to send for the man with the charmed bridle,
                    which, very much against his will, he was induced to do. The wizard came, and
                    was told by the clergyman that he had no faith in his witchcraft, but he should
                    very much like to have his counsel as a man of skill. The so-called wizard,
                    understanding with whom he had to deal, at once laid aside all pretension to
                    superhuman power, and asked the minister where his cows usually fed, saying that
                    they would go and take a look at the grass. They did so, when the wizard pointed
                    out a plant, then in flower, which he said was, in that condition, most
                    injurious to cows yielding milk. He advised the minister to keep the cows away
                    from that piece of pasture for a fortnight. This was done, and the cows
                    recovered. The wizard got his fee and a promise that nothing should be said to
                    affect the public confidence <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n19/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0019-0010"/> in his power. This is the kind of witchcraft that
                    has existed all along, and which has cost many poor helpless creatures their
                    lives at the stake.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Topography.—</hi> In dealing with the literature of the
                    Highlands we cannot overlook the topography of the country. It is to be
                    regretted that in Scotlaud we have no such MS. remains, containing topographical
                    terms with their origin, as are to be found in Ireland, nor have we any work on
                    the subject of topography possessed of the slightest authority. But we have
                    numerous ancient charters containing names of places, and we have what are
                    called the <hi rend="italic">retours,</hi> connected with the succession to
                    property throughout the country, and these contain extensive lists with the
                    spelling adopted for the names at different periods. These names belong to
                    different languages. There is apparently an original language, if not more than
                    one, which is now lost. Without this assumption there is no accounting for many
                    of the names applied to natural objects. Then there is the old Norse and the
                    Anglo-Saxon, the one using <hi rend="italic">wick</hi> for a bay, as in
                    Caithness, and the other for a town, as in Roxburghshire; then there is the
                    British, as in the old Strathclyde territory, and the Gaelic. The Gaelic, in its
                    topographical distribution, does not occupy the same field with that occupied by
                    it as a spoken tongue. The spoken language and the topography of Galloway are
                    quite at variance; so with Lewis and others of the Western Isles. The spoken
                    language of Galloway is Scottish, the topography is almost wholly Gaelic. The
                    spoken language of Lewis, Harris, Skye, &amp;c., is Gaelic, the topography is
                    almost wholly old Norse. But one thing is manifest, that Gaelic names are
                    distributed over the whole surface of Scotland, although not in equal
                    proportions. These names contain a history, could it be evolved. They speak of
                    races distinct and successive, although their testimony as to dates is difficult
                    to read. The county names of Scotland in Gaelic are suggestive :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Shetland</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Sialluimn.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Fife</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>. F <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi>
                            hi.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Orkney</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Arcaibh.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Stirling</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">.
                            Sruileadh.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Caithness</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Gallthaobh.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Galloway</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">.
                            Gallthaobh.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sutherland ..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Cataobh.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Dumfries</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">.
                            Dunphris.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ross</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Ros.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Lanark</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">.
                            Lanerch.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cromarty ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Cromhadh.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Argyll</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">.
                            Araghael.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Inverness ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Inbhearnaoise.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Dumbarton</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">.
                            Dwnbhreatuinm</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Nairn.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Inbhearnarunn.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Bute</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">.</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">Boite.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Moray</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Morthaobh.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Linlithgow</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">.
                            Lanneuthaich.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Banff</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Banabh.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Lothian, Μ. &amp; E. <hi
                            rend="italic">Loudaidh.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Aberdeen ....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Abaireadhain.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Renfrew</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">.
                            Rcnfreudh.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Kincardine...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Cinncchardainn.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ayr ,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">(
                            Siorramachd</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Forfar</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Farfair.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">(
                            Adhar.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Perth</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">...
                            Peart.</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Kirkcudbright</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic"
                            >Cillechuibeirt.</hi></p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>This list does not include Peebles (which is probably Celtic), Selkirk, Roxburgh,
                    and Berwick, as there are no Gaelic terms for them, but in the other cases it
                    will be seen to what an extent the county names are really Gaelic. The same is
                    true of names of parishes, which are, to a large extent, Gaelic both in the
                    north and in the south.</p>
                <p>It is to be observed that the Gaelic topography of Scotland differs widely from
                    that of Ireland. The Irish <hi rend="italic">sliabh,</hi> for a mountain, rarely
                    occurs in Scotland, where the word in use chiefly is <hi rend="italic"
                    >bcinn.</hi> It does occur, but the instances are few, while the Scottish <hi
                    rend="italic">ben</hi> is as rare in Ireland. <hi rend="italic">Daile,</hi> a
                    township, is sufficiently frequent in Scotland, but not so much so as the Irish
                    <hi rend="italic">bally.</hi> The word <hi rend="italic">strath,</hi> for a
                    great valley, occurs but rarely in Ireland; in Scotland it abounds over the
                    whole kingdom. The <hi rend="italic">abers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">pits</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">invers</hi> of Scotland are rare in Ireland, or altogether
                    unknown, while there is little resemblance in the names of rivers. These two
                    systems of topography may have originated with the same people, but in one of
                    the sections there were influences manifestly at work which were unknown in the
                    other. Even in the Dalriadic kingdom of Argyll there are features which indicate
                    a marked distinction between the topography and that of Ireland. The study of
                    this subject is full of interest, and is capable of producing important results
                    both linguistic and historical. The field is as yet unoccupied, and affords much
                    to encourage the judicious and painstaking student.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Names of Persons.—</hi> The literature of the Highlands may be
                    held further to include the names of persons as well as those of places. Indeed
                    some of the older MSS. are filled with pedigrees, sometimes of kings, sometimes
                    of lesser persons. Many of these ascend up to Noah, and even to Adam, showing at
                    least that they date since the conversion of the Gael to Christianity. There are
                    several interesting genealogical lists in the volume of transactions published
                    by the Iona Club, and there are MSS. in the Advocates’ Library, Edinburgh, which
                    contain several lists of a similar kind. The descent of family representatives
                    is in these traced up to the original source, which in many cases is found among
                    the ancient Scottish kings. The preparing and continuing of these pedigrees was
                    one of the duties of the ancient bards and sennachies, who transmitted their
                    knowledge of family history from generation to generation. It may be believed
                    that these officials would have a measure of bias in favour of their own
                    patrons, and this may have, in some cases, influenced their accounts of family
                    history: but, upon the whole, there seems to be a large amount of truth in what
                    they have transmitted to us, back to a certain date. The rest is pure fiction. A
                    specimen may be given, extracted from the genealogy of the family of Argyll.</p>
                <p>Genelach mac Cailin Gillespie mac Cailin anann mac Gillespie mac Donclι anaglιa
                    mac Cailin mac Gillespie πιoidħ mac Cailin oig mac Neill mac Cailin moir mac
                    Gillespie mac Dubgaill, &amp;c., and so on through King Arthur up to Seth, the
                    son of Adam, the son of God. In English this is—Tne genealogy of Mac Cailin:
                    Gillespick, son of Colin, son of Gillespick, son of Duncan the fortunate, son of
                    Colin, son of Gillespick thered, son of Colin the young, son of Neil, son of
                    Colin the great, son of Gillespick, son of Dougal, &amp;c. So far the genealogy
                    corresponds nearly with the usual genealogies of the family historians of the
                    house of Argyll. Similar pedigrees are furnished of most of the Highland
                    clans.</p>
                <p>The names of persons among the Gaelic races are for the most part patronymic.</p>
                <p>The first name in its earlier form is usually descriptive, <hi rend="italic"
                    >a⅛Dοnnghαl, Dubhghal, Bοnnachadh, Gillespnιig,—</hi> Donald, Dougal, Duncan,
                    Gillespick,—the brown man, the black man, the brown-faced man, the servant of
                    the bishop; often it is taken from the Scriptures, as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eoin</hi> John, <hi rend="italic">Scumas</hi> James, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Τornas</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Tabhas</hi> Thomas, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ρcadar</hi> Peter, &amp;c.; some of the names come from the Norse, as <hi
                    rend="italic">Toτcuil</hi> Tor-quil, <hi rend="italic">Tormaid</hi> Norman, <hi
                    rend="italic">Aulaidh</hi> 01ave, <hi rend="italic">Leod</hi> Leod, and some ar⅛
                    borrowed from the Normans, as <hi rend="italic">Uillcam</hi> William, <hi
                    rend="italic">Eanraic</hi> Henry, &amp;c. The surnames are for the most part
                    patronymics, as <hi rend="italic">Eoin Mac Neill,</hi> John the son of Neil; and
                    in case there should be another John M ’ Neil, another step is introduced, as
                    <hi rend="italic">Eoin Mac Neill mhic Dhornhnaill,</hi> and perhaps a third
                    until the person 13 thoroughly identified. Sometimes there is a reduplication of
                    the sonship, as <hi rend="italic">Mac Mhic Alasdair, Mac Mhic</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Allein,</hi> the son of the son of Alexander or Allan, names of
                    important Highland chiefs. In other cases the surname is descriptive, <hi
                    rend="italic">asDubh</hi> black, <hi rend="italic">Eoin dιιbh</hi> Black John,
                    <hi rend="italic">Beag</hi> little, <hi rend="italic">Mor</hi> big, <hi
                    rend="italic">Buidh</hi> yellow, <hi rend="italic">Crom</hi> bent, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ruadh</hi> red, &amp;c., whence many well known English names are
                    derived. A large number of Highland names and surnames are ecclesiastical, as
                    those derived from St John, St Columba, St Cattan, St Bridget, and others, and
                    thus become helps to historical inquiry. One thing is somewhat remarkable, that
                    there is not an <hi rend="italic">Cl,</hi> in accordance with Irish
                    nomenclature, among the Scottish Celts. The old O’Duinn of Argyle is lost, and
                    the patronymic of the Celt is marked by the uniform use of <hi rend="italic"
                    >mac,</hi> representing a son, as <hi rend="italic">O'</hi> does a grandson. The
                    age of fixed family names seems no older than the age of charters. Previous to
                    that patronymics universally prevailed, but when charters were taken fixed names
                    were essential to their value.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Proverbs.—</hi> From name3 of persons we may pass to proverbs
                    as a part, and a very curious part, of Gaelic literature. Few languages so
                    abound in proverbs, and proverbs of a very clever and popular caste. A
                    Highlander seldom gives expression to an important sentiment without backing it
                    with a proverb, and these give force and pungency to what he says. A collection
                    of these proverbs was made, in the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n20/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0020-0011"/> year 1819, by the Rev. Donald Mackintosh, and, to
                    form some idea of the number of them, it is only necessary to observe that,
                    under the letter “I” alone, they reach the number of 382 in the first edition of
                    the book. A large number of these proverbial sayings escaped the notice of Mr
                    Mackintosh, and additions were made in the second edition, while some of the
                    very best are not recorded even yet. Proverbial sayings in English are
                    represented by sayings of a different kind in Gaelic, having the same meaning.
                    “There is many a slip between the cup and the lip” is represented by <hi
                    rend="italic">Is</hi><hi rend="italic">le</hi><hi rend="italic">duine an</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ni</hi><hi rend="italic">a shluigeas e, αch cha leis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">an ni</hi><hi rend="italic">a chagaineas e,</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> u</hi> What a man swallows is his own, but not what he chews.” “It
                    never rains but it pours” is represented by <hi rend="italic">An uair a tlιeid
                    a</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >chailleach</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript"> ,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">n a ruith, theid i</hi><hi rend="italic">’n</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >a deann-ruith,</hi> “When the old woman takes to running, she runs with a
                    will.” “Sour grapes ”— <hi rend="italic">Mionnan a’ bhaird ris a</hi> ’ <hi
                    rend="italic">chaisteal, cha teid mi</hi><hi rend="italic">fhéin</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">do’n chaisteal bhreun, cha teid, cha leig iad ann mi, “</hi> The
                    bard’s oath to the castle, ‘ I went go to the vile castle; no, they won’t let me
                    in.’” The Gaelic proverbs are full of interest, and add much to the power of
                    either speech or writing when skilfully used.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sgeulachdan, or Tales of Fiction.—</hi> These at one time
                    abounded in the Highlands, and had much in common with the tales collected and
                    published by Grimm and Dasent, from the German and the Norse. Until lately,
                    these tales were entirely oral, and were little known beyond certain portions of
                    the West Highlands. Recently they have been collected, translated, and edited,
                    with peculiar care ’ and skill, by Mr J. F. Campbell, in four 8vo volumes. This
                    is a real addition to Gaelic literature, and Mr Campbell has laid every friend
                    of that literature under obligation. One real service it has done in preserving
                    for us admirable specimens of the most idiomatic and popular forms of the Gaelic
                    language. We have it there as used by the tellers of popular tales among the
                    people for generations. Whence many of these tales have come it is hard to say,
                    but tales have been collected in the small islands south of Barra, where the
                    people seldom tread the soil of even their main island, containing ideas and
                    forms of thought which never could have originated there, and the preservation
                    of which, in such a locality, is a remarkable fact. Are they relics of a higher
                    civilization existing in ages long gone by? It is remarkable that the Thomas the
                    Rhymer of Lowlaud tradition is well known in the traditions of the Highlands,
                    and that stories of him related on the borders in broad Scotch are related in
                    the Highlands in Gaelic as tales of great antiquity.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Clan History.—</hi> A portion of the literature of the Gaelic
                    Celt consists of clau history. The clan system does not seem to be very ancient.
                    In all probability it dates from the period when the Gaelic kingdom of Scotland
                    ceased to exist. It has been already said to date from the era of charters. But
                    the two eras are pretty nearly identical. Down to the reign of Malcolm III. the
                    Gaelic kingdom appears to have been to a large extent homogeneous. There were no
                    elements in it but what were Celtic, as it never really embraced within it the
                    Scandinavian sections. Then the land was governed by its <hi rend="italic"
                    >maormors</hi> and <hi rend="italic">toiseachs,</hi> men who represented the
                    central governing power. It would seem that when, in the reign of David I., the
                    kingdom became largely Anglo-Saxon and Anglo-Norman, the Gaelic people became
                    estranged from their native kings, and gathered themselves in sections under the
                    sway of their own chiefs; and hence came chiefs and clans, instead of a king and
                    his subjects forming a united nation. The change was a serious one for the
                    Gaelic people, as they never became again what they had been before. Clan names
                    appear at an early period, and in some form or other must have existed before
                    the time of the Saxonized kings; but not one of the great clans of Highland
                    history—the Macdonalds, the Macleans, the Campbells, the Macleods, the
                    Mackenzie^ the Mackintoshes, or others—appears at all. In the book of Deer,
                    supposed to be of the 11th or 12th century, the names of two clans—the clan
                    Morgan and the clan Canan— appear; but it is very questionable whether these
                    represent any clan existing now, although clan Morgan is said to be the old name
                    of the Mackays of Strathnaver. But the names in that interesting record are for
                    the most part purely patronymic, and do not indicate any connexion with existing
                    clans. The fact is that, till very recently, the clan name was confined to the
                    chief, as records of old deeds and processes at law serve to show.</p>
                <p>The Gaelic historical literature of one kind or another is of considerable
                    extent, and consists of relics, written and traditional, of the old sennachies
                    or family historians. In certain sections of the country the local traditions
                    are full of the stories of old feuds, and, though not to be implicitly relied
                    on, contain usually an element of truth. In Sutherland the feuds of the
                    Sutherlands and the Mackays, in Lewis those of the Mackenzies and Macleods, in
                    Skye the feuds of the M <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> Leods and the Macdonalds,
                    in eastern Inverness-shire· those of the Mackintoshes and Cummings, in Lochaber
                    those of the Mackintoshes and the Camerons, in Perthshire those of the Campbell
                    3 and the Macgregors, and others in other quarters are largely related. Native
                    accounts of the clans were sometimes committed to writing, a specimen of which
                    appears in the transactions of the Iona Club. For a good deal of what is
                    historical regarding the Highlands, recourse must be had to the Irish Annals,
                    which occasionally refer to events occurring in Scotland.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">MS. Literature.—</hi> The written Gaelic literature was at its
                    earlier period so mixed up with that of Ireland that it is not easy in every
                    instance to distinguish them. The early church of both countries was one, and
                    the early literature was the offspring of the early church. The very first
                    notices we have of the church, whether among the mission institutes of Ireland
                    or in Iona, indicate the existence and extensive cultivation of a native
                    literature. The transcription or translation of portions of the Scriptures is
                    shown to have been one of the frequent exercises of the early missionaries, and
                    they all learned to write the same dialect and make use of the same letters.
                    Many of the MSS. written in Iona may be credited to Ireland, and <hi
                    rend="italic">vice versa</hi>; and writings found in Continental libraries may
                    be presumed to have been the work of Scottish as truly as of Irish writers. The
                    early treatises, and glosses upon Latin treatises, on theological and other
                    subjects still existing in the early Gaelic dialect are numerous, and have
                    afforded materials for the] acute and masterly criticism of Zeuss, De Nigra,
                    Stokes, and others; and these are accompanied by treatises on grammar, history,
                    medicine, astrology, metaphysics, poetry, and similar subjects, which are of
                    much interest. Most of these remains are found in the collections in Trinity
                    College, Dublin, and in the library of the Irish Royal Academy; but there are
                    numerous remains in the Edinburgh Advocates’ Library, which prove at least that
                    there were in Scotland persons who valued and collected this literature. There
                    can be no doubt that there were many contributors to it as well.</p>
                <p>The earliest specimen of Gaelic writing, which can be pronounced to be Scottish
                    beyond any question, is the <hi rend="italic">Boole of Deer,</hi> said already
                    to be a work of the 11th or 12th century. The book itself consists of portions
                    of the New Testament written in Latin. The Gaelic portiou consists of historical
                    references, with notices of grants of land bestowed on the old monastery of
                    Deer, in Aberdeenshire. These references and notices are, for the most part,
                    written on the margin. They show that, at the time the book was written, the
                    Gaelic language was used, both for speaking and waiting, in the district around
                    Deer, where it is now unknown<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n21/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0021-0012"/> except in the topography. There is not a shade of
                    difference between the language of the <hi rend="italic">Book of Deer</hi> and
                    the language of the Irish writings of the same age. The following specimen of
                    the notices of grants of land may be interesting :— <hi rend="italic">Donchad
                    mac mec bead mec hided dorat αchad madchor docrist acus drostaη</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">acnsdocholuimcUle</hi><hi rend="italic">insôre</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">gobrdd malechi acusc6mgell acusgille crist mac finguni imιdienαsi
                    intestes, &amp;c.</hi> “Duncan, son of MacBeth, sou of Idid, gave</p>
                <p>Achad Madchor to Christ, and to Drostan, and to Columcille, in freedom for ever;
                    Malechi, and Comgall, and Gilchrist, son of Fingon, witnesses in proof of it.”
                    The notice of grauts continue in similar form, being records kept within the
                    monastery of what had been given. The <hi rend="italic">Book of Deer</hi> is a
                    work of much interest to the Gaelic scholar, and his best thanks are due to the
                    Spalding Club and the late Dr John Stuart for the excellent volume they have
                    published, containing all that is interesting in the original, with a full and
                    learned account of it.</p>
                <p>Of the period immediately after the <hi rend="italic">Book of Deer</hi> there are
                    several MS. remains of Scottish Gaelic writing in existence. There is the
                    Glenmasan MS. in the Edinburgh Advocates’ Library, inscribed with the date 1238,
                    and containing several interesting fragments. Here we find the famous lay of
                    Deirdre or Darthula, connected with the story of the sons of Usnoth. The whole
                    character of this MS. is identical with that of the Irish MSS., and yet it is
                    manifestly a Scottish work. There are lives of saints preserved; one of these,
                    in the Advocates’ Library, is the life of St Findchua. Mr Skene, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Chronicles of the Picts and Scots,</hi> gives transcripts of
                    several important MSS., as the Duan Albanach, or poetical accounts of the
                    Scottish kings, recited by the royal bard at the coronation of Malcolm Kenmore.
                    This was copied from an Irish MS., but is manifestly a Scottish composition. The
                    bards of both Ireland aud Scotland often crossed the Irish Channel, and their
                    works were well known on both sides of it.</p>
                <p>The 14th and 15th centuries were a period of revival of literature over the whole
                    continent of Europe, and the Celts of Great Britain and Ireland felt the
                    impulse. This was a period of much writing both in Ireland and in Scotland. The
                    remains that exist are of a varied kind, and are numerous, especially those of
                    the 15th century. Of this century is the only Gaelic charter that we possess,
                    which is printed, with a translation, in the <hi rend="italic">National Records
                    of Scotland.</hi> Of this age also are numerous medical MSS. Some of these
                    belonged to the famous family of Beatons, hereditary physicians to the Lords of
                    the Isles, and contain accounts of such remedies as were believed at the time to
                    have efficacy in the cure of disease. Others are metaphysical treatises, while
                    others deal with what were .looked upon as the great and important mysteries of
                    astrology. Of this period also are most of the written genealogies that remain.
                    The remarkable thing is the extent to which the Gaelic language bears the marks
                    of cultivation at the time. In both medicine and metaphysics words are found to
                    express the most abstract ideae, which could not be understood by the modern
                    Highlander. As has already been said, some ©f these writings are translations
                    from Arabic writers, as Averroes, Avicenna, Iacobus de Forlivio, and others. The
                    state of learning at the time in the Highlands was not behind that in the rest
                    of the kingdom. The clergy and the physicians, and even the bards, were
                    possessed of real learning, and have left evidence of it.</p>
                <p>The 16th century was the period of two important additions to Gaelic literature.
                    The first of these was what is called “The Dean of Lismore’s book,” a collection
                    of poetical pieces, and an obituary, chiefly of the M*Gregor chiefs, made about
                    the year 1512. The work has recently been transcribed, translated, and edited,
                    with notes by the Rev. Dr M <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> Lauchlan, and an
                    introduction and additional notes by Mr W. F. Skene. The work is one which has
                    helped to settle several interesting questions connected with Gaelic literature.
                    It makes clear that, down to the period of the dean of Lismore of 1512, there
                    was much in common between the Celtic scholars and bards of Ireland and those of
                    Scotland, while the latter were striking out a course for themselves, in laying
                    aside the Irish letter and orthography, and in using the Saxon letter and an
                    orthography almost purely phonetic. The dean of Lismore’s book is a substantial
                    addition to the literature of the Gael. The same century furnished us with
                    another important addition in the translation of the prayer-book usually called
                    “John Knox’s Liturgy” iuto Gaelic, by John Carswell, the bishop of the Isles.
                    This is the first Gaelic book that ever was printed, and bears the date of 1567.
                    There was till very recently only one complete copy of this work in existence,
                    that in the library of the duke of Argyll; but now the book has been reprinted,
                    edited by Dr M <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> Lauchlan, who has given an English
                    translation, and such notices of the life of Carswell as very scanty materials
                    would permit. This book is printed in the Roman letter. The publication of
                    Carswell’s Gaelic prayer-book would seem to indicate that at the time of its
                    publication the Highlanders could read Gaelic, and that they were familiar with
                    the dialect then in use among scholars both in Scotland and Ireland.</p>
                <p>Of the 17th century not many remains exist. Calvin’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catechism</hi> was published about the beginning of the century, probably
                    translated by Carswell, and published long after his death. A copy is now hardly
                    to be found. But two important contributions were made towards the close of the
                    century. The one of these was the metrical translation of the Gaelic Psalms,
                    executed both by the synod of Argyll and the Rev. Robert Kirke of Balquhidder;
                    and the other was an edition, in the Roman letter, of Bedell's Irish Bible for
                    the use of the Highlanders of Scotland. The first fifty of the psalms by the
                    synod were published in 1659, and the whole psalter was completed in 1694. Kirke
                    published his version in 1684. Both are highly creditable performances, and
                    Kirke is entitled to special commendation, inasmuch as the Gaelic language was
                    acquired by him after he was settled in the Highlands. Kirke’s version of the
                    Irish Bible for the use of the Highlanders was published in 1690. The New
                    Testament is that of O’Donnell. This work is accompanied by a glossary including
                    the words in the Irish Bible not generally in use in the Highlands. The book was
                    for a time used in Highland churches, but the Irish Bible, in the Irish letter,
                    was well known and read in the Highlands— both in churches and in families.</p>
                <p>The 18th century was productive of large additions to Gaelic literature, partly
                    due to an awakening of religious life, partly to the Jacobite rising, and partly
                    to the progress of literary culture. In the beginning of the century Lhuyd
                    produced his <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary,</hi> accompanied by a few interesting
                    Gaelic compositions from the Highlands. About the same time, the synod of Argyll
                    executed a translation of the Confession of Faith and Larger and Shorter
                    Catechisms. These were published in 1725. M <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi>
                    Donald's <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary</hi> appeared in the year 1741. It is the
                    first attempt at anything like a vocabulary of the Gaelic. It is of little value
                    except as being the first book in which the orthography approached to that of
                    the modern Gaelic. During this century several famous Gaelic bards flourished.
                    M‘Donald, the author of the <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary,</hi> filled the
                    country with Jacobite and other songs. The former are of a violent character,
                    indicating keen partisanship with the exiled Stuarts. MTntyre of Glenorchy,
                    commonly called Duncan Ban, flourished about the same period, and, though he was
                    a Jacobite at first, this appeared less in his compositions than in M <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Donald ’ s. His hunting and other descriptive songs
                    are admirable. M‘Kay or Calder, usually called Rob Donn, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n22/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0022-0013"/> the Reay bard, flourished about the same time,
                    and has left numerous admirable pieces of Gaelic poetry. Others were also
                    successful composers, such as William Ross of Gairloch, and the religious poet
                    of the Highlands, Dougal Buchanan. And towards the close of the century was
                    published Gillies’s <hi rend="italic">Collection of Gaelic Poetry·,</hi> one of
                    the best collections we possess, containing, as it does, many authentic pieces
                    of Ossianic poetry taken down when the old clan system was still in force in the
                    Highlands to a larger extent than now. But the 18th century was distinguished by
                    two works of special interest, in different departments. The first of these was
                    the Gaelic translation of the Bible, and the second was Macpherson’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Ossian.</hi> The former was executed chiefly by the Rev. James
                    Stewart, of Killin, and his son the Rev. Dr John Stewart, of Luss,—two eminent
                    scholars, who had all the soundness of judgment necessary for such a work. This
                    translation of the Bible has been most popular in the Highlands and throughout
                    the British colonies where the Gaelic is still spoken. The Gaelic learner cannot
                    do better at the outset than master the Gaelic Bible. Macpherson’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Ossian</hi> appeared about the same time, but not in Gaelic. It
                    appeared first in English dress. This was the only mode of making the general
                    public acquainted with it. Macpherson’s first small volume of fragments appeared
                    altogether in English; it would have been well if both the original and the
                    translation had been published simultaneously. The only part of the Gaelic that
                    was published before 1818 was what is called a “Specimen of the Original of
                    Temora,” given with the other poems in English in 1762. The opinions with regard
                    to the authenticity of Macpherson’s <hi rend="italic">Ossian</hi> are as various
                    as ever, and yet considerable progress has been made in the discovery of truth,
                    which all parties are prepared to acknowledge. It has been established that
                    poems ascribed to Ossian have been known and written down in the Highlands for
                    300 years, that many of them have been handed down by tradition, that these were
                    fragments referring to certain important events in the history of the Gaelic
                    race, and that there was nothing to make it improbable that such poems as those
                    translated by Macpherson could have existed. Further, it is clear that the
                    Highlanders at once, whether they knew the pieces or not as given by Macpherson,
                    recognized them as in a style familiar to them, and as relating to persons and
                    events with which they were familiar. That Macpherson found materials for his
                    work in the Highlands is beyond a doubt·, and it seems quite as manifest that he
                    used very considerable liberties with them in order to serve his object of
                    producing a great Gaelic epic poem or poems. In 1818 the full Gaelic version was
                    printed, long after the death of James Macpherson. <hi rend="italic">The Poems
                    of Ossian,</hi> as collected, and translated, and edited by Macpherson, are a
                    valuable and interesting addition to Gaelic literature, and enter largely into
                    the history of the modern literature of Europe. The Saxon may have his doubts
                    about Ossian, and may have little scruple or delicacy in stating them, but the
                    Gael knows more about Ossian than he does about Milton, and is more familiar
                    with his heroes than with those of Homer.</p>
                <p>The 19th century has seen many large contributions to the literature of the
                    Gaelic Celt. It has shared in the general progress of learning, and with this it
                    has risen in the estimation of the scholars of Europe. Grammars and dictionaries
                    have been compiled; magazines of various kinds have been started and carried on
                    for a time with much vigour; collections, such as Mackenzie’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Beauties of Gaelic Poetry,</hi> have been made; and such provisions have been
                    laid up for the future as to secure an ample supply of materials for the
                    scholars of a coming age. That appears to be the special work laid upon the
                    scholars of the present time. They have to collect materials and commit them to
                    writing, and to describe the peculiarities that are distinctive of a living
                    language, for the use of those who hereafter can only study it as existing in
                    books, where emphasis, and tone, and accent are altogether unknown, and where
                    the comments and expositions of living men, familiar with the language and the
                    literature from their childhood, are altogether awanting. For that the Gaelic
                    language is in a state of decay is manifest to the most ordinary observer. And
                    the decay is twofold, being both within and without. Within, the vocabulary is
                    waning, and English words are coming into use. Gaelic idioms are in like manner
                    disappearing, and English idioms replacing them; while from without, under the
                    influence of education, immigration, steamboats, railways, and other modern
                    devices, English is rapidly finding its way into the land, and pushing the
                    ancient tongue out of it. When this process is completed, a change will befall
                    the people. too, for there is no doubt that there is a close relation between
                    the character of a language and the character of the people who use it; so that,
                    when the Gaelic disappears, many of the features distinctive of the Highland
                    character will disappear along with it. In some respects this will be cause of
                    regret; in others perhaps it will not.</p>
                <p>At the close of the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Celtic</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Literature</hi> a list is given of the existing MS. remains of Gaelic
                    literature. It may interest readers and aid students of Gaelic to furnish here a
                    list of some of the more important printed books in the language. They are as
                    follows :—</p>
                <p>Fragments in <hi rend="italic">Report of Highland</hi><hi rend="italic">Society
                    on Ossian·,</hi> Fragments in <hi rend="italic">Chronicles of Picts</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">and Scots</hi><hi rend="italic">; The</hi><hi rend="italic">Book
                    of Deer; The Book of</hi><hi rend="italic">the Dean</hi><hi rend="italic">of
                    Lismore</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> CarsewelΓs Prayer Book; Bedell’s and
                    O’Donnell’s Bible; The Gaelic Psalter, various editions; The Confession of
                    Faith, and Catechisms; Lhuyd’s <hi rend="italic">Vocabulary</hi>; M'Donald’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Vocabulary, Ossian's Poems·,</hi> Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Sean
                    Dana·,</hi> Gillies’s <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi><hi rend="italic">of
                    Poems·,</hi> Macdonald⅛ <hi rend="italic">Poems·,</hi> M ’ Intyre ’ s <hi
                    rend="italic">Poems·,</hi> Eob Donn’s <hi rend="italic">Poems·,</hi> Dougal
                    Buchanan’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns·,</hi> M‘Callum’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Collection of</hi><hi rend="italic">Poetry,</hi> The Gaelic Bible; Stewart’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Collection of Poems·,</hi> Turner’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Collection</hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi><hi rend="italic">Poems·,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Sacred Poetry of the North,</hi> edited by Rose; <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Beauties of</hi><hi rend="italic">Gaelic Poetry</hi>,M‘Kenzie; Grant’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Hymns·,</hi> MTntosh’s <hi rend="italic">Gaelic Proverbs</hi>;
                    Stewart’s <hi rend="italic">Gaelic Grammar</hi>; Munro’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gaelic Gram</hi><hi rend="italic">mar·,</hi> Highland Society’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Gaelic Dictionary,</hi> Armstrong’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gaelic</hi><hi rend="italic">Dictionary,</hi> M'Alpin’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gaelic Dictionary, Highland Tales,</hi> collected and edited by J. F. Campbell;
                    <hi rend="italic">Leabhar na Feinn,</hi> by J. F. Campbell; <hi rend="italic"
                    >An</hi><hi rend="italic">Duanaire,</hi> by D. C. M <hi rend="superscript">
                    i</hi> Pherson; <hi rend="italic">An Teachdaire</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gaelach,</hi> by Rev. Dr M'Leod; <hi rend="italic">An Fhiauis,</hi> by Rev. Dr
                    Mackay; <hi rend="italic">An Gaidhcal,</hi> a magazine; numerous translations
                    from the English, chiefly religious works; Connell’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Astronomy</hi>; M'Kenzie’s <hi rend="italic">History of Scotland·,</hi> besides
                    many others. (T. M <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
