<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0622-0605-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GINSENG</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 605</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qn25">Ginseng</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42f7jq7r">Drugs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nr4v">Box</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4f766779">Boxing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp6g">Cossacks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:942792">Ginseng</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:837290">Boxing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:837281">Boxes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1051955">Panax</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GINSENG</label>, the root of a species of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Panax</hi> (P. <hi rend="italic">Ginseng,</hi> Meyer), belonging to the natural
                    order <hi rend="italic">Araliaceae,</hi> is a very celebrated Chinese medicine.
                    The demand is so great that many other roots are substituted for it, notably
                    that of <hi rend="italic">Panax quinquefolium,</hi> Linn., distinguished as
                    American ginseng, and imported from the United States. At one time the ginseng
                    obtained from Manchuria was considered to be the finest quality, and in
                    consequence became so scarce that an imperial edict was issued prohibiting its
                    collection. That prepared in Corea is now the most esteemed variety. The root of
                    the wild plant is preferred to that of cultivated ginseng, and the older the
                    plant the better is the quality of the root considered to be. Lockhart states
                    that all the ginseng collected in the Chinese empire is imperial property, and
                    is sold to those who have the privilege of dealing in it at its weight in gold.
                    Great care is taken in the preparation of the drug. The account given by
                    Koempfer of the preparation of nindsin, the root of <hi rend="italic">Sium
                    ηinsi,</hi> Thunb., in the Corea, will give a good idea of the preparation of
                    ginseng, ninsi being a similar drug of supposed weaker virtue, obtained from a
                    different plan∙t, and often confounded with ginseng. “In the beginning of winter
                    nearly all the population of Sjansai turn out to collect the root, and make
                    preparations for sleeping in the fields. The root, when collected, is macerated
                    for three days in fresh water, or water in which rice has been boiled twice; it
                    is then suspended in a closed vessel over the fire, and afterwards dried, until
                    from the base to the middle it assumes a hard, resinous, and translucent
                    appearance, which is considered a proof of its good quality.”</p>
                <p>Ginseng of good quality generally occurs in hard, rather brittle, translucent
                    pieces, about the size of the little finger, and varying in length from 2 to 4
                    inches. The taste is mucilaginous, sweetish, and slightly bitter and aromatic.
                    The root is frequently forked, and it is probably owing to this circumstance
                    that medicinal properties were in the first place attributed to it, its
                    resemblance to the body of a man being supposed to indicate that it could
                    restore virile power to the aged and impotent. In price it varies from 6 or 12
                    dollars to the enormous sum of 300 or 400 dollars an ounce. Root of this quality
                    can of course only be purchased by the most wealthy, and the greatest care is
                    taken of such pieces by the vendors.</p>
                <p>Lockhart gives a graphic description of a visit to a ginseng merchant. Opening
                    the outer box, the merchant removed several paper parcels which appeared to fill
                    the box, but under them was a second box, or perhaps two small boxes, which,
                    when taken out, showed the bottom of the large box and all the intervening space
                    filled with more paper parcels. These parcels, he said, ’ ‘ contained quicklime,
                    for the purpose of absorbing any moisture and keeping the boxes quite dry, the
                    lime being packed in paper for the sake of cleanliness. The smaller box, which
                    held the ginseng, was lined with sheet-lead; the ginseng further enclosed in
                    silk wrappers was kept in little silken-covered boxes. Taking up a piece, he
                    would request his visitor not to breathe upon it, nor handle it; he would dilate
                    upon the many merits of the drag and the cures it had effected. The cover of the
                    root, according to its quality, was silk, either embroidered or plain, cotton
                    cloth, or paper.” In China the ginseng is often sent to friends as a valuable
                    present; in such cases, “accompanying the medicine is usually given a small,
                    beautifully-finished double kettle, in which the ginseng is prepared as follows.
                    The inner kettle is made of silver, and between this and the outside vessel,
                    which is a copper jacket, is a small space for holding water. The silver kettle,
                    which fits on a ring near the top of the outer covering, has a cup-like cover in
                    which rice is placed with a little water; the ginseng is put in the inner vessel
                    with water, a cover is placed oyer the whole, and the apparatus is put on the
                    fire. When the rice in the cover is sufficiently cooked, the medicine is ready,
                    and is then eaten by the patient, who drinks the ginseng tea at the same time.”
                    The dose of the root is from 60 to 90 grains. During the use of the drug
                    tea-drinking is forbidden for at least a mouth, but no other change is made in
                    the diet. It is taken in the morning before breakfast, from.three to eight days
                    together, and sometimes it is taken in the evening before going to bed.</p>
                <p>At one time it was proposed by some Russians to establish ginseng plantations,
                    with the view of growing the root as an important article of trade with China.
                    Ginseng is also cultivated in Japan, having been introduced from Corea; but,
                    although it grows more luxuriantly there than in its native country, the root is
                    considered to be much less active. This may be due to the fact that, while in
                    the mountains of Corea the root is perennial, in Japan the plant runs to seed
                    the first year, and becomes annual. Europeans have hitherto failed to discover
                    any remarkable properties in the drug. Dr Porter Smith, however, mentions having
                    seen some cases in which life appeared to be prolonged for a time by its use;
                    and Μ. Maack states that one of the Cossacks of his party, having chopped off a
                    finger accidentally with an axe, applied ointment made from ginseng, and the
                    wound healed rapidly. Its properties, which may be likened to those of the
                    mandrake of Scripture, are perhaps dependent in great measure upon the faith of
                    the patient.</p>
                <p>See Porter Smith, Chinese Materia Medica, p. 103; Reports on Trade at the Treaty
                    Ports of China, 1868, p. 63; Lockhart, Med. Missionary in China, 2d ed., p. 107;
                    Bull, de la Société Imperiale de Nat. de Moscow, 1865, No. 1, pp. 70-76;
                    Pharmaceutical Journal, (2), vol. iii. pp. 197, 333, (2), vol. ix. p. 77; Lewis,
                    Materia Medica, p. 324; Journal of Botany, 1864, p. 320; Geoffroy, Trad, de
                    Materié Medicale, t. ii. p. 112; Loureiro, Flora Cochinchinensis, p. 656;
                    Koempfer, Amoenitates Exoticae, p. 824.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
