<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0024-0015-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GAINSBOROUGH, Thomas</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 15</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz3256r">Storms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4222r689">Boys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh24">Portraits</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1072324">Portraits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:828732">Baths</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100369">Rooms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:837358">Boys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n24/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GAINSBOROUGH, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label>
                    (1727—1788), a painter famous for the truth and elegance of his portraits, and
                    for the simple beauty of his landscapes, was born at Sudbury, Suffolk, in the
                    year 1727. His father, who carried on the business of a woollén crape-maker in
                    that town, was of a respectable character and family, and was noted for his
                    skill in fencing; his mother excelled in flower-painting, and encouraged her son
                    in the use of the pencil. There were nine children of the marriage. At ten years
                    old, Gainsborough had sketched every fine tree and picturesque cottage near
                    Sudbury, and at fifteen, having filled his taskbooks with caricatures of his
                    schoolmaster, forged his father’s handwriting to get a holiday, and sketched the
                    portrait of a man whom he had detected in the act of robbing his father’s
                    orchard, he was allowed to follow the bent of his genius in London, under such
                    advantages as Hayman, the historical painter, and the academy in St Martin’s
                    Lane, could afford, Three years of study in the metropolis were succeeded by two
                    years of idleness in the country. Here he fell in love with Margaret Burr, a
                    young lady of many charms, including an annuity of £200, married her after a
                    short courtship, and, at the age of twenty, became a householder in Ipswich, his
                    rent being £6 a year. The annuity was reported to come from Margaret’s real (not
                    her putative) father, who was one of the exiled Stuart princes, or else the duke
                    of Bedford. At Ipswich, Gainsborough tells us, he was “chiefly in the face-way,”
                    though his sitters were not so numerous as to prevent him from often rambling
                    with his friend Joshua Kirby (president of the Society of Artists) on the banks
                    of the Orwell, from painting many landscapes with an attention to details which
                    his later works never exhibited, or from joining a musical club, and
                    entertaining himself and his fellow-townsmen by giving concerts. But as he
                    advanced in years he became ambitious of advancing in reputation. Bath was then
                    the general resort of wealth and fashion, and to that city, towards the close of
                    the year 1759, he removed with his wife and two daughters, the only issue of
                    their marriage. His studio in the circus was soon thronged with visitors; he
                    gradually raised his price for a half-length portrait from 5 to 40 guineas, and
                    for a whole-length from 8 to 100 guineas. Among his sitters at this period were
                    the authors Sterne and Richardson, and the actors Quin, Henderson, and Garrick.
                    Meanwhile he contributed both, portraits and landscapes to the annual
                    exhibitions in London. He indulged his taste for music by learning to play the
                    viol-di-gamba, the harp, the hautboy, the violoncello, His house harboured
                    Italian, German, French, and English musicians. He haunted the green-room of
                    Palmer’s theatre, and painted gratuitously the portraits of many of the actors.
                    He gave away his sketches and landscapes to any one who had taste or assurance
                    enough to ask for them; and in the summer of 1774, having already attained a
                    position of great prosperity, he took his departure for the metropolis, and
                    fixed his residence at Schomberg House, Pall Mall, a noble mansion still
                    standing, for which the artist paid £300 a year,</p>
                <p>Gainsborough had not been many months in London ere he received a summons to the
                    palace, and to the end of his career he divided with West the favour of the
                    court, and with Reynolds the favour of the town. Sheridan, Burke, Clive,
                    Blackstone, Hurd, were among the number of those who sat to him. But in London
                    as in Bath his landscapes were exhibited, were commended, won the good opinion
                    of Walpole the fastidious and Wolcot the surly, and were year after year
                    returned to him, “till they stood,” says Sir William Beechey, “ranged in long
                    lines from his hall to his <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n25/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0025-0016"/> painting-room.” Gainsborough was a member of the
                    Royal Academy, but in 1784, being dissatisfied with the position assigned on the
                    exhibition-walls to his portrait of the three princesses, he withdrew that and
                    his other pictures, and he never afterwards exhibited there. lu February 1788,
                    while witnessing the trial of Warren Hastings, he felt an extraordinary chill at
                    the back of his neck; this was the beginning of a cancer (or, as some say, a
                    malignant wen) which proved fatal on 2d August of the same year.</p>
                <p>Gainsborough was tall, fair, and handsome, generous, impulsive to the point of
                    capriciousness, easily irritated, not of bookish likings. The property which he
                    left at his death was not large. One of his daughters, Mary, had married
                    contrary to his wishes, and was subject to fits of mental aberration.</p>
                <p>Gainsborough and Reynolds rank side by side as the greatest portrait painters of
                    the English school. It is difficult to say which stands the higher of the two,
                    although Reynolds may claim to have worked with a nearer approach to even and
                    demonstrable excellence. In grace, spirit, and lightness of insight and of
                    touch, Gainsborough is peculiarly eminent. His handling was slight for the most
                    part, and somewhat arbitrary, but in a high degree masterly; and his landscapes
                    and rustic compositions are not less gifted than his portraits. Among his finest
                    works are the likenesses of Lady Ligonier, the duchess of Devonshire, Master
                    Buttall (the Blue Boy), Mrs Sheridan and MrsTickell, Orpin the parish-clerk
                    (National Gallery), the Hon. Mrs Graham (Scottish National Gallery), his own
                    portrait (Royal Academy), Mrs Siddons (National Gallery); also the Cottage Door,
                    the Market Cart, the Return from Harvest, the Woodman and his Dog in a Storm
                    (destroyed by fire), and Waggon and Horses passing a Brook (National Gallery).
                    He made a vast number of drawings and sketches.</p>
                <p>In 1788 Philip Thicknesse, lieut.-governor of Landguard Fort, who had been active
                    in promoting Gainsborough’s fortunes at starting, but was not on good terms with
                    him when he left Bath, gave to the world <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Sketch of the Life and Paintings</hi><hi rend="italic">of
                    Thomas</hi><hi rend="italic">Gainsborough·,</hi> in 1829 Allan Cunningham
                    published a memoir of him in his <hi rend="italic">Lives of the Painters·,</hi>
                    and in 1856 there appeared <hi rend="italic">A Life</hi><hi rend="italic">of
                    Thomas Gainsborough, R.A.,</hi> by G. W. Fulcher.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
