<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0171-0160-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GENTILI, Alberico (9th edition, volume 10, page
                    160)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz36">Inns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c355">Flight</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085685">Questioning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1062841">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078722">Programs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n171/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GENTILI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Alberico</hi></label>
                    (1552-1608), may fairly be called the founder of the science of international
                    law. He was the second son of Matteo Gentili, a physician of noble family and
                    scientific eminence, and was born 14th January 1552’ at Sanginesio,.a small town
                    of the march of Ancona which looks down from the slopes of the Apennines upon
                    the distant Adriatic. After taking the degree of doctor of law at the university
                    of Perugia, and holding a judicial office at Ascoli, he returned to his native
                    city, and was entrusted with the task of recasting its statutes, but, sharing
                    the Protestant opinions of his father, shared also his flight to Carniola, where
                    Matteo was appointed physician to the duchy. The Inquisition condemned the
                    fugitives as contumacious, and they soon received orders to quit the dominions
                    of Austria. Alberico set out for England, travelling by way of Tübingen and
                    Heidelberg, and everywhere<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n172/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0172-0161"/> meeting with the reception to which his
                    already high reputation entitled him. He arrived at Oxford in the autumn of
                    1580, with a commendatory letter from the earl of Leicester, at that time
                    chancellor of the university, and was shortly afterwards qualified to teach by
                    being admitted to the same degree which he had taken at Perugia. His lectures on
                    Roman law soon became famous, and the dialogues, disputations, and commentaries,
                    which he published henceforth in rapid succession, established his position as
                    an accomplished civilian, of the older and severer type, and secured his
                    appointment in 1587 to the regius professorship of civil law. It was, however,
                    rather by an application of the old learning to the new questions suggested by
                    the modern relations of states that his labours have produced their most lasting
                    result. In 1584 he was consulted by Government as to the proper course to be
                    pursued with Mendoza, the Spanish ambassador, who had been detected in plotting
                    against Elizabeth. He chose the topic to which his attention had thus been
                    directed as a subject for a disputation when Leicester and Sir Philip Sidney
                    visited the schools at Oxford in the same year; and this was six months later
                    expanded into a book, the <hi rend="italic">De legationιbzιs</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">libri tres.</hi> In 1588 Alberico selected the law of war as
                    the subject of the law disputations at the annual “Act” which took place in
                    July; and in the autumn published in London the <hi rend="italic">De Jure
                        Belli</hi><hi rend="italic">commentatio</hi><hi rend="italic">prima.</hi> A
                    second and a third <hi rend="italic">Commentatio</hi> followed, and the whole
                    matter, with large additions and improvements, appeared at Hanau, in 1598, as
                    the <hi rend="italic">De Jure Belli</hi><hi rend="italic">libri</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">1res.</hi> It was doubtless in consequence of the reputation
                    gained by these works that Gentili became henceforth more and more engaged in
                    forensic practice, and resided chiefly in London, leaving his Oxford work to be
                    partly discharged by a deputy. In 1600 he was admitted to beamember of Gray’s
                    Inn, and in 1605 was appointed standing counsel to the king of Spain. He died
                    19th June 1608, and was buried, by the side of Dr Matteo Gentili, who had
                    followed his son to England, in the churchyard of St Helen’s, Bishopsgate. By
                    his wife, Hester de Peigni, he left two sons and a daughter. His notes of the
                    cases in which he was engaged for the Spaniards were posthumously published in
                    1613 at Hanau, as 2‰ <hi rend="italic">panicoe</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >advocationis</hi><hi rend="italic">libri</hi><hi rend="italic">duo.</hi>
                    This was in accordance with his last wishes; but his direction that the
                    remainder of his MSS. should be burnt was not complied with, since fifteen
                    volumes of them found their way, at the beginning of this century, from
                    Amsterdam to the Bodleian library.</p>
                <p>The true history of Gentili and of his principal writings has only been
                    ascertained quite recently, in consequence of a revived appreciation of the
                    services which he rendered to international law. The movement to do him honour,
                    which originated four or five years since, has in spreading through Europe
                    encountered two curious cross-currents of opinion,—one the ultra-Catholic, which
                    three centuries ago ordered his name to be erased from all public documents and
                    placed his works in the <hi rend="italic">Index·,</hi> another the
                    narrowly-Dutcb, which is, it seems, needlessly careful of the supremacy of
                    Grotius. Preceding writers had dealt with various international questions, but
                    they dealt with them singly, and with a servile submission to the decisions of
                    the church. It was left to Gentili to grasp as a whole the relations of states
                    one to another, to distinguish international questions from questions with which
                    they are more, or less intimately connected, and to attempt their solution by
                    principles entirely independent of the authority of Rome. He uses, without
                    yielding to them implicit deference, the reasonings of the civil and even the
                    canon law, but he proclaims as his real guide the <hi rend="italic">Jus
                        Haturce,</hi> the highest common sense of mankind, by which historical
                    precedents are to be criticized, and, if necessary, set aside.</p>
                <p>His faults are not few. His style is prolix, obscure, and to the modern reader
                    pedantic enough; but a comparison of his greatest work with what had been
                    written upon the same subject by, for instance, Belli, or Soto, or even Ayala,
                    will show that he greatly improved upon his predecessors, not only by the
                    fulness with which he has worked out points of detail, but also by clearly
                    separating the law of war from martial law, and by placing the subject once for
                    all upon a non-theological basis. If, on the other hand, the same work be
                    compared with <hi rend="italic">De Jure Belli</hi><hi rend="italic">et
                        Pacis</hi> of Grotius, it is at once evident that the later writer is
                    indebted to the earlier, not only for a large portion of his illustrative
                    erudition, but also for all that is commendable in the method and arrangement of
                    the treatise.</p>
                <p>The following is probably a complete list of the writings of Gentili, with the
                    places and dates of their first publication :— <hi rend="italic">Be
                        Juris</hi><hi rend="italic">interpretibus</hi><hi rend="italic">diαlοgi
                        sex,</hi> Lond., 1582; <hi rend="italic">Lectionum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >et</hi><hi rend="italic">epist.</hi><hi rend="italic">quae ad pus civile
                        pertinent</hi><hi rend="italic">libri</hi><hi rend="italic">ires,</hi>
                    Lond., 1583-4: <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic">divers,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">temp,</hi><hi rend="italic">appellationibus,</hi> Hanau, 1584;
                        <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic">Legationibus libri tres,</hi>
                    Lond., 1585; <hi rend="italic">Legal,</hi><hi rend="italic">comitiorum Oxon.
                        actio,</hi> Lond., 1585-6; <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >nascendi tempore disputatio,</hi> Witteb., 1586; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Disputationum decas prima,</hi> Lond., 1587; <hi rend="italic">Conditiornim
                        liber singularis,</hi> Lond., 1587; <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Jure Belli comm. prima,</hi> Lond., 1588; <hi rend="italic"
                        >secunda, ib.,</hi> 1588 -9; ferh'α, 1589; <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">injustitia bellica Romanorum,</hi> Oxon., 1590; <hi
                        rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic">Armis Romanis,</hi> &amp;c., Hanau,
                    1599; <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic">ludis scenicis epist.
                        duce,</hi> Middleburg, 1599; <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >actoribus et de abusu mendacii,</hi> Hanau, 1599; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lectiones</hi><hi rend="italic">Virgilianae,</hi> Hanau, 1600; <hi
                        rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic">nuptiis libri septem,</hi> 1601; <hi
                        rend="italic">Ad</hi> 1 <hi rend="italic">Maccab. et de linguarum
                        mistura,</hi> Lond., 1604; <hi rend="italic">In tit. si quis principi, et
                        ad</hi><hi rend="italic">leg. Jul. maiest.,</hi> Hanau, 1604; <hi
                        rend="italic">In tit. de Malef. ct Math., ct de Prof, ct Med.,</hi> Hanau,
                    1604; <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic">latin,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >vet. Bibl.,</hi> Hanau, 1604; <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >libro</hi><hi rend="italic">Pyano,</hi> Oxon., 1604; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Laudes</hi><hi rend="italic">Acad. Penis, ct 0xon.,</hi> Hanau, 1605; <hi
                        rend="italic">Be unione</hi><hi rend="italic">Anglioe et Scotioe,</hi>
                    Lond., 1605; <hi rend="italic">Disputationes tres,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >de</hi><hi rend="italic">libris</hi><hi rend="italic">jur.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">can.,</hi><hi rend="italic">de libris</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >jur.</hi><hi rend="italic">civ.,</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">latinitate</hi><hi rend="italic">vet. vcrs.,</hi> Hanau, 1605;
                        <hi rend="italic">Regales disput.</hi><hi rend="italic">tres,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">depot,</hi><hi rend="italic">regis absoluta,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">unione regnorum, de vi civium,</hi>
                    Lond., 1605; <hi rend="italic">Hispanicae advocationis libri</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">duo,</hi> Hanau, 1613; <hi rend="italic">In tit. de verb,
                        signif.,</hi> Hanau, 1614; <hi rend="italic">Be</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >legatis</hi><hi rend="italic">in test.,</hi> Amsterd., 1661. An edition of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Opera Omnia,</hi> commenced at Naples in 1770, was cut
                    short by the death of the publisher, Gravier, after the second volume. Of his
                    numerous unpublished writings, Gentili complained that four volumes were lost
                    “pessimo pontificiorum facinore,” meaning probably that they were left behind in
                    his flight to Carniola.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> Several tracts by the Abate Benigni in
                    Colucci, <hi rend="italic">Antichità</hi><hi rend="italic">Picene,</hi> 1790; a
                    Dissertation by W. Reiger annexed to the <hi rend="italic">Program of the
                        Groningen Gymnasium</hi> for 1867; an Inaugural Lecture delivered in 1874 by
                    T. E. Holland, and the preface to a new edition of the <hi rend="italic">Jus
                        Belli,</hi> 1877, by the same; works by Valdarnini and Foglietti, 1875;
                    Speranza and De Giorgi, 1876; Fiorini (a translation of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Jus Belli,</hi> with essay), 1877; A. Saffi, 1878. See also E. Comba, in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Rivista Christiana,</hi> 1876-7; and Sir T. Twiss, in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Law Review,</hi> 1878. (T. E. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
