<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0642-0625-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GIUSTI, Giuseppe</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 625</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pz51q1n">Fear</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xc0z">Proverbs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jm0g">Evil</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n642/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GIUSTI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Giuseppe</hi></label>
                    (1809-1850), Tuscan satirical poet, was born at Monsummano, a small village of
                    the Valdinie-vole, on May 12, 1809. His father, a cultivated and rich man,
                    accustomed his son from childhood to study, and himself taught him, among other
                    subjects, the first rudiments of music. Afterwards, in order to curb his too
                    vivacious disposition, he placed the boy under the charge of a priest near the
                    village, whose severity did perhaps more evil than good. At twelve Giusti was
                    sent to school at Florence, and afterwards to Pistoia and to Lucca; and during
                    those years he wrote his first verses. In 1826 he went to study law at Pisa:
                    but, disliking the study, he spent eight years in the course, instead of the
                    customary four. He lived gaily, however, though his father kept him short of
                    money, and learned to know the world, seeing the vices of society, and the folly
                    of certain laws and customs from which his country was suffering. The experience
                    thus gained he turned to good account in the use he made of it in his
                    satire.</p>
                <p>His father had in the meantime changed his place of abode to Pescia; but Giuseppe
                    did worse there, and in November 1832, his father having paid his debts, he
                    returned to study at Pisa, seriously enamoured of a woman whom he could not
                    marry, but now commencing to write in real earnest in behalf of his country.
                    With the poem called <hi rend="italic">La Ghigliottina</hi> (the guillotine),
                    Giusti began to strike out a path for himself, and thus revealed his great
                    genius. From this time he showed himself the Italian Béranger, and even
                    surpassed the Frenchman in richness of language, refinement of humour, and depth
                    of satirical conception. In Béranger there is more feeling for what is needed
                    for popular poetry. His poetry is less studied, its vivacity perhaps more
                    boisterous, more spontaneous; but Giusti, in both manner and conception, is
                    perhaps more elegant, more refined, more penetrating. In 1834 Giusti, having at
                    last entered the legal profession, left Pisa to go to Florence, nominally to
                    practice with the advocate Capo-quadri, but really to enjoy life in the capital
                    of Tuscany. He fell seriously in love a second time, and as before was abandoned
                    by his love. It was then he wrote his finest verses, by means of which, although
                    his poetry was not yet collected in a volume, but for some years passed from
                    hand to hand, his name gradually became famous. The greater part of his poems
                    were published clandestinely at Lugano, at no little risk, as the work was
                    destined to undermine the Austrian rule in Italy. After the publication of a
                    volume of verses at Bastia, Giusti thoroughly established his fame by his <hi
                    rend="italic">Gingillino,</hi> the best in moral tone as well as the most
                    vigorous and effective of his poems. The poet sets himself to represent the
                    vileness of the treasury officials, and the base means they used to conceal the
                    necessities of the state. The <hi rend="italic">Gingillino</hi> has all the
                    character of a classic satire. When first issued in Tuscany, it struck all as
                    too impassioned and personal. Giusti entered heart and soul into the political
                    movements of 1847 and 1848, served in the national guard, sat in the parliament
                    for Tuscany; but finding that there was more talk than action, that to the
                    tyranny of princes had succeeded the tyranny of demagogues, he began to fear,
                    and to express the fear, that for Italy evil rather than good had resulted. He
                    fell, in consequence, from the high position he had held in public estimation,
                    and in 1848 was regarded as a reactionary. His friendship for the marquis Gino
                    Capponi, who had taken him into his house during the last years of his life, and
                    who published after Giusti’s death a volume of illustrated proverbs, was enough
                    to compromise him in the eyes of such men as Guerrazzi, Montanelli, and
                    Niccolini. On May 31, 1850, he died at Florence in the palace of his friend.</p>
                <p>The poetry of Giusti, under a light trivial aspect, has a lofty civilizing
                    significance. The type of his satire is entirely original, and it had also the
                    great merit of appearing at the right moment, of wounding judiciously, of
                    sustaining the part of the comedy that “castigat ridendo mores.” Hence his
                    verse, apparently jovial, was received by the scholars and politicians of Italy
                    in all seriousness. Alexander Manzoni in some of his letters showed a hearty
                    admiration of the genius of Giusti; and the weak Austrian and Bourbon
                    Governments regarded them as of the gravest importance.</p>
                <p>His poems have been often reprinted, the best editions being those of Le Monnier
                    of Florence, and also that published in Verona, with valuable annotations, by
                    Professor Giovanni Fioretti in 1876. Besides the poems, and the proverbs already
                    mentioned, we have a volume of select letters, full of vigour and written in the
                    best Tuscan language, and a fine critical discourse on Giuseppe Parini, the
                    satirical poet of the last century, whose poetical works are published in a
                    volume by Le Monnier. In some of his compositions the elegiac rather than the
                    satirical poet is seen. Many of his verses have been excellently translated into
                    German by Paul Heyse. Good English translations were published in the A
                    tlaenaeum by the late Mrs T. A. Trollope.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
