<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0460-0445-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GERMANICUS, Caesar (9th edition, volume 10, page
                    445)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tm7251f">Grief</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wp9tb5s">Historians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n460/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GERMANICUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Caesar</hi></label>, a
                    distinguished Roman general and provincial governor in the reign of Tiberius,
                    was born 15 B.c., and died 19 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> His name
                    Germanicus, the only one by which he is known in history, he inherited from his
                    father Claudius Drusus Nero, the stepson of Augustus, and the most famous of his
                    generals. His mother was the younger Antonia, the daughter of Marcus Antonius
                    and niece of Augustus, and he married Agrippina the grand-daughter of the same
                    emperor. It was natural that a prince so intimately allied both by birth and
                    connexion with the reigning family should be regarded as a candidate for the
                    purple. Augustus, it would seem, long hesitated whether he should name him as
                    his successor, and as a compromise required Tiberius to adopt him, though
                    Tiberius had a son of his own When his uncle succeeded to the throne, Germanicus
                    was the only rival that he feared; and the emperor’s jealousy and suspicion of
                    him not only cut short his career of conquest but embittered the last years of
                    his life, and precipitated, if it did not indirectly cause, his unhappy and
                    premature end.</p>
                <p>For the facts of his life our chief and, except a brief notice in Suetonius,
                    almost our sole authority is Tacitus. Germanicus forms the central figure of the
                    first two books of the <hi rend="italic">Annals,</hi> and in the minute and
                    graphic record of his campaigns, the unravelling of the court intrigues to which
                    he was subject, and the pathetic description of his last hours and of the
                    outburst of grief and indignation which followed the news of his death, the
                    historian has put forth all his powers. But a modern biographer, though
                    compelled to trust to Tacitus for his materials, may yet be allowed to put upon
                    them his own construction, to make allowance for the glamour which surrounded an
                    amiable and ill-starred prince, and to discount the exaggerations of a master of
                    rhetoric who has set his favourite hero in a blaze of light in order to deepen
                    the shadows of his masterpiece Tiberius, the darkest and saddest portrait in all
                    history. The following article will consist of a brief abstract of the life as
                    related by Tacitus, and an estimate of the character as it presents itself to us
                    in the foregoing records.</p>
                <p>Of the early years and education of Germanicus little is known. That he possessed
                    considerable literary abilities, and that these were carefully trained, we
                    gather, not only from the speeches which Tacitus puts into his mouth, but from
                    the reputation he left as an orator, as attested by Suetonius and Ovid, and from
                    the fragments of his works which have survived. At the age of twenty he served
                    his apprenticeship in the art of war under his uncle Tiberius, and was rewarded
                    with the triumphal insignia for his services in crushing the revolt in Dalmatia
                    and Pannonia. In 12 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> he was made consul, though he
                    had neither attained the legal age nor passed through the grades of praetor and
                    aedile. Soon afterwards he was appointed by Augustus to the important command of
                    the eight legions on the Rhine. The news of the emperor’s death found Germanicus
                    at Lugdunum, where he was super intending the census of Gaul. Close upon this
                    came the report that a mutiny had broken out among his legions on the lower
                    Rhine. Germanicus hurried back to the camp, which was now in open insurrection.
                    The tumult was with difficulty quelled, partly by well-timed concessions for
                    which the authority of the emperor was forged, but mostly by the help of his
                    personal popularity with the troops. Some of the insurgents actually proposed
                    that he should put himself at their head and secure for himself the empire, but
                    their offer was rejected with righteous horror. In order to calm the excitement
                    and prevent further disaffection, Germanicus determined at once on an active
                    campaign. Crossing the Rhine at the head of 12,000 legionaries and an equal
                    number of allied troops, he attacked and routed the Marsi, and laid waste the
                    valley of the Ems. In the following year he marched against Arminius, the
                    conqueror of Varus, and reached the fatal battlefield in the Teutoburg Forest.
                    The bones of the Roman soldiers still lay bleaching on the ground near the
                    altars where their tribunes had been immolated, and the gibbets where the
                    prisoners had been hanged. Having performed the last rites and erected a barrow
                    to mark the spot, he led his army on, breathing vengeance against the foe.
                    Arminius, however, favoured by the marshy ground, was able to hold his own, and
                    it required another campaign before he was finally defeated. A masterly combined
                    movement by land and water enabled Germanicus to concentrate his forces against
                    the main body of the Germans encamped on the Weser, and to crush them in two
                    obstinately contested battles. A monument erected on the field proclaimed that
                    the army of Tiberius had conquered every tribe between the Rhine and the Elbe.
                    Great as the success of the Roman arms had been, it was not such as to justify
                    this boastful inscription. We read of renewed attacks from the barbarians, and
                    plans of a fourth campaign for the next summer.</p>
                <p>But no more victories were in store for Germanicus. His success had already
                    stirred the jealousy and fears of Tiberius, and he was reluctantly compelled to
                    obey the imperial summons<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n461/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0461-0446"/> and repair to Rome. The magnificence of a
                    triumph and the idle honours of a consulship had little attraction for a general
                    in mid-career of conquest, and a man of singularly simple habits and no
                    political ambition. The enthusiasm with which he was welcomed, not only by the
                    populace, which went in crowds to meet him as far as the twentieth milestone,
                    but by the emperor’s own praetorians, warned Tiberius that it might be equally
                    dangerous to keep so popular a favourite at Rome, and the earliest pretext was
                    seized to remove him from the capital. The recent death of Archelaus, king of
                    Cappadocia, and a disputed succession in Parthia and Armenia, afforded a
                    sufficient plea for Roman interference; and, a few months after his return,
                    Germanicus was despatched to the East with extraordinary powers, and started on
                    his mission without waiting to enter on his consulship. At the same time
                    Tiberius took the further precaution of superseding Silanus, a connexion of
                    Germanicus, in the government of Syria, and appointing in his stead one of the
                    most violent and ambitious of the old nobility, Cneius Calpurnius Piso, in order
                    to watch his nephew’s movements, and if necessary to check his ambition.
                    Germanicus proceeded by easy stages to his province, halting on his way in
                    Dalmatia, where he conferred with Drusus, his brother by adoption, and visiting
                    the battlefield of Actium, Athens, Ilium, and other places of historic interest.
                    At Rhodes he met for the first time his coadjutor Piso, who had followed in his
                    wake, and was seeking everywhere to thwart his policy and asperse his character.
                    When at last he reached his destination, he found little difficulty in effecting
                    the settlement of the disturbed provinces, notwithstanding the violent and
                    persistent opposition of Piso. At Artaxata Zeno, the popular candidate for the
                    throne, was crowned king of Armenia; to the provinces of Cappadocia and
                    Commagena Roman governors were assigned; and Parthia was conciliated by the
                    banishment of the dethroned king Vonones. After wintering in Syria Germanicus
                    started next year for a tour in Egypt. The chief motive for his journey was love
                    of travel and antiquarian study, and it seems never to have occurred to him,
                    till he was warned by Tiberius, that he was thereby transgressing an unwritten
                    Law of the empire forbidding any Roman of rank to set foot in Egypt without
                    express permission. On his return to Syria he found that all his arrangements
                    had been upset by Piso. Violent recriminations followed, the result of which, it
                    would seem, was a promise on the part of Piso to quit the province. But at this
                    juncture Germanicus fell ill. Piso deferred his departure, and, when at length
                    compelled to start, lingered in the neighbourhood of Syria, receiving with open
                    exultation the bulletins which told of the prince’s rapid decline. Germanicus on
                    his side was fully convinced that he had fallen a victim to the arts of his
                    unscrupulous enemy. He knew that lie was dying, and believed that he was dying
                    of poison. Even his gentle nature was stung to madness at the thought, and with
                    his dying words he called on his friends and family to denounce his murderer and
                    avenge his death. Whether these suspicions were true must remain an open
                    question, yet the arguments in favour of a death from natural causes seem to
                    preponderate. It is true that Piso desired his death, and, from what we∙ know of
                    their characters, neither he nor his wife Plancina were likely to stick at any
                    means for procuring it. But a poisoner does not generally let his wishes be
                    publicly known, nor show his exultation when they are attained. The evidence
                    from the appearance of the corpse is still more uncertain. Suetonius indeed
                    avouches that there were livid marks all over the body and foam at the mouth;
                    but he adds as a further proof of poison that on the funeral pyre the heart
                    remained unconsumed, which clearly shows that he was only retailing the vulgar
                    gossip. Tacitus, though inclined to believe the worst of Piso, allows that the
                    report of the symptoms varied with the prepossession of the observers.</p>
                <p>The sad tidings of his death cast a gloom over the whole Roman empire. To the
                    provincials he had endeared himself by his simple manners, his affability, his
                    generosity, his justice. The legions mourned their comrade who had always stood
                    their friend at need, their general who had never known a defeat. At Rome there
                    was a universal outburst of sorrow and indignation. The natural grief at the
                    loss of a favourite prince was aggravated by the suspicion of foul play, and by
                    hatred of the emperor who was at least guilty of recklessly exposing him to
                    danger, and who now sullenly refused to join the general mourning. Men recalled
                    the forboding words which had been whispered at his departure, “Whom the plebs
                    love, die young.” Nor was he unworthy of this passionate devotion. He had wiped
                    out a great national disgrace; he had quelled their most formidable foe; he had
                    pacified distant provinces; and in his high estate he had so borne himself that
                    all save one man had loved and honoured him. * His private life had been
                    stainless, and he possessed in a singular degree the gift of personal
                    attractiveness. And yet an impartial biographer must add that for his fair fame
                    his death was opportune. There were elements of weakness in his character which
                    his short life only half revealed: an almost feminine impetuousness which made
                    him twice threaten to take his own life; a superstitious vein which impelled him
                    to consult oracles and shrink from bad omens; an amiable dilettantism which led
                    him to travel in Egypt while his enemy was plotting his ruin; a want of nerve
                    and resolution which prevented him from coming to an open rupture with Piso till
                    it was too late. His very virtues, his elegant taste, his chivalrous sense of
                    honour, his unsuspecting openness and candour, unfitted him for the stern times
                    in which he lived. He was as little fitted to play the part of Augustus as that
                    of Alexander, to whom Tacitus fondly compares him; and had he lived to succeed
                    to the purple the historian might have been compelled to pronounce on him the
                    epitaph of Galba, that all would have thought him fit to réign if he had not
                    reigned. <hi rend="smallcaps">(f. s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
