<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0114-0105-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GASSENDI, Pierre</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 105</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1063025">Physics</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gx2h">Physics</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n114/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GASSENDI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre</hi></label>
                    (1592-1655), one of the most eminent French philosophers, was born of poor but
                    respectable parentage at Champtercier, near Digne, in Provence, on the 22d
                    January 1592. At a very early age he gave indications of remarkable mental
                    powers, and at the instance of his uncle, the curé of his native village, he was
                    sent to the college at Digne. He made rapid progress in his studies, showing
                    particular aptitude for languages and mathematics, and it is said that at the
                    age of sixteen he was invited to lecture on rhetoric at the college. He cannot
                    have retained this post for any length of time, for soon afterwards he entered
                    the university of Aix, to study philosophy under Fesaye. In 1612 he was called
                    to the college of Digne to lecture on theology. Four years later he received the
                    degree of doctor of theology at Avignon, and in 1617 he took orders as a priest.
                    In the same year he was called to the chair of philosophy at Aix, and seems
                    gradually to have withdrawn from theological study and teaching.</p>
                <p>At Aix he lectured principally on the Aristotelian philosophy, conforming as far
                    as possible to the orthodox methods. At the same time, however, he prosecuted
                    his favourite studies, physics and astronomy, and by the discoveries of Galileo,
                    Kepler, and others became more and more dissatisfied with the Peripatetic
                    system. It was, indeed, the very period of violent revolt against the authority
                    of Aristotle, and Gassendi shared to the full the practical and empirical
                    tendencies of the age. He, too, began to draw up in form his objections to the
                    Aristotelian philosophy, but did not at first venture to publish them. The
                    portion shown to his friends Peiresc and Gautier, however, was so vehemently
                    approved by them that in 1624, after he had left Aix for a canonry at Grenoble,
                    he printed the first part of his <hi rend="italic">Exercitatione</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">paradoxicae</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n115/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0115-0106"/><hi rend="italic">adversus Aristoteleos.</hi> A
                    fragment of tae second book was published later (1659), but the remaining five,
                    requisite to complete the work, were never composed, Gassendi apparently
                    thinking that after the <hi rend="italic">Discussiones Peripateticae</hi> of
                    Patricius little field was left for his labours.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Exercitationes</hi> on the whole seem to have excited more
                    attention than they deserved. They contain little or nothing beyond what had
                    been already advanced against Aristotle by the more vigorous of the Humanists,
                    by Valla and Vives, by Ramus and Bruno. The first book expounds clearly, and
                    with much vigour, the evil effects of the blind acceptance of the Aristotelian
                    dicta on physical and philosophical study; but, as is the case with so many of
                    the anti-Aristotelian works of this period, the objections do not touch the true
                    Aristotelian system, and in many instances show the usual ignorance of
                    Aristotle’s own writings. The second book, which contains the review of
                    Aristotle’s dialectic or logic, is throughout Ramist in tone and method.</p>
                <p>After a short visit to Paris in 1628, Gassendi travelled for some years in
                    Flanders and Holland with his friend Luillier. During this time he wrote, at the
                    instance of Mersenne, his examination of the mystical philosophy of Robert Fludd
                    <hi rend="italic">(Epistolica dissertatio</hi><hi rend="italic">in qua</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">praecipua principia philosophice</hi><hi rend="italic">Ro.
                    Fluddi</hi><hi rend="italic">deteguntur,</hi> 1631), an essay on parhelia <hi
                    rend="italic">(Epistola</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Parheliis),</hi> and some valuable observations on the transit of Mercury which
                    had been foretold by Kepler. He returned to France in 1631, and two years later
                    received the appointment of provost of the cathedral church at Digne. Some years
                    were then spent in travelling through Provence with the duke of Angoulême,
                    governor of the department. The only literary work of this period is the <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Peiresc,</hi> which has been frequently reprinted, and was
                    translated into English. In 1642 he was again engaged by Mersenne in
                    controversy, on this occasion against the celebrated Descartes. His objections
                    to the fundamental propositions of Descartes were published in 1642; they appear
                    as the fifth in the series contained in the works of Descartes. In these
                    objections Gassendi’s already great tendency towards the empirical school of
                    speculation appears more pronounced than in any of his other writings. In 1645
                    he was invited by the archbishop of Lyons, brother of Cardinal Richelieu, to the
                    chair of mathematics in the Collège Royal at Paris. He accepted this post, and
                    lectured for many years with great success. In addition to some controversial
                    writings on physical questions, there appeared during this period the first of
                    the works by which he is best known in the history of philosophy. He evidently
                    found himself more in harmony with Epicurus than with any other philosopher of
                    antiquity, and had collected much information regarding the Epicurean system. In
                    1647 Luillier persuaded him to publish some of his works, which took the form of
                    the treatise <hi rend="italic">De Vita,</hi><hi rend="italic">Moribus, et
                    Doctrina Epicum libri octo.</hi> The work was well received, and two years later
                    appeared his commentary on the tenth book of Diogenes Laertius <hi rend="italic"
                    >(De Vita,</hi><hi rend="italic">Moribus,</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Placitis Epicuri, seu Animadversiones</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >in</hi><hi rend="italic">X. librum Diog.</hi><hi rend="italic">Laer.).</hi> In
                    the same year the more important <hi rend="italic">Syntagma</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">philosophice Epicuri</hi> was published.</p>
                <p>In 1648 Gassendi had been compelled from ill-health to give up his lectures at
                    the Collège Royal. He travelled for some time in the south of France, spending
                    nearly two years at Toulon, the climate of which suited him. In 1653 he returned
                    to Paris and resumed his literary work, publishing in that year his well-known
                    and popular lives of Copernicus and Tycho Brahe. The disease from which he
                    suffered, lung complaint, had, however, established a firm hold on him. His
                    strength gradually failed, and he died at Paris on the 24th October 1655, in the
                    sixty-third year of his age.</p>
                <p>His collected works, of which the most important is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Syntagma</hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophicum</hi><hi rend="italic">(Opera,</hi>
                    i. and ii.), were published in 1655 by Montmort (6 vols, fol., Lyons). Another
                    edition, also in 6 folio volumes, was published by Averanius in 1727. These
                    volumes sufficiently attest the wide extent of his reading and the versatility
                    of his powers. The first two are occupied entirely with his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Syntagma</hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophicum</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the
                    third contains his critical writings on Epicurus, Aristotle, Descartes, Fludd,
                    and Lord Herbert, with some occasional pieces on certain problems of physics;
                    the fourth, his <hi rend="italic">Institutio Astronomica,</hi> and his <hi
                    rend="italic">Commentarii</hi><hi rend="italic">de Rebus Celestibus</hi>; the
                    fifth, his commentary on the tenth book of Diogenes Laertius, the biographies of
                    Epicurus, Peiresc, Tycho Brahe, Copernicus, Peurbach, and Regiomontanus, with
                    some tracts on the value of ancient money, on the Roman calendar, and on the
                    theory of music, to all which is appended a large and prolix piece entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Xotitia</hi><hi rend="italic">Ecclesioe</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Diniensis∙,</hi> the sixth volume contains his correspondence. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Lives,</hi> especially those of Copernicus, Tycho, and Peiresc,
                    have been justly admired. That of Peiresc has been repeatedly printed; it has
                    also been translated into English. Gassendi was one of the first after the
                    revival of letters who treated the <hi rend="italic">literature</hi> of
                    philosophy in a lively way. His writings of this kind, though too laudatory and
                    somewhat diffuse, have great merit; they abound in those anecdotal details,
                    natural yet not obvious reflexions, and vivacious turns of thought, which made
                    Gibbon style him, with some extravagance certainly, though it was true enough up
                    to Gassendi’s time—“le meilleur philosophe des litterateurs, et le meilleur
                    litterateur des philosophes.”</p>
                <p>Gassendi will always retain an honourable place in the history of physical
                    science. He certainly added little original to the stock of human knowledge, but
                    the clearness of his exposition and the manner in which he, like his greater
                    contemporary, Bacon, urged the necessity and utility of experimental research,
                    were of inestimable service to the cause of science. To what extent any place
                    can be assigned him iu the history of philosophy is more doubtful. His
                    anti-Aristotelian writing has been already noticed. The objections to
                    Descartes—one of which at least, through Descartes’s statement of it, has become
                    famous—have no speculative value, and iu general are the outcome of the crudest
                    empiricism. His labours on Epicurus have a certain historical value, but the
                    inherent want of consistency iu the philosophical system raised on Epicureanism
                    is such as to deprive it of all genuine worth. Along with strong expressions of
                    empiricism <hi rend="italic">(nihil in</hi><hi rend="italic">intellectu</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">quod non</hi><hi rend="italic">prius fuerit</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >in</hi><hi rend="italic">sensu)</hi> we find him holding doctrines absolutely
                    irreconcilable with empiricism in any form. For while he maintains constantly
                    his favourite maxim “that there is nothing in the intellect which has not been
                    in the senses,” and while he contends that the imaginative faculty, “phantasia,”
                    is the counterpart of sense, that, as it has to do with material images, it is
                    itself, like sense, material, and essentially the same both in men and brutes,
                    he at the same time admits that the intellect, which he affirms to be immaterial
                    and immortal—the most characteristic distinction of humanity—attains notions and
                    truths of which no effort of sensation or imagination can give us the slightest
                    apprehension <hi rend="italic">(Op.,</hi> ii. 383). He instances the capacity of
                    forming “general notions;” the very conception of universality itself <hi
                    rend="italic">(ib.,</hi> 384), to which he says' brutes, who partake as truly as
                    men in the faculty called “phantasia,” never attain; the notion of God, whom he
                    says we may imagine to be corporeal, but understand to be incorporeal; and
                    lastly, the reflex action by which the mind makes its own phenomena and
                    operations the objects of attention.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Syntagma</hi><hi rend="italic">Philosophicum,</hi> in fact,
                    is one of the eclectic systems which unite, or rather place in juxtaposition,
                    irreconcilable dogmas from various schools of thought.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n116/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0116-0107"/>
                <p>It is divided, according to the usual fashion of the Epicureans, into logic
                    (which, with Gassendi as with Epicurus, is truly <hi rend="italic"
                    >canonic),</hi> physics, and ethics. The logic, which contains at least one
                    praiseworthy portion, a sketch of the history of the science, is divided into
                    theory of right apprehension <hi rend="italic">(bene</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >imaginari),</hi> theory of right judgment <hi rend="italic">{bene</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">proponere),</hi> theory of right inference <hi rend="italic"
                    >(bene</hi><hi rend="italic">colligere),</hi> theory i&gt;f right method <hi
                    rend="italic">(fene</hi><hi rend="italic">ordinare).</hi> The first part
                    contains the specially empirical positions which Gassendi afterwards neglects or
                    leaves out of account. The senses, the sole source of knowledge, are supposed to
                    yield us immediately cognition of individual things; phantasy (which Gassendi
                    takes to be material in nature) reproduces these ideas; understanding compares
                    these ideas, which are particular, and frames general ideas. Nevertheless, he at
                    the same time admits that the senses yield knowledge—not of things—but of
                    qualities only, and holds that we arrive at the idea of thing or substance by
                    induction. He holds that the *true method of research is the analytic, rising
                    from lower to higher notions; yet he sees clearly, and admits, that inductive
                    reasoning, as conceived by Bacon, rests on a general proposition not itself
                    proved by induction. He ought to hold, and in disputing with Descartes he did
                    apparently hold, that the evidence of the senses is the only convincing
                    evidence; yet he maintains, and from his special mathematical training it was
                    natural he should maintain, that the evidence of reason is absolutely
                    satisfactory. The whole doctrine of judgment, syllogism, and method is a mixture
                    of Aristotelian and Ramist notions.</p>
                <p>In the second part of the <hi rend="italic">Syntagma,</hi> the physics, there is
                    more that deserves attention; but here, too, appears in the most glaring manner
                    the inner contradiction between Gassendi’s fundamental principles. While
                    approving of the Epicurean physics, he rejects altogether the Epicurean negation
                    of God and particular providence. He states the various proofs for the existence
                    of an immaterial, infinite, supreme Being, asserts that this Being is the author
                    of the visible universe, and strongly defends the doctrine of the foreknowledge
                    and particular providence of God. At the same time he holds, in opposition to
                    Epicureanism, the doctrine of an immaterial, rational soul, endowed with
                    immortality and capable of free determination. It is altogether impossible to
                    assent to the supposition of Lange <hi rend="italic">(Gesch.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Materialismus,</hi> 3d ed., i. 233), that all this portion of
                    Gassendi’s system contains nothing of his own opinions, but is solely introduced
                    from motives of self-defence. The positive exposition of atomism has much that
                    is attractive, but the hypothesis of the <hi rend="italic">calor vitalis,</hi> a
                    species of <hi rend="italic">anima muηdd</hi> which is introduced as physical
                    explanation of physical phenomena, does not seem to throw much light on the
                    special problems which it is invoked to solve. Nor is his theory of the weight
                    essential to atoms as being due to an inner force impelling them to motion in
                    any way reconcilable with his general doctrine of mechanical causes.</p>
                <p>In the third part, the ethics, over and above the discussion on freedom, which on
                    the whole is indefinite, there is little beyond a milder statement of the
                    Epicurean moral code. The final end of life is happiness, and happiness is
                    harmony of soul and body, <hi rend="italic">tranquillitas animi et
                    indolentia</hi><hi rend="italic">corp</hi><hi rend="italic">oms.</hi> Probably,
                    Gassendi thinks, perfect happiness is not attainable in this life, but it may be
                    in the life to come.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Syntagma</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> as</hi> thus an
                    essentially unsystematic work, and clearly exhibits the main characteristics of
                    Gassendi’s genius. He was critical rather than constructive, widely read and
                    trained thoroughly both in languages and in science, but deficient in
                    speculative power and original force. Even in the department of natural science
                    he shows the same inability steadfastly to retain principles and to work from
                    them; he wavers between the systems of Brahe and Copernicus. That his revival of
                    Epicureanism had an important influence on the general thinking of the 17th
                    century may be admitted; that it has any real importance in the history of
                    philosophy cannot be granted.</p>
                <p>Gassendi’s life is given by Sorbière in the first collected edition of the works,
                    by Bugerel, <hi rend="italic">Vie de Gassendi,</hi> 1737 (2d ed., 1770), and by
                    Damiron, <hi rend="italic">Mémoire sur Gassendi,</hi> 1839. An abridgment of his
                    philosophy was given by his friend, the celebrated traveller, Bernier <hi
                    rend="italic">(Abrégé de la Philosophie</hi><hi rend="italic">de Gassendi,</hi>
                    8 vols., 1678; 2d cd., 7 vols., iβ84). The most complete surveys of his work
                    seem to be those of Buhle <hi rend="italic">(Geschichte der neuern
                    Philosophie,</hi> iii,, 1, 87-222), and Damiron <hi rend="italic">(Mémoires pour
                    servir à VHistoire de Philosophie au ljme Siècle.)</hi> See also Ritter, <hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte der Philosophie, x. 543-571;</hi> Feuerbach, <hi
                    rend="italic">Gcsch. d. neu. Phil, von Bacon bis Spinoza,</hi> 127-150. (R.
                    AD.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
