<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0810-0787-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GORZ (9th edition, volume 10, page 787)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41g0hw2j">Capuchins</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881354">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n810/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GORZ</label>, with <hi rend="smallcaps">Gradisca,</hi> is one
                    of the crown-lands of the Austrian monarchy, between 45° 36' 3" and 46° 27" N.
                    lat., and bounded N. by Carinthia, E. by Carniola, Istria, and the Triestine
                    territory, S. by the Triestine territory and the Adriatic, and W. by Italy. On
                    all sides, except towards the south-west where it unites with the Friulian
                    lowland, it is surrounded by mountains, and four-sixths at least of its area of
                    1140 square miles is occupied by mountains and hills. From the ridge of the
                    Julian Alps, which rise in an almost unbroken line to a height of 6000 or 7000
                    feet, the country descends in successive terraces towards the sea, and may
                    roughly be divided into the upper highlands, the lower highlands, the hilly
                    district, and the lowlands. The highest summit is the Terglou, 9370 feet, in the
                    north-west. Geologically the country is a great limestone district, comprising
                    limestone of many different formations, Rhaetian, Jurassic, Neocomian, and
                    Nummulitic; and the strata have evidently undergone a series of powerful
                    disturbances. The hydrography is sufficiently peculiar, a considerable
                    proportion of the circulation of the waters taking place by underground
                    channels. The limits of the country coincide in the main with that of the basin
                    of the Isonzo, which rises in the extreme north at a height of 2650 feet, and
                    pursues a strange zigzag course for a distance of 78 miles before it reaches the
                    Adriatic. At Görz the Isonzo is still 138 feet above the sea, and it is
                    navigable only in its lowest section, where it takes the name of the Sdobba. Its
                    tributaries, of which the most important are the Idria, the Torre, and the
                    Wippach, are little more than mountain streams. Of special interest not only in
                    itself but for the frequent allusions to it in classical literature is the
                    Timavus or Timavo. In ancient times it appears, according to the well-known
                    description of Virgil <hi rend="italic">(Aen.,</hi> i. 244) to have rushed from
                    the mountain by nine separate mouths and with much noise and commotion, but at
                    present it usually issues from only three mouths and flows quiet and still. It
                    is strange enough, however, to see the river coming out full formed from the
                    rock, and capable at its very source of bearing vessels on its bosom. According
                    to a probable hypothesis it is a continuation of the river Reka which is lost in
                    a cleft of the rock in the south-east of the country near S. Canziano. The
                    coast-line of Görz and Gradisca, though extending for 25 miles, presents no
                    harbour of much importance. It is fringed by alluvial deposits and lagoons which
                    are for the most part of very modern formation; for as late as the 4th or 5th
                    centuries Aquileia was a great seaport. The harbour of Grado is the only one
                    accessible <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n811/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0811-0788"/> to the larger kind of coasting craft. A large
                    part of the country formerly covered with forest has been recklessly cleared,
                    but the Tarnova plateau is still a fine wooded district with an area of about 35
                    or 40 square miles. The red beech is the predominant and in some parts almost
                    the exclusive tree, but it is being displaced by the fir and the pine. Λ number
                    of pits in the plateau are full of ice all the year round, and yield about
                    16,000 cwts. annually for the consumption of the neighbouring countries. More
                    than a fifth of the area of the country is pasture-land, and less than a
                    twenty-fourth is under the plough.</p>
                <p>The vine is largely cultivated, being not only planted in regular vineyards but
                    introduced in long lines through the ordinary fields and carried up the hills in
                    terraces locally called ronchi. Wheat, maize, buck-wheat, and potatoes are the
                    usual crops. Silk growing is largely carried on, especially in the lowlands, and
                    furnishes the material for the most extensive industry of the country. There are
                    about 2000 workers in silk, and the produce is worth upwards of .£200,000, while
                    the cotton manufacture, which is next in importance, employs about 1000, and
                    produces £100,000. Leather, linen, paper, and soap are manufactured on a smaller
                    scale. The trade of the country is of very little importance. Görz and Gradisca,
                    according to the constitution of 1861, have a diet consisting of six
                    representatives of the landed proprietors, seven representatives of the towns
                    and industrial interests, and eight representatives of the rural communes. The
                    elector for the landed interest must pay 100 florins (about £10) of land-tax in
                    the Italian circle, and 50 florins (about £5) in the Slovenian circle. Two
                    representatives are sent to the imperial council. The political administration
                    is in the hands of the lieutenant of the coast-lands, which include not only
                    Görz and Gradisca but also Trieste and Istria, Roman Catholicism is the
                    exclusive religion, the only Protestant community being in the town of Görz, and
                    the Jews numbering only some 400. Ethuographically the population must contain
                    much more various elements, but in 1857, out of a total of 196,276 inhabitants,
                    130,748 were registered as Slovenians, 47,841 as Friulians, 15,134 as Italians,
                    and only 2150 as Germans.</p>
                <p>Görz first appears distinctly in history about the close of the 10th century, as
                    part of a district bestowed by the emperor Otto III. on John, patriarch of
                    Aquileia. In the 11th century it became the seat of the Eppenstein family, who
                    frequently bore the title of counts of Gorizia; and in the beginning of the 12th
                    century the eountship passed from them to the Lurngan family which continued to
                    exist till the year 1500, and acquired possessions in Tyrol, Carinthia, Friuli,
                    and Styria. In the course of the 13th and 14th centuries the counts often appear
                    as protectors <hi rend="italic">(Schirmvogt</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >Advocatιcs~)</hi> of the church of Aquileia and as captains-general of
                    Friulia. When the Venetians took possession of Friulia they gave Count Henry the
                    title of hereditary marshal as a compensation for his loss of office. The right
                    of coining was exercised by the counts from the 13th century. On the death of
                    Count Leonhard (12th April 1500) the fief reverted to the house of Hapsburg.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Görz,</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Görtz,</hi> or <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Göriz</hi> (Italian, <hi rend="italic">Gorizia·,</hi>
                    Modern Latin, (7or⅛⅛), the chief town of the crown-land, is beautifully situated
                    in the fruitful valley of the Isonzo, 25 miles N.N.W. of Trieste by railway. It
                    is the seat of an archbishop, of a circle court, and of a head tax-office. The
                    principal buildings are the cathedral, the former Jesuit church and college now
                    converted into barracks, the convents of the brothers and sisters of mercy, of
                    the·Francisans, of the Capuchins, and of the Ursulines, the municipal buildings,
                    the theatre, the house of the bishop, and the old castle of the former counts of
                    Tyrol and Görz now converted into a prison. Among the educational establishments
                    are a central episcopal seminary, a gymnasium, an upper real-school, a deaf and
                    dumb institute, and an agricultural school. The industries include cotton and
                    silk weaving, sugar refining, brewing, the manufacture of leather, and the
                    making of rosoglio. There is also a considerable trade in wooden work, fruit,
                    and wine. On account of its mild climate the town is coming to be much resorted
                    to by invalids in winter. Charles X., the exiled king of France, died at Görz
                    6th November 1836. The population of the town in 1869 was 16,659.</p>
                <p>Besides the great monograph of K. von Czörnig, <hi rend="italic">Das Land
                        Gorz</hi><hi rend="italic">und</hi><hi rend="italic">Gradisca,</hi> Vienna,
                    1873 and 1874, see Siegmund, <hi rend="italic">Südliche</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Klimatische</hi><hi rend="italic">Kurorte,</hi> Vienna, 1875; Coronini, <hi
                        rend="italic">Fastorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Goriti∙</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ensium</hi><hi rend="italic">lib.</hi> i., Vienna, 1769, and <hi
                        rend="italic">L'Antica moncta Goriziana,</hi> Gorz, 1785; Schweizer, <hi
                        rend="italic">Abrégé de l’histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">des comtes</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Gorice,</hi> Trieste, 1859; Carlo Morelli of Schönfeld, <hi
                        rend="italic">Istoria della Contea di Gorizia,</hi> Gorz, 1855-56; Della
                    Bona, <hi rend="italic">Suzdo istorico di Gorizia e di Gradisca,</hi> Gorz,
                    1853; Siebert, <hi rend="italic">Görz, Stadt und</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Land.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
