<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0610-0593-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GILDAS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 593</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:814376">Arianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v36q">Arianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n610/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GILDAS</label>, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Gγldus (c.</hi>
                    516-570), the earliest of British historians, surnamed by some Sapiens, and by
                    others Badonicus, seems to have been born in the year 516. Regarding him little
                    certain is known, beyond some isolated particulars that may be gathered from
                    hints dropped in the course of his work. Two short treatises exist, purporting
                    to be lives of Gildas, and ascribed respectively to the 11th and 12th centuries;
                    but the writers of both are believed to have confounded two, if not more,
                    persons that had borne the name. It is from an incidental remark of his own,
                    namely, that the year of the siege of Mount Badon—one of the battles fought
                    between the Saxons and the Britons— was also the year of his own nativity, that
                    the date of his birth has been derived; the place,however, is not mentioned. His
                    assertion that he was moved to undertake his task mainly by “zeal for God’s
                    house and for His holy law,” and the very free use he has made of quotations
                    from the Bible, leave scarcely a doubt that he was an eoclesiastic of some order
                    or other. In addition, we learn that he went abroad, probably to France, in his
                    thirty-fourth year, where, after 10 years of hesitation and preparation, he
                    composed, about 560, the work bearing his name. His materials, he tells us, were
                    collected from foreign rather than native sources, the latter of which had been
                    put beyond his reach by circumstances. The <hi rend="italic">Cambrian
                    Annals</hi> give 570 as the year of his death.</p>
                <p>The writings of Gildas have come down to us under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gildoe</hi><hi rend="italic">Sapientis</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Excidio Britannice Liber Querulus.</hi> Though at first written
                    consecutively, the work is now usually divided into three portions,—a preface,
                    the history proper, and an epistle,—the last, which is largely made up of
                    passages and texts of Scripture brought together for the purpose of condemning
                    the vices of his countrymen and their rulers, being the least important, though
                    by far the longest of the three. In the second he passes in brief review the
                    history of Britain from its invasion by the Romans till his own times. Among
                    other matters reference is made to the introduction of Christianity in the reign
                    of Tiberius; the persecution under Diocletian; the spread of the Arian heresy;
                    the election of Maximus as emperor by the legions in Britain, and his subsequent
                    death at Aquileia; the incursions of the Picts and Scots into the southern part
                    of the island; the temporary assistance rendered to the harassed Britons by the
                    Romans; the final abandonment of the island by the latter; the coming of the
                    Saxons and their reception by Guortigern (Vortigern); and, finally, the
                    conflicts between the Britons, led by a noble Roman,. Ambrosius Aurelianus, and
                    the new invaders. Unfortunately, on almost every point on which he touches, the
                    statements of Gildas are vague and obscure. With one exception already alluded
                    to, no dates are given, and events are not always taken up in the order of their
                    occurrence. These faults are of less importance during the period when Greek and
                    Roman writers notice the affairs of Britain; but they become more serious when,
                    as is the case from nearly the beginning of the 5th century to the date of his
                    death, Gildas’s brief narrative is our only authority for most of what passes
                    current as the history of our island during those years. Thus it is on his sole,
                    though in this instance perhaps trustworthy, testimony that the famous letter
                    rests, said to have been sent to Rome in 446 by the despairing Britons,
                    commencing:—“To Agitius (Aetius), consul for the third time, the groans of the
                    Britons.”</p>
                <p>Gildas’s treatise was first published in 1525 by Polydore Vergib but with many
                    avowed alterations and omissions. Forty-three years later Josseline, secretary
                    to Archbishop Parker, issued a new edition of it more in conformity with
                    manuscript authority; and in 1691 a still more carefully revised edition
                    appeared at Oxford by Thomas Gale. It was frequently reprinted on the Continent
                    during the 16th century, and once or twice since. The next English edition was
                    that published by the English Historical Society in 1838, and edited by the Rev.
                    J. Stevenson. Lastly, the text of Gildas, with elaborate introductions and the
                    various readings of existing manuscripts, is included in the Monumenta Historica
                    Britannica, edited by Petrie and Sharpe, London, 1848.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
