<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0013-0004-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GAD</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 4</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r753">Lying</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7p16n">Samaritans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1032344">Names</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198950">Revolt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1104504">Samaritans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205669">Jordan</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n13/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GAD</label> (Ι∣) in Hebrew and Chaldee means “luck”; hence,
                    in the Phoenician and Babylonian cultus, the god of luck, who is mentioned in
                    Isa. lxv. 11 (where for “that troop” should be read “Gad”), and whose name
                    appears in several names of places, such as Baal-Gad (Josh. xi. 17, xii. 7);
                    possibly also in Dibon-Gad, Migdol-Gad, and Nahal-Gad. Gad was the name given by
                    Leah, the wife of Jacob, to the patriarch’s seventh son, the first-born of
                    Zilpah, her maid; see Gen. xxx. 11, where the Hebrew K’tib is *1⅞3, and the K’ri
                    “U K3. The former is adopted by the LXX., and rightly rendered «V <hi
                    rend="italic">τvχr]</hi> (Vulgate <hi rend="italic">feliciter)·,</hi> the latter
                    reading is adopted in the Targums and Peshito, which translate “luck is come,”
                    and by the Samaritan and Ven., which interpret the expression as meaning “a
                    troop (or army) is come.” This last rendering has doubtless been influenced by
                    Gen. xlix. 19, where the name is played on as if it were *BΙ∣, “a plundering
                    troop”; “Gad, a plundering troop shall plunder him, but he shall plunder at
                    their heels.” Of the personal history of Gad nothing is related. According to
                    Gen. xlvi. 16, he had seven sons when he went down to Egypt along with Jacob;
                    and in Num. xxvi. 15 these appear as seven families, one of the names, however,
                    being changed (Ozni for Ezbon). At the Exodus the tribe numbered 45,650 fighting
                    men (Num. i. 25); but they declined to 40,500 during the forty years’ wandering
                    in the wilderness (Num. xxvi. 18). During the subsequent period the fortunes of
                    this tribe were very closely connected with those of the tribe of Reuben. At the
                    division of the country a portion in the trans-Jordanie territory was, at their
                    special request, allotted to them by Moses (Num. xxxii. 33), and this
                    arrangement was carried out by Joshua; but considerable difficulty arises when
                    the attempt is made to define the precise limits of the district thus assigned.
                    It is certain that Gad never extended further west than the Jordan; but in
                    different passages we find its northern, eastern, and southern boundaries
                    stretched as far as to the Sea of Galilee, Salkah in the desert, and the river
                    Arnon respectively. In the book of Numbers (xxxii. 34) the cities of Gad appear
                    to lie chiefly to the south of Heshbon; in Joshua xiii. 24-28 they lie almost
                    wholly to the north; while other texts present discrepancies that are not easily
                    reconciled with either passage. That Gad, at one time at least, held territory
                    as far south as Pisgah and Nebo would follow from Deut, xxxiii. 21, if the
                    rendering of the Targums, revived by Ewald and Diestel, were to be accepted—“and
                    he looked out the first part for himself, because there was the portion of the
                    buried lawgiver;” it is certain, however, that, at a late period, this tribe was
                    localized chiefly in Gilead, in the district which now goes by the name of Jebel
                    Jilad. Possibly some cities were common to both Reuben and Gad, and perhaps
                    0ther3 more than once changed hands. Both tribes were pastoral and warlike; but
                    the latter seems to have excelled in bravery and force of character, and indeed
                    there are indications that the tribe of Reuben had been absorbed, or become
                    extinct, at a somewhat early date. David’s men of Gad (1 Chr. xii. 8) are
                    famous, and Jephthah and Elijah seem to have belonged to that tribe. It followed
                    Jeroboam in the great revolt against the house of David; and a genealogy, a3 at
                    the time of Jeroboam II., is given in 1 Chr. v. 11-16, where the names are in
                    every case different from those in Numbers. The tribe was “carried into
                    captivity” by Tiglath Pileser in the 8th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>
                    (1 Chr. v. 26; comp. 2 Kings XV. 29), and at this point it wholly disappears
                    from history.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
