<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0570-0553-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GESENIUS, Friedrich Heinrich (9th edition, volume 10,
                    page 553)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:949578">Gymnasiums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1144248">Teachers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1061214">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048144">Orientalists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kz4v">Teachers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xf77">Criticism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n570/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GESENIUS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Friedrich
                        Heinrich</hi></label><hi rend="smallcaps">WTlhelm</hi> (1786— 1842),
                    Orientalist and biblical critic, was born at Nordhausen, Hanover, on the 3d of
                    February 1786. From the gymnasium of his native town he passed in 1803 as a
                    student of philosophy and theology to the university of Helmstadt, where Henke
                    was his most influential teacher; but the latter part of his undergraduate
                    course was taken at Gottingen, where Eichhorn and T. C. Tychsen were then at the
                    height of their popularity. In 1806, shortly after graduation, he became
                    “repetent” and “privat-docent” in that university; and, as he was fond of
                    afterwards relating, had Neander for his first pupil in Hebrew. In 1809, on the
                    recommendation of Johann von Müller, he was appointed to a mastership in the
                    gymnasium of Heiligenstadt, Westphalia, whence, in the following year, he was
                    transferred to the university of Halle, where, from being professor
                    extraordinarius in theology, lie was in a very short time promoted to an
                    ordinary chair (1811). Many offers were subsequently made to him of high
                    preferment elsewhere, but he clung to Halle for the remainder of his life, and
                    taught with great <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n571/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0571-0554"/> regularity for upwards of thirty years, the
                    only interruptions indeed being that of 1813-14, occasioned by the war of
                    liberation, during which the university was closed, and those occasioned by two
                    prolonged literary tours, first in 1820 to France and England in the society of
                    his colleague Thilo for the examination of rare Oriental manuscripts, and
                    afterwards in 1835 to England and Hollaud in connexion with his Phoenician
                    studies. At a very early period he became the most popular teacher of Hebrew and
                    of Old Testament introduction and exegesis in Germany; and during his later
                    years the annual number of students attending his lectures on these and kindred
                    subjects, such as church history and Biblical archaeology, amounted to nearly
                    500. Of his pupils many have risen to great eminence in the departments he
                    specially cultivated; among these the names of Von Bohlen, Hoffmann, Hupfeld,
                    Rödiger, Tuch, Vatke, and Benfey may be mentioned. In 1827 Gesenius was made a
                    consistorialrath; but, unless account be taken of the violent attacks to which
                    he, along with his friend and colleague Wegscheider, was in 1830 subjected by
                    Hengstenberg and his party in the <hi rend="italic">Evangelische
                        Kirchenzeitung,</hi> there are few noteworthy occurrences to be recorded in
                    his biography. His death took place at Halle, October 23, 1842. It would be
                    difficult to overestimate the services rendered by Gesenius to Semitic
                    philology. To him belongs in a large measure the credit of having freed it from
                    the trammels of theological and religious prepossession by which it had
                    previously been hampered, and of inaugurating the strictly scientific method
                    which has since been so fruitful in valuable results. Nor can it be doubted that
                    as au exegete he has exercised a powerful, and on the whole a beneficial,
                    influence on the tendencies of modern theological investigation.</p>
                <p>Of his very numerous works the earliest, published, in 1810, entitled Versuch
                    uber die Maltesische Sprache, was a successful refutation of the widely current
                    opinion that the modem Maltese was of Punic origin. In the same year appeared
                    the first volume of the Hebräisches u. Ghaldäisches Handwörteriruch, completed
                    in 1812 (8th ed., 1878; English translation by Tregelles, 1846-52). The
                    Hebräische Grammatik, published in 1813 (22d ed., by Kautzsch, 1878), was
                    followed in 1815 by the Geschichte der Hebräischen Sprache (now very rare), and
                    in 1817 by the Ausführliches Lehrgebäude der Hebräischen Sprache. The first
                    volume of his well-known commentary on Isaiah {Der Prophet Jcsajd), with a
                    translation, appeared in 1821; but the work was not completed until 1829. The
                    Thesaurus philologico-criticus Lingua Hebraicae et Chaldaicoe V. T., begun in
                    1829, he did not live to complete; the latter part of the third volume is edited
                    by Rödiger (1858). The other works of Gesenius are De Pentateuchi Samaritani
                    Origine, Indole, et Auctoritate (1815), supplemented in 1822 and 1824 by the
                    treatise De Samaritanorum theologia, and by an edition of Carmina Samaritana;
                    PaläographiscJie Studien uber Phönizische u. Punischc Schrift (1835), a
                    pioneering work which he followed up in 1837 by his collection of Phoenician
                    monuments {Scripturee lingueeque Phoeniciae monumenta guotguot supersunt'); an
                    Aramaic lexicon (1834-39); and a treatise on the Himyaritic language written in
                    conjunction with Rödiger in 1841. Gesenius also contributed extensively to Erseh
                    and Graber’s Encyclopädie, and enriched the German translation of Burckhardt <hi
                        rend="superscript"> ,</hi> s7'rarc⅛ in Syria and the Holy Land with valuable
                    geographical notes. For many years he also edited the Halle Allgemeine
                    Litcraturzcitung. A well executed sketch of his life was published in 1843
                    {Gesenius: eine Erinnerung für seine Freunde).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
