<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0739-0716-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GODWIN, Mary Wollstonecraft (9th edition, volume 10,
                    page 716)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46970190">Fiction</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:923709">Fiction</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947579">Green</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1119758">Sisters</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n739/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GODWIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mary Wollstonecraft</hi></label>
                    (1759-1797), an English authoress of the last century, was born at Hoxton, on
                    April 27, 1759. Her family was of Irish extraction, and Mary’s grandfather, who
                    was a respectable manufacturer in Spitalfields, realized the property which his
                    son squandered. Her mother, whose maiden name was Dixon, was Irish, and of good
                    family. Mr Wollstonecraft, after dissipating the greater part of his patrimony,
                    tried to earn a living by farming, which only plunged him into deeper
                    difficulties, and be led a wandering, shifty life. The family roamed from Hoxton
                    to Edmonton, to Essex, to Beverley in Yorkshire, to Laugharne, Pembrokeshire,
                    and back to London again.</p>
                <p>After Mrs Wollstonecraft’s death in 1780, soon followed by her husband’s second
                    marriage, the three daughters, Mary, Everina, and Eliza, sought to earn their
                    own livelihood. The sisters were all clever women,—Mary and Eliza far above the
                    average,—but their opportunities of culture had been few. They turned their
                    thoughts towards the profession of teaching, and Mary, the eldest, was to make
                    the first venture. She went in the first instance to live with her friend Fanny
                    Blood, a girl of her own age, whose father, like Wollstonecraft, was addicted to
                    drink and dissipation. As long as she lived with the Bloods, Mary helped Mrs
                    Blood to earn money by taking in needle-work, while Fanny painted in
                    water-colours. Everina went to live with her brother Edward, and Eliza made a
                    hasty and, as it proved, unhappy marriage with a Mr Bishop. All the
                    Wollstonecraft sisters were enthusiastic, excitable, apt to exaggerate trifles,
                    and to magnify inattentions into slights; and Eliza had the family temperament
                    in excess. Bishop was a man of violent temper, and when his wife’s reason had
                    almost given way under the miseries of her married life, Mary resolved to find
                    some means of supporting her, and arranged her secret and sudden flight. A legal
                    separation was afterwards obtained, and the sisters, together with Fanny Blood,
                    took a house, first at Islington, afterwards at Newington Green, and opened a
                    school, which was carried on with indifferent success for nearly two years.
                    During their residence at Newington Green. Mary was introduced to Dr Johnson,
                    who, as Godwin tells us, “treated her with particular kindness and attention.
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> '</p>
                <p>In 1785 Fanny Blood married Hugh Skeys, a merchant, and went with him to Lisbon,
                    where she died in childbed after sending for Mary to nurse her. “The loss of
                    Fanny,” as she said in a letter to Mrs Skeys’s brother, George Blood, “was
                    sufficient of itself to have cast a cloud over my brightest days. . . . I have
                    lost all relish for pleasure, and life seems a burden almost too heavy to be
                    endured.” Her first novel, <hi rend="italic">Mary, a Fiction,</hi> written in
                    1787, was intended to commemorate her friendship with Fanny. After closing the
                    school at Newington Green, Mary obtained a situation as governess in the family
                    of Lord Kingsborough, in Ireland, which she held for nearly a year. Her pupils
                    were much attached to her, especially Margaret King, afterwards Lady
                    Mountcashel; and indeed Lady Kingsborough gave the reason for dismissing her
                    that the children loved their governess better than their mother. Mary now
                    resolved to devote herself to literary work, and she was encouraged in this
                    purpose by Johnson, the publisher in St Paul’s Churchyard, in whose house she
                    resided for a few weeks, before she obtained lodgings in George Street,
                    Blackfriars. She acted as Johnson’s literary adviser, and undertook
                    translations, chiefly from the French. <hi rend="italic">Mary, a Fiction,</hi>
                    the story already mentioned, was not published till 1796. <hi rend="italic">The
                        Elements of Morality,</hi> an old fashioned bo,ok for children, and
                    Lavater’s <hi rend="italic">Physiognomy,</hi> were among her translations. Her
                        <hi rend="italic">Original Stories from Peal Life</hi> were published, with
                    illustrations by Blake, and in 1792 appeared <hi rend="italic">A Vindication of
                        the Eights of Woman,</hi> the work with which her name is always
                    associated.</p>
                <p>It is not among the least oddities of this book that it is dedicated to Μ.
                    Talleyrand Périgord, late bishop of Autun. Mary Wollstonecraft still believed
                    him to be sincere, and working in the same direction as herself. Tn the
                    dedication she states the “main argument” of the work, “built on this simple
                    principle that, if woman be not prepared by education to become the companion of
                    man, she will stop the progress of knowledge, for truth must be common to all,
                    or it will be inefficacious with respect to its influence or general practice.”
                    In carrying out this argument she used extraordinary plainness of speech, and it
                    was this that caused all, or nearly all, the outcry. For she did not attack the
                    institution of marriage, nor assail orthodox religion; her book was really a
                    plea for equality of education, passing into one for state education and for the
                    joint education of the sexes. It was a protest against the assumption that woman
                    was only the plaything of man, and she asserted that intellectual companionship
                    was the chief, as it is the lasting, happiness of marriage. It may, however, be
                    admitted that she discussed some subjects, not usually mentioned in print, with
                    a certain want of reticence and delicacy. She dealt directly with dangerous and
                    explosive questions, incidentally upheld greater freedom of divorce, and denied
                    the eternity of the torments of hell.</p>
                <p>Mrs Wollstonecraft, as she now styled herself, desired to watch the progress of
                    the Revolution in France, and went to Paris in 1792. Godwin, in his memoir of
                    his wife, considers that the change of residence may have been prompted by the
                    discovery that she was becoming attached to Fuseli, but there is nothing to
                    confirm this surmise; indeed, it was first proposed that she should go to Paris
                    in company with him and his wife, nor was there any subsequent breach in their
                    friendship. She remained in Paris during the Reign of Terror, when communication
                    with England was difficult or almost impossible. Some time in the spring or
                    summer of 1793 Captain Gilbert Imlay, an American, became acquainted with
                    Mary—an acquaintance which ended in a more intimate connexion. There was no
                    legal ceremony of marriage, and it is doubtful whether such a marriage would
                    have been valid at the time; but she passed as Imlay’s wife, and her brother,
                    Charles Wollstonecraft, wrote from Philadelphia that he had seen a gentleman who
                    informed him “that Mary was married to Captain Imlay of this country.” Imlay
                    himself terms her in a legal document, “Mary Imlay, my best friend and wife,”
                    and she believed that his love, which was to her sacred, would endure. In August
                    1793 Imlay was called to Havre on business, and was absent for some months,
                    during which time most of the letters published after her death by Godwin were
                    written. Towards the end of the year she joined Imlay at Havre, and there in the
                    spring of 1794 she gave birth to a girl, who received the name of Fanny, in
                    memory of the dear friend of her youth. Imlay became involved in a multitude of
                    speculations, which rendered him restless and dissatisfied, and his affection
                    for Mary and their child was already waning. He left her for some months at
                    Havre, and when he allowed her to join him in England, it appears from her
                    letters that she went with a heavy heart and forebodings of sorrow. In June
                    1795, in less than two months after their reunion, Mary again left England for
                    Norway, empowered by the document in which Imlay calls her his wife, to act for
                    him in his business <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n740/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0740-0717"/> relations with Norwegian timber merchants.
                    Her <hi rend="italic">Letters from Norway,</hi> divested of all personal
                    details, were afterwards published. She returned to England late in 1795, and
                    found letters awaiting her from Imlay, intimating his intention to separate from
                    her, and offering to settle an annuity on her and her child. For herself she
                    rejected this offer with scorn: “From you,” she wrote, “1 will not receive
                    anything more. I am not sufficiently humbled to depend on your beneficence.”
                    They met again, and for a short time lived together, until the discovery that he
                    was carrying on an intrigue under her own roof drove her to despair, and she
                    attempted to drown herself by leaping from Putney bridge, but she was rescued by
                    watermen. Imlay now completely deserted her, although she continued to bear his
                    name.</p>
                <p>In 1796, when Mary λVollstonecraft was living in London, supporting herself and
                    her child by working, as before, for Mr Johnson, she met William Godwin. A
                    friendship sprang up between them,—a friendship, as he himself says, which
                    “melted into love.” Godwin states that “ideas which he is now willing to
                    denominate prejudices made him by no means willing to conform to the ceremony of
                    marriage ;” but these prejudices were overcome, and they were married at St
                    Paneras Church on March 29, 1797. And now Mary had a season of real calm in her
                    stormy existence. Godwin, for once only in his life, was stirred by passion, and
                    his admiration for his wife equalled his affection. But their happiness was of
                    short duration. A daughter, Mary, afterwards the wife of Percy Bysshe Shelley,
                    was born August 30, 1797. At first all seemed to go well, but unfavourable
                    symptoms set in, and on September 10th,the mother, after enduring all her
                    sufferings with unvarying gentleness and sweetness of temper, passed away. She
                    was buried in the churchyard of Old St Paneras, but her remains were afterwards
                    removed by Sir Percy Shelley to the churchyard of St Peter’s, Bournemouth.</p>
                <p>Her principal published works are as follows:— <hi rend="italic">Thoughts on the
                        Education of Daughters,</hi> 1787; <hi rend="italic">The Female Reader</hi>
                    (selections), 1789; <hi rend="italic">Original Stories from Real Life,</hi>
                    1791; <hi rend="italic">An Historical and Moral Vieιv of the Origin a/nd
                        Progress of the French Revolution, and the Effects it has produced in
                        Europe,</hi> vol. i. (no more published), 1790; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vindication of the Rights of Woman,</hi> 1792; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vindication of the Rights of Man,</hi> 1793; <hi rend="italic">Mary, a
                        Fiction,</hi> 1796; <hi rend="italic">Letters written during a Short
                        Residence in Sweden, Norway, and Denmark,</hi> 1796; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Posthumous Works,</hi> 4 vols., 1798. It is impossible to trace the many
                    articles contributed by her to periodical literature, or to identify the
                    translations executed for Mr Johnson. A memoir of her life was published by
                    Godwin soon after her decease. A large portion of the work, <hi rend="italic"
                        >William Godwin, his Friends and Contemporaries,</hi> was devoted to her,
                    and a new edition of the <hi rend="italic">Letters to Imlay,</hi> London, 1879,
                    of which the first edition was published by Godwin, is prefaced by a somewhat
                    fuller memoir. (C. K. P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
