<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0584-0567-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GHIRLANDAJO, Domenico del</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 567</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1005463">Magi</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1115813">Shepherds</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n584/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GHIRLANDAJO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Domenico del</hi></label>
                    (1449-1494), an illustrious Florentine painter. His full name is given as
                    Domenico di Tommaso Curradi di DoffoBigordi; it appears therefore that his
                    father’s surname was Curradi, and his grandfather’s Bigordi. The painter is
                    generally termed Domenico Bigordi, but some authors give him, and apparently
                    with reason, the paternal surname Curradi. Ghirlandajo (garland-maker) was only
                    a nickname, coming to Domenico from the employment of his father (or else of his
                    earliest instructor), who was renowned for fashioning the metallic garlands worn
                    by Florentine damsels; he was not, however, as some have said, the inventor of
                    them, Tommaso was by vocation a jeweller on the Ponte Vecchio, or perhaps a
                    broker. Domenico, the eldest of eight children, was at first apprenticed to a
                    jeweller or goldsmith, probably enough his own father; in his shop he was
                    continually making portraits of the passers-by, and it was thought expedient to
                    place him with Alessio Baldovinetti to study painting and mosaic. His youthful
                    years were, however, entirely undistinguished, and at the age of thirty-one he
                    had not a fixed abode of his own. This is remarkable, as immediately afterwards,
                    from 1480 onwards to his death at a comparatively early age in 1494, he became
                    the most proficient painter of his time, incessantly employed, and condensing
                    into that brief period of fourteen years fully as large an amount of excellent
                    work as any other artist that could be named; indeed, we should properly say
                    eleven years, for nothing of his is known of a later date than 1491.</p>
                <p>In 1480 Ghirlandajo painted a St Jerome and other frescos in the church of
                    Ognissanti, Florence, and a life-sized Last Supper in its refectory, noticeable
                    for individual action and expression. From 1481-1485 he was employed upon
                    frescos in the Sala dell’ Orologio in the Palazzo Vecchio; he painted the
                    apotheosis of St Zenobius, a work beyond the size of life, with much
                    architectural framework, figures of Roman heroes, and other detail, striking in
                    perspective and structural propriety. While still occupied here, he was summoned
                    to Rome by Pope Sixtus IV. to paint in the Sixtine Chapel; he went thither not
                    earlier than 1482. In the Sixtine he executed, probably before 1484, a fresco
                    which has few rivals in that series, Christ calling Peter and Andrew to their
                    Apostleship,—a work which, though somewhat deficient in colour, has greatness of
                    method and much excellence of finish. The landscape background, in especial, is
                    very superior to anything to Le found in the works, which had no doubt been
                    zealously studied by Ghirlandajo, of Masaccio and Masolino in the Brancacci
                    Chapel. He also did some other works in Rome, now perished. Before 1485 he had
                    likewise produced his frescos in the chapel of S. Fina, in the Tuscan town of S.
                    Gemignano, remarkable for grandeur and grace,—two pictures of Fina, dying and
                    dead, with some accessory work. Sebastian Mainardi assisted him in these
                    productions in Rome and in S. Gemignano; and Ghirlandajo was so well <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n585/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0585-0568"/> pleased with his co-operation that he gave him
                    his sister in marriage.</p>
                <p>He now returned to Florence, and undertook in the church of the Trinita, and
                    afterwards in S. Maria Novella, the works which have set the seal on his
                    celebrity. The frescos in the Sassetti Chapel of S. Trinita are six subjects
                    from the life of St Francis, along with some classical accessories, dated 1485.
                    Three of the principal incidents are St Francis obtaining from Pope Honorius the
                    approval of the Rules of his Order; his Death and Obsequies; and the
                    Resuscitation, by the interposition of the beatified saint, of a child of the
                    Spini family, who had been killed by falling out of a window. Iu the first work
                    is a portrait of Lorenzo de’ Medici; and in the third the painter’s own
                    likeness, which he introduced also into one of the pictures in S. Maria Novella,
                    and in the Adoration of the Magi in the hospital of the Innocenti. The
                    altar-piece of the Sassetti •Chapel, the Adoration of the Shepherds, is now in
                    the Florentine Academy. Immediately after disposing of this commission,
                    Ghirlandajo was asked to renew the frescos in the choir of S. Maria Novella.
                    This choir formed the chapel of the Ricci family, but the Tornabuoni and
                    Torna-quinci families, then much more opulent than the Ricci, undertook the cost
                    of the restoration, under conditions, as to preserving the arms of the Ricci,
                    which gave rise in the end to some amusing incidents of litigation. The frescos,
                    in the execution of which Domenico had many assistants, are in four courses
                    along the three walls,—the leading subjects being the Lives of the Madonna and
                    of the Baptist. Besides their general richness and dignity of art, these w0rk3
                    are particularly interesting as containing many historical portraits—a method of
                    treatment in which Ghir-landιjo was pre-eminently skilled. There are no less
                    than twenty-one portraits of the Tornabuoni and Tomaquinci families; in the
                    subject of the Angel appearing to Zacharias, those of Poliziano, Marsilio
                    Ficino, and others; in the Salutation of Anna and Elizabeth, the beautiful
                    Ginevra de’ Benci; in the Expulsion of Joachim from the Temple, Mainardi and
                    Baldovinetti (or the latter figure may perhaps be Ghirlandajo’s father). The
                    Ricci chapel was re-opened and completed in 1490; the altar-piece, now removed
                    from the chapel, was probably executed with the assistance of .Domenico’s
                    brothers, David and Benedetto, painters of ordinary calibre; the painted window
                    was from Domenico’s own design. Other distinguished works from his hand are an
                    altar-piece iu tempera of the Virgin adored by Sts Zenobius, Justus, and others,
                    painted for the church of St Justus, but now in the Uffizi gallery, a remarkable
                    masterpiece; Christ in glory with Romuald and other Sainte, in the Badia of
                    Volterra; the Adoration of the Magi, in the church of the Innocenti (already
                    mentioned), perhaps his finest panelpicture, 1488; and the Visitation, in the
                    Louvre, bearing the latest ascertained date, 1491, of all his works. Ghirlandajo
                    did not often attempt the nude; one of his pictures of this character, Vulcan
                    and his Assistants forging Thunderbolts, wa3 painted for Lo Spedaletto, but
                    (like several others specified by Vasari) it exists no longer. The picture
                    attributed to him in the London National Gallery is dubious; it may perhaps have
                    come from the atelier of Verrocchio. The mosaics which he produced date before
                    1491; one, of especial celebrity, is the Annunciation, on a portal of the
                    cathedral of Florence.</p>
                <p>In general artistic attainment Ghirlandajo may fairly be regarded as exceeding
                    all his precursors or competitors; though the names of a few, particularly
                    Giotto, Masaccio, Lippo Lippi, and Botticelli, stand higher for originating
                    power. His scheme of composition is grand and decorous; his chiaroscuro
                    excellent, and especially his perspectives, which he would design on a very
                    elaborate scale by the eye alone; his colour is more open to criticism, but this
                    remark applies much less to the frescos than the tempera-pictures, which are
                    sometimes too broadly and crudely bright. He worked in these two methods
                    alone—never in oils; and his frescos are what the Italians term “buon fresco,”
                    without any finishing in tempera. A certain hardness of outline, not unlike the
                    character of bronze sculpture, may attest his early training in metal work. He
                    first introduced into Florentine art that mixture of the sacred and the profane
                    which had already been practised in Siena. His types in figures of Christ, the
                    Virgin, and angels are not of the highest order; and a defect of drawing, which
                    has been often pointed out, is the meagreness of his hands and feet. It was one
                    of his maxims that “painting is designing.” Ghirlandajo was an insatiate worker,
                    and expressed a wish that he had the entire circuit of the walls of Florence to
                    paint upon. He told his shop-assistants not to refuse any commission that might
                    offer, were it even for a lady’s petticoat-panniers: if they would not execute
                    such work, <hi rend="italic">he</hi> would. Not that he was in any way grasping
                    or sordid in money-matters, as is proved by the anecdote of the readiness with
                    which he gave up a bonus upon the stipulated price of the Ricci chapel frescos,
                    offered by the wealthy Tornabuoni in the first instance, but afterwards
                    begrudged. Vasari says that Ghirlandajo was the first to abandon in. great part
                    the use of gilding in his pictures, representing by genuine painting any objects
                    supposed to be gilded; yet this does not hold good without some considerable
                    exceptions— the high lights of the landscape, for instance, in the Adoration of
                    the Shepherds, now in the Florence Academy, being put in in gold. Many drawings
                    and sketches by this painter are in the Uffizi Gallery, remarkable for vigour of
                    outline. One of the great glories of Ghirlandajo is that he gave some early
                    art-education to Michelangelo, who cannot, however, have remained with him long.
                    Granacci was another of his pupils.</p>
                <p>This renowned artist died of pestilential fever on 11th January 1494, and was
                    buried in S. Maria Novella. He had been twice married, and left six children,
                    three of them being sons* He had a long and honourable line of descendants,
                    which came to a close in the 17th century, when the last members of the race
                    entered monasteries. It is probable that Domenico died poor; he appears to have
                    been gentle, honourable, and conscientious, as well as energetically diligent.
                    (w. Μ. κ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
