<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0869-0846-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GOTHS (9th edition, volume 10, page 846)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945091">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032344">Names</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1227863">Lithuania</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n869/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GOTHS</label>. The historical position of the Gothic nation
                    needs to be marked out with special care, both on account of various lax popular
                    uses of the Gothic name, and also on account of much legendary history and many
                    rash ethnological speculations, ancient and modern, which have gathered round
                    the true history of the Gothic people. An ignorant age used the words <hi
                        rend="italic">Goth</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gothic</hi> as vague names of
                    contempt for anything that was thought rude and barbarous. A hardly less
                    ignorant but better disposed age used the word <hi rend="italic">Gothic</hi> in
                    an equally vague way, but without the same feeling of contempt, for anything
                    which was thought to be mediaeval or “romantic,” as opposed to <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n870/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0870-0847"/> “classical.” The name came also to be used as
                    a philological or ethnological term; we heard of “Gothic nations,” “Gothic
                    languages,” &lt;fcc., meaning “Teutonic” in the widest sense. The name was also,
                    first scornfully, then respectfully, applied to a style of architecture which
                    has some claim to be called Teutonic as opposed to Greek or Roman, but which has
                    nothing whatever to do with the Goths as a nation. Long before this, two
                    European sovereigns who had nothing whatever to do with the national Goths, took
                    the title of King of the Goths out of a mere accidental likeness of names. All
                    these uses of the Gothic name must be carefully distinguished from the history
                    of the true national Goths who play so great a part in Europe from the 3d to the
                    8th century of our era. The Goths may on many grounds claim the foremost place
                    among the Teutonic nations which had a share in the break-up of the Roman power.
                    They were among the earliest, if not quite the earliest, of the Teutonic nations
                    to establish themselves within the empire, as distinguished from merely ravaging
                    its frontiers. Their history too is closely connected with the geography of the
                    whole empire. Their first historical appearance was in the East; their great
                    historical settlements were made in the West. No Teutonic people fills so great
                    a place in the political and military history of the 4th, 5th, and 6th
                    centuries, and no Teutonic people has left behind it such early remains of a
                    written native literature. The real greatness of the Goths quite accounts for
                    the many vague uses of the Gothic name. Alike in scorn and in honour, the Goths
                    have been, not unreasonably, taken as the representatives of the whole Teutonic
                    race. The wonderful thing is that a people who played so great a part for
                    several ages should have wholly passed away. The Goths have not for many ages
                    existed anywhere as a distinct nation, nor have they given-an abiding name to
                    any part of Europe. Franks, Angles, Saxons, Burgundians, Frisians, Thuringians
                        <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi>, Lombards, Bavarians, perhaps Vandals, are all
                    visible on the modern map. So several parts of Europe have at different times
                    been known as <hi rend="italic">Gothia·,</hi> but the name was never borne by
                    any large country, and it has nowhere lasted down to modern times.</p>
                <p>The chief ancient authority for the early history of the Goths is their national
                    historian Jordanis, who chiefly followed the Gothic history of Cassiodorus the
                    minister of Theodoric, and the lost history of Ablavius. (On the value of
                    Jordanis’s writings see Palimann, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">V'olher-wanderung,</hi> i. 23.) But he is careless and
                    uncritical, and, like other national historians, is full of mythical elements in
                    the early part. He has to be tested throughout by the contemporary Roman and
                    Greek writers from the 3d century to the 6th. Among these, perhaps the first
                    place is due to Ammianus in the 4th century and to Procopius in the 6 th.</p>
                <p>The first certain historical appearance of the Goths is in the lands north of the
                    lower Danube in the 3d century of our era. For any earlier account of them we
                    have to go either to mythical stories or to ingenious guesses and inferences.
                    There are a remarkable number of national and legendary names which have more or
                    less of likeness to the name <hi rend="italic">Goth</hi>; and this likeness has
                    naturally led to an unusual number of theories. The Goths first’appear in
                    history in the ancient land of the <hi rend="italic">Getae·,</hi> and this
                    geographical fact, combined with the likeness of the names, has naturally caused
                        <hi rend="italic">Getae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Goths</hi> to be looked
                    on as the same people. The identification is as old as our first historical
                    mention of the Goths (Aelius Spartianus, <hi rend="italic">Ant. Car.,</hi> 10).
                    Claudian always speaks of the Goths as <hi rend="italic">Getae.</hi> So does the
                    national historian Jordanis (cap. v.). The identity is mentioned doubtingly by
                    Procopius <hi rend="italic">{Bell. Vand.,</hi> i. 2; c∕. <hi rend="italic">Bell.
                        Goth.,</hi> v. 4). It is strongly maintained by Jacob Grimm <hi
                        rend="italic">{Geschichte der Deutschen Sprache,</hi> capp. ix., xviii.),
                    but is rejected by nearly all later writers. A more famous legend, which has
                    derived its chief currency from Jordanis, brings the Goths first of all from
                    Scandinavia (see Gibbon, c. x.; Geijer’s <hi rend="italic">History of
                        Sweden,</hi> c. x.). There is a so-called East and West Gothland in Sweden,
                    but the connexion of these lands with the Goths of Roman history is more than
                    doubtful. Ptolemy (ii. 11, 35) places the Γo⅛αι in Scandia, and Procopius <hi
                        rend="italic">{Bell. Goth.,</hi> ii. 15) knew the Γαυτοί among the
                    inhabitants of Thoule; but he clearly did not look on them as Goths (see Zeuss,
                        <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Deutschen,</hi> 500, 511; Grimm,
                    p. 312). Then there is the god <hi rend="italic">Gedt</hi> (see Kemble’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Saxons in England,</hi> i. 370), and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gedtas,</hi> who figure in Beowulf, and elsewhere in Old-English writings.
                    The Traveller’s Song (34, 115, 177) distinctly distinguishes <hi rend="italic"
                        >Goths</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gedtas,</hi> and couples the latter with
                    the Swedes. Pliny <hi rend="italic">{Nat. Hist.,</hi> iv. 11) places <hi
                        rend="italic">Getae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gaudoe</hi> together on the
                    lower Danube. His <hi rend="italic">Gaudae</hi> may possibly be Goths; if so,
                    they are distinguished from the <hi rend="italic">Getae.</hi> Then there are the
                        <hi rend="italic">Jutes</hi> of Old-English history, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Guttones, Gothones, Gothini</hi> (see Latham, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Germania,</hi> Epilegomena xxxviii. <hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">seqg.).</hi> Pytheas, according to Pliny <hi rend="italic"
                        >{Nat. Hist.,</hi> xxxvii. 7; <hi rend="italic">cf.</hi> iv. 14) placed the
                        <hi rend="italic">Guttones</hi> on the south coast of the Baltic (that seems
                    to be his meaning), and rules them to be a German people. This carries the name
                    back to the time of Alexander. Ptolemy also (iii. 5, 20) has Γυ'0ωveς in
                    Sarmatia on the Vistula. Tacitus <hi rend="italic">{Germania,</hi> 43)
                    distinguishes the German <hi rend="italic">Gothones</hi> in the same region from
                    the Celtic <hi rend="italic">Gothini,</hi> whom he places seemingly nearer to
                    the Carpathians. Tacitus moreover not only speaks of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gothones</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Gotones</hi> as a people, but mentions
                        <hi rend="italic">{Ann.,</hi> ii. 62) a particular man of the nation,
                    Catualda by name, as having restored the independence of his people after it had
                    been overthrown by Maroboduus. With this hint, it is perhaps not too much to
                    infer with Aschbach <hi rend="italic">{Westgotheη,</hi> 2d ed.) and Zeuss (136)
                    that for Boυτoves in Strabo (vii. 1), who are mentioned among the nations
                    subject to Maroboduus, we should read Γoυτoreς. And there is no doubt that names
                    like <hi rend="italic">Getae, Gethae, Guddoe,</hi> even <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gothi,</hi> lived on almost to modern times, first as national names, then
                    as names of contempt, in Poland, Lithuania, and Prussia (see Latham, and Zeuss,
                    672). Latham asserts the identity of the names <hi rend="italic">Getae,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Gothi,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gothones,</hi> but he holds
                    (see especially p. 42 of his Epilegomena) that both <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gothones</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Getae</hi> were Lithuanian, and that
                    the Teutonic Goths took the name of the people whom they had conquered. They
                    would, on this view, be Goths only in the sense in which Englishmen are
                    Britons.</p>
                <p>On the whole, it seems that there is no trustworthy evidence for a migration of
                    the Goths from Scandinavia, and that the idea was suggested only by the likeness
                    of name between the true Goths and the <hi rend="italic">Gauts</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">Gedtas</hi> of Swedish history. The application of the name
                        <hi rend="italic">Gothland</hi> to the island <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gotland,</hi> as well as to the continental <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gauthiod,</hi> is a further mistake. Nor does there seem to be any reason
                    for making <hi rend="italic">Goths</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Getae</hi> the
                    same. But the identification of the Goths with the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gothones,</hi> Γoυτoveς, <hi rend="italic">Guttones,</hi> on the south
                    coast of the Baltic (which is accepted by Pallmann and Dahn) has much more to be
                    said for it. <hi rend="italic">Gothi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Gothones</hi>
                    are strictly the same name; the double form is usual in the Latin shapes of
                    Teutonic names. But the whole history of the Goths in their northern seats is
                    summed up in the personal history of Catualda, who, after delivering his people
                    from Maroboduus, was himself overthrown by the Hermunduri. The continuous and
                    certain history of the Gothic nation begins in the Roman Dacia.</p>
                <p>The question now comes, Which of the nations which are historically connected
                    with the Goths had any closer connexion with them than that of common Teutonic
                    origin? Setting aside Getae and other doubtful theories, the real <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n871/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0871-0848"/> Gothic name is used by the Greek and Latin
                    writers in a wider and in a narrower sense. We must also bear in mind the vague
                    way in which the ancient writers used national names, and their fondness for
                    using obsolete names. Thus the Goths and other Teutonic nations are spoken of as
                    Scythians and Sarmatians. Procopius, in an evidently well-considered passage <hi
                        rend="italic">(Bell. Vaιul.,</hi> i. 2), speaks of the Goths as having been
                    formerly called Σαυρορ,άται και Μελαγχλαινοι, names which come out of
                    Herodotus’s description of the regions where the Goths first appear. But he
                    gives it as the definite result of his own observations that Goths,—by this name
                    he always means specially the East-Goths,— Vandals, West-Goths, and Gepidae
                    (Γ^7rαιδeς, with an evident intention to give the word a Greek meaning) were
                    originally one nation, speaking one Gothic language. The only question is about
                    the Vandals. The Gepidae are commonly acknowledged as a branch of the Gotlιs,
                    and Jordanis (17) has a legend which implies their kindred. The Taifake
                    (Ammianus, xxxi. 19), the Bastarnae, Peucini, and other tribes are also reckoned
                    among the Gothic races. In other passages Procopius speaks of several other
                    nations, as the Alans, Rogi, and Scirri, as Gothic, but he does not seem to be
                    in the same way pronouncing a definite judgment. Among all these, the historical
                    Goths, who play a part in European history by that name, consist of the East and
                    West Goths, and of the small division called Tetraxitae. The division into East
                    and West Goths does not appear in the earlier writers, as Ammianus and Zosimus,
                    but we find it both in Procopius and in Jordanis. Instead of East-Goths and
                    West-Goths, we read in Ammianus, Zosimus, and Claudian of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Greuthungi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tervingi.</hi> These seem to be (see
                    Aschbach, 21; Zeuss, 406; Köpke, 103) the strictly national names of the two
                    divisions, which took the names of East and West Goths from their geographical
                    position in the lands which they entered. There is an exact parallel in England,
                    where the national name of the <hi rend="italic">Gewissas</hi> gives way to the
                    geographical name of <hi rend="italic">West-Saxons.</hi> Jordanis indeed doubts
                    whether the East-Goths were so called from their eastern position, or from a
                    king Ostrogotha. Strange to say, this Ostrogotha seems to be a real person, and
                    not a mere mythical eponym. Ojστpιγ0τ0oς (Procop., <hi rend="italic">Bell.
                        Goth.,</hi> iv. 27) is an historical person at a later date, and the name is
                    borne in a feminine shape by one of the daughters of Theodoric. The history of
                    the East and λVest Goths, as far as the empire is concerned, falls naturally
                    into three periods. In the 3d century they are still settled outside the empire,
                    and appear as invaders and ravagera of the Roman territory from outside. After
                    an interval in which they almost sink out of notice, they appear again within
                    the bounds of the empire, in various relations of alliance and enmity, marching
                    to and fro, but not making any lasting settlement. It is not till the 5th
                    century that they begin to form settled powers. During their wandering stage
                    they appear mainly in the Eastern empire. But neither they nor any other
                    Teutonic people founded any permanent settlement within its borders. The
                    historical settlements of the Goths are the short and brilliant dominion of the
                    East-Goths in Italy, and the more lasting dominion of the West-Goths in Gaul and
                    Spain.</p>
                <p>After the first vague mention of the Goths under Antoninus Caracalla, they begin
                    to play a distinct part in the reign of Alexander Severus. They were then in
                    Dacia, and received a tribute or subsidy of some kind (Petrus Patricius, 124,
                    ed. Bonn). The next emperor, Maximin, is claimed by Jordanis (15) as himself of
                    Gothic birth, but we may suspect the usual confusion with the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Getoe.</hi> The narrative of Jordanis begins from this point to put on a
                    more historical character, and his account is helped out by various notices in
                    the Augustan History. In the reign of Philip (244-248 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >λ.d.)</hi> they passed the Danube and ravaged Moesia, and in 251 the
                    emperor Decius fell in battle against them (see Zosimus, i. 19 ci <hi
                        rend="italic">seqq.</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> y</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">).</hi> From this time they ravaged eastern Europe and western
                    Asia far and wide (251-268). They carried on their warfare by sea, and reached
                    as far east as Trebizond. And it seems to have been now that the first permanent
                    Gothic settlement was made, though not strictly within the lands of the empire.
                    This was in the Tauric Chersonesos or Crim. Here their settlement lasted for
                    many ages, and they became allies rather than subjects of the empire in the
                    reign of Justinian. Within the empire the Gothic inroads met with repulses at
                    several points, especially from the local forces of Athens under the historian
                    Dexippus (Trebellius, Gallienus 13, and the fragment of Dexippus himself). At
                    last, in 269, the Goths suffered a decisive defeat from the emperor Claudius at
                    Naissus in Dardania, which formed an epoch in Gothic history. It answers to the
                    repulse of the Saxons from Britain by the elder Theodosius. The first attempt at
                    Gothic settlement south of the Danube had been premature. It had to be repeated
                    at a later time with greater success.</p>
                <p>Further victories over the Goths are attributed to Aurelian. But the chief event
                    of his reign was one which amounted to a legal acknowledgment of Gothic
                    occupation north of the Danube. The Roman legions were withdrawn from Dacia, and
                    the name of Trajan’s great conquest was transferred to the land south of the
                    Danube (274). That is, the great river was established as the boundary between
                    the Roman and Gothic dominions. The wisdom of this cession is shown by its being
                    followed by a period of ninety years in which the peace between the Goths and
                    the empire was seldom seriously broken. The chief interruption was during the
                    reign of Constantine, when the Gothic king Araric invaded the empire, and, after
                    some momentary successes, was driven back. In the middle of the 4th century a
                    great power arose under the East-Gothic king Ermanaric (less correctly <hi
                        rend="italic">Hermanric -,</hi> the name is the same as <hi rend="italic"
                        >Eοrmenric,</hi> in the royal line of Kent), of the house of the Amali,
                    which was reckoned to be the noblest among the Goths. Ermanaric has become a
                    great figure in Teutonic legend, and it is not easy to say how far legend has
                    built upon history, and how far so-called history has drawn from legend. But
                    that Ermanaric was a real man, and the founder of a great dominion, is plain
                    from the few words of Ammianus (xxxi. 3). Yet there is something unsatisfactory
                    in the way in which we read vague accounts of the greatness of his power, with
                    hardly a glimpse of himself personally. The period assigned to his reign is full
                    of stirring events, in which we get a clear conception of much lesser Gothic
                    chiefs, but none of Ermanaric himself. Jordanis (23) claims for him a vast
                    dominion stretching from the Danube to the Baltic, and he is specially emphatic
                    on the subjection of the Slavonic nations to the rule of the Gothic overlord.
                    With regard to the Gothic nations, we can see that the rule of Ermanaric was a
                    mere overlordship. The West-Goths appear as a distinct people, with the power of
                    making war and peace on their own account. But they had no kings; their great
                    chief Athanaric appears only as “judge” (Ammianus, xxvii. 5; xxxi. 3), answering
                    to our <hi rend="italic">ealdorman</hi> or <hi rend="italic">heretoga (cf.</hi>
                    Jordanis, 26); and along with him are other West-Gothic chiefs, specially his
                    rival Frithigern. We hear of a civil war between these two rivals (Socrates, iv.
                    33), and it is more certain that Athanaric made war within the Roman border as
                    an ally of the usurper of Procopius in 365, and afterwards made peace with the
                    emperor Valens. By this time Christianity was making swift advances among the
                    Goths. According to the view of some modern writers (Köpke, 123; Pallmann, ii.
                    63), the outlying Gothic settlement in Crim had been Christian and Catholic from
                    the beginning; but now Christianity in its Arian form began to be gradually
                    accepted by the great <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n872/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0872-0849"/> mass of the Gothic nation. This was mainly
                    the work of the teaching of Ulfila (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Ulfila),</hi> the
                    Gothic apostle and translator of the Scriptures into the Gothic tongue (Sozomen,
                    iv. 24). According to some accounts (Pallmann, i. 71), he had, to avoid
                    persecution, led a Christian colony south of the Danube (348), who settled
                    peaceably at Nicopolis, and are hence known as Mcesogoths (seemingly the <hi
                        rend="italic">Gothi Minores</hi> of Jordanis, 51). Later, in 370, there was
                    another great persecution, in which Athauaric, the special enemy of everything
                    Roman, appears also as the enemy of the Christians, while Frithigern is their
                    friend (Sozomen, vi. 37; Socrates, iv. 33). The distinction between Christian
                    and heathen G∩ths remains of political importance for some time. But both East
                    and West Goths had fully embraced Arianism long before the end of the 5th
                    century, while the Goths of Crim seem to have remained Catholic, and received
                    Catholic bishops from Saint John Chrysostom, and afterwards from Justinian.</p>
                <p>Towards the end of the reign of Ermanaric several causes joined together to break
                    his great dominion asunder. There were clearly signs of division between East
                    and West Goths, between Christians and heathens, as well as discontents among
                    the subject nations. These causes of division were now strengthened by pressure
                    from without. Now began the first of those movements of the Turanian races into
                    the lands north of the Danube, which have had such an effect on the history of
                    south-eastern Europe down to our own time. The Huns pressed on the new dominion
                    of the Goths, which was already beginning to break in pieces. Ermanaric died at
                    the age, it is said, of 110, by the hands of subject princes stirred to wrath by
                    his cruelties (Jordanis, 24). All thought of a lasting Gothic dominion north of
                    the Danube died with him. With his fall the movements south of that river begin
                    again on a great scale.</p>
                <p>From this time the history of the East and West Goths parts asunder, to be joined
                    together again only incidentally and for a season. The great mass of the
                    East-Goths stayed north of the Danube, and passed under the overlordship of the
                    Hun. They do not for the present play any important part in the affairs of the
                    empire. The great mass of the West-Goths crossed the Danube into the Roman
                    provinces, and there played a most important part in various characters of
                    alliance and enmity. The great migration was in 376, when they were allowed to
                    pass as peaceful settlers under their chief Frithigern. His rival Athanaric
                    seems to have tried to maintain his party for a while north of the Danube in
                    defiance of the Hun3; but he had presently to follow the example of the great
                    mass of the nation. The peaceful designs of Frithigern were meanwhile thwarted
                    by the ill-treatment which the Goths suffered from the Roman officials, which
                    led first to disputes and then to open war. In 378 the Goths won the great
                    battle of Adrianople, in which the emperor Valens was killed. His successor
                    Theodosius the Great made terms with them in 381, and the mass of the Gothic
                    warriors entered the Roman service as <hi rend="italic">foederati.</hi> Many of
                    their chiefs were in high favour; but it seems that the orthodox Theodosius
                    showed more favour to the still remaining heathen party among the Goths than to
                    the larger part of them who had embraced Arian Christianity. Athanaric himself
                    came to Constantinople in 381; he was received with high honours, and had a
                    solemn funeral when he died. His saying is worth recording, as an example of the
                    effect which Roman civilization had on the Teutonic mind. “The emperor,” he
                    said, “was a god upon earth, and he who resisted him would have his blood on his
                    own head.”</p>
                <p>The death of Theodosius in 395 broke up the union between the West-Goths and the
                    empire. Dissensions arose between them and the ministers of Arcadius; the Goths
                    threw off their allegiance, and chose Alaric as their king. This was a
                    restoration alike of national unity and of national independence. The royal
                    title had not been borne by their leaders in the Roman service. Alaric's
                    position is quite different from that of several Goths in the Roman service, who
                    appear as simple rebels (see Köpke, 128). He was of the great WesbGothic house
                    of the Balti (bold), a house second in nobility only to that of the Amali. His
                    whole career was taken up with marchings to and fro within the lands, first of
                    the Eastern, then of the Western empire. The Goths are under him an independent
                    people under a national king; their independence is in no way interfered with if
                    the Gothic king, in a moment of peace, accepts the office and titles of a Roman
                    general. But under Alaric the Goths make no lasting settlement. In the long tale
                    of intrigue and warfare between the Goths and the two imperial courts which
                    fills up this whole time, cessions of territory are offered to the Goths,
                    provinces are occupied by them, but as yet they do not take root anywhere; no
                    Western land as yet becomes <hi rend="italic">Gothia.</hi> Alaric’s designs of
                    settlement seem in his first stage to have still kept east of the Adriatic, in
                    Illyricum, possibly in Greece. Towards the end of his career his eyes seem fixed
                    on Africa (see Köpke, 128).</p>
                <p>Greece was the scene of his great campaign in 39G, the second Gothic invasion of
                    that country. In this campaign the religious position of the Goths is strongly
                    marked. The Arian appeared as an enemy alike to the pagan majority and the
                    Catholic minority; but he came surrounded by monks, and his chief wrath was
                    directed against the heathen temples (Hertzberg, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte
                        Griechenlands,</hi> iii. 391). His Italian campaigns fall into two great
                    divisions, that of 402-3, when he was driven back by Stilicho, and that of
                    408-10, after Stilicho’s death. In this second war he thrice besieged Rome (408,
                    409, 410). The second time it suited a momentary policy to set up a puppet
                    emperor of his own, and even to accept a military commission from him. The third
                    time he sacked the city, the first time since Brennus that Rome had been taken
                    by an army of utter foreigners. The intricate political and military details of
                    these campaigns are of less importance in the history of the Gothic nation than
                    the stage which Alaric’s reign marks in the history of that nation. It stands
                    between two periods of settlement within the empire and of service under the
                    empire. Under Alaric there is no settlement, and service is quite secondary and
                    precarious; after his death in 410 the two begin again in new shapes.</p>
                <p>Contemporary with the campaigns of Alaric was a barbarian invasion of Italy,
                    which, according to one view, again brings the East and West Goths together. The
                    great mass of the East-Goths, as has been already said, became one of the many
                    nations which were under vassalage to the Huns; but their relation was one
                    merely of vassalage. They remained a distinct people under kings of their own,
                    kings of the house of the Amali and of the kindred of Ermanaric (Jordanis, 48).
                    They had to follow the lead of the Huns in war, but they were also able to carry
                    on wars of their own; and it has been held (see Köpke, 139; Pallmann, ii. 173,
                    277) that among these separate East-Gothic enterprises we are to place the
                    invasion of Italy in 405 by Radagaisus (whom Pallmann writes Ratiger, and takes
                    him for the chief of the heathen part of the East-Goths). One chronicler,
                    Prosper, makes.this invasion preceded by another in 400, in which Alaric and
                    Radagaisus appear as partners. The paganism of Radagaisus is certain. The
                    presence of Goths in his army is certain, but it seems dangerous to infer that
                    his invasion was a national Gothic enterprise.</p>
                <p>Under Ataulf, the brother-in-law and successor of Alaric, another era opens, the
                    beginning of enterprises which did in the end lead to the establishment of a
                    settled Gothic monarchy in the West. The position of Ataulf is well <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n873/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0873-0850"/> marked by the speech put into his mouth by
                    Orosius. He had at one time dreamed of destroying the Roman power, of turning
                        <hi rend="italic">Romania</hi> into <hi rend="italic">Gothia,</hi> and
                    putting Ataulf in the stead of Augustus; but he had learned that the world could
                    be governed only by the laws of Rome, and he had determined to use the Gothic
                    arms for the support of the Roman power. And in the confused and contradictory
                    accounts of his actions (for the story in Jordanis cannot be reconciled with the
                    accounts in Olympiodorus and the chroniclers), we can see something of this
                    principle at work throughout. Gaul and Spain were overrun both by barbarian
                    invaders and by rival emperors. The sword of the Goth was to win back the lost
                    lauds for Rome. And, amid many shiftings of allegiance, Ataulf seems never to
                    have wholly given up the position of an ally of the empire. His marriage with
                    Placidia, the daughter of the great Theodosius, was taken as the seal of the
                    union between Goth and Roman, and, had their son Theodosius lived, a dynasty
                    might have arisen uniting both claims. But the career of Ataulf was cut short at
                    Barcelona in 415, by his murder at the hands of another faction of the Goths.
                    The reign of Sigeric was momentary. Under Wallia in 418 a more settled state of
                    things was established. The empire received again, as the prize of Gothic
                    victories, the Tarraconensis in Spain, and Novempopulana and the Narbonensis in
                    Gaul. The “second Aquitaine,” with the sea-coast from the mouth of the Garonne
                    to the mouth of the Loire, became the West-Gothic kingdom of Toulouse. The
                    dominion of the Goths was now strictly Gaulish; their lasting Spanish dominion
                    does not yet begin.</p>
                <p>The reign of the first West-Gothic Theodoric (418-451) shows a shifting state of
                    relations betwen the Roman and Gothic powers; but, after defeats and successes
                    both ways, the older relation of alliance against common enemies was again
                    established. At last Goth and Roman had to join together against the common
                    enemy of Europe and Christendom, Attila the Hun. But they met Gothic warriors in
                    his army. By the terms of their subjection to the Huns, the East-Goths came to
                    fight for Attila against Christendom at Chalons, just as the Servians came to
                    fight for Bajazet against Christendom at Nicopolis. Theodoric fell in the
                    battle. (451). After this momentary meeting, the history of the East and West
                    Goths again separates for a while. The kingdom of Toulouse grew within Gaul at
                    the expense of the empire, and in Spain at the expense of the Suevi. Under Euric
                    (466-488) the West-Gothic power again became largely a Spanish power. The
                    kingdom of Toulouse took in nearly all Gaul south of the Loire and west of the
                    Rhone, with all Spain, except the north-west corner, which was still held by the
                    Suevi. Provence alone remained to the empire. The West-Gothic kings largely
                    adopted Roman manners and culture; but, as they still kept to their original
                    Arian creed, their rule never became thoroughly acceptable to their Catholic
                    subjects. They stood therefore at a great disadvantage when a new and aggressive
                    Catholic power appeared in Gaul through the conversion of the Frank Chlodwig.
                    Toulouse was, as in days long after, the seat of an heretical power, against
                    which the forces of northern Gaul marched as on a crusade. In 507 the
                    West-Gothic king Alaric fell before the Frankish arms at Bouglé, near Poitiers,
                    and his kingdom, as a great power north of the Alps, fell with him. That Spain
                    and a fragment of Gaul still remained to form a West-Gothic kingdom was owing to
                    the intervention of the East-Goths under the rule of the greatest man in Gothic
                    history.</p>
                <p>When the Hunnish power broke in pieces on the death of Attila, the East-Goths
                    recovered their full independence. They now entered into relations with the
                    empire, and were settled on lands in Pannonia. During the greater part of the
                    latter half of the 5th century, the East-Goths play in south-eastern Europe
                    nearly the same part which the West-Goths played in the century before. They are
                    seen going to and fro, in every conceivable relation of friendship and enmity
                    with the Eastern Roman power, till, just as the West-Goths had done before them,
                    they pass from the East to the West. They are still ruled by kings of the house
                    of the Amali, and from that house there now steps forward a great figure, famous
                    alike in history and in romance, in the person of Theodoric son of Theodemir.
                    Born about 454, his childhood was spent at Constantinople as a hostage, where he
                    was carefully educated. The former part of his life is taken up with various
                    disputes, intrigues, and wars within the Eastern empire, in which he has as his
                    rival another Theodoric, son of Triarius, and surnamed Strabo. This older but
                    lesser Theodoric seems to have been the chief (not king) of that branch of the
                    East-Goths which had settled within the empire at an earlier time. Theodoric the
                    Great, as he is sometimes distinguished, is sometimes the friend, sometimes the
                    enemy, of the empire. In the former case he is clothed with various Roman titles
                    and offices, as patrician and consul; but in all cases alike he remains the
                    national East-Gothic king. It was in both characters together that he set out in
                    488, by commission from the emperor Zeno, to recover Italy from Odoacer. By 493
                    Ravenna was taken; Odoacer was killed by Theodoric⅛ own hand; and the
                    East-Gothic power was fully established over Italy, Sicily, Dalmatia, and the
                    lands to the north of Italy. In this war the history of the East and West Goths
                    begins again to unite, if we may accept the witness of one writer (Anon. Vales.
                    728) that Theodoric was helped by West-Gothic auxiliaries. The two branches of
                    the nation were soon brought much more closely together, when, through the
                    overthrow of the West-Gothic kingdom of Toulouse, the power of Theodoric was
                    practically extended over a large part of Gaul and over nearly the whole of
                    Spain. A time of confusion followed the fall of Alaric, and, as that prince was
                    the son-in-law of Theodoric, the East-Gothic king stepped in as the guardian of
                    his grandson Amalaric, and preserved for him all his Spanish and a fragment of
                    his Gaulish dominion. Toulouse passed away to the Frank; but the Goth kept
                    Narbonne and its district, the land of Septimania—the land which, as the last
                    part of Gaul held by the Goths, kept the name of <hi rend="italic">Gothia</hi>
                    for many ages. While Theodoric lived, the West-Gothic kingdom was practically
                    united to his own dominion. He seems also to have claimed a kind of protectorate
                    over the Teutonic powers generally, and indeed to have practically exercised it,
                    except in the case of the Franks.</p>
                <p>The East-Gothic dominion was now again as great in extent, and far more splendid,
                    than it could have been in the time of Ermanaric. But it was now of a wholly
                    different character. The dominion of Theodoric was not a barbarian but a
                    civilized power. His twofold position ran through everything. He was at once
                    national king of the Goths, and successor, though without any imperial titles,
                    of the Roman emperors of the West. The two nations, differing in manners,
                    language, and religion, lived side by side on the soil of Italy; each was ruled
                    according to its own law, by the prince who was, in his two separate characters,
                    the common sovereign of both. The picture of Theodoric's rule is drawn for us in
                    the state papers drawn up in his name and in the names of his successors by his
                    Roman minister Cassiodorus. The Goths seem to have been thick on the ground in
                    northern Italy; in the south they formed little more than garrisons. In
                    Theodoric’s theory the Goth was the armed protector of the peaceful Roman; the
                    Gothic king had the toil of government, while the Roman consul had the honour.
                    All the forms of the Roman administration went on, and the Roman polity and
                    Roman culture had great influence on the Goths themselves. The <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n874/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0874-0851"/> rule of the prince over two distinct nations
                    in the same land was necessarily despotic; the old Teutonic freedom was
                    necessarily lost. Such a system as that which Theodoric established needed a
                    Theodoric to carry it on. It broke in pieces after his death.</p>
                <p>On the death of Theodoric (526) the East and West Goths were again separated. The
                    few instances in which they are found acting together after this time are as
                    scattered and incidental as they were before. Amalaric succeeded to the
                    West-Gothic kingdom in Spain and Septimania. Provence was added to the dominion
                    of the new East-Gothic king Athalaric, the grandson of Theodoric through his
                    daughter Amalasontha. The weakness of the East-Gothic position in Italy now
                    showed itself. The long wars of Justinian’s reign (535-555) recovered Italy for
                    the empire, and the Gothic name died out on Italian soil. The chance of forming
                    a national state in Italy by the union of Roman and Teutonic elements, such as
                    those which arose in Gaul, in Spain, and in parts of Italy under Lombard rule,
                    was thus lost. The East-Gothic kingdom was destroyed before Goths and Italians
                    had at all mingled together. The war of course made the distinction stronger;
                    under the kings who were chosen for the purposes of the war national Gothic
                    feeling had revived. The Goths were now again, if not a wandering people, yet an
                    armed host, no longer the protectors but the enemies of the Roman people of
                    Italy. The East-Gothic dominion and the East-Gothic name wholly passed away. The
                    nation had followed Theodoric. It is only once or twice after his expedition
                    that we hear of Goths, or even of Gothic leaders, in the eastern provinces. From
                    the soil of Italy the nation passed away almost without a trace, while the next
                    Teutonic conquerors stamped their name on the two ends of the land, one of which
                    keeps it to this day.</p>
                <p>The West-Gothic kingdom lasted much longer, and came much nearer to establishing
                    itself as a national power in the lands which it took in. But the difference of
                    race and faith between the Arian Goths and the Catholic Romans of Gaul and Spain
                    influenced the history of the West-Gothic kingdom for a long time. The Arian
                    Goths ruled over Catholic subjects, and were surrounded by Catholic neighbours.
                    The Franks were Catholics from their first conversion; the Suevi became
                    Catholics much earlier than the Goths. The African conquests of Belisarius gave
                    the Goths of Spain, instead of the Arian Vandals, another Catholic neighbour in
                    the form of the restored Roman power. The Catholics everywhere preferred either
                    Roman, Suevian, or Frankish rule to that of the heretical Goths; even the
                    unconquerable mountaineers of Cantabria seem for a while to have received a
                    Frankish governor. In some other mountain districts the Roman inhabitants long
                    maintained their independence, and in 534 a large part of the south of Spain,
                    including the great cities of Cadiz, Cordova, Seville, and New Carthage, was,
                    with the good will of its Roman inhabitants, reunited to the empire, which kept
                    some points on the coast as late as 624. That is to say, the same work which the
                    empire was carrying on in Italy against the East-Goths was at the same moment
                    carried on in Spain against the West-Goths. But in Italy the whole land was for
                    a while won back, and the Gothic power passed away for ever. In Spain the Gothic
                    power outlived the Roman power, but it outlived it only by itself becoming in
                    some measure Roman. The greatest period of the Gothic power as such was in the
                    reign of Leovigild (567-586). He reunited the Gaulish and Spanish parts of the
                    kingdom which had been parted for a moment; he united the Suevian dominion to
                    his own; he overcame some of the independent districts, and won back part of the
                    recovered Roman province in southern Spain. He further established the power of
                    the crown over the Gothic nobles, who were beginning to grow into territorial
                    lords. The next reign, that of his son Recared (586-601), was marked by a change
                    which took away the great hindrance which had thus far stood in the way of any
                    national union between Goths and Romans. The king and the greater part of the
                    Gothic people embraced the Catholic faith. A vast degree of influence now fell
                    into the hands of the Catholic bishops; the two nations began to unite; the
                    Goths were gradually Romanized, and the Gothic language began to go out of use.
                    In short, the Romance nation and the Romance speech of Spain began to be formed.
                    The Goths supplied the Teutonic infusion into the Roman mass. The kingdom,
                    however, still remained a Gothic kingdom. “Gothic,” not “Roman” or “Spanish,” is
                    its formal title; only a single late instance of the use of the formula “regnum
                    Hispaniae” is known. In the first half of the 7th century that name became for
                    the first time geographically applicable by the conquest of the still Roman
                    coast of southern Spain. The empire was then engaged in the great struggle with
                    the Avars and Persians, and, now that the Gothic kings were Catholic, the great
                    objection to their rule on the part of the Roman inhabitants was taken away. The
                    Gothic nobility still remained a distinct class, and held, along with the
                    Catholic prelacy, the right of choosing the king. Union with the Catholic Church
                    was accompanied by the introduction of the ecclesiastical ceremony of anointing,
                    a change decidedly favourable to elective rule. The growth of those later ideas
                    which tended again to favour the hereditary doctrine had not time to grow up in
                    Spain before the Mahometan conquest (711). The West-Gothic crown therefore
                    remained elective till the end. The modern Spanish nation is the growth of the
                    long struggle with the Mussulmans; but it has a direct connexion with' the
                    West-Gothic kingdom. We see at once that the Goths hold altogether a different
                    place in Spanish memory from that which they hold in Italian memory. In Italy
                    the Goth was but a momentary invader and ruler; the Teutonic element in Italy
                    comes from other sources. In Spain the Goth supplies an important element in the
                    modern nation. And that element has been neither forgotten nor despised. Part of
                    the unconquered region of northern Spain, the land of Asturia, kept for a while
                    the name of Gothia, as did the Gothic possessions in Gaul and in Crim. The name
                    of the people who played so great a part in all southern Europe, and who
                    actually ruled over so large a part of it, has now wholly passed away; but it is
                    in Spain that its historical impress is to be looked for.</p>
                <p>Of Gothic literature in the Gothic language we have the Bible of Ulfila, and some
                    other religious writings and fragments (see notice of Gothic Language below). Of
                    Gothic legislation in Latin, we have the edict of Theodoric of the year 500,
                    lately edited by Bluhnιe in the <hi rend="italic">Monumenta Germaniae
                        Historica</hi>; and the books of Kαr⅛ce of Cassiodorus may pass as a
                    collection of the state papers of Theodoric and his immediate successors. Among
                    the West-Goths written laws had already been put forth by Euric (466-484). The
                    second Alaric (484-507) put forth <hi rend="italic">ο,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Breviarium</hi> of Roman law for his Roman subjects; but the great
                    collection of West-Gothic laws dates from the later days of the monarchy, being
                    put forth by King Rekisvinth about 654. This code gave occasion to some
                    well-known comments by Montesquieu and Gibbon, and have been discussed by
                    Savigny <hi rend="italic">{Geschichte des Römischen Rechts,</hi> ii. 65) and
                    various other writers. They are printed in the old collections of Lindenbrog and
                    Heineccius. They do not seem to have been yet reprinted in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Monumenta Germanice.</hi> Of special Gothic histories, besides that of
                    Jordanis, already so often quoted, there is the Gothic history of Isidor,
                    archbishop of Seville, a special source of the history of the West-Gothic kings
                    down to Siunthala (621-631). But all the Latin and Greek writers contemporary
                    with the days of Gothic predominance<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n875/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0875-0852"/> make their constant contributions. Not for
                    special facts, but for a general estimate, no writer is more instructive than
                    Salvian of Marseilles in the 5th century, whose vzork <hi rend="italic"
                        >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Gubernatione</hi><hi rend="italic">Dei</hi> is
                    full of passages contrasting the vices of the Romans with the virtues of the
                    barbarians, especially of the Goths. In all such pictures we must allow a good
                    deal for exaggeration both ways, but there must be a ground-work of truth. The
                    chief virtues which the Catholic presbyter praises in the Arian Goths are their
                    chastity, their piety according tυ their own creed, their tolerance towards the
                    Catholics under their rule, and their general good treatment of their Roman
                    subjects. He even ventures to hope that such good people may be saved,
                    notwithstanding their heresy. All this must have had some ground-work of truth
                    in the 5th century, but it is not very wonderful if the later West-Goths of
                    Spain had a good deal fallen away from the doubtless somewhat ideal picture of
                    Salvian.</p>
                <p>Of modern writers dealing specially with Gothic history may be mentioned Manso
                        <hi rend="italic">{Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">des Ost-Golhischen
                        Reiches in</hi><hi rend="italic">Italien,</hi> Breslau, 1824); Aschbach <hi
                        rend="italic">{Geschichte der</hi><hi rend="italic">Wcstgothen,</hi>
                    Frankfort, 1827); Köpke <hi rend="italic">{Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Anfänge des
                        Königsthums bei den Gothen,</hi> Berlin, 1854; Dahn <hi rend="italic">{Die
                        Könige der Germanen,</hi> Munich and Würzburg, 1861-1871); Palimann <hi
                        rend="italic">(Geschichte der Völkerwanderung,</hi> Gotha and Weimar,
                    1863-1864). It is hard to find any work in English dealing specially with Gothic
                    history, though much may be learned from writers like Gibbon and Milman, who
                    deal with the Goths simply as part of some larger subject. Several chapters in
                    the third book of Milman’s <hi rend="italic">History of Latin Christianity</hi>
                    are of special importance in this way. (E. A. F.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Gothtc Language.</hi></p>
                <p>By this name, which may be taken generally as denoting the idioms of the various
                    divisions of the Gothic nation, is more particularly meant the language
                    exhibited in certain fragments of a translation of the Bible and other minor
                    documents, which, although preserved in manuscripts not dating farther back than
                    perhaps the 5th century, and clearly written in Italy during the rule of the
                    East Goths, are commonly assumed to have originated among the West-Goths at the
                    time when they were seated in Moesia, and to be therefore older by at least a
                    century than the manuscripts themselves. It is chiefly due to this assumption
                    that the more distinctive name of <hi rend="italic">Moesogothic</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">language</hi> is often used, in England and elsewhere, as well
                    as the simpler <hi rend="italic">Gothic.</hi> The latter name, however, seems to
                    be more appropriate, in spite of the great probability of the assumption
                    referred to,—since it is, for obvious reasons, utterly impossible to prove that
                    the language of the West-Goths at that time differed from that of the
                    East-Goths, or, even if there was any difference, to show that our manuscripts
                    represent the original forms of the speech of their supposed West-Gothic author.
                    Indeed, according to a fragment of a Gothic calendar preserved in one of the
                    Milan manuscripts, which gives the name of the Gothic people as <hi
                        rend="italic">Gut-thiuda</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>The same form of the name seems to occur a second time
                            in the Runic inscription of the Bucharest ring, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Gut-αnn6m lιailag,</hi> “dedicated to the Goths’ treasure.” <hi
                                rend="italic">Cf.</hi> H. F. Massmann, in Pfeiffer’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Germania</hi> (Vienna, 1857), ii. ρ. 209 <hi
                                rend="italic">sq.∙,</hi> and Ludv. Wimmer, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Aarbοger for nordisk Oldkyndighed og Histone</hi> (Copenhagen,
                            1867), p. 45.</p></note><hi rend="italic superscript"> τ</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">{thiuda,</hi> “people”), the most correct form of the name
                    would be <hi rend="italic">Gotic.</hi> This spelling at least has obviously
                    greater claims to authenticity than <hi rend="italic">Gothf Gotthi,</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">Γότθοι,</hi> and other similar forms most commonly (although
                    not exclusively) used by Latin and Greek writers, whose want of familiarity with
                    the sounds of the Gothic language is often abundantly manifest. From <hi
                        rend="italic">Gut-thiuda</hi> we may infer with certainty that the Goths
                    called themselves <hi rend="italic">Gutos,</hi> the corresponding adjective
                    being <hi rend="italic">gutisks.</hi></p>
                <p>We have no direct evidence of the character of the Gothic language until the time
                    of the above-mentioned manuscripts; but some conclusions regarding a more
                    archaic state of the language may be drawn from a careful examination of the
                    numerous words borrowed from Gothic at a much earlier period by some of the
                    Finnish tribes originally dwelling in the interior of Russia.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Dr Wilh. Thomsen, <hi
                                rend="italic">Ueber</hi><hi rend="italic">den Einfluss der
                                Germanischen Sprachen auf die Finnisch-Lappischen</hi> (Halle,
                            1870).</p></note> It may be safely assumed that some at least of these
                    words still retain forms of the Gothic language from as early a period as
                    perhaps the 1st, or 2d century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> By the same date
                    the Goths, as well as the other Teutonic nations, were no doubt already in
                    possession of the Runic alphabet, an adaptation of a particular form of the
                    Latin characters to their special wants and uses.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See especially Dr Ludv. Wimmer, <hi
                                rend="italic">Runeskriftens Oprindelse og</hi><hi rend="italic"
                                >Udυikling</hi><hi rend="italic">i Norden,</hi> Copenhagen,
                            1874.</p></note> No traces of this alphabet, however, have been left,
                    except the already mentioned short inscription of the Bucharest ring, a list of
                    the Gothic names of these runes, preserved in a Vienna manuscript of the 9th
                        century,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>J. Zacher,
                                <hi rend="italic">Das Gothische Alphabet Vulfilas und das
                                Runenalphabet,</hi> Leipsic, 1855.</p></note> and some letters in
                    Ulfila’s Gothic alphabet, which soon supplanted the less convenient Runic
                    characters, and so helped to inaugurate the short literary period of the Gothic
                    language so closely connected with the name of that prelate.</p>
                <p>Ulfila, or rather Vulfila (310-380 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Ulfila),</hi> was a man of the most profound learning. He
                    not only invented, as has been said, a new alphabet for his literary purposes,
                    but was also able to preach and to write in Latin and Greek as well as in his
                    native Gothic language, and he is reported to have left behind him a great
                    number of tracts and translations in these three idioms. The principal work of
                    his life, however, was his translation of the Bible, parts of which seem to have
                    reached us in the famous <hi rend="italic">Codex</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Argenteus,</hi> now at Upsala, and in several minor fragments at
                    Wolfenbüttel <hi rend="italic">{Codex Carolinus')</hi> and Milan <hi
                        rend="italic">{Codices Arnbrοsiani,</hi> including some leaves now kept at
                    Rome and Turin). In this way we possess the greater part of the gospels,
                    considerable portions of the epistles, and a few fragments of the Old Testament;
                    there is also a fragment of a commentary on St John’s gospel, commonly called
                        <hi rend="italic">Skeireiηs</hi> (or “explanation”), and the fragment of a
                    calendar which has been already mentioned as containing the original form of the
                    name of the Gothic people.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>A few Gothic words and names occur among the subscriptions to two
                            Latin charters, one of which is now preserved at Naples; tho other,
                            formerly kept at Arezzo, is now lost.</p></note> As to the authorship of
                    the last two fragments nothing can be said with certainty; and certain
                    differences in language and manner of translation make it doubtful even whether
                    the fragments of the Old Testament can be traced to the same origin as those of
                    the New. The bulk of the whole, however, may safely be ascribed to Ulfila, for
                    it can hardly be assumed that the same work would have been done twice over in
                    so short a space of time as that lying between the days of Ulfila and the date
                    of our manuscripts. The whole character of the translation too seems to indicate
                    a man of Ulfila’s mental power and theological learning. Although it cannot be
                    denied that several alterations of the original have been introduced into our
                    texts at a later time, it is certain both that the author carefully interpreted
                    the Greek text (which was of course the fundamental source of his work), and
                    also that he consulted, and in not a few places followed, the old Latin versions
                    where his own ideas seemed to differ from those of his Greek authorities.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For fuller particulars
                            see the two principal editions of the Gothic texts by V. d. Gabelentz
                            und Loebe (3 vols., Altenburg and Leipsic, 1843-76), and by E. Bernhardt
                            (Halle, 1875).</p></note></p>
                <p>As a specimen of the language, and of Ulfila’s mode of translation, we may insert
                    here his version of the Lord’s prayer :—</p>
                <p>Atta unsar thu in himinam. Weihnai namo thein. Qimai thiudinassus theins.
                    Wairthai wilja theins swe in himina jah ana <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n876/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0876-0853"/> airthai. Hlaif unsarana thana sinteinan gif
                    uns himma daga. Jah aflet uns thatei skulans sijaima, swaswe jah weis afletam
                    thaim skulam unsaraim. Jah ni briggais uns in fraistubnjai, ak lausais uns af
                    tharnma ubilin.</p>
                <p>The Gothic language did not very long survive the times of Ulfila. From Moesia,
                    where it had gained its highest literary culture, it disappeared together with
                    the Goths, when they were driven from these parts by later migrations. In the
                    western portions of Europe, that is, in Italy, France, and Spain, whither it had
                    been carried by the emigrants, the Gothic language seems to have died out even
                    sooner than the Gothic nationality, giving way to the overpowering influence of
                    Latin, and leaving behind it only a few indistinct relics in some proper names
                    and other words that had been received into that victorious language. It was
                    only in a remote spot of the Crimea that it continued to exist until the 16th
                    century, when the last remains of a Gothic people were detected, and a few
                    specimens of their language were gathered by Augerius de Busbeck, a Dutch
                    traveller, who visited the eastern parts of Europe in the years 1554-1564.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See his report and
                            word-lists, reprinted by Massmann, in <hi rend="italic">Zeit</hi><hi
                                rend="italic">schrift</hi><hi rend="italic">für Deutsches
                                Alterthurn,</hi> i. p. 345 <hi rend="italic">seq.</hi> The words
                            contained in these lists are not all intelligible, and some of them are
                            clearly of Slavonic or Iranian origin, but others are decidedly Gothic
                            as regards their form, thus <hi rend="italic">schlipen, to</hi> sleep;
                                <hi rend="italic">criten,</hi> to weep; <hi rend="italic"
                                >fyder,</hi> four; the correct Gothic forms being <hi rend="italic"
                                >slëpan, grëtan,</hi><hi rend="italic">fidvör.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>It is well known that the literary remains of Gothic are (with the exception,
                    perhaps, of a few Runic inscriptions belonging to the Scandinavian languages) by
                    several centuries the oldest specimens of Teutonic speech, and therefore have a
                    particular value for the student of the history of that family of languages.
                    Notwithstanding this fact, it would be altogether wrong to regard Gothic as the
                    common source of the more modern stages of these idioms. Although very archaic
                    in many of its forms and sounds, it is in these still far removed from the
                    original features of the common language, as that was spoken before any
                    separation of Teutonic tribes had taken place. Most nearly related to it seem to
                    have been the Scandinavian languages, which are now generally assumed to have
                    formed, together with Gothic, the so-called eastern branch<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>H. Zimmer, ‘· Ostgermanen und
                            Westgermanen,” in <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Deutsches
                                Alterthurn,</hi> xix. p. 393 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi></p></note>
                    of the Teutonic family, while English, Frisian, and Low and High German belonged
                    to a western division. The latter is chiefly marked by the introduction of a
                    considerable number of forms and sounds of a less archaic stamp, while the
                    eastern idioms are found to have adhered more closely to the original forms.
                    Thus, almost the only distinct innovation in the sound-system of the eastern
                    branch is the insertion of a <hi rend="italic">g</hi> sound into the groups <hi
                        rend="italic">iuw, auw, uw</hi> in accented syllables, as in Gothic <hi
                        rend="italic">triggws,</hi> Old Norse <hi rend="italic">tryggr,</hi>
                    compared with Old High German and Old Saxon <hi rend="italic">triuwi,</hi> Old
                    English <hi rend="italic">treowe, trywe,</hi> “true ”; or Old Norse <hi
                        rend="italic">höggva,</hi> to hew, Old High German and Old Saxon <hi
                        rend="italic">hauwan,</hi> Old English <hi rend="italic">hcawcm.</hi>
                    Western Teutonic, on the other hand, is at once discernible by its doubling all
                    single consonants ending a short root-syllable before <hi rend="italic"
                        >y</hi><hi rend="italic">(w, r,</hi> Z); thus Old English <hi rend="italic"
                        >theccan,</hi> Old Saxon <hi rend="italic">thekkian,</hi> Old High German
                        <hi rend="italic">decken,</hi> to cover (literally “to thatch”), but Gothic
                        <hi rend="italic">tlιakjan,</hi> Old Norse <hi rend="italic">thckja</hi>; or
                    Old English seZZowι,∙01d Saxon <hi rend="italic">sellian,</hi> Old High German
                        <hi rend="italic">selten,</hi> to sell, but Gothic <hi rend="italic"
                        >saljan,</hi> Old Norse <hi rend="italic">selja.</hi> As to the inflexional
                    system, the accusative plural of nouns has in Western Teutonic been replaced by
                    the nominative form, as in Old English <hi rend="italic">dagas,</hi> Old Saxon
                        <hi rend="italic">dagös,</hi> Old High German <hi rend="italic">tagâ,</hi>
                    days; Gothic still has <hi rend="italic">dagös</hi> for the nominative, and <hi
                        rend="italic">dagans</hi> for the accusative, the Old Norse forms being <hi
                        rend="italic">dagar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">daga</hi> respectively. The
                    same change is found in the adjectives, as Old English and Old Saxon <hi
                        rend="italic">blinde,</hi> Old High German <hi rend="italic">blinde,</hi>
                    blind (coεcι), corresponding to both Gothic <hi rend="italic">blindai</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">blindais,</hi> Old Norse <hi rend="italic">blinder</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">blinda.</hi> On the other hand, the formation of the
                    plural of certain neutral substantives by adding an <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> as
                    in Old English <hi rend="italic">lombric,</hi> lambs, Old High German <hi
                        rend="italic">lembir</hi> (still extant in the English plural <hi
                        rend="italic">children)</hi> is entirely lost in Eastern Teutonic (Gothic
                        <hi rend="italic">lamba,</hi> Old Norse <hi rend="italic">l'omb).</hi>
                    Another instance of change is to be seen in the loss of the dative case of the
                    reflective pronoun (Gothic <hi rend="italic">sis,</hi> Old Norse <hi
                        rend="italic">sér)</hi> in Western Teutonic, the corresponding forms of the
                    personal pronoun of the 3d person being used instead (Old English <hi
                        rend="italic">him, hire,</hi> &amp;c.) Western Teutonic has also introduced
                    the use of the genitive forms of the same personal pronoun instead of the
                    possessive pronoun (Gothic <hi rend="italic">seins,</hi> Old Norse <hi
                        rend="italic">sinn)</hi> when the possessor is denoted by a feminine or a
                    plural (Old English has gone even farther by dropping the possessive pronoun
                    altogether). In the verb, Western Teutonic has replaced the original form of the
                    2d person singular of the past indicative ending in <hi rend="italic">-t</hi>
                    (as in Gothic and Old Norse <hi rend="italic">wast, gaft,</hi> thou wert,
                    gavest) by the corresponding form of the subjunctive (Old English <hi
                        rend="italic">ware, geafe,</hi> Old Saxon and Old High German <hi
                        rend="italic">wäri, gäbe).</hi> Western Teutonic has also lost the faculty
                    of deriving passive or intransitive verbs from active verbs or adjectives by
                    adding the syllable <hi rend="italic">-na-</hi> after the root-syllable, as in
                    Gothic <hi rend="italic">fullnan,</hi> Old Norse <hi rend="italic">fιcllna,</hi>
                    to be filled, as compared with Gothic <hi rend="italic">fulls,</hi> Old Norse
                        <hi rend="italic">fullr,</hi> full; or Gothic <hi rend="italic"
                        >fulljan,</hi> Old Norse∕yZZα, to fill. Only a very few instances of this
                    formation are left in Western Teutonic, such as Old English <hi rend="italic"
                        >icaecnan,</hi> to awaken [intrans. ], or <hi rend="italic">lcornian,</hi>
                    German <hi rend="italic">lernen,</hi> to learn (c∕. Old English <hi
                        rend="italic">weccan,</hi> German <hi rend="italic">wecken,</hi> to awaken
                    [trans.], and German <hi rend="italic">lehren,</hi> to teach). As to the
                    vocabulary, we may mention the loss of the verb <hi rend="italic">dén,</hi> to
                    do, in Gothic and Scandinavian. The most conspicuous peculiarity in the syntax
                    is the frequent use of the dative (or perhaps originally the instrumental case)
                    instead of the accusative in Eastern Teutonic.</p>
                <p>Among the Teutonic languages Gothic holds by far the foremost rank as regards the
                    regularity of its sound-system and its inflexions. The vowel system is
                    remarkable for the absence of the short <hi rend="italic">e</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">o</hi> sounds, except in a few places where <hi rend="italic"
                        >é</hi> and &lt;5 (spelt <hi rend="italic">ai</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >au)</hi> occur under certain consonantal influences. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Umlaut,</hi> or assimilation of root-vowels to a following <hi
                        rend="italic">a-, i-,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">u-</hi> sound, is not
                    discernible in Gothic. Thus we find only five short vowels, <hi rend="italic">a,
                        (ai),</hi><hi rend="italic">i,</hi><hi rend="italic">(au),</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">u;</hi> five long vowels <hi rend="italic">a, ë,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">i</hi> (spelt <hi rend="italic">ei),</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ô,</hi><hi rend="italic">u</hi>; and three diphthongs <hi rend="italic">ai,
                        au,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">iu.</hi> There may have been other
                    distinctions of vowelqualities besides those expressed in spelling, but we have
                    no means of definitely settling this question; so much, however, can be said,
                    that the long vowels, and especially <hi rend="italic">ë</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">ö,</hi> probably had the close sounds, since these are often
                    interchanged with <hi rend="italic">ei</hi> and <hi rend="italic">u</hi> in our
                    manuscripts. The spelling of the consonantal system is also very simple. Besides
                        <hi rend="italic">y, w, r, l</hi> and three nasal sounds (the guttural nasal
                    being expresssed by <hi rend="italic">g</hi> after the Greek fashion), we find
                    three voiceless stops, <hi rend="italic">p, t, k (q</hi> being only a
                    combination of <hi rend="italic">kw);</hi> three voiced stops, <hi rend="italic"
                        >b, d, g;</hi> four voiceless spirants, ∕, <hi rend="italic">s, th, h;</hi>
                    and only one distinct sign for a voiced spirant, <hi rend="italic">z.</hi> This
                    system of spelling, however, is obviously insufficient to express all the sounds
                    of the language,—an insufficiency partly due to the fact that the transcription
                    of the Gothic speech-sounds was chiefly an imitation of the Greek graphic
                    system, which, at least in Ulfila’s time, had become rather imperfect, inasmuch
                    as different sounds developed out of one sound of an earlier period were still
                    often expressed by the same sign (just as in the English orthography of the
                    present day). It is highly probable, for instance, that the signs of <hi
                        rend="italic">b, d, g</hi> of the Gothic alphabet not only expressed the
                    sounds of voiced stop consonants <hi rend="italic">(mediae),</hi> but also
                    represented the sounds of voiced spirants, such as English <hi rend="italic"
                        >v</hi> and soft <hi rend="italic">th,</hi> or North German <hi
                        rend="italic">g</hi> after a vowel (these values being the only ones left to
                    the Modem Greek signs <hi rend="italic">β, y,</hi> δ). Hence the regular change
                    of <hi rend="italic">b, d</hi> final after a vowel into <hi rend="italic">f,
                        th,</hi> as in <hi rend="italic">gaf,</hi> I gave, from <hi rend="italic"
                        >giban,</hi> to give; or <hi rend="italic">bath,</hi> 1 bade, from <hi
                        rend="italic">bidjan,</hi> to bid.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>See W. Weingaertner, <hi rend="italic">Die Aussprache
                                des Gothischen</hi> (Leipsic, 1658); F. Dietrich, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Geber die Aussprache des Gothischen (Marburg,</hi> 1862); H. Paul,
                            “Zur Lautverschiebung,” <hi rend="italic">in Beiträge zur Geschichte der
                                Deutschen Sprache und Literatur,</hi> i. 147 <hi rend="italic"
                                >sq.</hi> (Halle, 1874).</p></note></p>
                <p>Great regularity prevails also in the inflexional system. In the substantival and
                    adjectival declensions the instrumental case has become extinct by an early
                    confusion with the dative (the case commonly called dative being, in fact, a
                    mixture of forms of the original dative and the instrumental and local cases),
                    while in the Western branch of Teutonic it was still in frequent use. At the
                    same time, Gothic is the only Teutonic idiom that has still preserved, in a few
                    cases, the vocative in a form distinct from that of the nominative <hi
                        rend="italic">(fisks,</hi> fish, for instance, has <hi rend="italic"
                        >fsk</hi> in the voc. ). The adjectival declension is remarkable for the
                    retention of special forms of the <hi rend="italic">i-</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">u-</hi> sterns, which in all other Teutonic languages have
                    been transferred to the inflexion of the <hi rend="italic">ja-</hi> sterns. In
                    the pronominal inflexion the instrumental case has been kept distinct in a few
                    instances, such as <hi rend="italic">thë, hvë</hi> (the latter form being the
                    same as English <hi rend="italic">τυhy).</hi> There are also some relics of the
                    dual number left in the 1st and 2d personal pronouns. As for the verb, Gothic is
                    quite unique in retaining the old formation of the passive voice by means of
                    simple derivation (as in <hi rend="italic">bairada, bairanda,</hi> he is, they
                    are borne, Greek <hi rend="italic">φiρcτaι,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >φέρονται),</hi> the dual number of the 1st and 2d persons throughout the
                    whole active voice <hi rend="italic">(bairδs, bairats,</hi> we, you two bear, in
                    the indicative, or <hi rend="italic">bairaiνa, bairaits</hi> in the subjunctive,
                    or <hi rend="italic">bëru, bëruts,</hi> we, you two bore [ind.], and <hi
                        rend="italic">bëreiva,</hi><hi rend="italic">bereits</hi> [subj.] along with
                    the plural forms <hi rend="italic">bairarn, bairith,</hi> &amp;c. ), and the 3d
                    person of the imperative (as <hi rend="italic">bairadau, bairandau,</hi> he,
                    they shall bear, Greek <hi rend="italic">φepiτω, φep0vτωv).</hi> The different
                    verbal classes are of course the same as in the other cognate idioms; but they
                    are kept more completely distinct in Gothic, for it is only there that the
                    reduplication has been preserved intact in the past of the reduplicative verbs,
                    Gothic <hi rend="italic">haihald,</hi> I held, for instance, corresponding to
                    such shortened forms as Old Norse <hi rend="italic">helt,</hi> Old English <hi
                        rend="italic">heold,</hi> Old Saxon <hi rend="italic">held,</hi> and Old
                    High German <hi rend="italic">hëlt,</hi><hi rend="italic">hcalt,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">hielt.</hi> Gothic again is the only language that seems to
                    give us a clue to the explanation of the formation of the past in weak verbs.
                    There we find such <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n877/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0877-0854"/> plural forms as <hi rend="italic"
                        >hausi-dêdum,</hi> we heard, while in Old Norse we have simple <hi
                        rend="italic">heyr-dum,</hi> in Old English <hi rend="italic">hier-don,</hi>
                    &amp;c. Now, this <hi rend="italic">-dëdum</hi> would be exactly the
                    corresponding form of the verb <hi rend="italic">dön,</hi> to do (lost in
                    Gothic, as mentioned above), so that <hi rend="italic">hausirdedum</hi> must
                    once have meant “we did hear.”</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding all these instances of great antiquity we must be on our guard
                    against the assumption that Gothic in all its features bears the same archaic
                    stamp. In fact, it often goes farther than the other cognate idioms in dropping
                    short final vowels. There are no traces left of the short vowels originally
                    ending <hi rend="italic">a-</hi> or <hi rend="italic">i-</hi> stems in
                    declension; thus, <hi rend="italic">dags</hi> from <hi rend="italic">daga-,</hi>
                    day; <hi rend="italic">haum</hi> from <hi rend="italic">horna-</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">,</hi> horn; <hi rend="italic">gasts</hi> from <hi
                        rend="italic">gasti-,</hi> guest; <hi rend="italic">hugs</hi> from <hi
                        rend="italic">hugi-,</hi> mind; but there are many instances of the
                    preservation of these vowels in the other languages, such as <hi rend="italic"
                        >dagar,</hi><hi rend="italic">horna,</hi><hi rend="italic">gastir</hi> in
                    Old Scandinavian Runic inscriptions, or <hi rend="italic">lιyge</hi> in Old
                    English, or Λwgf in Old Saxon and Old High German.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>E. Sievers, in <hi rend="italic">Beiträge
                                zur Geschichte der Deutselten Sprache und Literatur,</hi> v. 101 <hi
                                rend="italic">sq.</hi> (Halle, 1878).</p></note> Even the regularity
                    of the inflexional system is often not archaic, but due to later assimilations
                    of forms originally more distant than in Gothic. The most striking instance of
                    this is perhaps the loss, in the verbal system, of the so-called grammatical
                    change, that is, the transferring of a voiceless spirant into a voiced spirant
                    after a syllable unaccented in the earliest time before the general Teutonic
                    rule of fixing the accent on the root-syllables had come into use.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>W. Braune, “Ueber den
                            grammatischen Wechsel,” in <hi rend="italic">Beiträge,</hi> &amp;c., i.
                            513 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>; K. Verner, “Ueber eine Ausnahme der
                            ersten Lautverschiebung,” in <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für
                                vergleichende Sprachwissenschaft,</hi> xxiii. 97 <hi rend="italic"
                                >sq.</hi> (Berlin, 1877).</p></note> This change (still discernible
                    in such English forms as <hi rend="italic">I ιvas, we were)</hi> was fully
                    developed in all other cognate idioms, as for instance in Old English, <hi
                        rend="italic">cf. ic wcεs, we wceron,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ceosan,</hi>
                    to choose, <hi rend="italic">ic ceas, we curon, gecorcn,</hi> &amp;c., these
                    forms standing for <hi rend="italic">was,</hi><hi rend="italic">wëzüm,</hi>
                    &amp;c. Gothic has given up the voiced sound altogether, forming simply <hi
                        rend="italic">was, wesum,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">kiusan, kaus, kιιsum,
                        gakusans.</hi> It is only in some isolated words (such as <hi rend="italic"
                        >fadar</hi> and <hi rend="italic">brôthar,</hi> corresponding to Sanskrit
                        <hi rend="italic">pitAr</hi> and <hi rend="italic">bhratar),</hi> and some
                    derivatives that even traces of this fundamental rule are now to be found in the
                    Gothic language. (E. SI. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
