<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0699-0678-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GLEYRE, Marc Charles Gabriel (9th edition, volume 10,
                    page 678)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45x1d">Salons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47w67561">Visions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20q1q">Vision</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952743">Health</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104198">Salons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039865">Nubians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206063">Lebanon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n699/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GLEYRE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Marc Charles
                        Gabriel</hi></label> (1806-1874), a celebrated French painter, was of Swiss
                    origin, having been born at Chevilly in the canton of Vaud, May 2, 1806. His
                    father died, and then his mother, while he was yet a boy of some eight or nine
                    years of age; and he was brought up by an uncle at Lyons, who sent him to the
                    industrial school of that city. Going up to Paris a lad of seventeen or
                    nineteen, he spent four years in close artistic study— in Hersent’s studio, in
                    Suisse’s academy, in the galleries of the Louvre. To this period of laborious
                    application succeeded four years of meditative inactivity in Italy, where he
                    became acquainted with Horace Vernet and Léopold Robert; and six years more were
                    consumed in adventurous wanderings in Greece, Egypt, Nubia, and Syria. At Cairo
                    he was attacked with ophthalmia, and in the Lebanon he was struck down by fever;
                    and he returned to Lyons in shattered health. On his recovery he proceeded to
                    Paris, and, fixing his modest studio in the Rue de Université, began carefully
                    to work out the conceptions which had been slowly shaping themselves in his
                    mind. Mention is made of two decorative panels—Diana leaving the Bath, and a
                    Young Nubian—as almost the first fruits of his genius; but these did not attract
                    public attention till long after, and the painting by which he practically
                    opened his artistic career was the Apocalyptic Vision of St John, sent to the
                    Salon of 1840. This was followed in 1843 by Evening, which at the time received
                    a medal of the second class, and afterwards became widely popular under the
                    title of the Lost <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n700/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0700-0679"/> Illusions. It represents a poet seated on the
                    bank of a river, with drooping head and wearied frame, letting his lyre slip
                    from a careless hand, and gazing sadly at a bright company of maidens whose song
                    is slowly dying from his ear as their boat is borne slowly from his sight. In
                    spite of the success which attended these first ventures, Gleyre retired from
                    public competition, and spent the rest of his life in quiet devotion to his own
                    artistic ideals, neither seeking the easy applause of the crowd, nor turning his
                    art into a means of aggrandizement and wealth. After 1815, when he exhibited the
                    Separation of the Apostles, he contributed nothing to the Salon except the Danse
                    of the Bacchantes in 1849. And yet belaboured steadily and was abundantly
                    productive. He had au “infinite capacity of taking pains,” and when asked by
                    what method he attained to such marvellous perfection of workmanship, he would
                    reply, “En y pensant toujours.” A long series of years often intervened between
                    the first conception of a piece and its embodiment, and years not unfrequently
                    between the first and the final stage of the embodiment itself. A landscape was
                    apparently finished; even his fellow artists would consider it done; Gleyre
                    alone was conscious that he had not “found his sky.” Happily for French art this
                    high-toned laboriousness became influential on a large number of Gleyre’s
                    younger contemporaries <hi rend="italic">; for</hi> when Delaroche gave up his
                    studio of instruction he recommended his pupils to apply to Gleyre, who at once
                    agreed to give them lessons twice a week, and characteristically refused to take
                    any fee or reward. By instinct and principle he was a confirmed celibate:
                    “Fortune, talent, health,—he had everything; but he was married,” was his
                    lamentation over a friend. Though he lived in almost complete retirement from
                    public life, he took a keen interest in politics, and was a voracious reader of
                    political journals. For a time, indeed, under Louis Philippe, his studio had
                    been the rendezvous of a sort of liberal club. To the last—amid all the
                    disasters that befell his country—he was hopeful of the future, “la raison
                    finira bien par avoir raison.” It was while on a visit to the Retrospective
                    Exhibition, opened on behalf of the exiles from Alsace and Lorraine, that he
                    suddenly dropped down and expired May 5, 1874. He left unfinished the Earthly
                    P.ιradise, a noble picture, which Taine has described as “a dream of innocence,
                    of happiness, and of beauty—Adam and Eve standing in the sublime and joyous
                    landscape of a paradise enclosed in mountains,”—a worthy counterpart to the
                    Evening. Among the other productions of his genius are the Deluge, which
                    represents two angels speeding above the desolate earth, from which the
                    destroying waters have just begun to retire, leaving visible behind them the
                    ruin they have wrought; the Battle of the Lemanus, a piece of elaborate design,
                    crowded but not cumbered with figures, and giving fine expression to the
                    movements of the various bands of combatants and fugitives; the Prodigal Son, in
                    which the artist has ventured to add to the parable the new element of mother’s
                    love, greeting the repentant youth with a welcome that shows that the mother’s
                    heart thinks less of the repentance than of the return; Ruth and Boaz; Ulysses
                    and Nausicaa; Hercules at the feet of Omphale; the Young Athenian, or, as it is
                    popularly called, Sappho; Minerva and the Nymphs; Venus <hi rend="italic"
                        >πάνδημος;</hi> Daphnis and Chloe; and Love and the Parcae. Nor must it be
                    omitted that he left a considerable number of drawings and water-colours, and
                    that we are indebted to him for a number of portraits, among which is the sad
                    face of Heine, engraved in the <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes</hi> for
                    April 1852. In Clément’s catalogue of his works there are 683 entries, including
                    sketches and studies. Gleyre is in great favour in Switzerland; and a special
                    exhibition of his works was held at Lausanne in the Arland Museum, August and
                    September 1874.</p>
                <p>See Fritz Berthoud in Bibliothèque Universelle de Genève, 1874; Albert de Montet,
                    Diet. Biographique des Genevois et des Vaudois, 1877; and Vie de Charles Gleyre,
                    1877, written by his friend, Charles Clement, and illustrated by 30 plates from
                    his works.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
