<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0571-0554-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GESNER, or Gessner, Konrad</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 554</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1011191">Mass</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1011506">Masses</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s24s">Mass</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p527">Basel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n571/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GESNER, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Gessner, Konrad</hi></label>
                    (1516-1565), a very famous naturalist and author, surnamed the German Pliny and
                    literarum miraculum on account of his vast erudition, was born of poor parents
                    ät Zürich, 26th March 1516. He received the first elements of education from
                    Chaplain Frick, his maternal uncle; and it was while gathering plants in his
                    relative’s garden that he became imbued with that enthusiastic love of science
                    which remained with him through life. In 1513 he went to Strasburg, then to
                    Bourges, and in 1534 to Paris, studying at all those places with characteristic
                    passionate zeal. In 1535 we find him again in Zürich, where he married somewhat
                    imprudently, for he was very poor, and had no immediate prospect of bettering
                    his condition. His whole day was occupied in teaching, but at least the night
                    was his own, and too great a portion of the time that others give to rest was
                    occupied by Gesner in adding to his already great stock of erudition. In 1537 he
                    was appointed professor of Greek at Lausanne, and in 1541 professor of physics
                    and natural history at Zürich. But in neither of these offices was he well paid,
                    and during those years he wrote a large number of books, partly to support
                    himself, partly from the interest he felt in their subjects. He wrote several
                    works on ancient medicine and on botany, and a treatise on milk (in which he
                    described the rural economy of Switzerland), translated into Latin a Greek
                    logical manual and some works on the moral interpretation of Homer, carefully
                    edited a new edition of <hi rend="italic">Johannis</hi><hi rend="italic">Stobaei
                    Sententioe</hi> (Zürich, 1543) and an expurgated edition of Martial (1544),
                    prepared a new edition of the Latin dictionary of Ambrosius Calepinus (Basel,
                    1544), and wrote besides some lesser dissertations and translations. All this,
                    however, was only mere side work, for in 1545 he issued at Zürich the first part
                    of his justly renowned <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Universalis,</hi> a
                    catalogue of all the works in Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, extant and not extant,
                    published or as yet unpublished. Under each important name there was given a
                    vast mass of bibliographical information and criticism, original and selected.
                    Three years later the second part of this stupendous work appeared, likewise at
                    Zürich, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Pandectarum sive partitionum
                    universalium</hi><hi rend="italic">Conradi</hi><hi rend="italic">Gesneri
                    Tigurini Libri XXI.</hi> Only nineteen of these books then appeared; the
                    twenty-first, which was a theological encyclopaedia, was published in 1549, but
                    the twentieth, which was to contain the medical writings, and which he intended
                    should represent the quintessence of the labours of a lifetime, was never
                    finished and never published.</p>
                <p>The next few years were spent in writing small treatises, and in the preparation
                    of another <hi rend="italic">magnum opus,</hi> a zoological work entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Historia Animalium,</hi> which was published in six books (the
                    last of these unfinished) at Zürich between 1551 and 1587. To prepare himself
                    for the worthy execution of this undertaking he read 250 authors, travelled over
                    nearly all Europe, received hints from hosts of learned friends, and did not
                    disdain the information which he obtained from hunters and shepherds. He also
                    made himself a proficient artist, in order that he might by drawings assist his
                    labours. This work contained the names of all known animals in the ancient and
                    modern languages, a description of each as to every important particular, and a
                    mass of interesting literary information, embracing facts <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n572/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0572-0555"/> and legends regarding them. After this he again
                    occupied himself with lesser writings for some years. He devoted some attention
                    to philology, aided in the preparation of a German-Latin dictionary, and pointed
                    out the force and undreamt-of beauty that lay in that then vulgar and
                    halfdeveloped tongue. But again these and other publications were only secondary
                    labours, for he had a third great work in preparation. He had for some time
                    given great attention to botany, and he now proposed to publish a work on that
                    science corresponding to his great work on zoology. He had made a large
                    collection of materials towards this when his health, never very good,,
                    completely gave way. A few hours before his death he desired to be carried into
                    his museum, and there he spent the last moments of life. He died 13th December
                    1565, not having completed his fiftieth year.</p>
                <p>Gesner’s intense devotion to science, and his almost incredible powers of
                    acquisition, are seen from the recital of the facts of his biography, and from a
                    mere catalogue of his labours. It deserves to be added that his life was
                    singularly pure and blameless, that his love of knowledge was a3 disinterested
                    as it was engrossing, that he was always ready and glad to acknowledge any help
                    he received. When obliged to engage in controversy, he did so in a dignified and
                    courteous manner. His medical writings show him to have been far above the silly
                    prejudices of his day. A cheerful and amiable piety was a prominent feature in
                    his character—a character chastened, not soured, by the trials of a hard
                    lifetime.</p>
                <p>After Gesner’s death his unpublished writings went through a career of
                    vicissitudes not unlike that of their author. A part of them, edited by
                    Professor Schmiedel, was published at Nuremberg in 1753. Other parts followed,
                    but the work was never completed. Lives of Gesner have been written by J.
                    Simmler (Zürich, 1566) and J. Hanhart (Winterthur, 1824). See also Lebert’s
                    Gesner als Arzt (Zürich, 1854), and Gesner’s autobiography in his Bibliotheca
                    Universalis (1st ed., p. 180).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
