<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0119-0110-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GAUGE (9th edition, volume 10, page 110)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176150">Wire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1131462">Standardization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066737">Plate</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066824">Plating</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1017914">Metallizing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4251fv6s">Wire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65g52">Plating</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mn8h">Plate</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tm72270">Metals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n119/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GAUGE</label>, in the mechanical arts, is the name applied to
                    a great variety of instruments, of which the object may be broadly stated to be
                    the affording of increased facilities for comparing any two dimensions or
                    distances. Wherever it is necessary for this to be done with a degree of
                    accuracy unattainable by such means as the ordinary measuring rule affords, or
                    for (he same dimensions to be frequently measured with a maximum of speed and
                    certainty, there will the hand-craftsman at once avail himself of some form of
                    gauge. At the present day a due appreciation of the value of gauges is of
                    growing importance to the mechanician, since they enable him greatly to improve
                    the “fit” of the several portions of his machinery, whilst at the same time the
                    labour expended in fitting is materially reduced. Indeed the system of making
                    all similar parts “to gauge,” so that in any number of machines they are
                    interchangeable, is now effecting more than any other single cause for tho
                    improvement and cheapening of mechanical substitutes for manual labour.</p>
                <p>The gauges which come within the province of this article differ in two main
                    particulars, according as they refer the measurements which can be made by them
                    to some definite and established standard of length, or take cognizance only of
                    an arbitrary or haphazard one. The obvious advantage of being able to record,
                    and at any time again obtain with certainty, the thickness of a plate of metal,
                    or any other gauged dimension, would have led one to suppose that for all except
                    mere temporary purposes the gauges used would invariably be of the first
                    kind—Standard Gauges, as we shall distinguish them. But the fact is unhappily
                    far otherwise, at least as regards the important manufactures of sheetmetal and
                    wire (which cannot be easily measured without some form of gauge), the result
                    being that the thickness and diameters of these are expressed by various
                    complicated and irregular series of numbers and letters, which have no reference
                    either to each other or to any standard system of measurement. Of these
                    arbitrary series the B.W.G. or Birmingham Wire Gauge may be taken as the type.
                    The largest size of which it takes account is known as No. 0000, after which
                    come 000, 00, 0, and then the numerals from 1 to 36, which last is the smallest
                    size. It is frequently used for gauging the thickness of sheet metal as well as
                    for wire, in spite of the existence of the Birmingham Plate Gauge, which has an
                    equally arbitrary series of its own, consisting of the same numbers (from 1 to
                    36) used in the reverse manner, the low numbers being the small sizes. Other
                    arbitrary wire gauges also tend to add to the general confusion, amongst which
                    may be mentioned the Lancashire Gauge, which takes an alphabet and a half, in
                    addition to the numerals up to 80, for expressing the sizes of steel wire which
                    are referred to it, but which nevertheless does not apply to “music wire,” or
                    “needle-wire,” or sundry other special kinds of wire, which are favoured with
                    separate gauges of their own. Of late years careful comparisons have more than
                    once been independently made with a view to ascertaining the standard value of
                    these incongruous systems, but the discrepancies in the results only prove what
                    might have been predicted, viz., that errors have crept in, and that those which
                    profess to be alike differ amongst themselves, whilst there exists no
                    satisfactory means of rectifying these errors. Their gradual and entire
                    abolition therefore seems to be the only chance of real improvement, and it is
                    earnestly to be hoped that the Standard Gauge originally suggested by Sir J.
                    Whitworth, which is now largely employed, may soon entirely supersede them. In
                    this system the sizes are directly referred to the English imperial standard of
                    length, each being expressed by the number of thousandth parts of an inch which
                    it contains. Thus No. 36 wire means wire Ό36 of an inch in diameter. Under the
                    old systems this might have been either No. 20, No. 62, No. 3, or No. 18.</p>
                <p>Examples of some of the usual forms of gauges are given below. For wire the
                    simplest gauge consists of a steel plate with a series of holes drilled through
                    it, each hole being numbered according to the series to which the gauge refers.
                    By means of the Notched Gauge (fig. 1) sheet metal can be gauged by a similar
                    mode of obtaining a more or less accurate fit. Rough gauges on the same
                    principle are constantly employed also in workshop practice for comparing
                    together internal or external diameters, &amp;c.: and they serve the purpose
                    well enough so long as the object is a mere comparison, without taking account
                    of the amount of any minute difference which may exist. When a measurement of
                    such differences is required, or direct reference to a standard system, recourse
                    must be had to some form of gauge provided with means for enlarging them
                    sufficiently to be readily recognizable. Sliding or Calliper Gauges, such as
                    fig. 3, fulfil this requirement by having <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n120/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0120-0111"/> the graduated scale affixed to one of their
                    arms and a vernier in connexion with the other. A V-gauge, which, instead of a
                    series of notches round its edge, has only one long tapering notch, by the
                    graduations of which the diameter of any wire that will enter it can be read
                    off, is simple and tolerably efficient. So also is the kindred arrangement (fig.
                    5), in which a wire or plate can be inserted between a fixed pin and the edge of
                    a revolving cam with graduated face. But perhaps on the whole the best and
                    handiest form is the Micrometer Gauge (fig. 2), which, by means of a micrometer
                    screw with a divided head, measures to the one-thousandth part of an inch, and
                    in careful hands can render visible even smaller fractions. Gauges consisting of
                    two arms jointed together like pincers are also used in certain trades, minute
                    differences in the width of the jaws being magnified and rendered visible on a
                    graduated arc at the opposite ends of the arms.</p>
                <p>Far special purposes gauges of many other forms are employed, some of which are
                    of much greater delicacy, but these cannot be described here. The only others
                    which remain to be mentioned are those of which the Plug and Collar Gauges (fig.
                    4) are the type, sets of which are now to be found in almost all mechanical
                    workshops where the value of standard dimensions is recognized. Each gives only
                    the one external or internal dimension for which it is made, but it gives that
                    with the highest attainable accuracy, so that by carefully preserving a
                    comparatively small number of these for reference, and using them in conjunction
                    with measuring machines, the most minute differences can be measured and noted
                    in terms of the standard, so that exact sizes can at any future time be again
                    obtained without appreciable error. (c. p. <hi rend="smallcaps">b. s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
