<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0583-0566-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GHIBERTI, Lorenzo</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 566</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2td33">Goldsmithing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47659k3h">Goldsmiths</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:944605">Goldsmiths</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1130040">Spirit</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n583/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GHIBERTI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Lorenzo</hi></label>
                    (1378-1455), whose name alone is worthy to rank with that of Donatello amongst
                    the grand Italian sculptors of the Renaissance, was born at Florence in the year
                    1378. He learned the trade of a goldsmith under his father Ugoccione, commonly
                    called Cione, and his stepfather Bartoluccio; but the goldsmith’s art at that
                    time included all varieties of plastic arts, and required from those who devoted
                    themselves to its higher branches a general and profound knowledge of design and
                    colouring. In the early stage of his artistic career Ghiberti was best known as
                    a painter in fresco, and when his native city Florence was visited by the plague
                    he repaired to Rimini, where he executed a highly prized fresco in the palace of
                    the sovereign Pandolfo Malatesta. He was recalled from Rimini to his native city
                    by the urgent entreaties of his stepfather Bartoluccio, who informed him that a
                    competition was to be opened for designs of a second bronze gate in the
                    baptistry, and that he would do wisely to return to Florence and take part in
                    this great artistic contest. The subject for the artists was prescribed,—the
                    sacrifice of Isaac; and the competitors were required to observe in their work a
                    certain conformity to the first bronze gate of the baptistery, executed by
                    Andrea Pisano about 100 years previously. Of the six designs presented by
                    different Italian artists, those of Donatello, Brunelleschi, and Ghiberti were
                    pronounced the best, and of the three Brunelleschi’s and Ghiberti’s superior to
                    the third, and of such equal merit that the thirty-four judges with whom the
                    decision was left entrusted the execution of the work to the joint labour of the
                    two frieuds. Brunelleschi, however, withdrew entirely from the
                    contest,—according to one account, from his cordial admiration of Ghiberti’s
                    genius, according to another, from his unwillingness to share so great an
                    undertaking with any fellow-labourer. The first of his two bronze gates for the
                    baptistry occupied Ghiberti twenty years, and when completed was justly regarded
                    as the greatest work of its kind since the most glorious days of Grecian art.
                    Ghiberti brought to his task a deep religious feeling and the striving after a
                    high poetical ideal which are not to be found in the works of Donatello, though
                    in power of characterization the second sculptor often stands above the first.
                    lake Donatello, he seized every opportunity of studying the remains of ancient
                    art; but he sought and found purer models for imitation than Donatello, through
                    his excavations and studies in Rome, had been able to secure. The council of
                    Florence, which met during the most active period of Ghiberti’s artistic career,
                    not only secured him the patronage of the pontiff, who took part in the council,
                    but enabled him, through the important connexions which he then formed with the
                    Greek prelates and magnates assembled in Florence, to obtain from many quarters
                    of the Byzantine empire the precious memorials of old Greek art, which he
                    studied with untiring zeal. The unbounded admiration called forth by Ghiberti’s
                    first bronze gate led to his receiving from the chiefs of the Florentine guilds
                    the order for the second, of which the subjects were likewise taken from the Old
                    Testament. The Florentines gazed with especial pride on these magnificent
                    creations, which must still have shone with all the brightness of their original
                    gilding when, a century later, Michelangelo pronounced them worthy to be the
                    gates of paradise.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Through long exposure to the dusty atmosphere of the town they have of late
                    years begun to lose considerably in delicacy of outline; and it is much to be
                    feared that, unless measures are speedily taken for their preservation, they
                    will at no distant period suffer a still more marked deterioration.</p></note>
                    Next to the gates of the baptistry Ghiberti’s chief works still in existence are
                    his three statues of St John the Baptist, St Matthew, and St Stephen, executed
                    for the church of San Michele, among which three works, from th9 ideal character
                    of the entire figure and the peculiar felicity of expression, the palm is
                    generally awarded to the St Stephen. In the bas-relief of the coffin of St
                    Zenobio, in the Florence cathedral, Ghiberti put forth much of his peculiar
                    talent, and though he did not, as is commonly stated, execute entirely the
                    painted glass windows in that edifice, he furnished several of the designs, and
                    did the same service for a painted glass window in the church of San Michele. He
                    died at the age of 77.</p>
                <p>We are better acquainted with Ghiberti’s theories of art than with those of most
                    of his contemporaries, for he left behind him a commentary, in which, besides
                    his notices of art, he gives much insight into his own personal character and
                    views. Every page attests the religious spirit in which he lived and worked. Not
                    only does he aim at faithfully reflecting in his creations Christian truths; he
                    regards the old Greek statues witlι a kindred feeling, as setting forth the
                    highest intellectual and moral attributes of human nature. He appears to have
                    cared as little for money as Donatello, and expressly thanks heaven that he had
                    not been cursed with a sordid and mercenary spirit, but had ever loved and
                    laboured at art for art’s own sake.</p>
                <p>Benvenuto Cellini’s criticism on Ghiberti that in his creations of plastic art he
                    was more successful in small than in large figures, and that he always exhibited
                    in his works the peculiar excellences of the goldsmith’s quite as much as those
                    of the sculptor’s art, is after all no valid censure, for it merely affirms that
                    Ghiberti faithfully complied with the peculiar conditions of the task imposed
                    upon him. More frequent have been the discussions of late years as to the part
                    played by perspective in his representations of natural scenery. These have
                    acquired a fresh importance since the discovery of the data, from which it now
                    appears that Fabio Uccelli, commonly regarded as the first great master of
                    perspective, worked for several years in the studio or workshop of Ghiberti, and
                    it becomes difficult to determine to what extent Uccelli’s successful
                    innovations in perspective were due to Ghiberti’s teaching.</p>
                <p>Cicognaro ’ s criticism on Ghiberti, in his History of Sculpture, has supplied
                    the chief materials for. the illustrative text of Lasinio’s series of engravings
                    of the thre⅛ bronze gates of the baptistry. They consist of 42 plates in folio,
                    and were published at Florence by Bardi in 1821. Still more vivid
                    representations are the reproductions on a very large scale by the photographic
                    establishment of Alinari. In the Florence edition of Vasari <hi
                    rend="superscript"> v</hi> s Lives there is given at full length Ghiberti’s
                    commentary on art. Both Mr Perkins, in his History of Tuscan Sculpture, and Mr
                    Rio, in his Art Chrétien, have treated Ghiberti’s works with much fulness, and
                    in a spirit of sound appreciation. But the most recent contributions to what may
                    be termed the Ghiberti literature are the chapter expressly devoted to the
                    history of the competition for the baptistry gates in Semple’s Donatello
                    (Vienna, 18/5), and the articles by Adolf Rosembcrg in Dohme’s Kunst und
                    Künstler des Mittelalters (Leipsiβ, 1877).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
