<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0910-0026-0017-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">GALAPAGOS ISLANDS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 10, page 17</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:813089">Archipelagoes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1026803">Mosses</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1086436">Race</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:813061">Arches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j3q">Darwinism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3p025">Currents</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m35f">Fauna</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205578">Ecuador</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n26/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GALAPAGOS ISLANDS</label>, an archipelago of five larger and
                    ten smaller islands, situated in the Pacific Ocean exactly under the equator,
                    about 500 or 600 miles W. of Ecuador. They were discovered about the beginning
                    of the 16th century by the Spaniards, who gave them their present name from the
                    numerous <hi rend="italic">galapago</hi> or giant tortoises they found there.
                    The larger members of the group, several of them attaining an elevation of 3000
                    to 4000 feet, are Albemarle (75 miles long and 15 broad), Narborough,
                    Indefatigable, Chatham, and James Islands. The total area is estimated at 2250
                    square miles.</p>
                <p>The extraordinary number of craters, a few of them still active, “in size from
                    mere spiracles to huge caldrons several miles in circumference,” to be found
                    throughout the islands, gives evidence that the archipelago has been the result
                    of volcanic action. It stands in very deep water, and Mr Darwin thinks that it
                    has never been nearer to the mainland than it is now, nor have its members been
                    at any time closer together. None of the islands are inhabited, with the
                    exception of Charles, Chatham, and Albemarle, which, since 1829, have been used
                    by the Government of Ecuador <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n27/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0910-0027-0018"/> as a penal settlement for political offenders,
                    who find an easy subsistence on the bananas, Indian corn, and sweet potatoes
                    which readily grow in the black fertile mud of the higher parts, and on the
                    large herds, now become wild, of cattle, swine, and goats. The principal
                    settlement, founded by General Vilamil in 1832, is situated in Charles Island,
                    and bears the name of La Floreana, in honour of Floris, the president of
                    Ecuador. At one time it contained 200 or 300 inhabitants; but when the United
                    States steamer “Hassler” visited the Galapagos in 1871, there were little more
                    than a dozen. In 1872 about 2000 cattle had perished in the island. The
                    archipelago was formerly a frequent resort of vessels in quest of turtle; and it
                    is still visited by parties from Guayaquil in quest of a species of moss, which
                    is sent to the English market under the name of <hi rend="italic"
                    >orchidia.</hi></p>
                <p>Though the islands are under the equator, the climate is not intensely hot, as it
                    is tempered by cold currents from the Antarctic Sea, which, having followed the
                    barren coast of Peru as far as Cape Blanco, bear off to the N. W. towards and
                    through the Galapagos. Very little rain falls, &lt; except during the short
                    season from November to January. The clouds indeed hang low, and the nights are
                    misty, but this benefits those districts only which attain a height of over 800
                    or 1000 feet and enter the moist upper air; so that there alone, and chiefly on
                    the side from which the winds oftenest blow, is there anything like a luxuriant
                    vegetation. The low grounds are entirely parched and rocky, presenting merely a
                    few thickets of Peruvian cactus and stunted shrubs, and a shore as uninviting as
                    it well can be.</p>
                <p>The greatest interest attaches to the study of all the oceanic islands, for the
                    elucidation of the origin and development of their fauna and flora has an
                    important bearing on the question of the genesis of species. The Galapagos
                    archipelago possesses in this respect a rare advantage from its isolated
                    situation, and from the fact that its history has never been interfered with by
                    any aborigines of the human race, and that it is only very lately that the
                    operations of man or of animals introduced by his means have disturbed, and that
                    to a very limited extent only, the indigenous life. Many of the more remarkable
                    animal and vegetable forms are confined to one islet of the group, and are
                    represented on the others by allied but different species. Of the indigenous
                    gigantic tortoises there are five species at present known, each of which is an
                    inhabitant of a different island, and it is believed that many others have
                    become extinct. There are two species, one terrestrial, the other marine, of a
                    peculiar genus of lizard. Nearly all the land birds are peculiar to the
                    archipelago, and of these more than half belong to peculiar genera. The flora of
                    the Galapagos is most remarkable; it differs by upwards of one half of its
                    species from that of the rest of the globe. Both the fauna and flora indicate
                    affinity with the South American continent; and the peculiarities of their
                    distribution can be explained only by the supposition that species were
                    transported to the islands by some accident at very rare and remote intervals,
                    and have become changed through natural selection under the new conditions to
                    which they have been exposed. That there should be so few species common to the
                    different islands is accounted for by their separation from each other by deep
                    channels scoured by rapid currents, the direction of which, and of the winds,
                    rarely violent in this region, does not favour inter-migration. Many of the
                    islands are yet but imperfectly known.</p>
                <p>For more detailed information the following works may be consulted Darwin, <hi
                    rend="italic">Voyage of the Beagle·,</hi> O. Salvin, “On the avifauna of the
                    Galapagos Archip.,” <hi rend="italic">Trans. Zool. Soe.,</hi> part ix., 1876, p.
                    447; Sir J. D. Hooker, “On the Vegetation of the Gal. Arch.,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >Trans. Lin. Soe.,</hi> voL ∑x. p. 235; Dr A. Günther, “Description of the
                    living and extinct races of Gigantic Tortoises of the Galapagos Islands,” <hi
                    rend="italic">PhU. Trans.,</hi> vol. clxv. p. 251; A. R. Wallace, <hi
                    rend="italic">Geographical Distribzιtion of Animals·,</hi> Villavicencio, <hi
                    rend="italic">Geografia de la Rep. del Ecuador,</hi> 1858.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
