<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0608-0591-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GILBERT, Sir Humphrey (9th edition, volume 10, page
                    591)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20n86">Sails</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn0149t">Sailing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f47h26n">Squirrels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103513">Sailing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103579">Sails</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n608/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GILBERT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Humphrey</hi></label>
                    (1539-1583), a celebrated English navigator, was born in 1539 in the county of
                    Devon, second of the three sons of Otho Gilbert of Greenway. By his mother’s
                    side he was half-brother to Sir Walter Raleigh, who resembled him in many points
                    of character, and whose early life was largely influenced and guided by his
                    example. Educated first at Eton and then at Oxford, he was destined by his
                    father for the law; but being introduced at court by Raleigh’s aunt, Catherine
                    Ashley, he obtained the special favour of the queen, and was thus enabled to
                    follow his natural inclination for active enterprise. Recommended by royal
                    letter to Sir Philip Sidney, he received from him an appointment in the army in
                    Ireland; and his services contributed so powerfully to put down the rebellion
                    raging there that in 1570 he was made a knight and rewarded with the government
                    of Munster. He next served for about five years in the Netherlands, being the
                    first English colonel entrusted with command of English forces in that country.
                    On his return to his native land he wrote a remarkable treatise on a subject at
                    that time before the minds of men, the possibility of a north-west passage to
                    India; and in 1576 it was published without his knowledge by George Gascoigne as
                        <hi rend="italic">Discourse of a Discoverie for a New Passage to Cataia</hi>
                    (London, Henry Middleton for Richarde Ihones). The theory in question was
                    supported with no small force of argument, and the discourse was probably not
                    without its influence in leading Frobisher to set out on his first voyage to the
                    frozen north. In J une 1578 Gilbert received letters patent authorizing himself,
                    his heirs and assigns, to discover, occupy, and possess such remote “heathen
                    lands not actually possessed of any Christian prince or people, as should seem
                    good to him or them.” Disposing not only of his patrimony but also of the
                    estates in Kent which he had through his wife, daughter of John Aucher of
                    Ollerden, he strenuously prepared to put his permission to use, and his brother
                    Raleigh joined him in the enterprise. By the end of the summer of 1578 a fleet
                    of 11 sail, with 400 mariners and men-at-arms, was collected off the coast of
                    Devon; but the gallant projectors were singularly unfortunate in the character
                    of some of their associates. Dissensions broke out among the captains and
                    disorder among the crews. Knollys, for example, boasted that, as kinsman to
                    royalty, he was of more value than twenty knights, and insolently rejected
                    Gilbert’s invitation to dinner; and his men, encouraged by their captain’s
                    conduct, filled the town of Plymouth with uproar and riot, which finally
                    culminated in murder. It was not till the 19th of November that Gilbert set
                    sail, with his forces reduced to 7 ships and 150 men. The history of the voyage
                    is involved in obscurity; but about the beginning of summer or a little earlier
                    in 1579, the fleet returned to England, with little, it would appear, to report
                    except that it had lost one of its chief ships and one of its bravest captains,
                    Miles Morgan, in an encounter with the Spaniards. Gilbert lent his three ships
                    to the Government for service against the Spaniards on the Irish coast; but in
                    July 11, 1582, we still find him complaining to Walsingham that he had not
                    received the moneys that were due to him, and that thus he was prevented from
                    doing more for his queen and country. He was already planning a new expedition;
                    and at length in 1583 his fleet was got together. The queen, though she had at
                    first dissuaded Gilbert from his purpose, and would not permit Raleigh to
                    accompany him, wrote to him by his brother’s hand that she wished him “as great
                    good hap and safety to his ship as if herself were there in person,” and sent
                    him as a token a golden figure of an anchor guarded by a lady. On 11th of June
                    he departed from Plymouth with 5 sail; but on the 13th the “Ark Raleigh,” which
                    had been built and manned at his brother’s expense, “ran from him in fair and
                    clear weather having a large wind.” This desertion was a cause of no small
                    displeasure to the admiral, and he wrote to Sir George Peckham to solicit his
                    brother to make the crew an example to all knaves; but it appears not improbable
                    (according to Hayes in Hakluyt’s collection) that the reason of their conduct
                    was the breaking out of a contagious sickness in the ship. On the 5th of August
                    Gilbert landed in Newfoundland, and took formal possession of it in the queen’s
                    name; but proceeding southwards with three vessels, he lost the largest near
                    Cape Breton, and was at last constrained to return homewards with the “Golden
                    Hind” and the “Squirrel” as the only remnant of his fleet. “On Monday the 9th
                    September,” reports Hayes, the captain of the “Hind,” “the frigate was near cast
                    away, yet at that time recovered; and giving forth signs of joy, the general,
                    sitting abaft with a book in his hand, cried out unto us in the ‘ Hind,’ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> i</hi> We are as near to heaven by sea as by land.’ The
                    same Monday night the frigate’s lights were suddenly out, and it was devoured
                    and swallowed up by the sea.” So perished Sir Humphrey Gilbert.</p>
                <p>See Hakluyt’s Collection, vol. iii.; Hooker’s Supplement to Hollinshed’s Irish
                    Chronicle; Roger Williams, The Actions of the Low Countries, 1618; Bliss’s
                    edition of Wood’s Athenae Oxonienses, vol i. p. 493; North British Review, No.
                    45; and the Lives of Sir W. Raleigh by Tytler, James Augustus St John, and
                    Edward Edwards.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
