<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0030-0021-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GALATZ, or Galacz (9th edition, volume 10, page
                    21)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937112">Galatians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4px50">Roumanian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n30/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GALATZ, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Galacz</hi></label>, a town
                    and port of Roumania, principality of Moldavia, chief town of the district of
                    Covurlin, on the left bank of the Danube (there 2000 feet wide), between the
                    mouths of the Pruth and Sereth, about 85 miles from the Sulina mouth of the
                    Danube, and 130 miles N.E. of Bucharest, with which it is connected by rail,
                    lat. 45° 26' 12” N., long. 28° 3 ’ E. Galatz is said to have got its name from a
                    colony of the same Galatians who invaded Asia Minor in 278 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >b.c.,</hi> though this seems doubtful. The town stands c·n a level plateau,
                    and consists of two portions, an old and a new. The former, which is nearest to
                    the river, is irregularly and badly built, with crooked streets paved with wood,
                    some of them being regular sewers. This part of the town is liable to be
                    flooded, and, as in the greater part of Roumania, the sanitary conditions are
                    bad. The new town, which has rapidly extended during the past few years, is
                    built on the rising ground towards the north-west. It is partly paved, is much
                    more open and comfortable than the old town, and contains most of the public
                    buildings, consulates, &amp;c. Galatz is now to a considerable extent lighted
                    with gas, and some time ago a regular system of water-works was commenced to
                    supply the town with purified and filtered water. There are several Roman
                    Catholic and Greek churches, educational institutions, a hospital, a quarantine
                    building, &amp;c. In the church of St Mary is the tomb of Mazeppa, said,
                    however, to have been rifled of its contents by the Russians. Galatz is the seat
                    of the international commission instituted by the treaty of Paris, 1856, to
                    insure the free navigation of the mouths of the Danube; and by the treaty of
                    Berlin, 1878, Roumania is to be represented on this commission, which exercises
                    its duties as far as Galatz independently of all territorial rights. Galatz has
                    been a favourite place for crossing the Danube with military expeditions since
                    the time of the Roman emperors, though during the war of 1877-78 the Russians
                    did not adopt it except for parties of reconnaissance. There are very few
                    strictly Roumanian industries carried on at Galatz. There are several
                    flour-mills, saw-mills, and breweries, extensive cooperage works, and soap and
                    candle manufactories to a small extent; light wines are also made. Galatz is an
                    important free port, and shares with Ibraila most of the trade of the lower
                    Danube. The navigation of the Sulina mouth of the river has so improved that
                    steamers of 850 tons can sail up to Galatz. There are French, Austrian, Russian,
                    and British steamboat companies that carry on a regular trade with Galatz, and
                    attempts have been made by the municipality to construct solid stone wharfs. For
                    the traffic generally much inconvenience is felt from want of adequate quay and
                    warehouse accommodation; but now that Roumania is an independent state,
                    improvements may be made in this and other directions. A considerable proportion
                    of ships unload at Sulina and send their cargoes up to Galatz in lighters. The
                    river is generally frozen over for a few weeks during winter.</p>
                <p>The staple article of export from*Galatz is grain of various kinds, of which
                    large quantities are grown in all the districts situated on the Danube. In 1876
                    281 sailing ships, 157 steamers, and 873 lighters, of an aggregate tonnage of
                    258,391 tons, cleared from the port of Galatz. The lighters had a total of
                    102,564 tons, while of the remainder 13 sailing ships and 70 steamers of 49,779
                    tons were British. In the same year the principal articles of export were—wheat,
                    313,673 qrs.; maize, 423,775 qrs.; barley, 160,443 qrs.; oats, 421,457 qrs.;
                    rye, 1G7,84O qrs.; flour, 391,657 cwt.; fir planks, 766,869; besides
                    considerable quantities of linseed, rape seed, beans, and small quantities of
                    millet, wool, hides, cheese, and· dried prunes. Of wheat 8000 qrs. went to
                    Britain and 19,549 to Holland; maize, 71,500 qrs. to Britain, 21,000 to Malta;
                    rye,. 58,485 qrs. to Holland; barley, 37,347 qrs. to Britain. The total value of
                    exports from Galatz in 1876 was £1,215,621, being a considerable increase over
                    1875. There does not seem to be any return of exports by rail, though Galatz is
                    now connected with the general European railway system. The imports for 1876
                    were valued roughly at £1,750,000, among which manufactured goods figured at
                    £354,000; sugar, £117,000; coal, £112,000; iron, £80,000; caviare, £66,000; oil,
                    £65,000; rice, £58,000; coffee, £32,000; leather, £28,000; sacking, £29,000;
                    soap, £26,000. Galatz is to cease to be a free port on 13tb January 1880, after
                    which import duties will be imposed. Constant steam communication is maintained
                    between Galatz and Constantinople, and regular lines of steamers sail from
                    London, Liverpool, and Hull. There is a British consulate at Galatz. The
                    population in 1873 was estimated at 80,000; if this is correct, it has more than
                    doubled itself in ten years; it was only 8000 in 1835.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
