<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0910-0780-0757-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GOLDEN-EYE (9th edition, volume 10, page 757)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006685">Males</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899294">Ducks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205290">Greenland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n87327d">Ducks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w64d">Barrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n780/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">GOLDEN-EYE</label>, a name indiscriminately given in many
                    parts of Britain to two very distinct species of Ducks, from the rich yellow
                    colour of their irides. The commonest of them—the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Anasfuligula</hi> of Linnaeus and <hi rend="italic">Fuligula</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">cristata</hi> of most modern ornithologists—is, however,
                    usually called by English writers the Tufted Duck, while “Golden-eye” is
                    reserved in books for the <hi rend="italic">A. clangula</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">A. glaucion</hi> of Linnaeus, who did not know that the birds
                    he so named were but examples of the same species, differing only in age or sex;
                    and to this day many fowlers perpetuate a like mistake, deeming the “Morillon,”
                    which is the female or young male, distinct from the “Goldeneye” or
                    “Rattlewings” (as from its noisy flight they oftener call it), which is the
                    adult male. This species belongs to the group known as Diving Ducks, and is the
                    type of the very well-marked genus <hi rend="italic">Clangula</hi> of later
                    systematists, which, among other differences, has the posterior end of the
                    sternum prolonged <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit10newyrich/page/n781/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0910-0781-0758"/> so as to extend considerably over, and, we
                    may not unreasonably suppose, protect the belly—a character possessed in a still
                    greater degree by the Mergansers <hi rend="italic">{Herginee),</hi> while the
                    male3 also exhibit in the extraordinarily developed bony labyrinth of their
                    trachea and its midway enlargement another resemblance to the members of the
                    same Subfamily. The Golden-eye, <hi rend="italic">C.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >glaucion</hi> of modern writers, has its home in the northern parts of both
                    hemispheres, whence in winter it migrates southward; but as it is one of the
                    Ducks that constantly resorts to hollow trees for the purpose of breeding it
                    hardly transcends the limit of the Arctic forests on either continent. So well
                    known is this habit to the people of the northern districts of Scandinavia, that
                    they very commonly devise artificial nest-boxes for its accommodation and their
                    own profit. Hollow logs of wood are prepared, the top and bottom closed, and a
                    hole cut in the side. These are affixed to the trunks of living trees in
                    suitable places, at a convenient distance from the ground, and, being readily
                    occupied by the birds in the breedingseason, are regularly robbed, first of the
                    numerous eggs, and finally of the down they contain, by those who have set them
                    up.</p>
                <p>The adult male Golden-eye is a very beautiful bird, mostly black above, but with
                    the head, which is slightly crested, reflecting rich green lights, a large oval
                    white patch under each eye, and elongated white scapulars; the lower parte are
                    wholly white and the feet bright orange, except the webs, which are dusky. In
                    the female and young male, dark brown replaces the black, the cheek-spots are
                    indistinct, and the elongated white scapulars wanting. The Golden-eye of North
                    America has been by some authors deemed to differ, and has been named <hi
                        rend="italic">C. americana,</hi> but apparently on insufficient grounds.
                    That country, however, has, in common with Iceland, a very distinct species, <hi
                        rend="italic">C.</hi><hi rend="italic">islandica,</hi> often called Barrow’s
                    Duck, which is but a rare straggler to the continent of Europe, and never, so
                    far as known, to Britain. In Iceland and Greenland it is the only habitual
                    representative of the genus, and it occurs from thence to the Rocky Mountains.
                    In breeding-habits it differs from the commoner species, not placing its eggs in
                    tree-holes; but how far this difference is voluntary may be doubted, for in the
                    countries it frequents trees are wanting. It is a larger and stouter bird, and
                    in the male the white cheek-patche3 take a more crescentic form, while the head
                    is glossed with purple rather than green, and the white scapulars are not
                    elongated. The New World also possesses a third and still more beautiful species
                    of the genus in <hi rend="italic">C.</hi><hi rend="italic">αlbeοla,</hi> known
                    in books as the Buffel-headed Duck, and to American fowlers as the “Spirit-Duck”
                    and “Butter-ball” —the former name being applied from its rapidity in diving,
                    and the latter from its exceeding fatness in autumn. This is of small size, but
                    the lustre of the feathers in the male Î3 most brilliant, exhibiting a deep
                    plum-coloured gloss on the head. It breeds in trees, and is supposed to have
                    occurred more than once in Britain. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
