<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-7016-0001-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CALEDONIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240888">Australasia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:939002">Gauls</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193347016?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">CALEDONIA</label>, the ancient name of Scotland.
                    From the testimonies of Tacitus, Dio, and Solinus, we find that the ancient
                    Caledonia comprehended all that country situated to the north of the rivers
                    Forth and Clyde. In proportion as the Silures or Cimbri advanced northwards, the
                    Caledonians, circumscribed within narrower limits, were forced to pass over into
                    the islands which fringe the western coasts of Scotland. It is about this
                    period, probably, that we ought to fix the first great migration of the British
                    Gael into Ireland; that kingdom being much nearer to the promontory of Galloway
                    and Cantyre than many of the Scottish isles are to the continent of North
                    Britain.</p>
                <p part="N">To the country which the Caledonians possessed they gave the name of <hi
                        rend="italic">Gael-doch,</hi> which is the only appellation the Scots, who
                    speak the Gaelic language, know for their own division of Britain. <hi
                        rend="italic">Gael-doch</hi> is a compound formed from <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gael,</hi> the first colony of the ancient Gauls who transmigrated into
                    Britain, and <hi rend="italic">doch,</hi> a district or division of a country.
                    The Romans, by transposing the letter <hi rend="italic">l</hi> in <hi
                        rend="italic">Gael,</hi> and by softening into a Latin termination the <hi
                        rend="italic">ch</hi> of <hi rend="italic">doch,</hi> formed, it is
                    supposed, the well-known name of Caledonia.</p>
                <p part="N">At the period when Agricola invaded North Britain, A. D. 81, that
                    portion of the island appears to have been possessed by twenty-one tribes of
                    aboriginal inhabitants having little or no political connection with one
                    another, although evidently identical in origin, in language, in customs, and in
                    manners. The names and topographical positions of these Caledonian tribes or
                    clans have been preserved and pretty accurately ascertained. They were, 1. The
                        <hi rend="italic">Ottadini,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Ottadeni,</hi> who
                    occupied the south-east boundary of North Britain, extending along the whole
                    line of coast from the southern Tyne to the Frith of Forth, and including the
                    half of Northumberland, the eastern part of Roxburghshire, and the whole of
                    Berwickshire and of East Lothian; 2. The <hi rend="italic">Gadeni,</hi> who
                    inhabited the interior of the country, to the west of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ottadini,</hi> including the western part of Northumberland, a small part
                    of Cumberland to the north of the Irthing, the western part of Roxburghshire,
                    the whole of Selkirkshire, Tweeddale, a considerable part of Mid-Lothian, and
                    nearly all West-Lothian; their possessions extending from the Tyne on the south
                    to the Frith of Forth on the north; 3. The <hi rend="italic">Selgovae,</hi> who
                    inhabited Annandale, Nithsdale, and Eskdale in Dumfriesshire, and the eastern
                    part of Galloway as far as the river Deva or Dee, which was their western
                    boundary; 4. The <hi rend="italic">Novantae,</hi> who possessed the middle and
                    western parts of Galloway, from the Dee on the east to the Irish Sea on the
                    west; on the south they were bounded by the Solway Frith and the Irish Sea, and
                    on the north by the chain of hills which separates Galloway from Carrick; 5. The
                        <hi rend="italic">Damnii,</hi> the most important of the southern tribes,
                    who inhabited the whole extent of country from the ridge of hills which
                    separates Galloway frc-m Ayrshire on the south, to the river Erne on the north,
                    and possessed all Strathclyde, the shires of Ayr, Renfrew, and Stirling, and a
                    small part of those of Dumbarton and Perth; 6. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Horestii,</hi> who inhabited the country between <hi rend="italic"
                        >Eodotria</hi> or Forth on the south, and the <hi rend="italic">Tavus</hi>
                    or Tay on the north, comprehending the shires of Clackmannan, Kinross, and Fife,
                    with the eastern part of Strathern, and <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193347029?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-7029-0002"/> the
                    country westward of the Tay as far as the river Brann; 7. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Venricones,</hi> who possessed the territory between the Tay on the south
                    and the Carron on the north, comprehending Gowrie, Strathmore, Stormont, and
                    Strathardle in Perthshire, together with the whole of Angus, and the larger part
                    of Kineardineshire; J3. The <hi rend="italic">Taixali,</hi> who inhabited the
                    northern part of the Mearns, and the whole of Aberdeenshire as far as the
                    Doveran; 9. The <hi rend="italic">Vacomagi,</hi> who inhabited the eountry on
                    the south side of the Moray Frith, from the Doveran on the east to the Ness on
                    the west, comprehending the shires of Banff, Elgin, Nairn, the eastern part of
                    Inverness, and Braemar in Aberdeenshire; 10. The <hi rend="italic">Albani,</hi>
                    afterwards called <hi rend="italic">Damnii-Albani,</hi> who possessed the
                    interior districts between the lower ridge of the Grampians, which skirts the
                    southern side of the loeh and river Tay on the south, and the chain of mountains
                    which forms the southern limit of Inverness-shire on the north; 11. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Attacoti,</hi> who inhabited the whole of the country from
                    Lochfyne on the west to the eastward of the river Leven and Loehlomond,
                    comprehending the whole of Cowal in Argyleshire and the greater part of
                    Dumbartonshire; 12. The <hi rend="smallcaps">Caledonii</hi> proper,<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">This name,
                            according to Chalmers, is merely the latinized form of <hi rend="italic"
                                >Celyddοnl,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">Cclyddon,</hi> the
                            descriptive appellation given to the country by the British colonists,
                            and signifying literally <hi rend="italic">iiιc Coverts.</hi></p></note>
                    who inhabited the whole of the interior of the country from the ridge of
                    mountains which separates Inverness and Perth on the south, to the range of
                    hills whieh forms the forest of Bal-nagowan in Ross on the north, comprehending
                    all the middle parts of Inverness and Ross; 13. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cantoe,</hi> who possessed the east of Ross from the Moray Frith on the
                    south to the Frith of Dornoch on the north; 14. The <hi rend="italic">Logi,</hi>
                    who possessed the south-eastern coast of Sutherland, extending from the Dornoeh
                    Frith on the south-west to the Helmsdale river on the east; 15. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Carnabii,</hi> who inhabited the south, the east, and the
                    north-east of Caithness, from the Helmsdale river, comprehending the three great
                    promontories of Noss-head, Duneansbay-head, and Dunnet-head; 16. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Cattini,</hi> a small tribe, who inhabited the north-western
                    eorner of Caithness, and the eastern half of Strathnaver in Sutherlandshire,
                    having the river Naver, the <hi rend="italic">Navarijluvius</hi> of Ptolemy, for
                    their western boundary;</p>
                <p part="N">17. The <hi rend="italic">Mertae,</hi> who occupied the interior of
                    Sutherland;</p>
                <p part="N">18. The <hi rend="italic">Carnonacoe,</hi> who inhabited the northern
                    and western coast of Sutherland, and a small part of the western shore of Ross,
                    from the Naver on the east to the <hi rend="italic">Volsas</hi> bay on the
                    south-west; 19. The <hi rend="italic">Creones,</hi> who inhabited the western
                    coast of Ross, from the <hi rend="italic">Volsas</hi> bay on the north to
                    Loehduich on the south; 20. The <hi rend="italic">Cerones,</hi> who inhabited
                    the whole western coast of Inverness, and the districts of Ard-namurehan,
                    Morvern, Sunart,and Arđgower in Argyleshire, having Loehduich on the north, and
                    the Linne-loch on the south; and, 21. The <hi rend="italic">Εpidii,</hi> who
                    inhabited the south-west of Argyleshire, from Linne-loeh on the north, to the
                    Frith of Clyde and the Irish Sea on the south, including Cantyre, and were
                    bounded on the east by the country of the <hi rend="italic">Albani,</hi> and by
                    Loehfyne. Sueh, according to the best authorities, were the names and
                    geographical positions of the twenty-one tribes whieh, at the time of the Roman
                    invasion, oeeupied the whole of North Britain.</p>
                <p part="N">When the tribes of North Britain were attacked by the Romans under
                    Agrieola (see article <hi rend="smallcaps">Britain,</hi> ehap. i.), they entered
                    into associations, in order that, by uniting their strength, they might be more
                    able to repel the common enemy. But the particular name of the tribe whieh
                    either its superior power or military reputation placed at the head of the
                    association, was the general name given by the Romans to all the confederates.
                    Henee it is that the <hi rend="italic">Moeatoe,</hi> who inhabited the districts
                    of Scotland lying southward of the frith, and the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Caledonians,</hi> who inhabited the west and north-west parts, engrossed
                    the glory whieh belonged in eommon, though in an inferior degree, to the other
                    tribes settled of old in North Britain.</p>
                <p part="N">The origin of the appellations <hi rend="italic">Scoti</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Picti,</hi> introduced by the later Roman authors, has
                    occasioned mueh controversy among antiquaries in modern times. It seems
                    tolerably certain, however, that the Scots and Piets were one and the same
                    people; or rather, that the term <hi rend="italic">Picti</hi> or Picts was the
                    generic, and that of <hi rend="italic">Scoti,</hi> or Scots, only a spécifié
                    appellation. Eumenius the orator, who first mentions the Picts, alludes to the
                        <hi rend="italic">Caledones aliique Picti</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> an
                    expression whieh implies that the <hi rend="italic">Caledones</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">other</hi> tribes were considered as Picts. Again, with
                    reference to the question whether the Scots were aboriginal Britons, or merely
                    emigrants from Ireland, it has been shown by arguments whieh appear to Be
                    invincible, that they eame originally fromIreland;
                    but,ontheotherhand,itseemsequally eertain, that the Scots of Ireland, or the <hi
                        rend="italic">Scoticoe</hi><hi rend="italic">gentes</hi> of Porphyry, a
                    branch of the great Celtic family, passed over, at a very remote period, from
                    the shores of Britain into Ireland, and before the beginning of the fifth
                    eentury had given their name to the whole of that eountry. Their name, however,
                    does not occur in the Roman annals till <hi rend="smallcaps">a.</hi> D. 360; but
                    all the authors of the fourth century agree that Ireland was the proper country
                    of the Seots, and that they invaded the Roman territories in North Britain about
                    the period above mentioned. They are deseribed as an erratic or wandering race,
                    who earned on a predatory system of warfare, and also as a transmarine people,
                    who eame from Ireland, their native island. Under the denomination of Picts were
                    ineluded the Caledonians and Seots, and probably also the Attaeots, a warlike
                    elan, settled on the shores of Dumbarton and Cowal. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Scotland.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Caledonia,</hi> the name of a settlement
                    made by the Seots on the western side of the Gulf of Darien in 1698, out of
                    whieh they were starved at the request of the East India Company.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">New</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Caledonia,</hi>
                    an island in the South Sea, discovered by Captain Cook. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Australasia.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">’ CALEDONIAN <hi rend="smallcaps">Canal.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Navigation Inland,</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Scotland.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
