<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-0604-0277-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CEMENT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tk2p">Resins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4ft4w">Wax</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40v89s7n">Waxes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4000031d">Mastication</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1011580">Mastication</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750267">Mastic</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1172931">Waxes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1024112">Mixing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193350604?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">CEMENT</label>. Any substance which is employed in
                    uniting together things of the same or of different kinds may be termed a
                    cement. The following are some of the principal of those used for various
                    purposes.</p>
                <p part="N">To unite pieces of Derbyshire spar, or other stone, take seven or eight
                    parts of resin and one of wax; then melt them together, and mix them with a
                    small quantity of plaster of Paris. The stone should be made sufficiently hot to
                    melt the cement, and the pieces should be pressed so closely together, that the
                    smallest quantity possible of <pb break="no" facs="nls:193350617?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0706-0617-0278"/>the cement may remain between them. It is a
                    rule of general application, that the thinner the stratum interposed, the firmer
                    the hold will be.</p>
                <p part="N">Jewellers unite precious stones whieh have been accidentally broken, by
                    means of gum-mastic. The parts of the gem must be previously heated to a degree
                    sufficient to melt the cement. Cameos of white enamel or coloured glass are also
                    in this way joined to a real stone as a ground. Mastic is likewise employed by
                    jewellers in various ways as a cement. The jewellers in Turkey ornament trinkets
                    and weapons with gems, by uniting them together with the following composition
                    :—Isinglass soaked in water till it swells up and beeomes soft is dissolved in
                    Frcneh brandy or rum, so as to form a strong glue; then two small bits of gum
                    galbanum, or gum ammoniacum, are dissolved in two ounces of this by trituration;
                    and five or six pieees of mastic about the size of peas, being dissolved in as
                    much aleohol as will render them fluid, are to be mixed with the compound by
                    means of a gentle heat. This cement must be kept in a phial elosely stopped; and
                    when used it must be liquefied by immersing the phial in warm water. It will be
                    found to resist moisture.</p>
                <p part="N">If clay and oxide of iron be mixed with oil, they will form a cement
                    whieh hardens under water. A eement insoluble in water is prepared from skimmed
                    milk eheese. The cheese is cut into slices, the rind being thrown away, and
                    boiled till it becomes a strong glue, which, however, does not dissolve in the
                    water. It is to be afterwards washed in cold, and then kneaded in warm water.
                    This process must be several times repeated. The glue is then to be put warm on
                    a levigating stone, and kneaded with quicklime. Though this eement may be used
                    cold, it is best to warm it ;,and it will unite marble, stone, or earthenware,
                    so as to render the joining scarcely discernible.</p>
                <p part="N">Boiled linseed oil, litharge, red lead, and white lead, mixed together
                    and laid on both sides of a pieee of flannel, or even linen or paper, and then
                    put between two pieees of metal before they are brought home or elose together,
                    will make a durable joint, capable of resisting boiling water, or even a
                    considerable pressure of steam. The proportions of the ingredients are not
                    material; but the more the red lead predominates the sooner the eement will dry,
                    and the more of the white lead the contrary. This eement joins stones of any
                    dimensions.</p>
                <p part="N">The following is an excellent cement for iron, as it ultimately unites
                    with it into one mass :—Take two ounces of muriate of ammonia, one of flowers of
                    sulphur, and sixteen of cast-iron filings; mix them well in a mortar, and keep
                    the powder dry. When the eement is to be used, take one part of this mixture,
                    twenty parts of elear iron borings or filings, pound them together in a mortar,
                    mix them with w ater to a proper consistence, and apply the compound between the
                    joints.</p>
                <p part="N">A cement often used by coppersmiths to lay over the rivets and edges of
                    the sheets of eopper in large boilers, in order to serve as an additional
                    security to the joinings, and to secure eoeks and the like from leaking, is made
                    by mixing powdered quieklime with ox’s blood. This cement dries soon, and
                    accordingly must be used fresh.</p>
                <p part="N">Temporary cements are required in cutting, polishing, or grinding
                    optical glasses, and various articles of jewellery, as these must be fixed to
                    bloeks or handles for the purpose. Four ounees of resin, a quarter of an ounee
                    of wax, and four ounees of whitning, made previously red hot, forms a good
                    cement of this kind, as the articles may be united or separated by heat, though
                    they adhere with great tenacity when cold.</p>
                <p part="N">The following composition is recommended as a good cement for electrical
                    apparatus:—Five pounds of resin, one of bees’ wax, one of red ochre, and two
                    table-spoonfuls of plaster of Paris, all melted together. The following is an
                    analysis by Sir Humphry Davy, of Parker’s patent water cement.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">One hundred grains
                                contain</p><p part="N">Silex</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...22</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Alumina í</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">... 9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Oxide of iron and
                                manganese...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...13</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Carbonate of lime</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">...55</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">99</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">One hundred grains lost by
                                heating..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3∙25</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">102∙25</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">An excellent artificial water cement is obtained by heating for some
                    hours to redness a mixture of three parts clay and one part slaked lime, by
                    measure. As a cement for broken china, take quieklime and white of eggs, or old
                    thick varnish; pound and temper them well together, and the composition is ready
                    for use. Broken glass may be cemented in the following manner: Let glass which
                    is more easy of fusion than the parts to be united, be ground up like a pigment,
                    and interposed between the pieces; then let these be subjected to a heat which
                    will melt the cementing medium, and make the parts agglutinate without being
                    themselves fused. Any thing thus united will be found as strong as ever. (Ure’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Chemistry</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Philosophical ĩdagazinef</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Cement</hi><hi rend="italic">for Building.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Lime.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Cement</hi><hi rend="italic">Pots</hi> are
                    those earthen pots used in the cementation of metals.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
