<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-3581-0506-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHENIER, Marie Joseph de</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193353581?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">CHENIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Marie Joseph
                        de</hi></label>, was the son of Louis Chenier, well known as the author of
                        <hi rend="italic">Recherches Historiques sur les Maîtres,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Révolutions de l'Empire Otho-</hi><hi rend="italic">mam.</hi>
                    He was born in the year 1764, at Constantinople, where his father at that time
                    acted as consul-general of France. At a very early period of life he entered
                    into the French army; but he soon relinquished the military profession, and
                    settled at Paris, where he devoted much of his time to literary pursuits. He
                    commenced his dramatic career by a tragedy, which was acted in 1786, and was
                    completely unsuccessful. A few years afterwards, availing himself of the
                    political feelings of the period, he produced the tragedy of Charles IX., which
                    was received with vast applause by the party which predominated at the time.
                    This was followed by <hi rend="italic">Lα Mort</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        Calas,</hi> and the republican tragedies of <hi rend="italic">Gracchus</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Timoleon.</hi> These dramas in a great measure owed their
                    popularity to existing circumstances, and the author’s talent of addressing
                    himself to the prevailing feelings of the multitude. Plis performances, however,
                    were instrumental in procuring him a seat in the National Convention, and
                    obtained him the highest theatrical reputation, till he unfortunately brought
                    forward a tragedy founded on the accession of Cyrus to the throne of the Medes,
                    a subject which, as it gave less scope to political allusion than his former
                    productions, and had been previously treated with greater ability by other
                    writers, failed more completely even than the piece in which he first laid claim
                    to the favour of the public. After this failure Chenier appears to have
                    distrusted his dramatic genius, and chiefly employed himself in translating or
                    imitating the most celebrated productions of the Greek and German stage.</p>
                <p part="N">Chenier, however, did not confine himself to dramatic compositions, but
                    cultivated almost every species of poetry with tolerable success. His
                    productions arc chiefly satirical, lyric, and political. Being engaged in a
                    variety of literary as well as political quarrels, and being naturally of a
                    haughty, irritable temper, he was insensibly led to employ his talents for
                    poetry and satire on all who had provoked his enmity. His works of this
                    description, accordingly, are often misapplied, but are distinguished by
                    considerable gaiety and energy of composition. His lyric productions, of which
                    he published <hi rend="italic">a</hi> collection in 1797, consist partly of odes
                    imitated from the <hi rend="italic">Poems of Ossian.</hi> Most of his other
                    poems, as his <hi rend="italic">Poeme</hi><hi rend="italic">sur</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">ľ</hi><hi rend="italic">Assemblée des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Notables</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dithyrambe sur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ľ</hi><hi rend="italic">Assemblée Nationale,</hi> allude entirely, as their
                    name imports, to-the political events of the day.</p>
                <p part="N">Chenier also distinguished himself as a prose writer by his productions
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Mercure de France,</hi> and the discourses which he
                    prepared for the different academies of which he w as a member, which discourses
                    chiefly turn on subjects connected with the progress of knowledge in Europe, and
                    the literary history of his own country. In consequence of a task assigned by
                    Bonaparte to the Institute, of which Chenier was a member,.he undertook to give
                    a historical and critical account of the most celebrated production^, both in
                    prose and verse, which had enriched French literature from the years 1788 to
                    1808. This sketch was originally read at one of the sittings of the Institute,
                    and was afterwards published under the title <hi rend="italic">Tableau</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Historique</hi><hi rend="italic">de ľ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Etat et des Progrès de la Littérature Française depuis</hi> 1789. This work
                    comprehends a notice of all the best works which had appeared during that
                    period, from the light class of romances to the most important treatises on
                    morals, politics, and legislation; and in poetry it embraces a review from the
                    highest epic to burlesque and mock heroic.</p>
                <p part="N">Many of the orations and discourses pronounced by Chenier in the
                    different political assemblies which were formed during the existence of the
                    French republic, and of almost all which he was a member, related to similar
                    topics,—proposals for legislative measures with regard to literary works, and
                    the encouragement of arts and systems <hi rend="italic">of</hi> public
                    instruction. Those orations which were truly political breathed all the violent
                    spirit of the time, and of the assemblies in which they were delivered. As he
                    took an active part in the distracted politics of his country, and was engaged
                    on one side or other in most of the revolutions by which she was at that time
                    agitated, his character was frequently the object of the blackest calumnies, his
                    property of confiscation, and his person of proscription. All this was little
                    favourable to literary improvement. But when France at length settled under the
                    absolute dominion of one ruler, by being precluded from political intrigue and
                    discussion, he had ample leisure left for study and composition. He continued
                    thus usefully employed, in a state of comparative tranquillity,, till his death,
                    which happened at Paris on the 10th January 1811.</p>
                <p part="N">The character and writings of Chenier partook strongly of the spirit of
                    the times in which he lived. The former was marked by turbulence, restlessness,
                    and ambition; and although some of his poems, as well as his more recent prose
                    compositions, show that his taste was not naturally that of the school of the
                    French revolution, yet many of his tragedies and literary discourses are
                    disfigured by that exaggeration of sentiments and ideas, as <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193353594?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-3594-0507"/>well as
                    that declamatory and inflated style, which the tone and feelings of the period
                    had introduced or propagated. <hi rend="smallcaps">(q.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
