<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-0344-0257-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAVANILLES, Antonio Jose</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193350344?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">CAVANILLES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Antonio
                        Jose</hi></label>, a Spanish ecclesiastic, who devoted himself with great
                    assiduity to the study of botany, and has published several important works, was
                    born in 1745, at Valencia. He received his first education among the Jesuits in
                    that university, and he ever afterwards retained the urbanity of character and
                    manners characteristic of that celebrated order of men. But this was, in him,
                    accompanied with more estimable qualities of the heart than are usually
                    attributed to that order, or than any other exclusively possesses. He early
                    devoted himself to the studies of divinity and philosophy, and was distinguished
                    for diligence and ability, not only in these pursuits, but in the mathematics,
                    history, and belles-lettres. He afterwards removed to Murcia, where he acquired
                    so much credit that he was chosen by the Duke de l’Infantado to superintend the
                    education of his sons. In the house of this nobleman he was perfectly
                    domesticated; and when, after a course of years, the death of his patron broke
                    up a circle of more than usual domestic virtue and felicity, at least in that
                    elevated rank of life, the Abbé Cavanilles became only a more valuable and
                    confidential friend of the survivors. He accompanied the sons of the duke, in
                    their father’s lifetime, to Paris in 1777, where he resided twelve years, adding
                    to his various information, and particularly cultivating the science of botany,
                    with all the aids which that celebrated capital was so well calculated to
                    afford. Here he was more particularly associated with the famous Jussieu, and
                    the pupils of his school. From the Linnaean botanists of Paris he was a good
                    deal estranged; yet he acquired a great inclination towards the Swedish school,
                    and imbibed many of its good principles.</p>
                <p part="N">The first publication of the Abbé Cavanilles was in French, entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">Observations</hi><hi rend="italic">sur l'article</hi><hi
                        rend="italic superscript"> ii</hi><hi rend="italic">Espagne"</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> μ</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Nouvelle Encyclopédie.</hi> This pamphlet contained a defence of his
                    country, against what appeared to him an unfair attack upon it; but we know not
                    the particular subjects of the discussion. We have no difficulty in conceiving
                    that they might be manifold, and that there were few opinions upon which a man
                    of Cavanilles’ correctness and orthodoxy of character, to say nothing of his
                    patriotism, was likely to agree with the writers of the above-mentioned
                    celebrated work.</p>
                <p part="N">He soon afterwards devoted himself to a study which promised him a less
                    thorny path. In 1785 he published at Paris his first <hi rend="italic"
                        >Dissertation upon Monadelphous Plants,</hi> a <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193350357?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-0357-0258"/>Latin 4to,
                    containing the species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Sida,</hi> with some
                    plants nearly related thereto. The plates, uncoloured, were executed from his
                    own drawings; as were those of the rest of his numerous publications. The
                    specimens delineated in this first essay were too small and imperfect. In that
                    respect his following dissertations, making ten in all, have a considerable
                    superiority. His subsequent figures were also better engraved. The descriptions
                    are full and correct; the new species numerous; and the specific characters
                    tolerably classical, though not quite uncontaminated by the feebleness and
                    ambiguity of the French school. This work, in its beginning, not being received
                    by the Linnaean botanists of Paris, and especially by L’Heritier, with any
                    respectful attention, the author, in an evil hour, was induced to complain, in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Journal de Paris,</hi> of negleet and injustice.
                    L’Heritier had not noticed the book in his <hi rend="italic">Stirpes
                        Novae</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> had published the same plants by
                    different names, without citing Cavanilles; and had even antedated some of his
                    own <hi rend="italic">Fasciculi,</hi> in order to conceal, as it appeared, this
                    literary incorrectness. His reply could not, in the opinion of unprejudiced
                    witnesses, clear him of illiberal conduct; though, it is very certain, he
                    neither did nor could borrow any thing from Cavanilles. It would have been
                    better to have declared the truth, that his own plates were already engraved
                    with different names, or that he had at least chosen such as seemed to him
                    preferable. The authority of L’Heritier’s works, by their transcendent merit,
                    has prevailed, while Cavanilles has retained all the credit due to correctness
                    of principle and intention. The ninth and teneth <hi rend="italic"
                        >fasciculi</hi> of Cavanilles, on the <hi rend="italic">Monadelphous</hi>
                    Plants, were indeed published at Madrid, to which place the author returned in
                    1790. The number of plates in the whole work are 296, many of which, especially
                    in the earlier part, contain several species. It cannot be denied that the merit
                    of this work kept increasing as it advanced. The abilities of the writer gained
                    strength by exercise, and his knowledge was enriched by experience. He is
                    charged with admitting as <hi rend="italic">monadelphous</hi> too many plants,
                    the union of whose stamens is very light or uncertain; but it were ungrateful to
                    complain of any book for the riches of its materials. A more real fault is, the
                    usual one of too great and artificial a subdivision of genera. This is also the
                    fault of the school in which he studied, though the great man at its head is
                    perhaps as free from it as any leading writer.</p>
                <p part="N">Soon afterwards the Abbé Cavanilles began a larger and more
                    comprehensive publication, in folio, entitled <hi rend="italic">Icones et
                        Descriptiones</hi><hi rend="italic">Plantarum quae</hi><hi rend="italic">aut
                        sponte in Hispania crescunt, aut in Hortis hospitantur.</hi> The first
                    volume appeared in 1791, containing 100 plates, with ample descriptions. It was
                    followed by five more, of equal size and merit, the last of which came out in
                    1801. The whole work is enriched with critical remarks, and with much
                    economical, as well as what may be called picturesque and sentimental, matter,
                    respecting many native Spanish plants. The exotic part of these volumes is
                    derived from the highly valuable and novel discoveries of the Spaniards in
                    Mexico, Peru, and Chili, and the acquisitions of some voyagers to New Holland
                    and the Philippine Islands. Hence numerous very fine plants, originally
                    discovered by our own celebrated circumnavigators, but unfortunately not yet
                    published by them, have first been made known in the pages of Cavanilles.</p>
                <p part="N">In the course of the botanical tours of our author, he collected
                    materials for a general <hi rend="italic">History of the Kingdom of
                        Valencia,</hi> which appeared in 1795, in Spanish, making two volumes. This
                    work, which we have never seen, is said to bo rich, not only in what relates to
                    the three kingdoms of nature, but likewise, in statistical and antiquarian
                    information.</p>
                <p part="N">Having in June 1801 been intrusted with the directorship of the royal
                    garden at Madrid, he published in 1802 another work in his native tongue,
                    containing the characters and descriptions of the plants demonstrated in his
                    public botanical lectures. To these is pre⅛ <hi rend="subscript"> e</hi> d an
                    exposition of the elementary principles of the science, together with
                    explanations of botanic terms. Cavanilles wιs also a frequent and important
                    contributor to the periodica <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>, work entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">Anales</hi><hi rend="italic">de Ciencias</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Naturales,</hi> published at Madrid. Some observations of his, translated
                    from this journal, may be found in Dr Sim’s and Mr König’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Annals of Botany,</hi> vol. i. 409. The first of these indeed, relative to
                    certain seemingly lenticular bodies, supposed to have an important share in the
                    impregnation of ferns and mosses, he has himself contradicted, as arising from
                    an optical deception. His candid avowal of this, in a letter to Dr Schwartz, is
                    published in volume second of the said <hi rend="italic">Annals,</hi> p. 587. We
                    think him also mistaken in the true stigma of the <hi rend="italic">Iris,</hi>
                    his opinion being sufficiently refuted by those of Kolreuter and Sprengel, given
                    in a note, in the very place just quoted; nor is his idea of the stamens of
                    certain <hi rend="italic">Asclepiadea</hi> correct. If he errs, however, he errs
                    with great authorities.</p>
                <p part="N">The subject of our present memoir undoubtedly excelled more in practical
                    observation than in physiological speculation. He is said to have prepared, and
                    partly printed, the first volume of a <hi rend="italic">Hortus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Matritensis,</hi> being a sort of sequel to his <hi
                        rend="italic">leones</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> for it was intended to
                    contain, not merely the figures and descriptions of curious or new plants from
                    the garden, but also of rare dried specimens from the museum at Madrid. This
                    work, with any other project in favour of science which he might have formed,
                    was cut short by his death, in May 1804, in the fifty-ninth year of his age. An
                    engraved portrait of the Abbé Cavanilles, at the age of forty-four, is given in
                    Schrader’s <hi rend="italic">Neues</hi><hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> published
                    at Erfurt in 1805. Dr Schwartz, in the <hi rend="italic">Annals of Botany</hi>
                    above quoted, gives this testimony to his worth, Cavanilles was, like many
                    others, often rather hasty in his conclusions, but always eager to promote
                    science. He was, indeed, a man of a very noble mind, and of the most generous
                    communicative turn; so that I feel I have lost much by his untimely decease,
                    which I shall ever regret.” (x. x.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
