<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-0253-0250-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAUCASUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:861575">Circassians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814767">Armenians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804157">Albanians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f63">Chains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16p3t">Albanians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193350253?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">CAUCASUS</label>, a vast chain of mountains in
                    Western Asia, commencing to the south of the fortress of Kopil, at the mouth of
                    the river Kuban, which falls into the Black Sea, and, after running to the
                    south, traverses Mingrelia in an easterly direction to the town of Georgiefsk,
                    and the source of the river Kuma. Here the ridge, diverging towards the south,
                    enters Georgia near the source of the river Kur, and afterwards taking an
                    easterly course, runs along the western shores of the Caspian Sea, and through
                    the Persian provinces of Daghestan and Schirvan; and thence penetrating Ghilan,
                    is connected with the Hindoo Coosh Mountains, a branch of the great Himalaya
                    chain. The mountains of Causasus are not, however, understood to extend beyond
                    the isthmus that lies between the Black and the Caspian Seas. In this restricted
                    sense, the length of the chain is calculated at 644 miles, but its breadth is
                    various; from Mosdok to Tiflis, however, it is computed at 184 miles. This
                    region is described by Sir R. Ker Porter as exhibiting nature in her most
                    sublime aspect of rude and terrific grandeur. In many parts it is one continued
                    chain of precipices, or of craggy and impassable mountains, in which the
                    mountain torrent is seen tumbling in cataracts over rocks, or roaring and
                    foaming in the dark and unfathomable abysses through which it makes its way in
                    its progress to the plains. At other times the dreadful avalanche, descending
                    from the mountains, spreads death and desolation around. These awful phenomena
                    of nature are often exhibited in the mountains of Caucasus on a tremendous
                    scale. Vast masses of snow falling from the mountains obstruct the torrents,
                    until they gradually accumulate, and, bursting through with the most fearful
                    desolation, ravage and destroy all that occurs in their course. In other parts
                    these mountains stretch out into level plains. This great ridgc is divided into
                    two parallel chains, the highest summits of which rise to an elevation,
                    according to a Russian measurement, of 16,000 and 17,000 feet. The Elburz, which
                    is on the western declivity, is 16,700 feet high; and the Casibeg is 17,388 feet
                    in height. The highest summits of these mountains are covered with perpetual
                    snow and ice; the lower parts are clothed with thick forests. There are two
                    passes into these mountains, which, from their narrowness, are called gates;
                    namely, the Caucasian Pass, and the Albanian or Caspian Pass. This great chain
                    of mountains is the dividing ridge between the rivers which run with an easterly
                    course to the Caspian Sea, and those which flow west into the Black Sea. The
                    Terek, on the northern declivity, flows into the former; while the Kuban, on the
                    southern declivity, flows into the latter; and beyond these rivers the mountains
                    by degrees decline into the sandy plains of Southern Russia. On the southern
                    declivity the Kur and the Rioni flow respectively into the Caspian and Black
                    Seas; and beyond these rivers are seen the mountain chains of Turkish and
                    Persian Armenia, which connect the Caucasus with the other chains of Western
                    Asia. The southern declivity of these mountains is highly fertile, abounding in
                    forests and fountains, orchards, vineyards, corn-fields, and pastures, in rich
                    variety. Grapes, chestnuts, figs, &amp;c. grow spontaneously in these countries;
                    as well as grain of every description, rice, cotton, hemp, &amp;c. But the
                    inhabitants are barbarous and indolent. They consist of mountain tribes,
                    remarkably ferocious, whose delight is in war, and with whom robbery is a
                    hereditary trade; and their practice is to descend from their fastnesses, and to
                    sweep every thing away from the neighbouring plains, not only grain and cattle,
                    but men, women, and children, who are carried into captivity. The names of the
                    different tribes are the Georgians, Abassians, Lesghians, Ossetes, Circassians,
                    Taschkents, Khists, Ingooshes, Cha-rabulaks, Tartars, Armenians, Jews, and in
                    some parts wandering Arabs. They are mostly barbarous in their habits, and
                    idolatrous in their religion, worshipping stars, mountains, rocks, and trees.
                    There are among them Greek and Armenian Christians, Mahommedans, and Jews.
                    Several of the tribes, particularly the Circassians and Georgians, are accounted
                    the handsomest people in the world; and the females are much sought after by the
                    eastern monarchs, to be immured in their harams. The inhabitants amount to about
                    900,000, who are partly ruled by petty sovereigns, and partly by their seniors.
                    The most famous are the Lesghians, who inhabit the eastern regions, and, living
                    by plunder, are the terror of the Armenians, Persians, 'Turks, and Georgians.
                    Their sole occupation is war; and their services can at any time be purchased
                    by' every prince in the neighbourhood for a supply of provisions and a few
                    silver rubles. Since the extension of the Russian empire in this quarter, many
                    of thcsc mountain tribes have been restrained in their predatory habits. Under
                    the iron rule of that powerful state they have been taught to tremblĉ and obey;
                    military posts have been dispersed over the country, fortresses have been
                    erected, towns have arisen, and commerce and agriculture begin slowly to
                    supplant the barbarous pursuits of war and plunder, in which these mountain
                    tribes have hitherto been engaged. But the work of civilization in these wild
                    regions is still slow; it is difficult to reclaim the people from their
                    long-settled habits of violence and disorder; and it would not be safe for any
                    traveller to pass alone through the⅞e countries, where he would be exposed to
                    robbery and murder.</p>
                <p part="N">All the regions on and about the Caucasus are comprehended under the
                    name of Caucasian countries. They are supposed to extend over an area of 116,078
                    square miles, and to contain 1,673,500 inhabitants. Theprovinces which are under
                    the dominion of Russia are six in number, namely, <hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">st,</hi> the province of Tiflis, or Georgia, containing a
                    population of 390,000: <hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >2d,</hi> ĩmiretta, 270,000; 3c∕, Circassia, 550,000 (here are Russian
                    military posts, to guard against the attacks of the mountain tribes): <hi
                        rend="italic">ith,</hi> Daghestan, or the mountain land, on the Caspian Sea,
                    of which Derbent is the capital, 184,000: <hi rend="italic">oth,</hi> Schirvan,
                    with Bakou, the best harbour on the Caspian, 133,000. In the neighbourhood are
                    the fountains of naphtha to which the <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193350266?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-0266-0251"/>Parsees
                    perform pilgrimages from India. Beyond the Terek, on the northern side of the
                    Caucasus, lies, <hi rend="italic">f&gt;th,</hi> the provinceof Caucasia, which,
                    previously to 1822, was the government of Georgiefsk. Of the inhabitants of this
                    province, amounting to 146,500, 21,000 are Russians, and 48,000 colonists. Here
                    are twenty-two fortified places, among which are Georgiefsk, Kĩzĥar, a
                    commercial city with a population of 9000, and Alexandrovsk, which form, along
                    with the Kuban, the Kama, and the Terek, defences against the inroads of savage
                    tribes. Since 1825 Stavropol has been the capital of this province. Here is the
                    Scottish missionary station of Kara, founded in 1803, and enlarged by Moravians
                    from Sarepta, with schools and a printing office. Hitherto the efforts of the
                    missionaries have not been very successful in disseminating the Christian faith
                    among the savage tribes. <hi rend="smallcaps">(f.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
