<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-0487-0268-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CECIL, William</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1119758">Sisters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938095">Garters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02z952">Cannon</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193350487?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">CECIL, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>,
                    Lord Burghlcy, treasurer of England in the rcign of Queen Elizabeth, was the son
                    of Riehard Cecil, Esq. master of the robes to King Henry VIII. Hc was born in
                    the house of his grandfather, David Ceci), Esq. at Bourn, in Lincolnshire, in
                    the year 1520, and received the rudiments of his education in the grammar school
                    at Grantham. From this seminary he was removed to Stamford, and about the year
                    1535 was entered of St John’s College, Cambridge. Here he began his studies with
                    a degree of cnthusiastie application very uncommon in young gentlemen of family.
                    At the age of sixteen he read a sophistry lecture, and at nineteen a voluntary
                    Greek lecture, whieh was the more extraordinary as at that time the Greek
                    language was by no means universally understood. In 1541 he went to London, and
                    became a member of the soeiety of Gray’s Inn, with an intention of studying the
                    law; but he had not been long in this situation before an accident introduced
                    him to King Henry, and gave a new bias to his pursuits. O’Neil, a famous Irish
                    chief, having brought to court with him two <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193350500?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-0500-0269"/>Irish
                    chaplains, violent bigots to the Romish faith, Mr Cecil, happening to meet these
                    ecclesiastics when on a visit to his father, had a warm dispute with them in
                    Latin, in which he displayed uncommon abilities. The king, being informed of the
                    circumstance, ordered the young man into his presence, and was so pleased with
                    his conversation that he commanded his father to find a place for him. He
                    accordingly requested the reversion of the <hi rend="italic">custos
                        brevium,</hi> which Mr Cecil afterwards possessed. About this time hc
                    married the sister of Sir John Cheke, by whom he was recommended to the Earl of
                    Hertford, afterwards Duke of Somerset and protector.</p>
                <p part="N">Soon after King Edward’s accession, Mr Cecil came into the possession of
                    the office of <hi rend="italic">custos brevium,</hi> worth about L.240 a year;
                    and his first lady dying in 1543, he married the daughter of Sir Anthony Cook,
                    director of the king’s studies. In 1547 he was appointed by the protector master
                    of requests, and soon afterwards attended his noble patron in his expedition
                    against the Scots, and was present at the battle of Musselburgh. In this battle,
                    which was fought on the 10th of September 1547, Mr Cecil’s life was miraculously
                    preserved by a friend, who, on pushing him out of the line of a cannon-shot, had
                    his arm shattered to pieces. The sight and judgment of his friend must have been
                    as extraordinary as his friendship, to perceive the precise direction of a
                    cannon-ball; unless we suppose that the ball was almost quite spent, in which
                    case the thing is not impossible. The story is told in his life by a domestic.
                    In the year 1548 Mr Cecil was made secretary of state; but in the following year
                    the Duke of Northumberland’s faction prevailing, he suffered in the disgrace of
                    the protector Somerset, and was sent prisoner to the Tower. After three months’
                    confinement he was released, restored to his office in 1551, and soon afterwards
                    knighted and sworn of the privy council. In 1553 he was made chancellor of the
                    order of the Garter, with an annual fee of a hundred merks.</p>
                <p part="N">On the death of Edward VI. Sir W <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi> illiam
                    Cecil prudently refused to have any concern in Northumberland’s attempt in
                    favour of the unfortunate Lady Jane Grey; and when Queen Mary succeeded to the
                    throne, he was graciously received at court; but not choosing to change his
                    religion, was dismissed from all his employments. During this reign he was twice
                    elected knight of the shire for the county of Lincoln, and often spoke in the
                    House of Commons with great freedom and firmness, in opposition to the ministry.
                    Nevertheless, though a protestant and a patriot, he had die address to steer
                    through a very dangerous sea without suffering shipwreck.</p>
                <p part="N">Queen Elizabeth’s accession, in the year 1558, immediately dispelled the
                    cloud which had obscured his fortunes and ministerial capacity. During the
                    horrid reign of her sister he had constantly corresponded with the princess
                    Elizabeth; upon the very day of her accession, he presented her with a paper
                    containing twelve articles necessary for her immediate dispatch; and, in a few
                    days after, he was sworn of the privy council, and made secretary of state. His
                    first advice to the queen was to call a parliament; and the first business he
                    proposed after it had assembled was the establishment of a national church. A
                    plan of reformation was accordingly drawn up under his immediate inspection, and
                    the legal establishment of the church of England was the consequence. Sir
                    William Cecil’s next important concern was to restore the value of the coin,
                    which had been considerably debased in the preceding reigns. In 1561 he was
                    appointed master of the wards, and, in 1571, created Baron of Burghley as a
                    reward for his services, particularly in having lately stifled a formidable
                    rebellion in the north. The following year he was honoured with the garter, and
                    raised to the office of lord high treasurer of England. From this period we find
                    him the prime mover of every material transaction during the glorious reign of
                    Queen Elizabeth. Notwithstanding the temporary influence of other favourites,
                    Lord Burghley was, in fact, her prime minister, and the person in whom she
                    chicfly confided in matters of real importance. Having filled the highest and
                    most important offices of the government for forty years, and guided the helm of
                    the state during the most glorious period of English history, he departed this
                    life on the 4th of August 1598, in the seventyeighth year of his age. His body
                    was removed to Stamford, and there deposited in the family vault, where a
                    magnificent tomb was erected to his memory.</p>
                <p part="N">He wrote, 1. <hi rend="italic">La Complainte</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        l</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Ame</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">pécheresse,</hi> or the Complaint of a sinful Soul, in French
                    verse; 2. Materials for Patten’s <hi rend="italic">Diarium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Exped. Scoticoe,</hi> London, 1541, 12mo; 3. Slanders and Lies,
                    maliciously, grossly, and impudently vomited out in certain trãiterous books and
                    pamphlets against two counsellors, Sir Francis Bacon and Sir William Cecil; 4. A
                    Speech in Parliament, 1562, Strype’s Mem. vol. iv. p. 107; 5. Precepts or
                    Directions for the well ordering of a Man’s Life, 1637, Harl. Cat. vol. ii. p.
                    755; 6. Meditations on the Death of his Lady, Ballard’s Mem. p. 184; 7.
                    Meditations on the state of England during the reign of Queen Elizabeth,
                    manuscript; 8. The execution of justice in England for the maintenance of public
                    and Christian peace, &amp;c. Lond. 1581, 1583, Somers Tracts, 4th Collect, vol.
                    i. p. 5; 9. Advice to Queen Elizabeth in Matters of Religion and State, ib. p.
                    101, 106; 10. A great number of Letters; 11. Several Pedigrees, some of which
                    are preserved in the Archbishop of Canterbury’s library at Lambeth.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
