<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0706-1072-0313-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CHAMBERS, David</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:946934">Gray</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193351072?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">CHAMBERS, <hi rend="smallcaps">David</hi></label>, a
                    Scotch historian, priest, and lawyer, was born in the shire of Ross about the
                    year 1530, and educated in the university of Aberdeen. From thence he went to
                    France and Italy, where he continued some time, particularly at Bologna, where
                    in 1556 he was a pupil of Mariannus Sozenus.</p>
                <p part="N">After his return to Scotland, he was appointed by Queen Mary, parson of
                    Suddy, and chancellor of Ross. He was soon afterwards employed in digesting the
                    laws of Scotland, and was principally concerned in publishing the acts of
                    parliament of that kingdom by authority in 1566. He was also appointed one of
                    the lords of session, and continued her majesty’s faithful servant till her
                    declining fortune obliged her adherents to seek for refuge in othe∙ kingdoms.
                    Chambers went first to Spain, where he was graciously received by king Philip;
                    and thence travelled to Paris, where he was no less kindly welcomed by Charles
                    IX. of that kingdom, to whom, in 1572, he presented his history of Scotland. He
                    died at Paris in the year 1592, much regretted, says Mackenzie, by all who knew
                    him. His writings were chiefly calculated to assist his royal mistress, and to
                    extol the wisdom of the Scotch nation.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Chambers,</hi><hi rend="italic">Ephraim,</hi>
                    author of the Cyclopaedia which bears his name, was born at Milton, in the
                    county of Westmoreland. His parents were dissenters of the Presbyterian
                    persuasion, and his education was no other than that common one which is
                    intended to qualify a youth for trade and commerce. λVhen he became of a proper
                    age, he was put as apprentice to Mr Senex the globe-maker, a business which is
                    connected with science, and especially with astronomy<pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193351085?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0706-1085-0314"/> and
                    geography. It was during Mr Chambers’ residence with this skilful mechanic that
                    he contracted that taste for science and learning which accompanied him through
                    life, and directed all his pursuits. It was even at this time that he formed the
                    design of his great work, the <hi rend="italic">Cyclopoedia</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> and some of the articles of it were written behind the
                    counter. Having conceived the idea of so extensive an undertaking, he justly
                    concluded that the execution of it would not consist with the avocations of
                    trade; and therefore lie quitted Mr Senex, and took chambers at Gray’s Inn,
                    where he chiefly resided during the rest of his days. The first edition of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia,</hi> which was the result of many years’
                    intense application, appeared in 1728, in two volumes folio. It was published by
                    subscription, the price being L4. 4s.; and the list of subscribers was
                    exceedingly respectable. The dedication to the king is dated the 15th October
                    1727. The reputation which Mr Chambers acquired by bis execution of this
                    undertaking procured him the honour of being elected fellow of the Royal Society
                    on the 6th November 1729. In less than ten years time a second edition became
                    necessary, which accordingly was printed, with corrections and additions, in
                    1738; and it was followed by a third in the course of next year.</p>
                <p part="N">Although the <hi rend="italic">Cyclopoedia</hi> was the grand business
                    of Mr Chambers' life, and may be regarded as almost the sole foundation of his
                    fame, his attention was not wholly confined to this undertaking. He was
                    concerned in a periodical publication entitled <hi rend="italic">The Literary
                        Magazine,</hi> which was begun in 1735. In this work he wrote a variety of
                    articles, and particularly a review of Morgan’s <hi rend="italic">Moral
                        Philosophy.</hi> He was engaged likewise, in conjunction with Mr John
                    Martyn, fellow of the Royal Society, and professor ofbotany at Cambridge, in
                    preparing for the press a translation and abridgment of the Philosophical
                    History and Memoirs of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Paris, or an Abridgment
                    of all the Papers relating to Natural Philosophy which have been published by
                    the Members of that illustrious Society. This undertaking, when completed, was
                    comprised in five volumes 8vo, which did not appear till 1742, some time after
                    our author’s decease, when they were published under the joint names of Mr
                    Martyn and Mr Chambers. In a subsequent publication, Mr Martyn passed a severe
                    censure upon the share which his fellowlabourer had had in the abridgment of the
                    Parisian papers. The only work besides, that we find ascribed to Mr Chambers, is
                    a translation of the <hi rend="italic">Jesuit's Perspective,</hi> from the
                    French; which was printed in 4to, and has gone through several editions. Mr
                    Chambers’ close and unremitting attention to his studies at length impaired his
                    health, and obliged him occasionally to take a lodging at Canonbury-house,
                    Islington. This not having greatly contributed to his recovery, he made an
                    excursion to the south of France, but did not reap that benefit from it which he
                    had himself hoped, and which his friends wished; for, returning to England, he
                    died at Canonbury-housc, and was buried at Westminster, where the following
                    inscription, written by himself, is placed on the north side of the cloisters of
                    the Abbey:</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> Multis pervulgatis, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Paucis notus; </l>
                    <l part="N"> Qui vitam, inter lucem et umbram, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Nec eruditus, nec idiota, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Literis deditus, transegit; sed ut homo </l>
                    <l part="N"> Qui humani nihil a se alienum putat. </l>
                    <l part="N"> Vita simul, et laboribus functus, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Hic requiescere veluit, </l>
                    <l part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Ephraim Chambers,</hi> R. S. S. </l>
                    <l part="N"> Obiit xv. Mail <hi rend="smallcaps">mdccxl.</hi></l>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
