<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0203-0190-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TERRA-COTTA (9th edition, volume 23, page 190)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w53k">Erosion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w66">Cat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n203/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TERRA-COTTA</label>.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>An Italian word meaning literally “baked earth.”</p></note>
                    Strictly speaking this name is applicable to all objects made of baked clay,
                    from the rudest brick to the finest piece of pottery, but it usually has a more
                    limited meaning, to denote fictile objects which do not come under the head of
                    pottery, such as statuettes and busts; and in its architectural use it specially
                    implies the finer sorts of decorative clay-work, to the exclusion of common
                    building bricks. In ancient times, especially among the Greeks and Romans,
                    terracotta was employed for an immense variety of purposes, from the commonest
                    objects of everyday use to the most elaborate and ambitious works of art, such
                    as colossal statues and groups. Though the natural colour and surface of the
                    burnt clay are generally very pleasing in tone and texture, it seems to have
                    been universally the custom in classical times to cover the terra-cotta
                    completely with a thin white coating, which formed an absorbent ground for the
                    further application of colour. For internal work, except in rare instances,
                    these colours were mixed with a tempera medium, and applied after the clay had
                    been fired. They were therefore not true ceramic colours; and pigments of great
                    variety and brilliance could be employed, as they had not to undergo the severe
                    ordeal of the kiln. For external work, such as that shown in fig. 5, only earth
                    pigments such as ochres and lime were used, and the colours were fired.</p>
                <p>No branch of archaeology has during the last dozen years or so developed so
                    rapidly as that of Greek terracotta figures; on this most fascinating subject an
                    astonishingly large mass of literature has been published in Germany and
                    France.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See list at the
                    end of the present article.</p></note> The discovery of this new world of Greek
                    art began practically in 1873, with the first excavations in the tombs of
                    Tanagra, a Boeotian town on the high road from Athens to the north, which
                    brought to light a number of very beautiful terra-cotta statuettes.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi rend="italic">Bulk
                    Corn. Insk Arch.,</hi> 1874, p. 120. Many thousand tombs have been opened at
                    Tanagra, partly cut in the rock and partly built of masonry. The statuettes were
                    either arranged round the body or packed in large vases. The costume of the
                    female figures is the same as that described by classical writers as being
                    peculiar to the neighbouring city of Thebes. The finest of the Tanagra figures
                    are from 8 to 9 inches high.</p></note> Subsequent excavations at Corinth,
                    Smyrna, Cyme, Tarentum, the Cyrenaica, and many other places also yielded a vast
                    number of terra-cotta figures of various dates and styles. By far the greater
                    number belong to the second half of the 4th century <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi>; but examples of an earlier <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n204/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0204-0191"/> date are not wanting, not only of figures in the
                    round, but also of reliefs, which appear to have been largely used for the
                    decoration of the flat surfaces of walls and friezes. The earliest of all date
                    from a quite prehistoric period, and are mostly small idol-like figures of the
                    rudest possible form, having an almost shapeless trunk with stick-like
                    projections for the limbs, and the breasts and eyes roughly indicated by round
                    dots. They are usually decorated with coarse stripes or cheques in ochre
                    colours. Examples of these have been found at Hissarlik (Troad), in Cyprus and
                    other islands, and in the citadel of Tiryns in 1884-85 by Dr Schliemann and Dr
                    Dörpfeld. Later but still very archaic figures, 2 or 3 inches high, have been
                    exhumed in many parts of the Aegean Islands; some of these are stiff seated
                    figures of deities,—links between Oriental and Hellenic art, like the statues of
                    the Sacred Way at Branchidae (south of Miletus). Comparatively few specimens
                    exist of the best period of Greek art—the 5th century.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A good example of a terra-cotta relief of the
                    first part of the 5th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> is figured in vol.
                    ii. p. 352.</p></note> A relief in the Louvre (about 18 by 12 inches) with a
                    pierced background, dating from the first half of the 5th century, represents
                    two female mourners at a sepulchral stele,—one standing and the other seated;
                    under the foot of the latter is inscribed AΛEKTP. On the other side of the stele
                    are two youths (the Dioscuri) standing by a horse. The whole design is simple,
                    but very graceful, and the modelling is skilfully treated in very low relief.
                    The colouring—blue, red, white, and dark brown—is well preserved. This relief
                    was pressed in a mould, and was intended to be attached to a wall, probably that
                    of a tomb, as a votive offering to the dead.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Some very beautiful fragments of reliefs in terra-cotta are
                    preserved in the museums of the Louvre, of Copenhagen, and the Kircheriano in
                    Rome. These represent on a small scale parts of Phidias’s Panathenaic frieze,
                    which have all the appearance of being works of the 5th century <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> but may possibly be forgeries or Roman copies; see
                    Waldstein, <hi rend="italic">Art of Pheidias,</hi> Cambridge,
                    1885.</p></note></p>
                <p>In most cases the terra-cotta figures and reliefs occur in or close by tombs, but
                    it is only in comparatively rare instances that the subjects represented have
                    any reference to death. Another large class have been found in the vicinity of
                    temples, and are probably votive offerings, such as the small statuettes of
                    horses from the acropolis of Athens, now in the Louvre. In other cases, as at
                    Halicarnassus, great quantities of small figures were buried under a temple,
                    probably to purify the site, as was done in Egypt under the later dynasties,
                    when many hundred figures of bronze were sometimes buried under one building.
                    Owing to the fact that the statuettes found scattered in and round tombs have
                    frequently their heads broken off, Pottier and Reinach have suggested that they
                    were brought as offerings to the dead and their heads were broken off by the
                    mourners at the side of the tomb. Rayet believes that this practice was a sort
                    of survival of the custom of sacrificing female and boy slaves at the tombs of
                    the dead. In many cases, however, the figures are intact, and it is probable
                    that many of the tombs were broken open and rifled long ago, which would explain
                    the mutilated and scattered condition of the figures. The tombs of Tanagra have
                    yielded by far the richest finds of these figures, the specimens being very
                    remarkable for their beauty. These exquisite statuettes do not (in most cases)
                    represent deities or heroic personages, but the homely every-day life of the
                    Greeks, treated with great simplicity and evident realism: they are in plastic
                    art what in painting would be called <hi rend="italic">genre</hi><note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In some the most homely sort
                    of <hi rend="italic">genre</hi> is represented,—a girl milking a cow, a cook or
                    a barber at his work, &amp;c. Even portrait figures occur, as, for example, a
                    wonderfully lifelike group of a man and his wife in the collection of Mr
                    Ionides, recently lent to the South Kensington Museum.</p></note><hi
                    rend="italic">?</hi> and in their strong human interest and naturalistic pathos
                    bring us in closer contact with the life and personalities of the past than any
                    more ambitious style of art could possibly do. Moreover, they prove more clearly
                    even than the great plastic works in bronze and marble how deeply a feeling for
                    beauty and a knowledge of art must have penetrated the whole mass of the people.
                    Their immense number shows that they must have been far from costly, within the
                    reach of every one, and certainly not the production of any famous sculptors.
                    Nevertheless, sketchy as they are in treatment and often faulty in detail, they
                    are in pose, in motive, and in general effect works of the highest beauty, full
                    of the most inimitable grace, and evidently the production of men in whom the
                    best qualities of the sculptor were innate by a sort of natural birthright.
                    Several small figures from Myrina (Mysia) have the artist’s name inscribed on
                    them; but signatures of this sort are rare.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See <hi rend="italic">Gaz. des B.-Arts,</hi> xxxiii., 1886,
                    p. 278.</p></note><hi rend="superscript"> 4 1</hi></p>
                <p>It is impossible to describe the many subjects treated. Only a few examples can
                    bementioned. Among single figures the most frequent are those of girls standing
                    or seated in an immense variety of pose, and with plentiful drapery arranged in
                    countless methods, showing the great taste with which a Greek lady could dispose
                    the folds of her ample pallium, whether it hung in graceful loops or was wound
                    closely round the figure or formed a hood-like veil over the head. In some the
                    lady holds a leaf-shaped fan, or is looking in a circular mirror, or holds a
                    ball ready for the game. Many have a strange broad hat, probably of straw, which
                    does not fit on the head, but must have <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n205/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0205-0192"/> been fastened by a pin to the hair or veil. One
                    very beautiful motive is that of a girl playing with an infant Eros, who flies
                    to her for shelter, and is received with welcome half tinged with dread. Fig. 1
                    shows a very lovely statuette of this kind, now in the Hermitage Palace. A
                    favourite subject is taken from a game in which one girl carries her playmate on
                    her back,—a motive which, though difficult to treat in sculpture, is managed
                    very gracefully in terra-cotta. Other very lovely groups are Aphrodite suckling
                    the baby Eros, or with more than one cupid hovering round her. A very beautiful
                    example (see fig. 2) occurs in the South Kensington Museum (from the Castellani
                    sale). It represents a half-nude figure of Aphrodite reclining on a couch, with
                    two cupids behind holding up a veil, which was coloured blue to form a
                    background to the creamy white of Aphrodite’s body.</p>
                <p>The Tanagra and other figures are all formed of thin pieces of soft clay pressed
                    into a mould, usually formed in two halves and then stuck together; and they are
                    made hollow so as not to warp and crack in the firing, and have a hole at the
                    back for the escape of moisture during that process. The head is solid and was
                    formed in a separate mould, as were also any accessories, such as fans or
                    mirrors, and arms if they extend away from the body. Replicas of the same figure
                    are often varied by having different heads or accessories;’ three or four
                    examples have been found from the same mould. After the whole was put together
                    it was usually touched up and finished with modelling tools. The colour was
                    applied after baking: a coating of creamy white lime or chalk all over served as
                    the flesh tint and also as a good ground for the other colours. The hair of the
                    females is always, of a rich auburn red, such as the Venetians were so fond of
                    painting in the 16th century; blue was touched on the eyes and crimson on the
                    lips. Drapery, if not white, was usually rose-colour or blue, often with a
                    fringe or bands of gold on the border. Necklaces, earrings, and other ornaments
                    were generally gilt, the gold leaf being applied over a slightly raised surface
                    of slip, as on the Greek vases. Similar examples have been found in tombs at
                    Thebes, at Thespiae, and round Athens. Some of the Attica figures are covered,
                    not with the usual non-ceramic colours, but with a real white enamel, the
                    vitrified surface of which is very often slightly decomposed; further coloured
                    decoration was in some cases added over this enamel.</p>
                <p>A number of places in the west of Asia Minor have yielded large quantities of
                    terra-cotta figures, very similar in size and technique to those of Tanagra, but
                    belonging for the most part to quite a different school of sculpture. Unlike the
                    Tanagra figures, which are rather pictorial in style and deal with <hi
                    rend="italic">genre</hi> subjects, those from Smyrna, Cyme, Myrina, and other
                    places in Asia Minor are thoroughly sculpturesque in design, and are frequently
                    miniature reproductions of large statues or groups (see fig. 3). Many of them
                    stand on moulded pedestals, while the Tanagra figures have only a thin slab of
                    clay as a base. The average size of both classes is from 6 to 10 inches high.
                    Very elaborate groups with three or four figures often occur. Dionysiae and
                    Bacchanal subjects are frequently chosen, or scenes from sacred mythology, such
                    as the labours of Heracles.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Fine examples of all these existed in the collection of Μ. Lecuyer, which is
                    now dispersed (see Lenormant, <hi rend="italic">Coll. Lecuyer de
                    ierre-cuites,</hi> Paris, 1884, which is well illustrated with
                    photographs).</p></note> These also mostly date from the 4th century <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and the statuettes often appear to be copies from
                    sculpture of the school of Praxiteles or Scopas. One instance is the fine nude
                    figure of Eros as a youth leaning against a cippus, holding a bronze arrow in
                    his hand, in the collection of M. de Branteghem, now in Rome.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In a few other examples
                    objects of bronze are placed in the hands of the figures.</p></note> The whole
                    of it was gilt, which was frequently the case with the Asia Minor statuettes,
                    but rarely so in those of Tanagra.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The lovely series of little figures of dancing cupids from
                    Tanagra, some of which are in the Louvre and others in the South Kensington
                    Museum, were wholly gilt, but the larger statuettes of Tanagra appear to have
                    had gold applied only for special ornaments.</p></note> A very beautiful figure
                    of a winged Victory in the same collection (from the Castellani sale) presents
                    the same motive as the colossal Victory of Samothrace (in the Louvre); it
                    supplies the missing right hand, which in the terra-cotta contains a bunch of
                    roses. The drapery of this figure is blue, mottled, or shot with gold. Other
                    figures, from their heights being arranged in even gradations, seem to be copies
                    from some large pedimental sculpture. Unfortunately little is yet known of the
                    various fabriques of these Asia Minor figures, as in most cases their <hi
                    rend="italic">provenance</hi> is very doubtful.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For many reasons both finders and dealers
                    usually wish to keep secret where valuable finds are made. In most museums the
                    labels simply repeat the dealer’s account (for want of better information), so
                    that the statement of the <hi rend="italic">provenance</hi> must usually be
                    accepted with caution.</p></note> The Lecuyer collection possessed some groups
                    with several figures forming important compositions. One of these shows two
                    female mourners at a tomb, and a warrior clad in full armour with his horse. The
                    most remarkable group (see fig. 4) is that of a soul led by Hermes Psycho-pompus
                    to the bark of Charon, who is represented as a bent aged man. Hermes, a graceful
                    nude figure, gently urges the shrinking soul—a draped female figure—to the boat,
                    at the brink of the rush-grown Styx. The whole scene is imagined -with much
                    tender grace and real pathos, though not highly finished in its details. One of
                    the most important terra-cotta figures yet discovered has recently been brought
                    to England from Smyrna. It is a very beautiful copy of the Diadumenos of
                    Polycletus, which in the details of its modelling reproduces some
                    characteristics of the later school of Praxiteles. The forearms and the legs
                    below the knee are lost; but in breadth <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n206/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0206-0193"/> of modelling and grandeur of style this little
                    figure, which was only about 14 inches high when perfect, has the effect of a
                    much larger statue, and it is a real masterpiece of Greek plastic art.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi rend="italic">Jσu,rη.
                    of Hellenic Studies,</hi> vol. vi., 1886, p. 243.</p></note> In the
                    neighbourhood of Smyrna and Ephesus a large number of caricature figures have
                    been exhumed, some of which are modelled with a wonderful feeling for
                    humour.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The British
                    Museum possesses some fine caricatures of actors from Caniuo, very skilfully
                    modelled and of a peculiar fabrique.</p></note> These strange figures have
                    attenuated limbs, large heads, flapping ears, and goggle eyes. Some play on
                    musical instruments; others represent actors; and one in the De Branteghem
                    collection is a caricature of a discobolus in almost the attitude of Myron’s
                    celebrated statue.</p>
                <p>A very different class of statuettes has recently come to light in the Cyrenaica,
                    on the northern coast of Africa. Many of these are nude female dancers wearing
                    an elaborate stephanos-like head-dress. They are realistic in modelling and very
                    ungraceful in pose,—a striking contrast to the exquisite taste of the Tanagra
                    and most of the Asia Minor figures. Recent excavations in the tombs of Corinth
                    have produced a large number of fine terracottas, ranging in date over a very
                    long period. Another and artistically very perfect class of figures is being dug
                    up from among the tombs of Tarentum. Some of these belong to the finest period
                    of Greek art, probably about 400 B.c., and others are even earlier. Many are not
                    statuettes, but merely small busts of heroic style, and of the highest
                    sculpturesque beauty. They are certainly not portraits, and do not appear to
                    represent deities. It has been suggested that they are idealized representations
                    of ancestors, whose commemoration, in some places, formed an important cult; but
                    their real meaning must for the present remain uncertain. Many thousand votive
                    figures and reliefs in clay have been found within the <hi rend="italic"
                    >temeni</hi> of the temples of the Chthonian deities at Tarentum and elsewhere.
                    It seems to have been customary for the priests periodically to clear out of the
                    temples the broken or too numerous offerings which were then buried within the
                    enclosure; whole series arranged chronologically in groups have been discovered
                    buried in separate holes.</p>
                <p>In addition to statuettes and reliefs, terra-cotta was used by the Greeks for
                    various minor ornamental purposes. Delicately moulded necklaces and pendants for
                    ears were stamped out in clay and then thickly covered with gold leaf; this
                    produced a very rich effect at a small cost; many fine examples are preserved in
                    the Louvre. Children’s toys, such as miniature horses and chariots, and dolls
                    with movable limbs of terra-cotta fastened with wooden pegs, occur in many
                    tombs.</p>
                <p>On a larger scale terra-cotta was adapted by the Greeks to important
                    architectural ornamentation. Many fine examples have been found at Olympia and
                    among the ruined temples of Selinus. In some cases the main cornices of the
                    building were simply blocked out square in stone, and then covered with moulded
                    plaques of terracotta, carefully formed to fit on and round the angles of the
                    block. The large cymatium which forms the upper member of the cornice is curved
                    upwards, so as to prevent the rain water from dripping all along the edge; and
                    at intervals it is pierced by ornamental clay pipes, which project like a
                    mediaeval gargoyle. In some examples from Selinus the cymatium is pierced with a
                    beautiful open pattern of lotus leaf (see fig. 5). The greatest care was taken
                    in fitting these applied mouldings where each plaque joined the next, and
                    especially in making them fit closely on to the stone blocks, in which rebates
                    were cut to receive each plaque. The whole surface of the terra-cotta is covered
                    with elaborate painted ornaments of great beauty, in ochre colours applied on a
                    white ground, as in the case of the statuettes. These beautiful temple
                    decorations are well illustrated by Dörpfeld and others in <hi rend="italic">Die
                    Verwendung von Terra-cotten,</hi> Berlin, 1881. Though no complete examples of
                    terra-cotta statuary now exist, it is certain that the Greeks produced it on a
                    large scale and of the highest class of workmanship. Pliny (ZZ.W., XXXV. 36)
                    mentions that certain statues of Hercules Musagetes and the Nine Muses were
                    “opera figlina,” executed by the painter Zeuxis. These were brought from Athens
                    by M. Fulvius Nobilior, and placed in the temple of Hercules Musagetes, which
                    adjoined the Porticus Octaviae in the Campus Martius of Rome. Other and earlier
                    examples of clay statues are mentioned by Pausanias.</p>
                <p>Among the Etruscans the use of clay for important sculpture was very
                    frequent,—painted terra-cotta or bronze almost excluding marble and stone. An
                    important example was the clay quadriga on the pediment of the temple of
                    Capitoline Jupiter, which, according to one legend, was brought from Veii by
                    Tarquinius Superbus. This existed till the destruction of the temple by fire in
                    83 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> and was considered one of the seven precious
                    relics on -which the safety of the Roman state depended. The great statue of
                    Jupiter in the central cella of this triple temple was also of terra-cotta, and
                    was said to be the work of an Etruscan sculptor from Fregenae. Vitruvius
                    mentions “signa fictilia” as being specially Etruscan. Many other statues in the
                    early temples of Rome were made of the same material. Among the existing
                    specimens of Etruscan terra-cotta the chief are large sarcophagi, with recumbent
                    portrait effigies of the deceased on the top, the whole being of clay, decorated
                    with painting. Fine examples exist in the Louvre and the British Museum; a good
                    specimen from the latter collection is figured in vol. viii., plate VIII. The
                    Museo Gregoriano in the Vatican possesses some very beautiful friezes of a later
                    date—about the 4th century B.c.—when native Etruscan art had been replaced by
                    that of Greece. These friezes are very rich and elaborate, with heads and scroll
                    foliage in very salient relief. Some of them have at intervals cleverly moulded
                    heads of satyrs, painted a brilliant crimson.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The use of this strongly glowing red is
                    almost peculiar to Hellenic Italy; the other colours used there were much the
                    same as those of Greece itself. The same magnificent crimson often occurs on
                    oenoclioae, moulded into the form of satyrs’ heads, which are found in the tombs
                    of Masma Graecia.</p></note></p>
                <p>Another very elaborate application of terra-cotta is shown in the numerous large
                    asci, covered with statuettes, which are found in the tombs of Canosa
                    (Canusium), Cales, and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n207/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0207-0194"/> many parts of Magna Graecia. The statuettes are
                    somewhat similar in style and colouring to the Tanagra figures, and date from
                    about the same period (4th century B.c.), but are not equal to them as works of
                    art; they are also usually crowded together in a somewhat awkward manner.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A very large ascus from
                    Canosa in the British Museum is decorated with no less than five statuettes of
                    women and Victories, two large masks of Medusa, and six projecting figures of
                    horses.</p></note> The British Museum is specially rich in these elaborate
                    terra-cottas; few of the colours used appear to be true ceramic pigments.</p>
                <p>As in other branches of art, the Romans closely copied the Greeks in their wide
                    application of terra-cotta for statues, reliefs, and architectural ornaments. A
                    large number of beautiful Graeco-Roman reliefs exist, many having designs
                    evidently copied from earlier Greek sculpture. Berlin, the Louvre, the British
                    Museum, and many places in Italy possess fine collections. Friezes with
                    beautiful reliefs 12 to 18 inches deep often occur, little inferior in execution
                    to the earlier Greek work. Many subjects of great interest are represented: a
                    very fine plaque in the Louvre has the scene of Orestes taking refuge at the
                    sacred omphalos at Delphi, which is represented as a conical stone about 3 feet
                    high, hung round with ornamental festoons made of gold.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Compare a similar representation of the
                    omphalos on a Greek vase illustrated by Jahn, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vasenbilder,</hi> Hamburg, 1839.</p></note> These terra-cottas belong to the
                    early period of the empire; in the 2d century <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>
                    they became much coarser and less Greek in style, like all the sculpture of that
                    time. A plaque in the Louvre, which represents a chariot-race in the circus,
                    bears its maker’s stamp, L.S.ER. At the end of the first and in the early part
                    of the 2d century A.D. the use of terra-cotta for architectural adornment was
                    carried to a high point of perfection in Rome. Many buildings of this period
                    have the most elaborate decoration moulded in clay and fitted together with
                    wonderful neatness. Not only enriched cornices and friezes were made of
                    terra-cotta, but even Corinthian columns with their elaborate acanthus capitals.
                    In all cases the whole surface appears to have been covered with a thin coating
                    of “opus albarium” and then decorated with colours and even gold. The best
                    existing examples in Rome are the Amphitheatrum Castrense, many tombs on the Via
                    Latina, and the barracks of the VIIth cohort of the guards <hi rend="italic"
                    >(vigiles)</hi> in the Trastevere. But few examples exist of the large Roman
                    terra-cotta sculpture; the best are some seated female figures from tombs, small
                    life-size, in the Capitoline museum,—works of great beauty and very skilfully
                    fired without cracks or warping. The British Museum also contains fine specimens
                    of terra-cotta sculpture on a large scale, especially the torso of a nude male
                    figure (Hercules), some terminal figures of Bacchus, and a beautiful statue of
                    Urania (see fig. 6).</p>
                <p>In the 14th and more especially in the 15th century terra-cotta was adapted in
                    various parts of Europe to the most magnificent and elaborate architectural
                    purposes. In Germany the mark of Brandenburg is specially rich in terra-cotta
                    work.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                    >See Adler,</hi> Mittelalterliche Backstein-Bauwerke, <hi rend="italic">Berlin,
                    1862.</hi></p></note> The church of St Catherine in the town of Brandenburg is
                    decorated in the most lavish way with delicate tracery and elaborate
                    string-courses and cornices, enriched with foliage, all modelled in clay; the
                    town-hall is another instance of the same use of terra-cotta. At Tangermünde,
                    the church of St Stephen and other buildings of the beginning of the 15th
                    century are wonderful examples of this method of decoration; the north door of
                    St Stephen’s especially is a masterpiece of rich and effective moulding. In
                    northern Italy this use of terra-cotta was carried to an equally high point of
                    perfection.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">See Gruner,</hi> Terra-cotta Architecture ofN. Italy, <hi
                    rend="italic">London, 1867.</hi></p></note> The western façade of the cathedral
                    of Monza is a work of the most wonderful richness and minute elaboration, wholly
                    executed in clay, in the latter part of the 14th century. The cathedral of
                    Crema, the communal buildings of Piacenza, and S. Maria delle Grazie in Milan
                    are striking examples of the extreme splendour of effect that can be obtained by
                    terra-cotta work. The Certosa near Pavia has a most gorgeous specimen of the
                    early part of the 16th century; the two cloisters are especially magnificent.
                    Pavia itself is very rich in terra-cotta decoration, especially the ducal palace
                    and the churches of S. Francesco and S. Maria del Carmine. Some delicate work
                    exists among the mediaeval buildings of Rome, dating from the 14th and 16 th
                    century, as, for example, the rich cornices on the south aisle of S. Maria in
                    Ara Coeli, c. 1300; the front of S. Cosimato in Trastevere, built <hi
                    rend="italic">c.</hi> 1490; and a once very magnificent house, near the Via di
                    Tordinone, which dates from the 14th century. The most important application of
                    terra-cotta in mediaeval Italy was to statuary—reliefs, busts, and even groups
                    of many life-sized figures—during the 15th and 16th centuries. Much of the
                    Florentine terra-cotta sculpture of the 15th century is among the most beautiful
                    plastic work the world has ever seen, especially that by Jacopo della Quercia,
                    Donatello, and the sculptors of the next generation.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The South Kensington Museum possesses a very
                    fine collection of Florentine terra-cottas of the best period.</p></note> For
                    life, spirit, and realistic truth, combined with sculpturesque breadth, these
                    pieces are masterpieces of invention and manipulation. The portrait busts are
                    perfect models of iconic sculpture (see fig. 7). In some respects the use of
                    burnt clay for sculpture has great advantages over that of marble: the soft clay
                    is easily and rapidly moulded into form while the sculptor’s thought is fresh in
                    his mind, and thus terra-cottas often possess a spirit and vigour w hich can
                    hardly be reproduced in the laboriously finished marble. These <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n208/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0208-0195"/> qualities are specially remarkable in the best
                    works of the Della Robbia family (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Robbia).</hi> In the
                    16th century a more realistic style was introduced, and this was heightened by
                    the custom of painting the figures in oil colours. Many very clever groups of
                    this class were produced by Ambrogio Foppa (Caradosso) for S. Satiro at Milan
                    and by Guido Mazzoni and Begarelli (1479-1565) for churches in Modena. These
                    terra-cotta sculptures are unpleasing in colour and far too pictorial in style;
                    but those of Begarelli were enthusiastically admired by Michelangelo.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Vasari, ed. Le Monnier,
                    xii. 281.</p></note> Much fine terra-cotta work was produced in France during
                    the 16th century, partly under Italian influence,—many sculptors from northern
                    and central Italy having settled in France, especially under the patronage of
                    Francis I. In the same century a similar Italian influence prevailed largely
                    throughout Spain, and very clever works were produced there, remarkable for
                    their vivid realism and deceptive pictorial style. In England the elaborate use
                    of terra-cotta did not come into vogue till the early part of the 16th century,
                    and then only in certain counties. Essex possesses the finest examples, such as
                    those of the manor house of Layer Marney, built in the reign of Henry VIII. The
                    richly moulded windows and battlements of this house are very un-English in
                    style, and it seems probable that all the terra-cotta decorations were made in
                    Holland or Flanders. A richly decorated terra-cotta tomb with recumbent effigy
                    exists in the church of Layer Marney; and in the collegiate church of Wymondham
                    in Norfolk there are very large and elaborate sedilia with lofty canopied
                    niches, all of clay, which appear to be of the same date and fabrique as the
                    Essex examples. Most of the terracotta sculpture in England, such as that by
                    Torrigiano, of which fragments exist in Westminster Abbey, the colossal heads of
                    the Caesars at Hampton Court, and the recumbent effigy in the Chapel of the
                    Rolls,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This interesting
                    building is now threatened with destruction.</p></note> were the work of Italian
                    sculptors, mostly from Florence, who were invited to England in the reigns of
                    Henry VII. and Henry VIII.</p>
                <p>Of late years terra-cotta for architectural purposes has been employed for some
                    very important buildings in London, such as the natural history museum at South
                    Kensington, the Albert Hall, and the front of the other museum in the Exhibition
                    Road. The durability of well-fired clay, its dense texture, pleasant colour, and
                    smooth surface make it specially suitable to an atmosphere laden with acids and
                    soot as is that of London. The surface resists decomposition, and affords little
                    hold to the minute particles of carbon. The great improvements which have been
                    made in the manufacture of terra-cotta will probably lead to its more extensive
                    use. The great difficulty is to retain the sharpness of impression given by the
                    mould, and above all to avoid the uneven shrinkage and warping which is so
                    liable to take place when it is fired in large pieces. Any want of truth in the
                    lines of a long cornice becomes painfully apparent, and each moulded block of a
                    door or window-jamb must fit accurately on to the next one, or else the line of
                    moulding becomes broken and irregular. Terracotta is now made of many different
                    colours, a rich red and a warm ochre or cream colour being the most pleasant to
                    the eye. In order to avoid defects it is necessary that the clay should contain
                    a large proportion of powdered silica, and that the whole mass should be
                    thoroughly homogeneous. The method by which these ends are secured is much the
                    same as that employed in the making of pottery (see vol. xix. p. 642 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.).</hi></p>
                <p>The most important public collections are in the Louvre, the British Museum, the
                    museums of Berlin and Athens, and a few fine specimens exist in the South
                    Kensington Museum. The splendid Sabouroff collection is now in the Hermitage
                    Palace at St Peters burg. Many museums in Italy—such as those at Florence,
                    Perugia, Capua, Rome, and other places—contain many examples from Etruria and
                    Magna Graecia. A large number of the finest of the Tanagra figures and the like
                    are in private hands; some are illustrated in the works mentioned in the
                    following list; that of Prince Liechtenstein at Vienna is one of the
                    finest.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Very clever
                    forgeries of terra-cotta are being manufactured, and in many cases real
                    specimens have genuine heads which do not belong to them. The colouring has
                    frequently been touched up and falsified while in the dealers’ hands. Even the
                    celebrated Campana collection contained many clever forgeries of terra-cotta
                    reliefs.</p></note><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> Léon Heuzey, “Recherches
                    sur les figurines de femmes voilées,” in <hi rend="italic">Mon. assoc, des
                    études grecques,</hi> Paris, 1874; Id., “Rech, sur un groupe de Praxitèle, . . .
                    en terre cuite,” in <hi rend="italic">Gaz. des B.-Arts,</hi> September 1875;
                    Id., “Rech, sur les terres cuites grecques,” in <hi rend="italic">Mon. assoc,
                    des étud. grec.,</hi> 1876; Id., <hi rend="italic">Les origines des terres
                    cuites,</hi> Paris, 1882; Id., <hi rend="italic">Catalogue des figurines
                    antiques du Louvre,</hi> Paris, 1882-83; Id., “Papposilène et le dieu Bes," in
                    <hi rend="italic">Bull. Cor. Hell.,</hi> 1884, pp. 161-167; Fröhner, <hi
                    rend="italic">Les terres cuites d'Asie-Mineure,</hi> Paris, 1879-81; Id., <hi
                    rend="italic">Cat. de la Coll. Lecuyer,</hi> Paris, 1883, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cat. de la Coll. Barre,</hi> Paris, 1878; Kekulé, <hi rend="italic">Griechische
                    Thonfiguren aus Tanagra,</hi> Berlin, 1878; Id., <hi rend="italic">Griechische
                    Terracotten vom Berliner Museum,</hi> Berlin, 1878; Id., <hi rend="italic">Die
                    antiken Terracotten von Pompeii,</hi> Stuttgart, 1880; Rayet, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Monuments de l'art antique,</hi> Paris, 1884, vol. ii. pp. 74-90; Id., “Sur une
                    plaque estampée,” in <hi rend="italic">Bull. Cor. Hell.,</hi> 1879, pp. 329-333;
                    Id., <hi rend="italic">Cat. de la Coll. Rayet,</hi> 1880; Id., “Les figurines de
                    Tanagra (Louvre),” in <hi rend="italic">Gaz. des B.·Arts,</hi> 1875; Id., “L’art
                    grec au Trocadéro,” in <hi rend="italic">Gaz. des B.-Arts,</hi> 1878;
                    Furtwaengler, <hi rend="italic">La Coll. Sabouroff,</hi> Paris, 1882-85,
                    splendidly illustrated in colours; Martha, <hi rend="italic">Cat. des figurines
                    du musée d'Athènes,</hi> 1880; Id., “Figurines corinthiennes en terre cuite,” in
                    <hi rend="italic">Bull. Cor. Hell.,</hi> 1879, pp. 29-42; Id., “Figurines de
                    Tanagra," <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 1880, pp. 71-75; Pottier, “Terres cuites
                    Chypriotes,” <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 1879, pp. 86-94; Pottier and Reinach,
                    “Fouilles de Myrina,” <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> various articles in vols,
                    for 1882-83; Paul Girard, “Nécropoles de la Grèce du Nord,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >ibid.,</hi> 1879, pp. 211-221; Max. Collignon, “Plaque estampée de Santorin,”
                    <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 1881, pp. 436-438; Cesnola, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cyprus,</hi> London, 1877; Schliemann, <hi rend="italic">Troy, Mycenae,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Tiryns;</hi> E. Curtius, <hi rend="italic">Giebelgruppen
                    aus Tanagra,</hi> Berlin, 1878; Delauney, “Terres cuites de Tanagra,” in <hi
                    rend="italic">Revue de France,</hi> May and June 1878. An account of the first
                    discovery of the Tanagra figures is given by Otto Lüders in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bull. Inst. Cor. Arch.,</hi> 1874, p. 120; see also various articles in <hi
                    rend="italic">Gaz. Archéol., Archäol. Zeitung,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Mon.
                    Inst. Arch. Rom.</hi> (especially vol. vi.). For the earlier known terra-cottas,
                    see Panofka, <hi rend="italic">Terracotten des k. Museums zu Berlin,</hi> 1842;
                    Combe, <hi rend="italic">Terra-cottas in the British Museum,</hi> London, 1810;
                    and Gerhard, Λfonwmenii <hi rend="italic">figulini di Sicilia,</hi> Berlin,
                    1835. Other works have been already referred to. Clever but not quite
                    satisfactory copies of the finest Tanagra and other figures are now made in
                    Berlin and vienna; they cost from twenty to thirty shillings each. (J. H.
                    Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
