<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0598-0577-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TRITON (9th edition, volume 23, page 577)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830184">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882872">Crests</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176048">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142046">Tail</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1157225">Tritone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103754">Salamandridae</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62661">Amphibia</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x333">Crests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n598/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TRITON</label>. The genus <hi rend="italic">Triton</hi> was
                    constituted by Laurenti, in his <hi rend="italic">Synopsis Reptilium,</hi> and
                    the name was adopted by nearly all writers on <hi rend="italic">Amphibia.</hi>
                    In <hi rend="italic">Brit. Mus. Cat.: Batrachia Gradientia,</hi> by G. A.
                    Boulenger, the genus is expanded and called by the name <hi rend="italic"
                    >Molge,</hi> which was used by Merrem in his <hi rend="italic">Tentamen Syst.
                    Amphibia,</hi> 1820. The genus belongs to the division <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mecodonta</hi> of the family <hi rend="italic">Salamandrida</hi> in Strauch’s
                    classification (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Amphibia,</hi> vol. i. p. 771). The
                    definition of <hi rend="italic">Molge</hi> given by Boulenger, which closely
                    agrees with that of Triton adopted by Strauch, is as follows. Tongue free along
                    the sides, adherent or somewhat free posteriorly. Palatine teeth in two straight
                    or slightly curved series. Fronto-squamosal arch present (except in <hi
                    rend="italic">M. cristatus),</hi> ligamentous or bony. Toes five. Tail
                    compressed. In Bell’s <hi rend="italic">British Reptiles,</hi> 2d ed., 1849,
                    four species were described as occurring in Britain. According to Boulenger,
                    there are only three British species, <hi rend="italic">Molge cristata,</hi>
                    Boul. (Laurenti), <hi rend="italic">M. vulgaris,</hi> Boul. (Linn.), and <hi
                    rend="italic">M. palmata,</hi> Boul. (Schneider). We give a short account of
                    these under the names <hi rend="italic">Triton cristatus, T. vulgaris,</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">T. palmatus</hi> respectively.</p>
                <p>The name <hi rend="italic">Triton cristatus</hi> for the first species has been
                    used by a great number of authoritative writers on <hi rend="italic"
                    >Amphibia,</hi> including Laurenti, Tschudi, Bonaparte, Duméril and Bibron, and
                    Strauch, and also by Bell and Fleming among students of British fauna.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The species of Triton are
                    called in English efts, evets, or newts</p></note> The diagnosis of <hi
                    rend="italic">T. cristatus</hi> is as follows :—The males have a dorsal crest
                    which is toothed; the fronto-squamosal arch is absent; the colour of the ventral
                    surface is orange with black spots. This species is commonly known as the great
                    water-newt. The average length of the adult is 6 inches. The colours are most
                    brilliant in the male, and more developed in the breeding season—spring and
                    summer—than in winter. The back is blackish or yellowish brown, with round black
                    spots; the sides of the tail are white. The dorsal crest of the male is
                    separated entirely from the tail crest, and both disappear in winter. The skin
                    is covered with warty tubercles. There are no parotids; but glandular pores are
                    present over the eyes and in a longitudinal series along each side. The species
                    is pretty common in ponds and ditches in most parts of Britain, but more
                    abundant in the south than in the north; in the neighbourhood of London it is
                    found in great numbers. Its food consists of aquatic insects and other small
                    animals; in the spring it devours the young tadpoles of the frog with avidity,
                    and occasionally it feeds on the smaller species, <hi rend="italic">T.
                    vulgaris.</hi> In winter it hibernates, either quitting the water and hiding
                    under stones or remaining torpid at the bottom of the water. It breeds chiefly
                    in May and June. As in all <hi rend="italic">Salamandrida,</hi> a true
                    copulation takes place and the fertilization of the ova is internal. The female
                    deposits each egg separately in the fold of a leaf, which she bends by means of
                    her hind feet; the adhesive slime surrounding the vitellus keeps the leaf
                    folded. The tadpole when first hatched is much more fish-like in form than that
                    of the frog, the body diminishing in thickness gradually to the end of the tail.
                    A continuous median fin runs along the back from the head, round the end of the
                    tail, along the ventral median line, to the region of the gills, thus extending,
                    as in many fish larvae, in front of the anus. The larva possesses three pairs of
                    branched external gills, and in front of these a pair of processes by which it
                    can adhere to fixed objects in the water. <hi rend="italic">T. cristatus</hi> is
                    abundant throughout Europe, ranging from Sweden and Russia southwards to Greece,
                    and from Britain to the Caucasus.</p>
                <p>The diagnosis of <hi rend="italic">T. vulgaris,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lissotriton punctatus</hi> of Bell, is :—Males with a dorsal crest continuous
                    with the caudal, and festooned; belly not brilliantly coloured; back spotted.
                    This species, often called the common or small newt, has a smooth skin, no
                    glandular pores on the sides, but two patches on the head. It is as abundant in
                    Britain as the former, or more so, but differs somewhat in habits, in autumn and
                    winter being almost entirely terrestrial, and only living in water during the
                    breeding season. Like the former species it is carnivorous. It is found in most
                    parts of Britain, and throughout Europe, except in the south of France, Spain,
                    and Portugal; it also extends into temperate Asia.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">T. palmatus</hi> Tschudi (Schneider), the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lissotriton palmipes</hi> of Bell, is thus distinguished :—Male with dorsal
                    crest, which is low with an even margin and continuous with the caudal;
                    fronto-squamosal arch long; toes in male webbed. Other less distinctive features
                    are that the back is flattened, with a raised line on each side, and the tail in
                    the male truncate, terminating in a short slender filament. This species is not
                    so common in Britain as the other two; it is widely distributed throughout
                    Europe. It was first discovered in Britain in 1843.</p>
                <p>Boulenger recognizes nineteen species of <hi rend="italic">Molge,</hi> of which
                    nine besides those found in Britain are European. Only two species occur in
                    America. Strauch gives twenty species.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
