<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0474-0455-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TORTOISE (9th edition, volume 23, page 455)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115719">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:863820">Claws</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:835916">Bone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:835991">Bones</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49w0915x">Hydromedusae</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k13n">Chelonia</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d52v">Bones</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fx73z68">Bone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n474/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TORTOISE</label>. Of the three names generally used for this
                    order of reptiles, viz., Tortoise, Turtle, and Terrapin, the first is derived
                    from the old French word <hi rend="italic">tortis,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> twisted, and was probably applied first to the common European
                    species on account of its curiously bent forelegs. Turtle is believed to be a
                    corruption of the same word, but the origin of the name terrapin is unknown:
                    since the time of the navigators of the 16th century it has been in general use
                    for freshwater species of the tropics, and especially for those of the New
                    World. The name tortoise is now generally applied to the terrestrial members of
                    this group of animals, and that of turtle to those which live in the sea or pass
                    a great part of their existence in fresh water.</p>
                <p>Tortoises and turtles constitute one of the orders of Reptiles, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Chelonia.</hi> They are characterized by having the trunk of the
                    body incased in a more or less ossified carapace, which consists of a dorsal
                    more or less convex portion, and of a flat ventral one, the so-called plastron.
                    These portions are generally more or less firmly united on the side, but leave a
                    wide opening in front through which the head and neck and the fore-limbs
                    protrude, and one behind for the tail and hind-limbs. The dorsal carapace is
                    (with the exception of <hi rend="italic">Sphargis)</hi> formed by the dorsal
                    vertebrae, by the ribs which are so much expanded as to form sutures with each
                    other, and by a number of lateral dermal ossifications (marginals). The plastron
                    consists of from eight to eleven more or less dilated dermal bones, the sternal
                    elements of higher <hi rend="italic">Vertebrata</hi> being absent. This osseous
                    case or shell receives in its interior the organs of the chest and abdomen, the
                    humeral and pelvic bones, and the muscles for the humerus and femur. In many
                    species, especially those of the family <hi rend="italic">Testudinidae,</hi> or
                    tortoises proper, the neck and head and the limbs can be withdrawn within the
                    shell, the cervical and the proximal caudal vertebrae retaining their mobility.
                    In the majority of Chelonians the osseous shell is covered with a hard
                    epidermoid coat, which is divided into large symmetrical plates (commonly called
                    “tortoise-shell” in those species from which the article of commerce is
                    obtained), which can be detached from the underlying bones. These epidermoid
                    plates do not correspond in arrangement or extent with the bones of the
                    carapace; they vary considerably in form, and are therefore generally noticed in
                    the descriptions of species. Their arrangement and terminology may be learned
                    from the accompanying illustrations (figs. 1, 2).</p>
                <p>The integuments of the head, neck, tail, and limbs are either soft and smooth or
                    tubercular or scaly, the tubercles and scales having frequently an osseous
                    nucleus.</p>
                <p>Other parts also of the skeleton show remarkable peculiarities, so that the
                    sometimes very fragmentary remains of Chelonians can almost always be recognized
                    as such. All the bones of the skull are suturally united, with the exception of
                    the mandible and hyoid bone; the dentary portion of the mandible consists of one
                    bone only. The pectoral arch is composed of the scapula, with which the
                    precoracoid is united, and the coracoid. Clavicles (epi-plastra) are represented
                    by the anterior elements of the plastron. Two pairs of limbs are invariably
                    present.</p>
                <p>All Chelonians possess a tail, which is generally short, but sometimes elongate,
                    and always provided with strong muscles at the base. No Chelonian possesses
                    teeth; but their jaws are provided with horny sheaths, with hard, and sharp
                    edges, forming a beak like that of a parrot.</p>
                <p>The number of Chelonians known at present may be estimated at about 220, the
                    freshwater species being far the most numerous, and abundant in well-watered
                    districts of the tropical and subtropical zones. Their number and variety
                    decrease beyond the tropics, and in the north they disappear entirely about the
                    50th parallel in the western and about the 56th in the eastern hemisphere,
                    whilst in the southern hemisphere the terrestrial forms seem to advance to 36
                    <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi> S. lat. only. The marine turtles, which are
                    spread over the whole of the equatorial and subtropical seas, sometimes stray
                    beyond those limits. As in other <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n475/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0475-0456"/> orders of Reptiles, the most specialized and the
                    largest forms are restricted to the tropics (with the exception of <hi
                    rend="italic">Macroclemmys);</hi> but, unlike lizards or snakes, Chelonians <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Figs.</hi> 1. 2.—Shell of <hi rend="italic">Testudo
                    pardalis</hi> to show the divisions of the integument, which are marked by
                    entire lines, and of the osseous carapace, these being marked by dotted lines.
                    Fig. 1, Upper or dorsal aspect. Fig. 2, Lower or ventral aspect.</p>
                <p>Dermal Scutes:— <hi rend="italic">eο,</hi> costals; v, vertebrals; <hi
                    rend="italic">m,</hi> marginals; <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> gulars; <hi
                    rend="italic">pg,</hi> post-gulars; <hi rend="italic">p,</hi> pectorals; <hi
                    rend="italic">ab,</hi> abdominals; <hi rend="italic">pa,</hi> praeanals; <hi
                    rend="italic">an,</hi> anais.</p>
                <p>Bones of the Carapace :— <hi rend="italic">co',</hi> costals; <hi rend="italic"
                    >ne,</hi> nenrals; <hi rend="italic">nu,</hi> nuchal; <hi rend="italic">py,</hi>
                    pygal; <hi rend="italic">m</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">,</hi> marginals; <hi
                    rend="italic">ent,</hi> entoplastron, <hi rend="italic">ep,</hi> epiplastron;
                    <hi rend="italic">hyo,</hi> hyoplastron; <hi rend="italic">hyp,</hi>
                    hypoplastron; <hi rend="italic">xyp,</hi> xyphiplastron.</p>
                <p>are unable to exist in sterile districts or at great altitudes. Chelonians are
                    strictly animals of plains, or at least of low country.</p>
                <p>Chelonians show a great divergence in their mode of life,—some living constantly
                    on land, others having partly terrestrial partly aquatic habits, others again
                    rarely leaving the water or the sea. The first-mentioned, the land tortoises
                    proper, have short club-shaped feet with blunt claws, and a very convex, heavy,
                    completely ossified shell. In the freshwater forms the joints of the limb bones
                    are much more mobile, the digits distinct, armed with sharp claws, and united by
                    a membrane or web; their shell is less convex, and is flattened, and more or
                    less extensive areas may remain cartilaginous to lessen its specific gravity. As
                    a rule, the degree of development of the interdigital web and of convexity of
                    the shell indicates the prevalence of aquatic or terrestrial habits of a species
                    of terrapin. Finally, the marine turtles have paddle-shaped limbs resembling
                    those of Cetaceans.</p>
                <p>Land tortoises are sufficiently protected by their carapace, and therefore have
                    no need of any special modification of structure by means of which their
                    appearance would be assimilated to the surroundings, and thus give them
                    additional security from their enemies. These, however, are but few in number:
                    the large cats of South America are said to be able to tear them out of the
                    shell with their claws; and the ancient tale of Aeschylus having been killed by
                    a tortoise carried aloft by an eagle and dropped on the head of the unfortunate
                    poet seems to be founded on the fact that tortoises are a favourite prey of the
                    Lämmergeyer <hi rend="italic">(Cypaetus),</hi> which has the habit of dropping
                    them from a height on rocks in order to break the shell. On the other hand,
                    among the carnivorous terrapins and freshwater turtles instances of protective
                    resemblance are not scarce, and may even attain to a high degree of
                    specialization, as in <hi rend="italic">Chelys</hi>; their shells offer them
                    less protection, and their enemies (crocodiles and alligators) are more
                    numerous; they also require this special provision to enable them to approach or
                    seize their prey with greater ease. The colours of land tortoises are generally
                    plain or in simple patterns, whilst those of many terrapins are singularly
                    varied, bright, and beautiful.</p>
                <p>Chelonians are diurnal animals; only a few are active during the night,
                    habitually or on special occasions, as, for instance, during oviposition. Land
                    tortoises are slow in all their movements, but all kinds living in water can
                    execute extremely rapid motions, either to seize their prey or to escape from
                    danger. All Chelonians are stationary, residing throughout the year in the same
                    locality, with the exception of the marine turtles, which periodically migrate
                    to their breeding-stations. Species inhabiting temperate regions hibernate.</p>
                <p>Chelonians possess great tenacity oflife, surviving injuries to which other
                    Reptiles would succumb in a short time. The heart of a decapitated tortoise
                    continues to beat for many hours after every drop of blood has been drained from
                    the body, and the muscles of the trunk and head show signs of reflex action
                    twenty-four hours after the severance of the spinal cord. The longevity of
                    tortoises is likewise a well-known fact, to which reference will again be
                    made.</p>
                <p>Land tortoises, a few terrapins, and some of the marine turtles are herbivorous,
                    the others carnivorous, their prey consisting chiefly of fish, frogs, and other
                    small aquatic animals.</p>
                <p>All Chelonians are oviparous, and the eggs are generally covered with a hard
                    shell.</p>
                <p>In the system<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The more
                    important works on this order of Reptiles have been enumerated in the article
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Reptiles,</hi> vol. xx. p. 440.</p></note> proposed by
                    Duméril and Bibron, and afterwards modified by Gray and Strauch, the Chelonians
                    are arranged according to their mode of life, and divided into terrestrial,
                    paludine, fluviatile, and marine forms. However natural such an arrangement may
                    appear at first, a more careful examination proves it to be (as all arrangements
                    based solely upon the mode of life) at variance with the structural affinities,
                    whether the recent forms alone be considered or the fossil as well. The division
                    of the bulk of the order into <hi rend="italic">Cτyptodira</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Pleurodira,</hi> as suggested by Agassiz, Cope, and Rütimeyer, was
                    a decided progress, as is also the elimination of the suborders <hi
                    rend="italic">Atheca</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tτionychoidea</hi> recently
                    proposed by Cope and Baur.</p>
                <p>The order of Chelonians may then be divided into the following suborders and
                    families:<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Only the more
                    important and best known of the extinct genera are admitted into this
                    synopsis.</p></note> —</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Suborder</hi> I. ATHECAe.</p>
                <p>Vertebras and ribs free, separated from a bony exoskeleton. Family 1. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Sphargidae.</hi></p>
                <p>Limbs paddle-shaped, clawless; phalanges without condyles. Plastron reduced to an
                    annular series of eight small bones. Exoskeleton consisting of numerous small
                    bony plates arranged likö mosaic. Pelagic.</p>
                <p>Genus: <hi rend="italic">Dermαtοchelys (Sphargis).</hi></p>
                <p>Fossil genera: <hi rend="italic">Psephοphοrus</hi> (Pliocene), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Protosphargis</hi> (Cretaceous), <hi rend="italic">Protostega</hi>
                    (Cretaceous), <hi rend="italic">Psephoderma</hi>? (Triassic).</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n476/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0476-0457"/>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Suborder</hi> II. TESTUDINATA.</p>
                <p>Dorsal vertebrae and ribs immovably united and expanded into bony plates forming
                    a carapace, which is bordered by a complete series of marginal bones. Epiplastra
                    (clavicles) in contact with hyoplastra; entoplastron (interclavicle), if
                    present, oval, rhomboidal, or T-shaped. Sacral and caudal ribs articulating with
                    the centrum and the neural arch. Digits with not more than three phalanges.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Series</hi> A. CRYPTODIRA.</p>
                <p>Neck retractile by a sigmoid curve in a vertical plane. Pelvis not anchylosed to
                    the carapace and plastron. Rarely one or two epidermic scutes (intergular) in
                    addition to the normal six pairs.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Group</hi> A. Digitata.</p>
                <p>Digits short or moderately elongate; phalanges with condyles; claws four or five.
                    Neck completely retractile.</p>
                <p>Family 1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Testudinidae.</hi></p>
                <p>Plastral bones nine. Nuchal bone without costiform processes. Carapace with
                    epidermic scutes. Caudal vertebrae procoelous. Tropical and temperate zones,
                    with the exception of Australia.</p>
                <p>Recent genera: <hi rend="italic">Dermatemys, Batagιιr, Clemmys, Pangslιura,
                    Geoemyda, Cycle-mys, Emys, Cisludo, Manouria,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Testudo,</hi><hi rend="italic">IIomopus, Cinyxis, Pyxis.</hi></p>
                <p>Fossil genera: <hi rend="italic">Euryslernum</hi> (Jurassic), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chilracephalus</hi> (Cretaceous), <hi rend="italic">A&lt;locus</hi>
                    (Cretaceous), <hi rend="italic">Palxochelys</hi> (Miocene), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Plychog&lt;ρster</hi> (Miocene), <hi rend="italic">Colossochelys</hi>
                    (Pliocene).</p>
                <p>Family 2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Platysternidae.</hi></p>
                <p>Plastral bones nine. Nuchal bone without costiform processes. Carapace with
                    epidermic scutes. Caudal vertebrae mostly opistho-caelous. Indian region.</p>
                <p>Genus: <hi rend="italic">Platysternym.</hi></p>
                <p>Family 3. <hi rend="smallcaps">Baenidae.</hi></p>
                <p>Plastral bones eleven, mesoplastτa being present. Nuchal bone without costiform
                    processes. Carapace with epidermic scutes. Caudal vertebrae opisthocaelous.</p>
                <p>Fossil genera: <hi rend="italic">Platychelys</hi> (Jurassic); <hi rend="italic"
                    >Baena</hi> (Eoeene).</p>
                <p>Family <hi rend="italic">4.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Chelydridae.</hi></p>
                <p>Plastral bones nine. Nuchal bone with long costiform processes, extending below
                    the marginals. Carapace with epidermic scutes. Caudal vertebrae mostly
                    opisthocaelous. Northern and tropical American regions.</p>
                <p>Recent genera: <hi rend="italic">Chelydra, Macroclemmys.</hi></p>
                <p>Fossil genus: <hi rend="italic">Trelosternum</hi> (Cretaceous).</p>
                <p>Family 5. <hi rend="smallcaps">Staurotypidae</hi> (Boulenger).</p>
                <p>Plastral bones nine. Nuchal bone with short costiform processes, extending below
                    the marginals. Carapace with epidermic scutes. Caudal vertebrae procoelous.
                    Central-American district.</p>
                <p>Genera: <hi rend="italic">Staurotypus, Claudius.</hi></p>
                <p>Family 6. <hi rend="smallcaps">Cinosternidae.</hi></p>
                <p>Plastral bones eight, the entoplastron being absent. Nuchal bone with short
                    costiform processes, extending below the marginals. Carapace with epidermic
                    scutes. Caudal vertebrae procoelous. Northern and tropical American regions.</p>
                <p>Gepera: <hi rend="italic">Aromochelys, Cinoslemunt.</hi></p>
                <p>Family 7. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pseudotrionychidae</hi> (Boulenger).</p>
                <p>Shell without epidermic scutes.</p>
                <p>Fossil genera: <hi rend="italic">Pseudotrionyx</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Anosiira</hi> (Eocene), <hi rend="smallcaps">Group</hi> B. Pinnata.</p>
                <p>Limbs paddle-shaped; phalanges without condyles; claws one or two. Neck
                    imperfectly retractile; cervical vertebrae short, mostly articulated by
                    amphiarthrosis.</p>
                <p>Family 8. <hi rend="smallcaps">Chelonidae.</hi></p>
                <p>Plastral bones nine. Nuchal without costiform processes. Carapace with epidermic
                    scuteS. Hyo-and hypo-plastra not meeting mesially. Pelagic.</p>
                <p>Recent genera: <hi rend="italic">Chelone, Caouana, Caretta.</hi></p>
                <p>Fossil genus: <hi rend="italic">Puppigerus</hi> (Miocene and Eocene)</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Series</hi> B. PLEURODIRA.</p>
                <p>Neck not retractile, bending laterally. Pelvis anchylosed to the carapace and
                    plastron. When epidermic scutes are present, one or two intergulars in addition
                    to the normal plastral scutes.</p>
                <p>Family 1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Chelydidae.</hi></p>
                <p>Plastral bones nine. Carapace with epidermic scutes. Limbs with four or five
                    claws. Australian and tropical American regions.</p>
                <p>Recent genera; <hi rend="italic">Plalemys, Chelymys,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Elsey</hi><hi rend="italic">a, Chelodina, Hy dr</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >aspis,</hi><hi rend="italic">Hydromedusa, Chelys.</hi></p>
                <p>Fossil genera: <hi rend="italic">Plesioclιelys</hi> (Jurassic), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Craspedochelys</hi> (Jurassic), <hi rend="italic">Idiochelys</hi> (Jurassic),
                    <hi rend="italic">Nolomorpìta</hi> (Eocene).</p>
                <p>Family 2. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pelomedusidae.</hi></p>
                <p>Plastral bones eleven, mesoplastιa being present. Carapace with epidermic scutes.
                    Limbs with four or five claws. African and tropical American regions.</p>
                <p>Recent genera: <hi rend="italic">Pelomedusa, Stemolhxrus, Dumerilia, Podocnemis,
                    Pelto-cep∕ιalus.</hi></p>
                <p>Fossil genera: <hi rend="italic">Pletιrostemum</hi> (Cretaceous, Eocene), <hi
                    rend="italic">Bothremys</hi> (Cretaceous), <hi rend="italic">Taphrosphys</hi>
                    (Cretaceous).</p>
                <p>Family 3. <hi rend="smallcaps">Carettochelydidae.</hi></p>
                <p>Plastral bones nine. No epidermic scutes on the shell. Limbs paddle-shaped, with
                    only two claws. New Guinea.</p>
                <p>Genus: <hi rend="italic">Careltochelys.</hi></p>
                <p>Family 4. <hi rend="smallcaps">Miolaniidae</hi> (Boulenger).</p>
                <p>Caudal vertebrae opisthocaelous; tail long and encased in a bony sheath.
                    Australia.</p>
                <p>Fossil genus: <hi rend="italic">Miolania</hi> (Pleistocene).</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Suborder</hi> III. TRIONYCHOIDEA.</p>
                <p>Dorsal vertebrae and ribs immovably united, forming a carapace; no pygal plate;
                    marginal plates absent or forming an incomplete series. Plastron formed of nine
                    bones, epiplastra separated from the hyoplastra by the entoplastron, which is
                    /(-shaped, without longitudinal process. Sacral and caudal ribs attached to
                    transverse processes of the neural arch. Fourth digit with four or five
                    phalanges.</p>
                <p>Family 1. <hi rend="smallcaps">Trionychidae.</hi></p>
                <p>No epidermic scutes. Limbs with three claws. Indian, African, and American
                    regions.</p>
                <p>Genera: <hi rend="italic">Chilra, Heplathyra, Trionyx, Cyclanosteus,
                    Emyda.</hi></p>
                <p>We add a few notes on such of the genera enumerated in this synopsis as have some
                    special interest attached to them, either from a scientific or an economic point
                    of view.</p>
                <p>The family <hi rend="italic">Sphargidae</hi> is represented in the recent fauna
                    by a single species, <hi rend="italic">Dermatochelys</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sphargis</hi><hi rend="italic">coriacea,</hi> the Leathery Turtle, the range of
                    which extends over the tropical and subtropical seas of both hemispheres, and
                    which occasionally strays into the northern parts of the Atlantic, its
                    occurrence on the British coast having been recorded three or four times within
                    the last century. It differs from all other Chelonians by its carapace being
                    formed by ossifications of the skin only. Neither the vertebrae nor the ribs
                    enter into its formation; the latter remain free, and are not particularly
                    dilated. During the life of the animal the carapace is flexible like thick
                    leather, the bony deposits being arranged like mosaic, with several longitudinal
                    ridges of larger osseous tubercles. The limbs are, as in other marine turtles,
                    paddle-or fin-shaped, the anterior much longer than the posterior, and all
                    destitute of claws. This turtle is probably the largest living Chelonian,
                    exceeding 6 feet in length. The names <hi rend="italic">Testudo lyra,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Sphargis mereurialis,</hi> &amp;c., have reference to the myth
                    that the shell of this or some other turtle was used by Mercury in his
                    construction of the lyre.</p>
                <p>The family <hi rend="italic">Testudinidae</hi> is composed of an unbroken series,
                    from thoroughly aquatic freshwater tortoises like <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dermatemys</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Balagur</hi> to the tortoises which live
                    exclusively on land and are perfectly helpless in water. In the Central-American
                    genus <hi rend="italic">Dermatemys</hi> the digits are very broadly webbed, the
                    epidermic scutes are thin, and the nose is much produced,—characters which,
                    together with the strong depression of the shell, give these terrapins somewhat
                    the aspect of the freshwater turtles or <hi rend="italic">Trionychidae.</hi>
                    They feed exclusively upon leaves, grass, and especially fruit, and are eaten by
                    the natives. Of the freshwater tortoises of the Old World the most thoroughly
                    aquatic are the Batagurs, which inhabit the East Indies, and attain to a length
                    of 2 feet. Like their American representative, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dermatemys,</hi> they are essentially herbivorous, and their flesh is eaten.
                    The genus <hi rend="italic">Clemmys</hi> is extremely abundant in species, most
                    of which are of small size, and elegantly ornamented with symmetrical markings
                    of bright colour. The majority of the species occur in North America and Mexico,
                    and are of amphibious habits. Only one species, <hi rend="italic">C.
                    leprosa,</hi> inhabits southern Europe. A second European species belongs to the
                    genus <hi rend="italic">Emys, E. orbicularis,</hi> which, towards the end of the
                    Quaternary period appears to have been distributed over a great part of northern
                    Europe, remains having been found in peat in England, Belgium, Denmark, and
                    Sweden. Its habitat is now restricted to southern Europe, south-western Asia,
                    and north-western Africa; but singularly it has survived in a few isolated
                    northern stations, for instance, in the neighbourhood of Berlin and Königsberg,
                    although it is there on the verge of extinction. The mobility of the lobes of
                    the plastron, which distinguishes <hi rend="italic">Emys</hi> from <hi
                    rend="italic">Clemmys,</hi> is carried a degree further in the North-American
                    genus <hi rend="italic">Cistudo,</hi> the Box Tortoise; this terrapin possesses
                    a hinge in the plastron, rendering its anterior and posterior portions movable,
                    and converting them into lids by which the openings of the shell can be
                    completely closed when the head and limbs are retracted. A similar protective
                    apparatus exists in the tortoises of the genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cinostermιm.</hi> In the African terrestrial genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cinyxis</hi> it is the posterior portion of the carapace that is movable, and
                    separated from the anterior by a hinge. True land tortoises, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Testudo,</hi> occur in Africa, southern Europe, southern Asia, South America,
                    and the southern parts of North America. Those best known in Europe are <hi
                    rend="italic">Testudo</hi><hi rend="italic">graeca</hi> and the Moorish
                    Tortoise, <hi rend="italic">Testudo</hi><hi rend="italic">mauritanien,</hi>
                    large numbers of which are imported into the United Kingdom, chiefly from
                    Morocco. But the most interesting are the gigantic tortoises which formerly
                    inhabited in extreme abundance the Mascarene and Galapagos Islands, and are now
                    on the verge of extinction, or have actually <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n477/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0477-0458"/> become extinct. At the time of their discovery
                    those islands were uninhabited by man or any large mammal; the tortoises,
                    therefore, enjoyed perfect security; and this, as well as their extraordinary
                    degree of longevity, accounts for their enormous size and their large numbers.
                    They could be captured in any quantity with the greatest ease within a few days,
                    and proved to the ships’ companies who during their long voyages had to subsist
                    mainly on salt provisions a most welcome addition to their table. They could be
                    carried in the hold of a ship, without food, for months, and were slaughtered as
                    occasion required, each tortoise yielding, according to size, from 80 to 300
                    pounds of excellent and wholesome meat. Under these circumstances the numbers of
                    these helpless creatures decreased so rapidly that in the beginning of this
                    century their extermination was accomplished in the Mascarenes, and now only a
                    few remain in a wild state in Aldabra and in some of the islands of the
                    Galapagos group. Singularly, the majority of these islands were inhabited each
                    by one or more peculiar forms, specifically distinct from those of the other
                    islands. A large male specimen from Aldabra, which was imported into London some
                    years ago, weighed</p>
                <p>870 lb, and, although known to have been more than eighty years old, was still
                    growing at the time of its death. There is no evidence to show that any of these
                    tortoises were indigenous in the Seychelles; the specimens kept there in a
                    semi-domesticated state have been either directly imported from Aldabra or are
                    the descendants of imported individuals.</p>
                <p>The family of <hi rend="italic">Chelydridae</hi> includes freshwater tortoises,
                    which are known under the names of Snappers or Alligator Terrapins (fig. 3), on
                    account of their ferocity and long compressed crested tail. They are now
                    confined to North America east of the Rocky Mountains, Central America, and
                    northwest South America, but remains of two species of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chelydra,</hi> closely related to their recent representative, have been found
                    in the Oligocène and Miocene of central Europe. A second genus, closely allied
                    to <hi rend="italic">Chelydra, Macroclemmys temminckii,</hi> the shell of which
                    attains to a length of 3 feet, and which is the largest known freshwater
                    Chelonian, is restricted to the river-systems tributary to the Gulf of
                    Mexico.</p>
                <p>The family of <hi rend="italic">Cinosternidae</hi> contains a rather large number
                    of small-sized species, distributed from the northern parts of the United States
                    to the northern parts of Brazil. They are of amphibious habits. The front and
                    hind lobes of the plastron are movable, and in certain species of <hi
                    rend="italic">Cinoslernum</hi> the animal can completely shut itself up in its
                    shell.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Chelonidae,</hi> or marine turtles, contain but few
                    species, which are referred to three genera,— <hi rend="italic">Caouaηa,
                    Chelone,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Carella.</hi> Their limbs are wholly
                    modified into paddles, by means of which they can propel themselves with
                    extraordinary rapidity through the water, but which are entirely unfit for
                    locomotion on land, where the progress of these animals is as awkward as that of
                    a seal. The toes are enclosed in a common skin, out of which only one or two
                    claws project. The carapace is broad and much depressed, so that when the
                    turtles are surprised on shore and turned over on their back, they cannot regain
                    their natural position. Their capture forms a regular pursuit wherever they
                    occur in any numbers. Comparatively few are caught in the open sea, others in
                    stake nets, but the majority are intercepted at well-known periods and
                    localities where they go ashore to deposit their eggs. These are very numerous,
                    from 100 to 250 being produced by one female, and buried by her in the sand;
                    they are eagerly searched for and eaten. Some of the marine turtles are highly
                    esteemed for the delicacy of their meat and of the gelatinous skinny parts of
                    their neck and fins; others yield oil, and others again the tortoiseshell of
                    commerce. Probably the largest of these marine turtles is the Loggerhead <hi
                    rend="italic">{Caouana),</hi> which possesses fifteen vertebral and costal
                    shields, and occurs in the Atlantic as well as in the Indian <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n478/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0478-0459"/> Ocean (fig. 4). It is carnivorous, feeding on
                    fish, molluscs, and crustaceans, and not esteemed as food, although it is eaten
                    by the native fishermen. A great part of the turtle-oil which finds its way into
                    the market is obtained from the Atlantic species of this genus; also
                    tortoiseshell of an inferior quality is obtained from it. The Green Turtle (fig.
                    5), which yields the materials for the celebrated soup, belongs to the genus <hi
                    rend="italic">Chelonia∙,</hi> it is distinguished from <hi rend="italic"
                    >Caouana</hi> by having thirteen vertebral and costal shields only, which are
                    not imbricate. These animals are herbivorous, feeding on marine <hi
                    rend="italic">Algae</hi> only; they occur in the Indo-PacificandAtlantic; and,
                    although several species have been distinguished, they all may possibly be
                    referable to one only. The turtle imported into Europe comes chiefly from the
                    West Indies. Instances are recorded of the flesh of this species having acquired
                    poisonous qualities. The Hawksbill Turtle, <hi rend="italic">Caretta</hi> (fig.
                    6), so named from its rather elongate and compressed curved upper jaw, does not
                    reach the same size as the other turtles, and is readily recognized by the
                    thirteen imbricate scutes of its carapace. It seems to be more abundant in the
                    Indian than in the Atlantic Ocean, but is plentiful only in certain localities.
                    As, however, these turtles always resort to the locality where they were born,
                    or where they have been wont to propagate their kind, and as their capture is
                    very profitable, they become scarcer and scarcer at places where they are known
                    to have been abundant formerly. If the plates of tortoiseshell are detached from
                    the animal when decomposition has set in, their colour becomes clouded and
                    milky, and hence the cruel expedient is resorted to of suspending the turtle
                    over fire till heat makes the shields start from the bony part of the carapace,
                    after which the creature is permitted to escape to the water. There is no doubt
                    that turtles thus allowed to escape to the water after such an operation may
                    survive; but it is very improbable that the epidermal shields are ever
                    sufficiently regenerated to be fit for use. At Celebes, whence the finest
                    tortoiseshell is exported to China, the natives kill the turtle by blows on the
                    head, and immerse the shell in boiling water to detach the plates; dry heat is
                    only resorted to by the unskilful. The natives eat the flesh of this turtle, but
                    it is unpalatable to Europeans; the eggs, however, are regarded as equal to
                    those of the other turtles.</p>
                <p>Of the family <hi rend="italic">Chelydidae</hi> the most remarkable type is the
                    Matamata, <hi rend="italic">Chelys</hi><hi rend="italic">fimbriata,</hi> a
                    native of the Guianas and northern Brazil (fig. 7). In its strongly depressed
                    and flat head, long tubelike snout, weak jaws, minute eyes, skinny tentacles, it
                    bears a striking similarity to the Surinam toad, <hi rend="italic">Pipa
                    americana,</hi> which inhabits the same countries. The neck is very broad and
                    depressed, and fringed with foliated tentacles, floating in the water like some
                    vegetable growth, whilst the rough bossed carapace resembles a stone,—an
                    appearance which evidently is of as great use to this creature in escaping the
                    observation of its enemies as in alluring to it unsuspicious animals on which it
                    feeds.</p>
                <p>The family of <hi rend="italic">Carettochelydidae</hi> contains a single genus,
                    <hi rend="italic">Caretto∙ chelys,</hi> quite recently discovered in the Fly
                    river, New Guinea, and exhibiting a remarkable combination of characters. Its
                    limbs are formed very much like those of the marine turtles, whilst the shell
                    lacks epidermic scutes, as in the <hi rend="italic">Trionychidae.</hi></p>
                <p>In the freshwater turtles, or <hi rend="italic">Trionychidae</hi> (figs. 8 and
                    S), the carapace is reduced to a flat disk, which is covered with soft skin. The
                    neck and limbs can be lodged under the broad skinny borders of the carapace;
                    also the plastron is very imperfectly ossified, and sometimes dilated into large
                    flexible lobes which may cover the limbs. The latter are much flattened and
                    broadly webbed, and only the three inner toes armed with claws. The jaws are
                    concealed under broad, fleshy lips, the nose projecting like a short proboscis.
                    These turtles are carnivorous, and very ferocious; when they want to bite or
                    seize their prey they project their neck and head with lightning rapidity. They
                    are well known on the upper Nile, Euphrates, Ganges, Yangtse-kiang, and
                    Mississippi, and, indeed, distributed over all the large fresh waters of the
                    geographical regions to which <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n479/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0479-0460"/> these rivers belong. Some of the species exceed a
                    length of 3 feet. In the United States, where twospecies, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Trionyx</hi><hi rend="italic">muticus</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Trionyx</hi><hi rend="italic">ferox,</hi> occur, the flesh of the latter is
                    said to be most delicate to eat, far surpassing in flavour that of the green
                    turtle. (A. C. G. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
