<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0314-0297-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THESSALONIANS, Epistles to the (9th edition, volume 23,
                    page 297)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tk26">Sabbath</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102941">Sabbath</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n314/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THESSALONIANS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Epistles to
                    the</hi></label>. Thessalonica, now <hi rend="smallcaps">Salonica</hi> (<hi
                    rend="italic">q.v.</hi>), was in the time of the Romans the most important town
                    of Macedonia. In consequence of its advantageous situation, on a good harbour
                    and on the Via Egnatia, the great trade road which connected the Adriatic with
                    the Hellespont, the town had surpassed the old capital Pella, and had indeed
                    become one of the chief commercial centres of the ancient world. Since the Roman
                    conquest the seat of the Roman provincial government had been here. Here, as in
                    Corinth, the conditions were favourable for the reception of Christianity. The
                    population was not purely Greek, but cosmopolitan, a mixture of divers
                    nationalities. Such a population is always more susceptible to religious
                    novelties for good and for evil than one of old, firmly established national
                    growth. The apostle Paul experienced this to his great joy and satisfaction here
                    also, as he for the first time set foot on the shores of Europe with the message
                    of Jesus Christ. It was about the year 52 or 53 that he, on his arrival from
                    Philippi, preached the gospel of Christ in the rich merchant city. As in other
                    places, he began with the Jews. There was a Jewish congregation at Thessalonica,
                    as at all the great ports and trading centres of the Mediterranean, with their
                    own synagogue and regular service. For three Sabbaths Paul stood up in the
                    synagogue, proving by the Scriptures that Jesus was the promised and expected
                    Messiah (Acts xvii. 1-3). He had not much success with the Jews, but this was
                    more than compensated by the number of “devout Greeks” <hi rend="italic"
                    >(i.e.,</hi> Gentiles who already had some connexion with Judaism) whom he won
                    to a belief in Christ. He found hearing especially with the chief women (Acts
                    xviii. 4). But Paul had also converted a not smaller number of real heathens.
                    Indeed, they must have constituted the majority of the Christian church there
                    formed, for in his first epistle he says quite generally that his readers, in
                    consequence of his preaching, had turned from idols to the one true God (1
                    Thess. i. 9).</p>
                <p>Paul’s stay in Thessalonica was short. The plots of the Jews soon obliged him to
                    leave the town, and he betook himself to Beraea (Acts xvii. 10), thence to
                    Athens (Acts xvii. 15), and finally to Corinth (Acts xviii. 1). The two epistles
                    were written to the church of Thessalonica during a stay of a year and a half in
                    Corinth (Acts xviii. 11), about 53-54, not before this in Athens, as is asserted
                    in the subscription of both epistles in the Codex Alexandrinus and other MSS.
                    For when Paul wrote the first epistle some time had elapsed since the formation
                    of the church: some members were already dead (1 Thess. iv. 13), and Paul had
                    worked for some time, not only in Macedonia, but also in Achaia (i. 7, 8). On
                    the other hand, the church appears to be comparatively young; the conversions
                    are still spoken of everywhere in Macedonia and Achaia (i. 9). All this points
                    to the conclusion that the first epistle was written in Corinth, and this is
                    confirmed by the opening salutation (i. 1), in which Silvanus (Silas) and
                    Timotheus are named as joint authors, for they were in Corinth with Paul (Acts
                    xviii. 5).</p>
                <p>The first epistle gives us a very clear picture of the disposition and state of
                    such a young church, composed of former heathens. They had received with
                    enthusiasm the gospel of Jesus Christ, the Bringer of salvation, the Saviour in
                    the approaching day of judgment (i. 9, 10). But the realization of this
                    salvation is now awaited with impatience, and a sense of disappointment is
                    experienced because some members of the church have died without having seen the
                    advent of the Lord (iv. 13). At the same time many there are still living in
                    gross heathen sins and vices (iv. 1-8). Paul had sent back Timotheus from Athens
                    to Thessalonica in order to advise the young inexperienced church, and to obtain
                    news concerning it (iii. 1-5). He has just returned to Paul (iii. 6), and the
                    information received through this source is the occasion of the first
                    epistle,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>According to
                    Acts xvii. 14-15 and xviii. 5, Silas and Timotheus had remained behind in
                    Beraea, and first met Paul again in Corinth. But according to 1 Thess. iii. 1-5
                    it must be understood that Timotheus was in Athens with Paul, and had been sent
                    thence to Thessalonica.</p></note> designed to supply the place of Paul’s
                    personal presence and bring new exhortation and instruction from the apostle to
                    the young church, which still much needed guidance.</p>
                <p>We have no information concerning the effect of this letter. It is conceivable,
                    however, that the church required yet further advice and direction from the
                    apostle, and so far it is not remarkable that Paul saw the need for a second
                    similar letter of teaching and exhortation. This second epistle also, if it is
                    genuine, was written during Paul’s stay of a year and a half at Corinth, very
                    soon after <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n315/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0315-0298"/> the first. For it also is written in the
                    conjoined names of Silvanus and Timotheus, who were still with Paul, while we
                    must understand from Acts xviii. 18 that after Paul’s departure from Corinth
                    they ceased to be his companions. The occasion of this epistle seems especially
                    to have arisen from the circumstance that the church had been put into fear and
                    anxiety about the advent of Christ, perhaps by a pretended letter from Paul. Two
                    passages point to the existence of such a thing: in ii. 2, Paul says that the
                    church shall not let itself be alarmed “by word or by letter as from us” (i.e.,
                    nominally coming from us), and in iii. 17 again Paul lays emphasis on his
                    signature by his own hand as the token (of genuineness) to be noticed in each
                    letter. In any case the chief aim of the epistle is to tranquillize the church
                    concerning the advent of Christ, which is not yet immediately imminent. He
                    particularly exhorts them not to let themselves be shaken in mind, as that the
                    day of Christ is at hand (ii. 1, 2). For before this day comes the “man of sin”
                    must first appear, who seats himself in the temple of God, and gives himself out
                    for God (ii. 3-5). And he too is for the present kept back by another power (ii.
                    6, 7). Only when the latter is taken out of the way shall “that wicked” be
                    revealed, and the great falling away shall follow (ii. 8-12).</p>
                <p>The genuineness of the two epistles has not remained unquestioned by the newer
                    criticism. Baur declared himself against the genuineness of both epistles,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Paulus der
                    Apostel Jesu</hi><hi rend="italic">Christi,</hi> 1845, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Theologische Jahrbücher,</hi> 1855, p. 141-168, reprinted in 2d ed. of <hi
                    rend="italic">Paulus,</hi> ii. 341-369.</p></note> and he is followed by Van der
                    Vies<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">beide</hi><hi rend="italic">brieven</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">aan de Thessalonicensem,</hi> Leyden, 1865.</p></note> and several
                    others.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Holsten also <hi
                    rend="italic">(Jahrb. f. prot. Theol.,</hi> 1877, p. 731 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.)</hi> and Steck <hi rend="italic">(Jahτb.</hi><hi rend="italic">f. prot.
                    Theol.,</hi> 1883, p. 509-524) dispute the genuineness of the first epistle,
                    presupposing the spuriousness of the second.</p></note> But in general the
                    predominant opinion of impartial criticism at present is that the genuineness of
                    the first epistle is certain, while that of the second must be given up.</p>
                <p>This is the opinion of Hilgenfeld <hi rend="italic">(Z. f.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >wies.</hi><hi rend="italic">Theol.</hi>, 1862, p. 225-264; 1866, p. 295-301;
                    1869, p. 441 <hi rend="italic">sq.∙,</hi> 1870, p. 244 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.),</hi> Van Manen <hi rend="italic">(Onderzoek ηaar de echtheid van Paulus
                    tweeden brief aaη de Thessalonicensen,</hi> Utrecht, 1865), S. Davidson <hi
                    rend="italic">(Introd, to the New Testament,</hi> 2d ed., 1882, i. 4—16,
                    336-351), Weizsäcker <hi rend="italic">(Das apostolische Zeitalter,</hi> 1886,
                    p. 249-261); and Holtzmann also leans to the same view, without, however,
                    definitely committing himself <hi rend="italic">(EM. in d. N. T.,</hi> 2d ed.,
                    1886, p. 233-241). The genuineness of the first epistle is vindicated by Lipsius
                    <hi rend="italic">(Theol. St. u. Kr.,</hi> 1854, p. 905-934), Von Soden <hi
                    rend="italic">(ibid.,</hi> 1885, p. 263-310), and Paul Schmidt <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Der erste Thessalonicherbriefneuerklärt,</hi> Berlin, 1885), while, on the
                    other hand, Kern (<hi rend="italic">Tubing. Zeitschr. f. Theol.,</hi> 1839, ii.
                    145-214) and Bahnsen <hi rend="italic">(Jahrb.</hi><hi rend="italic">für</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">prot. Theol.,</hi> 1880, p. 681-705) attack that of the second.
                    Grimm <hi rend="italic">(Theol. St. u. Kr.,</hi> 1850, p. 753-816) and Westrik
                    <hi rend="italic">(De echtheid van den tweeden brief aan de
                    Thessalonicensen,</hi> Utrecht, 1879) have entered the lists for the genuineness
                    of both epistles.</p>
                <p>The final decision of the newer criticism is justified by the evidence. No real
                    difficulties can be brought against the genuineness of the first epistle, but
                    they certainly can against that of the second. W <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi>
                    hen Baur finds that the epistles lack the characteristic Pauline ideas, he is
                    only so far right that the doctrine of justification by faith is not dealt with,
                    for which, however, no occasion arises. It has been asserted that there are
                    traces of imitation of the epistles to the Corinthians, but the points of
                    resemblance are^not such as to justify this conclusion. The connexion of the
                    passage in 1 Thess. ii. 16 (the wrath of God is already come upon the Jews) with
                    the destruction of Jerusalem rests on an arbitrary, nay false, interpretation.
                    And it cannot be maintained on impartial examination that in 1 Thess. ii. 14,
                    15, the Jewish churches of Palestine are set forth in a way unlike Paul, as an
                    example for the heathen churches.</p>
                <p>The objections to the second epistle are much weightier, though here also not all
                    the arguments adduced by hostile critics are valid. It has been often said that
                    the author, like the author of the Apocalypse, regards Nero as the Antichrist,
                    expecting him to reappear as the arch-enemy of Christ. But this interpretation
                    of the short statement of our epistle cannot be proved. The assumption that
                    before the dawn of salvation godlessness would reach its height, through the
                    appearance of an arch-enemy of God and His church is, so to speak, a dogmatic
                    postulate which rests on the prophecies of Daniel and other prophets of the Old
                    Testament. And, in so far as the picture of this archenemy is endowed with
                    historical features, they can quite as well have been drawn from Caligula as
                    from Nero. For Caligula had already laid claim to the honours of a god, and
                    because of this appeared to the Jews to be the embodiment of godlessness. The
                    assumption of such an Antichrist would not be striking in Paul. Even if it is
                    correct (as is generally and with reason taken for granted) that by the
                    hindrance which keeps back the appearance of Antichrist (2 Thess. ii. 6, 7) the
                    established might of the Roman emperor and empire is to be understood, this view
                    would be quite in keeping with Paul’s views about the Roman dominion (Rom. xiii.
                    1-7). Yet it must be conceded that the statements on this head create real
                    difficulty, if we compare them with those of the first epistle, in which all
                    stress is laid on the fact that the day of the Lord comes as a thief in the
                    night, and that man must be prepared for it at any moment (1 Thess. v. 1-11). In
                    the second epistle it is pointed out with equal emphasis that the day of the
                    Lord is not immediately imminent, and that certain events must come first (2
                    Thess. ii. 1-10). It is certainly very striking that Paul, so soon after the
                    admonitions of the first kind, should have given the quieting assurances of the
                    second. And 2 Thess. ii. 2 and iii. 7 can hardly be explained except by the
                    supposition that the readers had been thrown into alarm by a pretended epistle
                    from Paul. Could this have been dared in that early time, almost under the eyes
                    of the apostle <hi rend="italic">1</hi> Finally, it is not to be denied that the
                    style of the second epistle is different from that of the first, and that the
                    contents often appear a mere imitation, except in the eschatological passages on
                    account of which it was written. It must therefore be admitted that weighty if
                    not conclusive considerations have been produced against its genuineness. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(e. s*.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
