<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0449-0430-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TOCQUEVILLE, Alexis Henri Charles Chérel, Comte de (9th
                    edition, volume 23, page 430)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1023771">Missions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n449/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TOCQUEVILLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Alexis Henri Charles
                    Chérel, Comte de</hi></label> (1805-1859), was born at Verneuil on July 29,
                    1805. His family on the father’s side were of good descent, and distinguished
                    both in the law and in arms, while his mother was the granddaughter of
                    Malesherbes. Alexis de Tocqueville was brought up for the bar, or, rather,
                    according to the division of that profession in France, for the bench, and
                    became an assistant magistrate in 1830. A year later he obtained from the
                    Government of July a mission to examine prisons and penitentiaries in America,
                    and proceeded thither with his lifelong friend Gustave de Beaumont. He returned
                    in somewhat less than two years, and published a report on the subject of his
                    mission, but the real result of his tour was the famous <hi rend="italic">He la
                    Hémocratie</hi><hi rend="italic">en Amérique,</hi> which appeared in 1835, and
                    very soon made his reputation. It was at once caught up by influential members
                    of the Liberal party in England, which country Tocqueville soon after visited,
                    and where he married an Englishwoman. Returning to France, and beginning life as
                    a country gentleman at Tocqueville, he thought to carry out the English ideal
                    completely by standing for the chamber of deputies. But, with a scruple which
                    illustrated his character, he refused Government nomination from Molé, and was
                    defeated. Later he was successful, and sat for several years both before and
                    after the revolution of February, becoming in 1849 vice-president of the
                    assembly, and for a few months minister of foreign affairs. He was a warm
                    supporter of the Roman expedition, but an equally warm opponent of Louis
                    Napoleon, and after being one of the deputies who were arrested at the <hi
                    rend="italic">coup d’etat</hi> he retired from public life. Twenty years after
                    his first, he produced another book, <hi rend="italic">He V</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Ancien Régime,</hi> which almost, if not quite, equalled its
                    success. His health was never very strong, and in 1858 he broke a blood-vessel.
                    He was ordered to the south, and, taking up his residence at Cannes, died there
                    on the 16th of April 1859. He had published some minor pieces during his
                    lifetime, and his complete works, including much unpublished correspondence,
                    were produced after his death in uniform shape by De Beaumont.</p>
                <p>During the last twenty years of his life, and for perhaps half that time after
                    his death, Tocqueville had an increasing European fame, which for the last ten
                    or fifteen years has been stationary if not diminishing. Both phenomena are
                    susceptible of explanation. Although he has been accused by some of his own
                    countrymen of having “le style triste,” his manner, which is partly imitated
                    from Montesquieu, has considerable charm; and he was the first and has remained
                    the chief writer to put the orthodox liberal ideas which governed European
                    politics during the first half or two-thirds of the 19th century into an orderly
                    and attractive shape. He was, moreover, as has been said, much taken up by
                    influential persons in England,—Senior, John Stuart Mill, and others,— and he
                    had the great advantage of writing absolutely the first book of reasoned
                    politics on the facts of democratic government as observed in America. Besides
                    all this he was, if not an entirely impartial writer, neither a fanatical
                    devotee of democracy nor a fanatical opponent of it. All this gave him a very
                    great advantage which he has not yet wholly lost. At the same time he had
                    defects which were certain to make themselves felt as time went on, even <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n450/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0450-0431"/> without the alteration of the centre of liberal
                    opinion which has taken place of late years. The chief of these was a certain
                    weakness which can hardly be described in English by any word more dignified
                    than the familiar term “priggishness.” His correspondence with Molé above
                    alluded to is an instance of this, and it was also reflected on in various
                    epigrams by countrymen and contemporaries; one of these accuses him of having
                    unluckily “begun to think before he had begun to learn,” while another, with
                    more real than apparent inconsistency, declares that he “avait l’air de savoir
                    de toute éternité ce qu’il venait d’apprendre.” His book on America, though
                    undoubtedly a very remarkable piece of political deduction, has the drawback of
                    proceeding on very insufficient premisses and of trying to be too systematic.
                    His book on the <hi rend="italic">Ancien Régime</hi> is also wanting in solid,
                    information,.and commits the great error of assuming rather than proving that
                    the Revolution of 1789 was a proceeding of unmixed good, which delivered France
                    from a state (not of unmixed evil, for Tocqueville was too careful a student to
                    imagine that, but) of evil exclusively caused by the existence of monarchical
                    and aristocratic institutions. In fact, the fault of both books is that their
                    author is not a practical politician, a fault which is constantly illustrated
                    and exhibited in his correspondence. He appears both in reading history and in
                    conducting actual political business (of which, as has been seen, he had some
                    experience) to have been constantly surprised and disgusted that men and nations
                    did not behave as he expected them to behave. This excess of the deductive
                    spirit explains at once both the merits and the defects of his two great works,
                    which will probably remain to some extent political classics, though they are
                    less and less likely to be used as practical guides.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
