<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0333-0316-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THOUSAND AND ONE NIGHTS (9th edition, volume 23, page
                    316)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1037627">Night</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950782">Hammers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hs61">Moslems</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n333/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THOUSAND AND ONE NIGHTS</label>. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thousand and One Nights,</hi> commonly known in English as <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Arabian Nights’ Entertainments,</hi> is a collection of tales written in
                    Arabic, which first became generally known in Europe in the early part of last
                    century through the French translation by Antoine <hi rend="smallcaps">Galland
                    (ç.u),</hi> and rapidly attained such universal popularity that it is
                    unnecessary to describe the contents of the book. But the origin of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Arabian Nights</hi> claims discussion in this place. In the <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi rend="italic">Asiatique</hi> for 1827, p. 253, Von
                    Hammer drew attention to a passage in the <hi rend="italic">Golden Meadows</hi>
                    of Mas'údí (ed. Barbier de Meynard, iv. 89 <hi rend="italic">sq.),</hi> written
                    in 943 A.D., in which certain stories current among the old Arabs are compared
                    with “the books which have reached us in translations from Persian, Indian, and
                    Greek, such as the book of <hi rend="italic">Hezár Afsáne,</hi> a title which,
                    translated from Persian into Arabic, means ‘the thousand tales.’ This book is
                    popularly called <hi rend="italic">The Thousand and One Nights,</hi> and
                    contains the story of the king and his vizier and of his daughter Shirazád and
                    her slave girl Dínázád. Other books of the same kind are the book of <hi
                    rend="italic">Ferza and Símás,</hi> containing stories of Indian kings and
                    viziers, the book of Sindibád, &amp;c.” Von Hammer concluded that the <hi
                    rend="italic">Thousand and One Nights</hi> were of Persian or Indian origin.
                    Against this conclusion De Sacy protested in a memoir <hi rend="italic">(Mem. de
                    l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Acαd. des Inscr.,</hi> 1833, x. 30 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sqj),</hi> demonstrating that the character of the book we know is genuinely
                    Arabian, and that it must have been written in Egypt at a comparatively recent
                    date. Von Hammer in reply adduced, in <hi rend="italic">Jour. As.,</hi> 1839,
                    ii. p. 175 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> a passage in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fihrist</hi> (987 A.D.), which is to the following effect:—</p>
                <p>“The ancient Persians were the first to invent tales, and make books of them, and
                    some of their tales were put in the mouths of animals. The Ashghanians, or third
                    dynasty of Persian kings, and after them the Sásánians, had a special partin the
                    development of this literature, which found Arabic translators, and was taken up
                    by accomplished Arabic literati, who edited it and imitated it. The earliest
                    book of the kind was the <hi rend="italic">Hezár afsán</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thousand</hi><hi rend="italic">Tales,</hi> which had the following origin. A
                    certain Persian king was accustomed to kill his wives on the morning af ter the
                    consummation of the marriage. But once he married a clever princess called
                    Shahrazád, who spent the marriage night in telling a story which in the morning
                    reached a point so interesting that the king spared her, and asked next night
                    for the sequel. This went on for a thousand nights, till Shahrazád had a son,
                    and ventured to tell the king of her device. He admired her intelligence, loved
                    her, and spared her life. In all this the princess was assisted by the king’s
                    stewardess Dínázád. This book is said to have been written for the princess
                    Homái (MSS. Homání), daughter of Bahman. ... It contains nearly two hundred
                    stories, one story often occupying several nights. I have repeatedly seen the
                    complete book, but it is really a meagre and uninteresting production” <hi
                    rend="italic">(Fihrist,</hi> ed. Flügel, p. 304).</p>
                <p>Persian tradition (in Firdausi) makes Princess Homái the daughter and wife of
                    Bahman Ardashír, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> Artaxerxes I. Longimanus. She is
                    depicted as a great builder, a kind of Persian Semiramis, and is a half-mythical
                    personage already mentioned in the Avesta, but her legend seems to be founded on
                    the history of Atossa and of Parysatis. Firdausi says that she was also called
                    Shahrazád (Mohl, v. 11). This name and that of Dínázád both occur in what
                    Mas'ddí tells of her. According to him, Shahrazád was Homái’s mother (ii. 129),
                    a Jewess (ii. 123). Bahman had married a Jewess (i. 118), who was instrumental
                    in delivering her nation from captivity. In ii. 122 this Jewish maiden who did
                    her people this service is called Dínázád, but “the accounts,” says our author,
                    “vary.” Plainly she is the Esther of Jewish story. Tabari (i. 688) calls Esther
                    the mother of Bahman, and, like Firdausi, gives to Homái the name of Shahrazád.
                    The story of Esther and that of the original <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> have
                    in fact one main feature in common. In the former the king is offended with his
                    wife, and divorces her; in the <hi rend="italic">Arabian Nights</hi> he finds
                    her unfaithful, and kills her. But both stories agree that thereafter a new wife
                    was brought to him every night, and on the morrow passed into the second house
                    of the women (Esther), or was slain <hi rend="italic">(Nights).</hi> At length
                    Esther or Shahrazád wins his heart and becomes queen. The issue in the Jewish
                    story is that Esther saves her people; in the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> the
                    gainers are “the daughters of the Moslems,” but the old story had, of course,
                    some other word than “Moslems.” Esther’s foster-father becomes vizier, and
                    Shahrazád’s father is also vizier. Shah-razád’s plan is helped forward in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> by Dínázád, who is, according to Mas'údí, her
                    slave girl, or, according to other MSS., her nurse, and, according to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Fihrist,</hi> the king’s stewardess. The last account comes
                    nearest to Esther ii. 15, where Esther gains the favour of the king’s
                    chamberlain, keeper of the women. It is also to be noted that Ahasuerus is read
                    to at night when he cannot sleep (Esther vi. 1). And it is just possible that it
                    is worth notice that, though the name of Ahasuerus corresponds to Xerxes,
                    Josephus identifies him with Artaxerxes I.</p>
                <p>Now it may be taken as admitted that the book of Esther was written in Persia, or
                    by one who had lived in Persia, and not earlier than the 3d century B.c. If now
                    there is real weight in the points of contact between this story and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Arabian Nights—</hi> and the points of difference cannot be held
                    to outweigh the resemblances between two legends, each of which is necessarily
                    so far removed from the hypothetical common source—the inference is important
                    for both stories. On the one hand, it appears that (at least in part) the book
                    of Esther draws on a Persian source; on the other hand, it becomes probable that
                    the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> are older than the Sásánian period, to which
                    Lane, iii. 677, refers them.</p>
                <p>It is a piece of good fortune that Mas'údí and the <hi rend="italic">Fihrist</hi>
                    give us the information cited above. For in general the Moslems, though very
                    fond of stories, are ashamed to recognize them as objects of literary curiosity.
                    In fact, the next mention of the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> is found only
                    after <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n334/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0334-0317"/> a lapse of three centuries. Makrízí, describing
                    the capital of Egypt, quotes from a work of Ibn Sa'íd (c. 1250 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">a.d.),</hi> who again cites an older author (Al-Kortobí), who,
                    in speaking of a love affair at the court of the caliph Al-Ámir (1097-1130),
                    says “what is told aboutit resembles the romance of Al-Battál, or the <hi
                    rend="italic">Thousand and One Nights” (Hitat,</hi> Búlák ed., i. 485, ii.
                    181).</p>
                <p>That the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> which we have are not the original
                    translation of the <hi rend="italic">Hezár Äfsáne</hi> is certain, for the
                    greater part of the stories are of Arabian origin, and the whole is so
                    thoroughly Mohammedan that even the princes of remote ages who are introduced
                    speak and act as Moslems. It might be conceived that this is due to a gradual
                    process of modernization by successive generations of story-tellers. But against
                    this notion, which has been entertained by some scholars, Lane has remarked with
                    justice that, much as MSS. of the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> differ from one
                    another in points of language and style, in the order of the tales, and the
                    division into nights, they are all so much at one in essentials that they must
                    be regarded as derived from a single original. There is no trace of a recension
                    of the text that can be looked on as standing nearer to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hezar Afsáne.</hi> And the whole local colour of the work, in point of dialect
                    and also as regards the manners and customs described, clearly belongs to Egypt
                    as it was from the 14th to the 16th century. Some points, as De Sacy and Lane
                    have shown, forbid us to place the book earlier than the second half of the 15th
                    century. Galland’s MS. copy, again, was in existence in 1548. Lane accordingly
                    dates the work from the close of the 15 th century or the beginning of the 16th,
                    but this date appears to be too late. For Abu’l-Mahásin, an Egyptian historian
                    who died in 1470, writing of Hamdi, a famous highwayman of Baghdad in the 10th
                    century, remarks that he is probably the figure who used to be popularly spoken
                    of as Ahmed al-Danaf (ed. Juynboll, ii. 305). Now in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nights</hi> Ahmed al-Danaf really plays a part corresponding to that of the
                    historical Hamdi, being now a robber (Lane, ii. 404) and again a captain of the
                    guard (Lane, ii. 249). It would seem that Abu’l-Mahásin had read or heard the
                    stories in the <hi rend="italic">Nights,</hi> and was thus led to compare the
                    historical with the fictitious character. And, if this be so, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Nights</hi> must have been composed very soon after 1450.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The hypothesis of gradual and
                    complete modernization is also opposed to the fact that the other romances used
                    by Cairene storytellers (such as those of Antar and of Saif) retain their
                    original local colour through all variations of language and
                    style.</p></note></p>
                <p>No doubt the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> have borrowed much from the <hi
                    rend="italic">Hezár Afsáne,</hi> and it is not improbable that even in the
                    original Arabic translation of that work some of the Persian stories were
                    replaced by Arab ones. But that our <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> differ very
                    much from the <hi rend="italic">Hezár Afsáne</hi> is further manifest from the
                    circumstance that, even of those stories in the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi>
                    which are not Arabian in origin, some are borrowed from books mentioned by
                    Mas'údí as distinct from the <hi rend="italic">Hezár Afsáne.</hi> Thus the story
                    of the king and his son and the damsel and the seven viziers (Lane, chap, xxi.
                    note 51) is in fact a version of the <hi rend="italic">Book of
                    Sindbád,</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>On this
                    famous book, the Syriac <hi rend="italic">Sindibán,</hi> the Greek <hi
                    rend="italic">Syntipas,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Seven Sages</hi> of the
                    European West, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Syriac Literature</hi> (vol. xxii. p.
                    850) and <hi rend="smallcaps">Spain</hi> (vol. xxii. p. 354).</p></note> while
                    the story of Jalí'ád and his son and the vizier Shammás (M‛Naghten, iv. 366 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.; cf.</hi> Lane, iii. 530) corresponds to the book of <hi
                    rend="italic">Ferza and Símás.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>De Sacy and Lane suppose that the original title of the
                    Arabic translation of the <hi rend="italic">Hezár Afsáne</hi> was <hi
                    rend="italic">The Thousand Nights.</hi> But most MSS. of Mas'údí already have
                    <hi rend="italic">The Thousand and One Nights,</hi> which is also the name given
                    by Makrízí. Both ciphers perhaps mean only “a very great number,” and Fleischer
                    <hi rend="italic">(De</hi><hi rend="italic">Glossis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Habiehtianis,</hi> p. 4) has shown that 1001 is certainly used in this
                    sense.</p></note></p>
                <p>Not a few of the tales are unmistakably of Indian or</p>
                <p>Persian origin, and in these poetical passages are rarely inserted. In other
                    stories the scene lies in Persia or India, and the source is foreign, but the
                    treatment thoroughly Arabian and Mohammedan. Sometimes, indeed, traces of Indian
                    origin are perceptible, even in stories in which Hárún al-Rashíd figures and the
                    scene is Baghdad or Basra.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Gildemeister, <hi rend="italic">De Rebus</hi><hi rend="italic">Indicis,</hi>
                    p. 89 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi></p></note> But most of the tales, in substance
                    and form alike, are Arabian, and so many of them have the capital of the caliphs
                    as the scene of action that it may be guessed that the author used as one of his
                    sources a book of tales taken from the era of Baghdad’s prosperity.</p>
                <p>The late date of the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> appears from sundry
                    anachronisms. In the story of the men transformed into fish— white, blue,
                    yellow, or red according as they were Moslems, Christians, Jews, or Magians
                    (Lane, i. 99),—the first three colours are those of the turbans which, in 1301,
                    Mohammed b. Keláún of Egypt commanded his Moslem, Christian, and Jewish subjects
                    respectively to wear.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Quatremère, <hi rend="italic">Sultans Mamloues,</hi> ii. 2, p. 177 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.</hi></p></note> Again, in the story of the humpback, whose
                    scene is laid in the 9th century, the talkative barber says, “this is the year
                    653” (= 1255 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi>; Lane, i. 332, writes 263, but see
                    his note), and mentions the caliph Mostansir (died 1242), who is incorrectly
                    called son of Mostadí.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Lane, i. 342, arbitrarily writes “Montasir” for “Mostansir.”</p></note> In
                    the same story several places in Cairo are mentioned which did not exist till
                    long after the 9th century (see Lane, i. 379).<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See also <hi rend="italic">Ediηb.
                    Review,</hi> July 1886, p. Ï9l <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi></p></note> The very
                    rare edition of the first 200 nights published at Calcutta in 1814 speaks of
                    cannon, which are first mentioned in Egypt in 1383; and all editions sometimes
                    speak of coffee, which was discovered towards the end of the 14th century, but
                    not generally used till 200 years later. In this and other points, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> in the mention of a mosque founded in 1501 (Lane, iii.
                    608), we detect the hand of later interpolators, but the extent of such
                    interpolations can hardly perhaps be determined even by a collation of all
                    copies. For the nature and causes of the variations between different copies the
                    reader may consult Lane, iii. 678, who explains how transpositions actually
                    arise by transcribers trying to make up a complete set of the tales from several
                    imperfect copies.</p>
                <p>Many of the tales in the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> have an historical basis,
                    as Lane has shown in his notes. Other cases in point might be added: thus the
                    chronicle of Ibn al-Jauzí (died 1200 A.D.) contains a narrative of Kamar, slave
                    girl of Shaghb, the mother of Al-Moktadir, which is the source of the tale in
                    Lane, i. 310 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> and of another to be found in
                    M‛Naghten, iv. 557 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>; the latter is the better story,
                    but departs so far from the original that the author must have had no more than
                    a general recollection of the narrative he drew on.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See De Goeje in <hi rend="italic">Gids,</hi>
                    1876, ii. pp. 397-411.</p></note> There are other cases in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Nights</hi> of two tales which are only variations of a single theme, or even
                    in certain parts agree almost word for word. Some tales are mere compounds of
                    different stories put together without any art, but these perhaps are, as Lane
                    conjectures, later additions to the book; yet the collector himself was no great
                    literary artist. We must picture him as a professional story-teller equipped
                    with a mass of miscellaneous reading, a fluent power of narration, and a ready
                    faculty for quoting, or at a push improvising, verses. His stories became
                    popular, and were written down as he told them,—hardly written by himself, else
                    we should not have so many variations in the text, and such insertions of “the
                    narrator says,” “my noble sirs,” and the like. The frequent coarseness of tone
                    is proper to the condition of Egyptian society under the Mameluke sultans, and
                    would not have been tolerated in Baghdad in the age <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n335/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0335-0318"/> to which so many of the tales refer. Yet with all
                    their faults the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> have beauties enough to deserve
                    their popularity, and to us their merit is enhanced by the pleasure we feel in
                    being transported into so entirely novel a state of society.</p>
                <p>The original of some of the most interesting tales in Galland’s version, as
                    “Aladdin and the Wonderful Lamp,” “Ali Baba and the Forty Thieves,” has just
                    been discovered by Dr Zotenberg in a MS. recently acquired by the National
                    Library at Paris. A careful examination of this MS. and of the Wortley-Montagu
                    MS. in the Bodleian may lead perhaps to a more certain conclusion as to the time
                    of composition.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Thousand and One Nights</hi> became known in Europe
                    througlι A. Galland’s French version (12 vols., 12mo, Paris, 1704-12); the
                    publication was an event in literary history, the influence of which can be
                    traced far and wide. This translation, however, left much to be desired in point
                    of accuracy, and especially failed to reproduce the colour of the original with
                    the exactness which those who do not read merely for amusement must desire. It
                    was with a special view to the remedying of these defects that Lane produced in
                    1840 his admirably accurate, if somewhat stilted, translation, enriched with
                    most valuable notes and a discussion of the origin of the work (new edition,
                    with some additional notes, 3 vols., 8vo., London, 1859). Lane’s translation
                    omits the tales which he deemed uninteresting or unfit for a European public. No
                    full translation into English can be published, and, though two such have been
                    privately printed, and one of these (by Sir R. Burton) is being reproduced in an
                    expurgated form, Lane’s version is still unsuperseded for all serious use. Of
                    the Arabic text of the <hi rend="italic">Nights</hi> the principal editions
                    are—(1) M ’ Naghten’s edition, 4 vols., 8vo, Calcutta, 1839-42; (2) the Breslau
                    edition, 12 vols., 12mo, 1835-43, the first 8 vols, by Habicht, the rest by
                    Fleischer (compare as to the defects of Habicht’s work, Fleischer, <hi
                    rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Glossis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Habichtianis,</hi> Leipsic, 1836); (3) the first Búlák edition, 4 vols.,
                    1862-3. (Μ. J. <hi rend="smallcaps">deG.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
