<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0317-0300-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THIBAUT, Anton Friedrich Justus (9th edition, volume
                    23, page 300)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mn08">Jurists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46m3337r">Civilization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766g40">Sovereigns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n317/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THIBAUT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Anton Friedrich
                    Justus</hi></label> (1774-1840), one of the greatest of German jurists, was born
                    at Hameln, in Hanover, January 4, 1774, that is, ten years after his
                    contemporary and rival Hugo, about a year before Feuerbach, and five years
                    before Savigny. Thibaut’s father was an officer in the Hanoverian army, a
                    skilful mathematician, and, like his son, a man of much force of character. His
                    mother was the daughter of the Oberbürgermeister of the town. The Thibauts were
                    of French descent; they came from a family which had been driven out of France
                    on the revocation of the edict of Nantes. As a child and youth, Thibaut lived in
                    Hameln, Harburg, and Hanover. He was fond of rowing, skating, and swimming, and,
                    above all, of music, which remained his passion through life. As a lad he set
                    his heart, chiefly for romantic reasons, on being a forester, and he actually
                    spent two years as such. But he soon became disenchanted, and in 1792 went to
                    Göttingen to study. In 1793 he moved to Königsberg, where Kant still taught.
                    Thibaut was deeply affected by the critical philosophy; his very latest writings
                    bear traces of it, and it is not unimportant in the history of jurisprudence in
                    Germany that Hugo was equally influenced by it. From Königsberg Thibaut moved in
                    1794 to Kiel, where he formed a friendship with Niebuhr, at that time a student
                    there. They lived for a year in the same house, taking their meals together, and
                    holding much converse on literature and politics. Both already displayed the
                    bent of their minds—Niebuhr despondent and affrighted at the progress of the
                    French Revolution, Thibaut hopeful, undismayed, and certain that eventually all
                    would be well. In 1798 he was appointed extraordinary professor of civil law,
                    and in the same year appeared his <hi rend="italic">Versuche über
                    einzelne</hi><hi rend="italic">Theile</hi><hi rend="italic">der Theorie des
                    Rechts</hi> (Kiel, 1798), a collection of essays, of which by far the most
                    important was entitled “Ueber die Einfluss der Philosophie auf die Auslegung der
                    Positiven Gesetze.” Taking as his text an observation of Leibnitz, he sought to
                    show that history without philosophy could not interpret and explain law. The
                    essay was partly by anticipation a corrective of the teaching of the historical
                    school of jurists. It enters into speculations on the possibility of forming an
                    ideal body of law as a measure and mode of exposition of particular law,
                    —speculations which have never been continued, certainly not by Thibaut. In 1799
                    he was made ordinary professor of civil law. In that year was published his <hi
                    rend="italic">Theorie der logischen Auslegung des römischen Rechts,</hi> one of
                    his most remarkable works, a favourite book of Austin’s, and, as his
                    well-annotated copy in the Inner Temple library shows, one which he had most
                    carefully studied. In 1800 Thibaut married the daughter of Professor Ehlers at
                    Kiel. In 1802 <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n318/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0318-0301"/> he published a short criticism of Feuerbach’s
                    theory óf criminal law. It is an excellent illustration of his good sense; it
                    discriminates between what is good and what is unsound and crude in the writings
                    of criminal law reformers; it recalls in many ways the speculations of Bentham.
                    The same year appeared Thibaut’s essay <hi rend="italic">Ueber</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Besitz und Verjährung.</hi> In 1803 Thibaut was called to Jena,
                    where he spent three years, made happier than they otherwise would have been by
                    intercourse with Goethe and Schiller. At the invitation of the grand-duke of
                    Baden he went to Heidelberg to fill the chair of civil law and to assist in
                    organizing the university; and he never quitted that town, though he received in
                    after years, as his fame grew, invitations to Göttingen, Munich, and Leipsic.
                    His class was large, his influence great; and, except Hugo and Savigny, no
                    civilian of his time was so well known. In the work of the university he took an
                    active part; and he cultivated with rare devotion his favourite art. In 1814
                    appeared his <hi rend="italic">Civilistische Abhandlungen,</hi> of which the
                    principal was his famous essay, the parent of so much literature, on the
                    necessity of a national code for Germany. He had no wish to enter into official
                    or practical life. “I am Professor Thibaut, and wish to be nobody else.” In 1819
                    he was appointed representative in the first chamber of the Baden parliament. He
                    was also made member of the Scheidungsgericht. In 1825 appeared anonymously his
                    work <hi rend="italic">Ueber die</hi><hi rend="italic">Reinheit der
                    Tonkunst,</hi> in which he eulogized the old music, and especially that of his
                    favourite master, Palestrina. It involved him in a contest with Nägeli and other
                    admirers of the new school of music, whose merits Thibaut was somewhat slow to
                    own. This has been translated into English by W. H. Gladstone. In 1836 Thibaut
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Erörterungen des römischen Rechts.</hi> One of
                    his last works was a contribution in 1838 to the <hi rend="italic">Archiv
                    für</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic">civilistische</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Praxis,</hi> of which he was one of the editors (see below). He
                    died peacefully, full of years and honour, on the 29th of March 1840.</p>
                <p>Thibaut was of the middle height and broad-shouldered, his eyes bright and
                    piercing, his head noble and striking; his whole appearance told of power,
                    simplicity, and reserve. All who knew him speak of his strong personality, his
                    manly consistent nature. Young men loved him, and he drew to the young. If he
                    sometimes signed his letters <hi rend="italic">“Semper idem</hi> A. F. J.
                    Thibaut,” it was not a phrase. Every incident told of him has a curious flavour.
                    He was much more than a jurist: he deserves to be remembered in the history of
                    music. Palestrina and the early composers of church music were his delight.
                    “Jurisprudence is my business; my music room is my temple.” His friend, Dr
                    Baumstark, has left an interesting record of his musical pursuits and of the
                    work of his “Sangverein” at Heidelberg. Among the masters of German prose
                    Thibaut holds no mean place. Nothing could be clearer, more unpedantic and
                    unpretentious, than his exposition; his prose is scarcely inferior to Lessing’s.
                    Like his speech, his written style was simple and manly, but it is simplicity
                    marked by care, and is rich in the happy accidents of expression which come only
                    to true artists. He liked the old classical models; he read and reread the
                    classics, ancient and modern, his taste being catholic enough to include Plato
                    and Chrysostom, Montaigne, Hume’s <hi rend="italic">Essays,</hi> Adam Smith’s
                    works, Ferguson’s <hi rend="italic">Essay on the History of Civil Society</hi>
                    (which he particularly admired), and the later developments of German
                    literature.</p>
                <p>Most of Thibaut’s works have already been mentioned. Several of them, however,
                    deserve further notice. And first as to his essay on the necessity of a code for
                    Germany (“Ueber die Noth Wendigkeit eines allgemeinen bürgerlichen Rechts für
                    Deutschland”). No more persuasive argument for codification was ever advanced.
                    It has all the vigour of Bentham’s arguments for the same cause, but is without
                    his pamphleteering recklessness of expression. Unlike Hugo, whose education
                    dated back to the time when French literature was supreme in Germany and who
                    felt himself somewhat a stranger to later German culture, Thibaut was of his own
                    time, sensitive to the great change which had come over Germany after the battle
                    of Leipsic, conscious of the insufficiency of Roman law, and eager to promote
                    the greatness of his country. In his contribution to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Archiv für</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic">civilistische
                    Praxis,</hi> in 1838, on “the so-called historical and unhistorical school,” he
                    tells the history of his memorable essay on the necessity of a code for Germany.
                    He had seen many German soldiers in 1814 about to march to Paris. He realized
                    the change which this denoted; and out of the fulness of his heart he wrote the
                    essay in a fortnight. The mode of treatment is more comprehensive than the
                    theme; and to-day, perhaps partly for this reason, the essay is as readable as
                    it ever was; jurists have not yet carried out all the suggestions which it
                    contains. For Germany, its soil freed and its honour vindicated, a happy future
                    had, he predicted, been opened up. ‘ ‘ The division into small states was
                    inevitable, and not to be deplored. The existence of great states is always in a
                    sense unnatural; it implies a warm life only at one point,—a constant repression
                    of individuals for a common object, and no real unity between the rulers and the
                    subjects. In a land of small states, on the other hand, the peculiarity of each
                    has full play; there is development of variety, and the unity of princes and
                    people is deeper and more living.” The only unity practicable and needful in
                    Thibaut’s judgment was one of law; and for such all the German Governments
                    should labour. His review of the state of jurisprudence in Germany is severe; it
                    recalls the contemporaneous criticisms passed by Bentham on English law. Thibaut
                    pointed out luminously the contrast between the fundamental conceptions of Roman
                    and German society, and the inadequacy of Roman law to supply defects in German
                    jurisprudence. It was not pleasing to many jurists to be told that a few
                    lectures on the laws of the Persians and Chinese would do more to awaken a true
                    judicial sense than minute disquisitions on the Roman laλv of intestacy—
                    observations the full effect of which Thibaut himself did not perhaps conceive.
                    The essay was as much a condemnation of the entire state of jurisprudence as an
                    argument for codification; it was a challenge to civilians to justify their very
                    existence. Savigny took up the challenge thus thrown down; and a long
                    controversy as to points not very clearly defined took place. The glory of the
                    controversy belonged to Savigny; the real victory rested with Thibaut. By recent
                    legislation Germany has carried out some of the ideas of Thibaut; and others
                    indicated but not developed in his essay remain to be completed by a scientific
                    school of jurists. One of his works best worth reading is his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Theory of Construction.</hi> Though directly applicable to Roman law, it is of
                    general use. The subject is divided into two branches—“Interpretation nach der
                    Absicht des Gesetzgeber” and “Interpretation nach dem Grunde des Gesetzes,” or,
                    as Austin expresses the distinction in a marginal note on his copy, “What the
                    legislator would have contemplated had he conceived his purpose completely and
                    distinctly, and what the legislator actually contemplated.” It would be
                    interesting to compare the rules of interpretation stated by Thibaut with the
                    rules of construction, familiar to English lawyers, laid down by Coke in
                    Heydon’s Case, 3, 7ð, <hi rend="italic">Reports.</hi> Thibaut’s best-known work
                    is on the Pandects <hi rend="italic">(System</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Pandektenrechts,</hi> 3 vols., 1803), a part of which was translated by
                    Lord-Justice Lindley. He was one of the earliest to criticize the divisions
                    found in the Institutes, and he carried on with Hugo a controversy as to these
                    points. Thibaut’s own classification earlier is unsatisfactory. He divided the
                    subject into public law (that which treats of the relations between Government
                    and subjects), private law, and international law. Public law he subdivided into
                    constitutional law <hi rend="italic">(Staatsrecht,</hi> the laws binding on the
                    sovereign) and administrative law <hi rend="italic">(Regierungsrecht,</hi> or
                    criminal law, and laws relating to finance and police). The laws relating to
                    civil process were dealt with partly under administrative law and partly under
                    private law. Status was placed partly in the former partly in the latter; and
                    the law as to guardianship and parental authority is treated as a part of the
                    law of police. Thibaut, however, abandoned in practice this unscientific
                    division. One of his most interesting works is his posthumous treatise on the
                    “Code Civil,” <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch des französischen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Civilrechts in</hi><hi rend="italic">steter Vergleichung mit dem römischen
                    Civil-recht.</hi> While criticizing the code, which he designates as in the
                    highest degree unsystematic, he recognizes in. it merits which German jurists of
                    his time were reluctant to admit.</p>
                <p>In modern German legal literature Thibaut’s influence is not very perceptible.
                    Even at Heidelberg it was quickly superseded by that of his successor, Vangerow,
                    and in Germany his works are now little used as text-books. But those best able
                    to judge Thibaut have most praised him. Austin, who owed much to him, describes
                    him as one “who for penetrating acuteness, rectitude of judgment and depth of
                    learning, and eloquence of exposition may be placed, by the side of Von Savigny,
                    at the head, of all living civilians ;” and elsewhere he praises Thibaut’s
                    indefatigable perseverance and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n319/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0319-0302"/> “sagacity not surpassable.” High though such
                    eulogies are, they are scarcely adequate. In Thibaut’s works are promises which
                    he did not fulfil, and they contain fertile suggestions which future jurists may
                    utilize. It was not the least of his merits that he introduced scientific
                    methods into legal practice and practical sense into jurisprudence. (J. M+.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
