<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0648-0627-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TURGAI (9th edition, volume 23, page 627)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847249">Cardium</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205592">Morocco</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n648/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TURGAI</label>, a Russian province in Central Asia, formerly
                    a part of the Kirghiz steppe, and now embodied in the governor-generalship of
                    the Steppes, is bounded by Uralsk and Orenburg on the W. and N., by Akmolinsk on
                    the E., and by Syr-Daria and the Sea of Aral on the S. This extensive and
                    irregularly-shaped territory, which has an area (176,800 square miles) as large
                    as that of Caucasia and Transcaucasia taken together, belongs to the
                    Aral-Caspian depression. It has, however, the Mugojar Hills on its western
                    border and includes a part of the southern Urals; and from Akmolinsk it is
                    separated by a range of hills which runs between the two chief rivers of the
                    Kirghiz steppe—the Turgai and the Sary-su. In the north it includes the low belt
                    of undulating land which stretches from the Mugojar Hills towards the north-east
                    and separates the rivers belonging to the Aral basin from those which flow
                    towards the Arctic Ocean, and beyond this range it embraces the upper Toboɫ. The
                    remainder is steppe land, sloping gently towards the Sea of Aral. The Mugojar
                    Hills consist of an undulating plateau nearly 1000 feet in height, built up of
                    Permian and Cretaceous deposits, and deeply grooved by rivers. They are not the
                    independent chain which our maps make them out to be<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See P. S. Nazaroff, in “Recherches
                    Zoologiques dans les Steppes des Kirghizes,” in <hi rend="italic">Bull. Soc. des
                    Natur. de Moscow,</hi> 1886, No. 4.</p></note>: they merely continue the Urals
                    towards the south, and are connected with the Ust Urt plateau by a range of
                    hills which was formerly an island of the Aral-Caspian Sea. Their northern
                    extremity joins the undulating plateau (400 to 600 feet), built up of sandstones
                    and marls, which separates the tributaries of the Toboɫ from those of the Ural,
                    and falls by a range of steep crags—probably an old shore-line of the Aral
                    basin—towards the steppes. The steppe land of Turgai is only some 300 feet above
                    the sea-level, and is dotted with lakes, of which the Tchoɫgar-denghiz, which
                    receives the Turgai and its tributary the Irghiz, is the largest. The Turgai
                    was, at a recent epoch, a large river flowing into the Sea of Aral and receiving
                    an extensive system of tributaries, which are now lost in the sands before
                    joining it. Remains of aquatic plants buried in the soil of the steppe, and
                    shells of <hi rend="italic">Mytilus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cardium,</hi>
                    both still found in the Sea of Aral, show that during the Glacial period this
                    region was covered by the waters of the Aral-Caspian Sea.</p>
                <p>The climate of Turgai is exceedingly dry and continental. Orsk, a town of
                    Orenburg, on its north-western border, has a January as cold as that of the west
                    coast of Nova Zembla ( - 4° Fahr.), while in July it is as hot as July in
                    Morocco (73°); the corresponding figures for Irghiz, in the centre of the
                    province, are 7° and 77°. At Irghiz and Orsk the annual rainfall is somewhat
                    under 10 and 12 inches respectively (3 inches in summer). The west winds are
                    desiccated before they reach the Turgai steppes, and the northeast winds, which
                    in winter bring cold, dry snows from Siberia, raise in summer formidable clouds
                    of sand. A climate so dry is of course incompatible with a vigorous forest
                    growth. There is some timber on the southern Urals, the Mugojar Hills, and the
                    waterparting of the Toboɫ; elsewhere trees are rare,—only shrubs, such as the
                    wild cherry (<hi rend="italic">Cerαsus Chamaecerasus)</hi> and the dwarf almond
                    (<hi rend="italic">Amygdalus nana)</hi> growing on the hilly slopes, while the
                    rich blackearth soil of the steppe is chiefly covered with feather grass (<hi
                    rend="italic">Stipa pennata),</hi> the well-known ornament of the south Russian
                    steppes. In spring the grass vegetation is luxuriant, and geese and cranes are
                    attracted in vast numbers by the fields of the Kirghiz from the depth of the
                    steppe. The jerboa (<hi rend="italic">Dipus jaculus)</hi> and the marmot (<hi
                    rend="italic">Spermophilus rufescens)</hi> are characteristic of the fauna of
                    the region; another species of marmot (<hi rend="italic">Arctomys bobac)</hi>
                    and the <hi rend="italic">Canis corsac</hi> are common; and the saiga antelope
                    of Central Asia is occasionally met with. Further south the black earth
                    disappears and with it the feather grass, its place being taken by its congener,
                    <hi rend="italic">Stipa capillata.</hi> Trees disappear, and among the bushes
                    along the banks of the rivers willows and the pseudo-acacia or Siberian pea tree
                    (<hi rend="italic">Caragana microphyla)</hi> are most prevalent. In the middle
                    parts of the province the clayey soil is completely clothed with wormwood (<hi
                    rend="italic">Artemisia fragrans</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A. monogyna),</hi>
                    with a few grassy plants on the banks of the rivers and lakes (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Lasiagrostis splendens, Alhagi camelorum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A.
                    kirghizorum, Obione portulacoides, Hali-modendrum argenteum)</hi>; while large
                    areas consist of shifting sands, salt clays clothed with a rich carpet of
                    various <hi rend="italic">Salsolaceae,</hi> and dried beds of old lakes. Such
                    lakes as still exist, notwithstanding the rapid desiccation now going on, are
                    surrounded by rush thickets, —the retreat of wild boars. Turgai is thus the
                    borderland between the flora of Europe and that of Central Asia.</p>
                <p>In 1882 the population of Turgai was estimated at 323,110, all nomad Kirghiz,
                    with the exception of some 3600, who are settled in four villages officially
                    described as towns. Agriculture is in its earliest stage of development; but
                    some 100,000 quarters of corn are raised in the south-west by the Kirghiz, who
                    sell some of it in Orenburg. Cattle-breeding is the chief occupation, and within
                    the province there are some 800,000 horses, 335,000 cattle, about 200,000
                    camels, and more than two million sheep. But the want of fodder in spring
                    occasions violent murrains, which sometimes result in actual famine among the
                    Kirghiz. Endeavours have recently been made to induce the people to make
                    communal stores of hay, but the 300,000 cwts. yearly collected in this way are
                    insufficient. The Kirghiz of the southern parts go in winter to the better
                    sheltered parts of Syr-Daria, while in the summer some 30,000 <hi rend="italic"
                    >kibitkas</hi> (felt tents) of nomads come from the neighbouring provinces to
                    graze their cattle on the grassy steppes of Turgai. Some 30,000 cwts. of salt
                    are annually got from the lakes. The four settlements of the province are
                    Turgai, chief town and seat of the provincial administration, with less than 400
                    inhabitants, and the “district towns” of Irghiz (920), Ak-tube (400), and
                    Kara-butak (300), the last two being more or less fortified. Several merchants
                    in these carry on trade with the Kirghiz, exchanging manufactured goods for wool
                    and skins, which are sent to the frontier settlements of Orenburg. There is a
                    brisk caravan traffic through Turgai.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
