<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0516-0497-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TRACY, Antoine Louis Claude Destutt, Comte de (9th
                    edition, volume 23, page 497)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095999">Restorationism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010769">Marshals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984609">Judgments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984572">Judgment</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n516/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TRACY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Antoine Louis Claude Destutt,
                    Comte de</hi></label> (1754-1836), was born in Bourbonnais on July 20, 1754. The
                    noble family to which he belonged was of Scottish descent, tracing its origin to
                    Walter Stutt, a gentleman who in 1420 accompanied the earls of Buchan and
                    Douglas to the court of France, and whose family afterwards rose to be counts of
                    Tracy. The father of Destutt de Tracy (as he is usually called) was a soldier,
                    and died a field-marshal. Destutt de Tracy began his studies under the
                    superintendence of his mother, and afterwards prosecuted them at the university
                    of Strasburg. During his student days, however, he was chiefly noted for his
                    skill in every kind of manly exercise. On leaving the university he embraced a
                    military career, in which his advance was rapid. When the Revolution broke,
                    Tracy, who was then thirty-five years of age, took an active part in the
                    provincial assembly of Bourbonnais. He was elected a deputy of the nobility to
                    the states-general, where he sat alongside of his friend La Fayette. In the
                    spring of 1792 he received the rank of field-marshal, along with the sole
                    command of the cavalry in the army of the North; but, as the conduct of affairs
                    fell more and more into the hands of the extremists, he took an indefinite leave
                    of absence, and settled with his family at Auteuil. Here, in the society of
                    Condorcet and Cabanis, he devoted himself to scientific studies. Under the Reign
                    of Terror he was arrested and imprisoned for nearly a year. It was his solitary
                    meditations at this period, we are told, which discovered to him his true bent.
                    Under the influence of Locke and Condillac he abandoned the natural sciences for
                    the study of mind. On the motion of Cabanis he was named associate of the
                    Institute in the class of the moral and political sciences. He soon began to
                    attract attention by the <hi rend="italic">mémoires</hi> which he read before
                    his colleagues—papers which formed the first draft of his comprehensive work on
                    ideology. The society of “ideologists” at Auteuil embraced, besides Cabanis and
                    Tracy, who have been called respectively the physiologist and the metaphysician
                    of the school, Volney, who has been called its moralist, and Garat, its
                    professor in the National Institute. Under the empire he was a member of the
                    senate, but took little part in its deliberations. Under the Restoration he
                    became a peer of France, but protested against the reactionary spirit of the
                    Government, and remained in opposition. In 1808 he was elected a member of the
                    French Academy in room of Cabanis, and in 1832 he was also named a member of the
                    Academy of Moral Sciences on its reorganization. He appeared, however, only once
                    at its conferences. He was old and nearly blind, and filled with sadness, it is
                    said, by the loss of his friends and the discredit into which his most firmly
                    cherished opinions had fallen. “His only distraction was to have Voltaire read
                    aloud to him.” He died at Paris on the 9th of March 1836.</p>
                <p>Destutt de Tracy was the last eminent representative of the sensualistic school
                    which Condillac founded in France upon a onesided interpretation of the
                    doctrines of Locke. He pushed the sensualistic principles of Condillac to their
                    last consequences, being in full agreement with the materialistic views of his
                    friend Cabanis, though the attention of the latter was devoted more to the
                    physiological, that of Tracy to the psychological or ‘ ‘ ideological” side of
                    man. His ideology, he frankly stated, formed “a part of zoology,” or, as we
                    should say, of biology. To think is to feel. The four faculties into which he
                    divides the conscious life—perception, memory, judgment, will—are all varieties
                    of sensation. Perception is sensation caused by a present affection of the
                    external extremities of the nerves; memory is sensation caused, in the absence
                    of present excitation, by dispositions of the nerves which are the result of
                    past experiences; judgment is the perception of relations between sensations,
                    and is itself a species of sensation, because if we are aware of the sensations
                    we must also be aware of the relations between them; will he identifies with the
                    feeling of desire, and therefore includes it as a variety of sensation. It is
                    easy to see that such conclusions ignore important distinctions, and are,
                    indeed, to a large extent an abuse of language. As a psychologist Destutt de
                    Tracy deserves credit for his distinction between active and passive touch,
                    which has developed into the modern theory of the muscular sense. His account of
                    the notion of external existence, as derived, not from pure sensation, but from
                    the experience of action on the one hand and resistance on the other, may be
                    compared with the account of Bain and later psychologists. Tracy worked up his
                    separate monographs extending over a number of years into the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Elements d'Idéologie</hi> (1817—18 and 1824-5), which presents his complete
                    doctrine. He also wrote in 1806 a <hi rend="italic">Commentaire sur l’Esprit des
                    Lois de Montesquieu,</hi> in which he argues ably in support of a free
                    constitution on grounds which hardly admit of being harmonized with his general
                    philosophical principles. The book was translated in America by his friend
                    President Jefferson, who recommended it for use in the colleges. The first
                    French edition appeared in 1817, and it was several times reprinted.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
