<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0121-0110-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TEGNÉR, Esaias (9th edition, volume 23, page
                    110)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t429">Palms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dp5n">Communion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1051793">Palms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n121/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TEGNÉR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Esaias</hi></label> (1782-1846),
                    the most celebrated of Swedish writers, was born November 13, 1782, at Kyrkerud
                    in Wermland. His father was a pastor, and his grandparents on both sides were
                    peasants. His father, whose name had been Esaias Luβasson, took the surname of
                    Γegnerus—altered by his fifth son, the poet, to Tegnér —from the hamlet of
                    Tegnaby in Smâland, where he was born. In 1799 Tegnér, hitherto educated in the
                    country, entered the university of Lund, where he graduated in philosophy in
                    1802, and continued as tutor until 1810, when he was elected Greek lecturer. In
                    1812 he was named professor, and continued to work as a lecturer in Lund until
                    1824, when he was made bishop of Wexiö. At Wexiö he remained until his death,
                    twenty-two years later. Tegnér’s early poems have little merit. He was
                    comparatively slow in development. His first great success was a dithyrambic
                    war-song for the army of 1808, which stirred every Swedish heart. In 1811 his
                    patriotic poem <hi rend="italic">Svea</hi> won the great prize of the Swedish
                    Academy, and made him famous. In the same year was founded in Stockholm the
                    Gothic League <hi rend="italic">{Götiska forbundet),</hi> a sort of club of
                    young and patriotic men of letters, of whom Tegnér quickly became the chief. The
                    club published a magazine, entitled <hi rend="italic">Iduna,</hi> in which it
                    printed a great deal of excellent poetry, and ventilated its views, particularly
                    as regards the study of old Icelandic literature and history. Tegnér, Geijer,
                    Afzelius, and Nicander became the most famous members of the Gothic League. Of
                    the very numerous poems written by Tegnér in the little room at Lund which is
                    now shown to visitors as the Tegnér museum, the majority are short, and even
                    occasional lyrics. His celebrated <hi rend="italic">Sony to the Sun</hi> dates
                    from 1817. He completed three poems of a more ambitious character, on which his
                    fame chiefly rests. Of these, two, the romance of <hi rend="italic">Axel</hi>
                    and the delicately-chiselled idyl of <hi rend="italic">Nattvards-barnen</hi>
                    (“The First Communion,” 1820), translated by Longfellow, take a secondary place
                    in comparison with Tegnér’s masterpiece, of world-wide fame. In 1820 he
                    published in <hi rend="italic">Iduna</hi> certain fragments of an epic or cycle
                    of epical pieces, on which he was then working, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Frithiofssaga</hi> or the Story of Frithiof. In 1822 he published five more
                    cantos, and in 1825 the entire poem. Before it was completed it was famous
                    throughout Europe; the aged Goethe took up his pen to commend to his countrymen
                    this “alte, kräftige, gigantisch-barbarische Dichtart,” and desired Amalie von
                    Imhoff to translate it into German. This romantic paraphrase of an ancient saga
                    was composed in twenty-four cantos, all differing in verse form, modelled
                    somewhat, it is only fair to say, on an earlier Danish masterpiece, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Helge</hi> of Oehlenschlagaer. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Frithiofssaga</hi> is the best known of all Swedish productions; it is said to
                    have been translated nineteen times into English, eighteen times into German,
                    and once at least into every European language. It is far from satisfying the
                    demands of more recent antiquarian research, but it still is allowed to give the
                    freshest existing impression, in imaginative form, of life in early Scandinavia.
                    In later years Tegnér began, but left unfinished, two important epical poems,
                    <hi rend="italic">Gerda</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Kroηbruden.</hi> The period
                    of the publication of <hi rend="italic">Frithiofssaga</hi> (1825) was the
                    critical epoch of his career. It made him one of the most famous poets of
                    Europe; it transferred him from his study in Lund to the bishop’s palace in
                    Wexiö; it marked the first breakdown of his health, which had hitherto been
                    excellent; and it witnessed a singular moral crisis in the inner history of the
                    poet, about which much has been written, but of vrhich little is known. Tegnér
                    was at this time passionately in love with a certain beautiful Euphrosyne Palm,
                    the wife of a town-councillor in Lund, and this unfortunate passion, while it
                    inspired much of his finest poetry, turned the poet’s blood to gall. From this
                    time forward the heartlessness of woman is one of Tegnér’s principal themes. It
                    is a remarkable sign of the condition of Sweden at that time that a man not in
                    holy orders, and so little in possession of the religious temperament as Tegnér,
                    should be offered and should accept a bishop’s crozier. He did not hesitate in
                    accepting it: it was a great honour; he was poor; and he was anxious to get away
                    from Lund. No sooner, however, had he begun to study for his new duties than he
                    began to regret the step he had taken. It was nevertheless too late to go back,
                    and Tegnér made a respectable bishop as long as his health lasted. But he became
                    moody and melancholy; as early <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n122/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0122-0111"/> as 1836 he complained of fiery heats in his
                    brain, and in 1840, during a visit to Stockholm, he suddenly became insane. He
                    was sent to an asylum in Schleswig, and early in 1841 he was cured, and able to
                    return to Wexiö. It was during his convalescence in Schleswig that he wrote <hi
                    rend="italic">Kronbruden.</hi> He wrote no more of importance; in 1843 he had a
                    stroke of apoplexy, and on the 2d of November 1846 he died in Wexiö. From 1819
                    he had been a member of the Swedish Academy, where he was succeeded by his
                    biographer and best imitator Böttiger. In prose Tegnér wrote letters, which have
                    been collected, and which are considered the best of their kind in the Swedish
                    language. As a poet he will scarcely be preferred to Bellman or to Runeberg by
                    Swedish verse amateurs, but he still exceeds these and all other writers in
                    popularity.</p>
                <p>See Böttiger, <hi rend="italic">Teckηiηg af Tegnérs Lcfnad</hi>; Georg Brandes,
                    <hi rend="italic">Esaias Tegnér·,</hi> Thomander, <hi rend="italic">Tankar οch
                    Lδjen.</hi> (E. W. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
