<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0540-0521-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TRANSYLVANIA (9th edition, volume 23, page 521)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964057">Hungarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:814767">Armenians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4px50">Roumanian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n540/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TRANSYLVANIA</label> (Germ. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Siebenbürgen),</hi> a mountainous principality (Gross-Fürstenthum) forming the
                    extreme eastern portion of Austria-Hungary, is bounded on the W. and N. by
                    Hungary proper, on the E. by Bukowina and Moldavia, and on the S. by Walachia.
                    The German name is usually derived from the seven principal fortified towns or
                    “burgs” founded by the German colonists, though some authorities prefer to
                    connect it with the Zibin Mountains on the south frontier. The Latin name
                    appears first after the 12th century, and signifies “beyond the woods,” <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> from Hungary; the Magyar and Roumanian names (Erdély
                    and Ardealu) both mean “forest-land.” For all political and administrative ends,
                    and in the official statistics and returns, Transylvania is now wholly
                    incorporated with <hi rend="smallcaps">Hungary</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(q.v.),</hi> and to all intents and purposes is a part of that kingdom. The
                    principality has the form of an irregular circle, with an area of about 21,000
                    square miles, and is on all sides surrounded by mountain chains, while the
                    interior is barred and striped with lower ranges. On the west or Hungarian side
                    there are various wide and comparatively easy passes into the interior, but on
                    the east and south frontiers the lofty bounding mountains present steep and
                    rugged faces outwards, giving to Transylvania the general aspect of a huge
                    natural fortress. These mountains are a continuation of the Hungarian and
                    Galician Carpathians; in fact, the mountains of Transylvania may be regarded
                    together as forming the southeastern main group of the Carpathian system. The
                    loftiest and most rugged peaks are on the north and south boundaries. On the
                    north the highest summit is the Pietross (7534 feet), one of the Rodna Alps; on
                    the south are the Butshetsh (8262 feet), the Königstein (7357 feet), and the
                    Negoi (8340 feet). The east is bounded by several parallel chains, the highest
                    peak in which is the Pietrossul (6910 feet); and on the west border the greatest
                    height is attained towards the south, where several peaks reach 7200 feet. On
                    the west are the Transylvanian Ore Mountains (Erzgebirge), with the curious
                    Detunata (“thunder-smit ”), and the Bihar group, with its numerous caverns.
                    There are numerous valleys, ravines, and canons in the network of mountains
                    covering the interior of the country, but it is only along the courses of the
                    principal rivers that plains of any size are found. The chief rivers are the
                    Aluta or Alt, which flows south, pierces the southern boundary mountains at the
                    Rother Thurm Pass, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n541/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0541-0522"/> and joins the Danube, and the Maros, to the west,
                    and the Szamos, to the north, both tributaries of the Theiss, which also falls
                    into the Danube. All these are navigable, and are fed by various tributaries.
                    The largest lake is the Hodoser or Eseger See, 13 miles long. Transylvania
                    abounds in mineral springs of all kinds, especially saline and chalybeate. The
                    climate is tolerably severe: hot summers alternate with very cold winters; but
                    the rainfall is not great.</p>
                <p>The mineral wealth of Transylvania is very considerable. Gold is found in certain
                    quantity in mines, and it is also “washed” in some of the streams, chiefly by
                    Gipsies. The gold is often found in conjunction with tellurium (first discovered
                    in Transylvania in 1782, and until the present century not found anywhere else,
                    see <hi rend="smallcaps">Tellurium).</hi> Silver, copper, lead, and iron are
                    also worked to some profit. Coal occurs in considerable abundance, and it is
                    mined in the Schilthal, but the superabundance of timber has retarded its
                    exploitation. Hills largely formed of pure salt are met with here and there, and
                    there are also very rich subterranean deposits of salt, sometimes cropping up on
                    the surface. Some of the saline springs also yield salt enough to render their
                    evaporation profitable. The vegetation of Transylvania is luxuriant, except of
                    course in the higher mountain zones. Fruits abound, as apples, pears, peaches,
                    apricots, plums, cherries, chestnuts, and almonds; mulberries are also
                    cultivated. The vine flourishes best in the valley of the Maros. Agriculture is
                    one of the most important industries, though the available good land is by no
                    means fully taken up. The chief crop is maize; but wheat, rye, and other grains,
                    potatoes, saffron, hemp, flax, and tobacco are also grown. Extensive forests
                    clothe much of the country, but are in a somewhat neglected condition. On the
                    boundary mountains the trees are mainly coniferous; in the interior oaks, elms,
                    beeches, and ashes are conspicuous.</p>
                <p>The forests afford cover for many wild animals. Bears, wolves, foxes, boars, and
                    various varieties of game are found, and on some of the mountains the chamois.
                    There is abundant pasturage on which excellent cattle are reared; and in some
                    districts buffaloes are bred for draught purposes. More important is the
                    breeding of a sturdy race of horses, thousands of which are annually exported.
                    The mountains maintain very large flocks of sheep, of which two kinds are
                    distinguished—with a fine short-stapled and a coarse long-stapled wool
                    respectively. Silkworms are bred, and some silk is spun; and the export of honey
                    and wax, from both wild and domestic bees, is not inconsiderable. Neither the
                    means of communication with the external world nor the manufacturing industry in
                    Transylvania is developed to any important extent; the latter, indeed, has to a
                    certain extent gone back. The most industrious and in general the most advanced
                    of the population are the “Saxons”; and trade, the great bulk of which is with
                    Roumania, is mainly in the hands of Armenians and Greeks. The chief commercial
                    centres and principal towns are Herrmannstadt, Kronstadt, Bistritz, and
                    Szamos-Ujvar.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the most interesting point in connexion with Transylvania is the variety
                    of its population, which in 1880 numbered 2,084,048 in all. Until 1848 the chief
                    influence and privileges, as well as the only political rights, were divided
                    among the three “privileged nations” of the Hungarians, Szeklers, and Saxons.
                    The first are the descendants of the Magyar conquerors. The Szeklers, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> “guardians,” chiefly on the east borders, settled in
                    eastern Transylvania to act as guardians of the frontiers. The Saxons are the
                    posterity of the German immigrants brought by King Geisa II. (1141-1161) from
                    Flanders and the lower Rhine to cultivate and repeople his desolated
                    territories. At first these were known as Teutones, Teutonici Hospites, and
                    Flandrenses, but since the beginning of the 13th century the general name of
                    “Saxons,” as tantamount to “Germans,” has prevailed <hi rend="italic"
                    >(cf.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Saxony,</hi> vol. xxi. p. 351). The Hungarians
                    and Szeklers together number 609,208, and the Saxons 204,713, but by far the
                    most numerous element, though long excluded from power and political equality,
                    is formed by the Walachians or Roumanians, 1,146,611 in number, a mixed race,
                    not entitled to the descent which they claim from the early Roman colonists of
                    Dacia. The Gipsies of Transylvania, who are heard of under a voivode or prince
                    of their own in 1417, are estimated at 46,460; many of them have abandoned a
                    nomadic life and have taken to agriculture or gold-washing. Jews, Armenians,
                    Bulgarians, Ruthenians, and Greeks are also represented in the medley of
                    peoples. About 70,000 (chiefly children) are returned, unclassed, as “not able
                    to speak.” The Magyars are mostly Roman Catholics or Unitarians, the Germans
                    Protestants, and the Roumanians adherents of the Greek Church.</p>
                <p>Transylvania formed part of the Roman province of Dacia. After the withdrawal of
                    the Romans the country became for centuries the prey of the various peoples who
                    swept across it in their restless migrations. At the beginning of the 11th
                    century (1004) Stephen I. of Hungary made himself master of the land, which was
                    thenceforward governed as an Hungarian province by a voivode. In 1538 the
                    voivode, John Zapolya, succeeded in rendering himself independent, and he and
                    his successors, who were generally elected by the people, were supported by the
                    Turks against the house of Austria, while the difficult nature of their country
                    preserved them on the other hand from becoming too dependent on their powerful
                    allies. After the defeat of the Turks at Vienna in 1683, their influence in
                    Transylvania waned, and in 1699, by the peace of Carlowitz, the Porte
                    acknowledged the suzerainty of Leopold I. of Austria over Transylvania. By the
                    Leopoldine diploma of 1691 Leopold had guaranteed the ancient rights and laws of
                    the land, and united it formally with the Hungarian crown. In 1765 Maria Theresa
                    made it a grand principality (Gross-Fürstenthum). The efforts of the Roumanian
                    inhabitants to secure recognition as a fourth “nation,” and the opposition of
                    the non-Magyar population to a closer union with Hungary, led to troubles and
                    disagreement early in the 19th century, culminating in bloody internecine
                    struggles in 1848. In 1849 Transylvania was divided from Hungary by an imperial
                    decree, and became an Austrian crown-land; but in 1860 the old order was
                    renewed, and the complete incorporation with Hungary was perfected in 1868.
                    Since that time the policy of the Hungarian party has on the whole prevailed,
                    and the Magyarization of the principality is steadily being carried through, in
                    spite of the bitter protests and discontent of both the Saxons and Roumanians.
                    An Hungarian university was founded at Klausenburg in 1872; and Hungarian is
                    recognized as the official language. (F. MU.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
