<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0197-0184-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TEREDO (9th edition, volume 23, page 184)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:959074">Home</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1353235">Homes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033950">Nats</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158581">Tubes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1119669">Siphons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115719">Shells</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp7r">Home</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68d53">Tubes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205459">Algeria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n197/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TEREDO</label>, a genus of Larnellibranchiate <hi
                    rend="italic">Mollusca,</hi> of the order <hi rend="italic">Isomya,</hi>
                    sub-order <hi rend="italic">Sinupallia,</hi> family <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pholadacea</hi> (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mollusca,</hi> vol. xvi. p. 685). The
                    animals included in this genus are commonly known as “ship-worms,” and are
                    notorious for the destruction which they cause in ships’ timbers, the woodwork
                    of harbours, and piles or other wood immersed for a long period in the sea. They
                    inhabit long cylindrical holes, which they excavate in the wood, and usually
                    occur in great numbers, crowded together so that often only a very thin film
                    remains between the adjacent burrows. Each burrow is lined with a layer of
                    calcareous substance secreted by the mollusc; this lining is not usually
                    complete, but stops short a little distance from the inner end of the burrow,
                    where the boring process continues to take place. In some burrows, however, the
                    lining is complete, either because the animal has reached its full size or
                    because some cause prevents it continuing its tunnel; in such cases the
                    calcareous tube has a hemispherical termination. The burrows are usually driven
                    in the direction of the grain of the, wood, but not invariably so. When a knot
                    or nail or the tube of a neighbour is reached, the course of the burrow is
                    altered so as to bend round the obstruction. One burrow is never found to break
                    into another.</p>
                <p>The adult <hi rend="italic">Teredo,</hi> when removed from its burrow and
                    calcareous tube, is from a few inches to 3 feet in length, according to the
                    species to which it belongs, and is cylindrical and worm-like in appearance. The
                    anterior end, which lies at the bottom of the burrow, is somewhat enlarged and
                    bears a pair of shells or valves, which are not connected by the usual ligament,
                    but are widely separated dorsally. The valves are triangular in shape and very
                    concave on the side which is in contact w ith the animal. In front their edges
                    are widely separated, and the mantle tube, which is elsewhere closed, has here a
                    slight median aperture, through which the short sucker-like foot can be
                    protruded. The next portion of the body behind the shell-bearing part is naked,
                    except for the shelly lining of the burrow, which is secreted by this part.
                    Anteriorly this portion contains part of the body proper; posteriorly it forms a
                    tube divided internally by a horizontal partition into two chambers. In the
                    lower chamber are the elongated gill plates, which have the typical
                    larnellibranchiate structure. In the upper chamber anteriorly is the rectum. A
                    thick muscular ring terminates this region of the body, and bears two calcareous
                    plates shaped like spades or battledores. The expanded parts of these plates are
                    free and project backwards; the handle is fixed in a deep socket or pit lined by
                    epidermis. These calcareous plates are called pallets (Fr. <hi rend="italic"
                    >palmules).</hi> Behind the pallets the tubular body bifurcates, forming two
                    siphons similar to those of other Lamellibranchs; the siphons can be contracted
                    or expanded within wide limits of length. The principal organs of the
                    body—stomach, heart, generative organs, and nephridia—are situated in the
                    anterior part of the body, forming a visceral mass, which extends some distance
                    behind the valves. The heart is above the intestine and not perforated by it.
                    The two valves are connected by an anterior adductor muscle.</p>
                <p>From its resemblance to <hi rend="italic">Phοlαs, Teredo</hi> is placed by
                    conchologists in the family <hi rend="italic">Pholadidae,</hi> among the <hi
                    rend="italic">Isomya</hi>; but it is still undecided<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n198/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0198-0185"/> which part of the body corresponds to the
                    posterior adductor. According to Quatrefages, it is a muscular band passing
                    transversely between the handles of the pallets. His discussion of this point is
                    connected with another, namely, the nature of the long tubular portion of the
                    body behind the valves. Deshayes limits the extent of the mantle to the part
                    covered by the shell, and considers all the rest of the animal as formed by the
                    siphons; the branchiae and part of the other viscera in this view are contained
                    in the siphons. Quatrefages argues that the siphons commence at the point where
                    their retractor muscles are inserted, namely, at the muscular ring corresponding
                    to the pallets. This reasoning is plausible; but it is difficult to accept the
                    view that the retractor muscles of the siphons and the posterior adductor muscle
                    are so closely connected as Quatrefages thinks; in other <hi rend="italic"
                    >Isomya</hi> the retractors of the siphons and the posterior adductor are
                    distinct and separate. Deshayes believes that the single adductor between the
                    valves results from the fusion of the two muscles usually separate. Jeffreys
                    believes that the posterior adductor is really present between the posterior
                    parts of the valves; but the opinion of a conchologist on a question of
                    morphology is not of very great weight. In other <hi rend="italic">Isomya</hi>
                    the visceral (parieto-splanchnic) ganglia are attached to the ventral surface of
                    the posterior adductor. In <hi rend="italic">Teredo</hi> these ganglia are
                    situated at the posterior end of the body proper, some distance behind the
                    shells, and immediately behind the generative organ. It is here probably that
                    the rudiment of the posterior adductor, if it exists, is to be sought; or, if it
                    does not exist, it is here that it originally was placed.</p>
                <p>It is evident that the anatomy of <hi rend="italic">Teredo</hi> has not yet been
                    investigated from the point of view of modern morphology; but as far as can be
                    judged at present the body proper extends back some distance behind the shells,
                    to the posterior limit of the visceral mass. The part between this and the
                    pallets is a tubular prolongation of the mantle chamber containing the extended
                    gill laminae, and beyond the pallets are the separate siphons. Besides the
                    visceral ganglia a cerebral and a pedal pair are present. The stomach is
                    provided with a large crystalline style. The function of the pallets is to form
                    an operculum to the calcareous tube when the siphons are withdrawn into it. In
                    some species the external or narrower end of the calcareous tube is provided
                    with transverse laminae projecting into the lumen; and in some the external
                    aperture is divided by a horizontal partition into two, one for each siphon.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Teredo,</hi> according to Quatrefages, is dioecious, though
                    Gwyιι Jeffreys believes it to be hermaphrodite. As in the case of the oyster,
                    the ova are retained in the branchial chamber during the early stages of their
                    development. The segmentation of the ovum is unequal, and leads to the formation
                    of a gastrula by epibole. By the growth of a preoral lobe provided with a ring
                    of cilia, and by the formation of a mouth and an anus, the trochosphere stage is
                    reached. A pair of thin shells then appear on the sides of the larva, connected
                    by a hinge on the dorsal median line, and the foot grows out between mouth and
                    anus. By the time the larvae “swarm,” or leave the branchial cavity of the
                    parent to live for a time as free-swimming pelagic larvae, the valves of the
                    shell have grown so large as to cover the whole of the body when the velum is
                    retracted; the foot is also long, cylindrical, and flexible, and can be
                    protruded far beyond the shell. The valves of the shell at this stage are
                    hemispherical in shape, so that the whole larva when its organs are retracted is
                    contained in a globular case.</p>
                <p>Concerning the later changes of the larva and the method by which it bores into
                    wood nothing or little is known from direct observation. Much has been written
                    about the boring of this and other marine animals, but even yet the matter
                    cannot be said to be satisfactorily elucidated. Osler, in a paper in <hi
                    rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1826, argued that the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Teredo</hi> bores by means of its shells, fixing itself by the surface of the
                    foot, which it uses as a sucker, and then rasping the wood with the rough front
                    edges of the shell-valves. This view was founded on the similarity of the
                    arrangement of the shells and muscles in <hi rend="italic">Teredo</hi> to those
                    occurring in <hi rend="italic">Photos,</hi> in which the method of boring
                    described was actually observed. W. Thompson, in a paper in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Edinb. New Phil. Joum.,</hi> 1835, supported the view that the
                    excavation is due to the action of a solvent secreted from the surface of the
                    animal. Albany Hancock, again <hi rend="italic">''Ann. and Mag. Nah Hist.,</hi>
                    vol. xv. ), thinks that the excavating power of <hi rend="italic">Teredo</hi> is
                    due to silicious particles embedded in the anterior portion of the integument,
                    in front of the valves. But the actual existence of either silicious particles
                    or acid secretion has been denied by others. Jeffreys believes that the foot is
                    the organ by which the animal burrows. In the larger number of Lamellibranchs
                    the foot is doubtless a burrowing organ, and it is difficult to see how the
                    limpet hollows out the rock to which it is attached if not by means of the
                    surface of its foot. At the same time it is difficult to explain how the soft
                    muscular foot can penetrate into hard wood. The process is of course slow, and
                    Jeffreys supposes that particles are detached one by one from the moistened
                    surface to which the foot is applied. In any case the valves are covered by an
                    epidermis, which could scarcely be there if they were used in burrowing.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Teredo</hi> grows and burrows at an extremely rapid rate:
                    spawning takes place in the spring and summer, and before the end of the year
                    the animals are adult and their burrows of large size. Quatrefages relates that
                    at Guipuzcoa (N. Spain) a ferry-boat was sunk accidentally in the spring, and
                    was raised four months afterwards, when its timbers were already rendered
                    useless by <hi rend="italic">T. pedicellata.</hi> How long the animals live is
                    not accurately known, but Quatrefages found that they nearly all perished in the
                    winter. This cannot be generally the case, as the size of the tubes varies so
                    greatly. In Holland their greatest ravages are made in July and August. Iron
                    ships have nothing to fear from their attacks, and the copper sheathing now
                    almost universally used protects wooden hulls. A great deal of loss is, however,
                    caused by <hi rend="italic">Teredo</hi> in harbour works and shipping stages,
                    and the embankments in Holland are continually injured by it. The most efficient
                    protection is afforded by large-headed nails driven in in close proximity.
                    Soaking wood in creasote is not a certain safeguard; Jeffreys found at
                    Christiania in 1863 that a large number of harbour piles previously soaked in
                    creasote had been completely destroyed by <hi rend="italic">T. navalis.</hi>
                    Coal tar and the silicate of lime, used for coating stonework, have been
                    suggested as protective coverings, but they do not seem to have been adequately
                    tested.</p>
                <p>Species of <hi rend="italic">Teredo</hi> occur in all seas. The animal was known
                    to the ancients and is mentioned by Theophrastus, Pliny, and Ovid. In 1715 it is
                    mentioned by Valisnieri, in 1720 by Deslandes. In 1733 great attention was drawn
                    to it on account of the discovery that the wooden dykes of Holland were being
                    rapidly destroyed by ship-worms, and that the country was in danger of
                    inundation. Three treatises were published concerning the animal, by P. Massuet,
                    J. Rousset, and Godfrey Sellius. The work of the last-named, which was the best,
                    described the anatomy of the creature and showed that its affinities were with
                    bivalve molluscs. The truth of Sellius’s view was not grasped by Linnaeus, who
                    placed <hi rend="italic">Teredo</hi> together with <hi rend="italic"
                    >Serpula</hi> in the genus <hi rend="italic">Dentalvu/rn</hi>; but its proper
                    position was re-established by Cuvier and Lamarck. Adanson, unaware of the work
                    of Sellius, in 1757 believed himself to be the first to discover the molluscan
                    affinities of <hi rend="italic">Teredo.</hi> It will not be necessary to give
                    here a definition of the genus taken from any systematist; it will be sufficient
                    to point out that the long cylindrical body with its two small anterior
                    polygonal valves, the absence of a ligament and accessory valves, the muscular
                    ring into which are inserted the calcareous pallets, and the continuous
                    calcareous tube lining the hole bored by the animal are the diagnostic
                    features.</p>
                <p>Jeffreys, in his <hi rend="italic">British Conchology,</hi> gives the following
                    species as British:— <hi rend="italic">Teredo norvegica,</hi> Spengler; <hi
                    rend="italic">T. navalis,</hi> Linn.; <hi rend="italic">T. pedicellata,</hi>
                    Quatrefages; <hi rend="italic">T. megotara,</hi> Hanley. <hi rend="italic">T.
                    norvegica</hi> occurs chiefly on the west coast of Great Britain. It was taken
                    by Thompson at Portpatrick in Wigtownshire, and occurred in Jef-reys’s time in
                    abundance at Milford Haven. This species has been described by Gmelin and a
                    number of British authors as <hi rend="italic">T. navalis,</hi> Linn. It is
                    distinguished by having the base of the pallets simple, not forked, and the tube
                    semi-concamerated at its narrower posterior end. The length does not usually
                    exceed a foot. It is the <hi rend="italic">T. navium</hi> of Sellius. <hi
                    rend="italic">T. navalis</hi> has been identified from the figures of Sellius,
                    to which Linnaeus referred; Sellius called it <hi rend="italic">T. marina.</hi>
                    It occurs on all the western and southern coasts of Europe, from Christiania to
                    the Black Sea, and is the species which causes so much damage to the Dutch
                    embankments. The pallets of this species are small and forked, and the stalk is
                    cylindrical. The tube is simple and not chambered at its narrow end. <hi
                    rend="italic">T. pedicellata</hi> was originally discovered by Quatrefages in
                    the Bay of Los Pasages on the north coast of Spain; it has also been found in
                    the Channel Islands, at Toulon, in Provence, and in Algeria. In <hi
                    rend="italic">T. megotara</hi> the tube is simple and the pallets like those of
                    <hi rend="italic">T. norvegica</hi>; it occurs at Shetland and Wick, and also on
                    the western shore of the Atlantic, where its range extends from Massachusetts to
                    South Carolina. <hi rend="italic">T. malleolus,</hi> Turton, and <hi
                    rend="italic">T. bipinnata,</hi> Turton, belong to the West Indies, but are
                    often drifted in floating timber to the coasts of Europe. Other occasional
                    visitants to the British shores are <hi rend="italic">T. excavata, bipartita,
                    spatha, fusticulus, cucullata,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fimbriata.</hi> These
                    were described by Gwyn Jeffreys in <hi rend="italic">Ann. and Mag. Nah
                    Hist.,</hi> 1860. <hi rend="italic">T. fimbriata</hi> is stated to be a native
                    of Vancouver’s Island. A kind of ship-worm, the <hi rend="italic">Nausitora
                    dunlopei</hi> of Perceval Wright, has been discovered in India, 70 miles from
                    the sea, in a stream of perfectly fresh water, namely, the river Kumar, one of
                    the branches of the Ganges. <hi rend="italic">T. corniformis,</hi> Lam., is
                    found burrowing in the husks of cocoa-nuts and other woody fruits floating in
                    the tropical seas; its tubes are extremely crooked and contorted for want of
                    space. Fossil wood and palm-fruits of Sheppey and Brabant are pierced in the
                    same way.</p>
                <p>Twenty-four fossil species have been recognized in the Lias and succeeding beds
                    of Europe and the United States. The sub-genus <hi rend="italic">Teredina,</hi>
                    Lam., is a fossil of the Eocene of Great Britain and France.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> See, besides the works already mentioned,
                    Godfrey Sellius, <hi rend="italic">Historia Naturalis Teredinis seu Xyloρhagi
                    Marini,</hi> 1733; Adanson, <hi rend="italic">Histoire Naturelle du
                    Sénégal,</hi> Paris, 1757; Quatrefages, <hi rend="italic">Annales des Sei.
                    Nat.,</hi> 1848-50; <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n199/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0199-0186"/> Forbes and Hanley, <hi rend="italic">Brit.
                    Mollusca,</hi> 1853; B. Hatschek, <hi rend="italic">Entwicklungv. Teredo:
                    Arbeiten aus dem Zool. Inst. Wien,</hi> 1880; Deshayes, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mollusques d’Algérie</hi>; Sir E. Home, “Anatomy of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Teredo,"</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi> vol. xcvi.; Frey and
                    L·euckart, <hi rend="italic">Beiträge zur Kenutniss wirbelloser Thiere,</hi>
                    1847; woodward, <hi rend="italic">Manual of Mollusca,</hi> London, 1851. (J. T.
                    C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
