<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0506-0487-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TOURACO (9th edition, volume 23, page 487)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vc4w">Feathers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s253">Albinism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10v2q">Crows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q760">Jays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:922098">Feathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n506/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TOURACO</label>, the name, evidently already in use, under
                    which in 1743 Edwards figured a pretty African bird,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Apparently the first ornithologist to make
                    the bird known was Albin, who figured it in 1738 from the life, yet badly, as "
                    The Crownbird of Mexico.” He had doubtless been misinformed as to its proper
                    country; but Touracos were called “Crown-birds” by the Europeans in West Africa,
                    as witness Bosman’s <hi rend="italic">Description of the Coast of Guinea</hi>
                    (1721), ed. 2, p. 251, and W. Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Voyage to Guinea</hi>
                    (1745), p. 149, though the name was also given to the Crowned Cranes, <hi
                    rend="italic">Balearica.</hi></p></note> and presumably that applied to it in
                    Guinea, whence it had been brought alive. It is the <hi rend="italic">Cuculus
                    persa</hi> of Linnseus, and <hi rend="italic">Turacus</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Corythaix persa</hi> of later authors, who perceived that it required generic
                    separation. Cuvier, in 1799 or 1800, Latinized its native name (adopted in the
                    meanwhile by both French and German writers) as above, for which barbarous term
                    liliger, in 1811, substituted a more classical word. In 1788 Isert described and
                    figured <hi rend="italic">(Beobacht. Gesellsch. naturf. Freunde,</hi> iii. pp.
                    16-20, pl. 1) a bird, also from Guinea, which he called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Musophaga violacea.</hi> Its affinity to the original Touraco was soon
                    recognized, and both forms have been joined by modern systematists in the Family
                    <hi rend="italic">Musophagidae,</hi> commonly Englished Plantain-eaters or
                    Touracos, sometimes spelt Tourakoos.</p>
                <p>To take first the Plantain-eaters proper, or the genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Musophaga,</hi> of which only two species are known. One about the size of a
                    Crow is comparatively common in museums, and is readily recognized by having the
                    horny base of its fine yellow bill prolonged backwards over the forehead in a
                    kind of shield. The top of the head, and the primaries, except their outer edge
                    and tip, are deep crimson; a white streak extends behind the eye; and the rest
                    of the plumage is of a rich glossy purple. The second species, <hi rend="italic"
                    >AL rossae,</hi> which is rare, chiefly differs by wanting the white eye-streak.
                    Then of the Touracos—the species originally described is about the size of a
                    Jay, and has the head, crest (which is vertically compressed and tipped with
                    red), neck, and breast of a fine grass-green, varied by two conspicuous white
                    streaks—one, from the gape to the upper part of the crimson orbit, separated by
                    a black patch from the other, which runs beneath and behind the eye. The
                    wingcoverts, lower part of the back, and tail are of a bright steel-purple, the
                    primaries deep crimson, edged and tipped with bluish-black. Over a dozen other
                    congeneric species, more or less resembling this, have now been described, and
                    all inhabit some district of Africa; but there is only room here to mention that
                    found in the Cape Colony and Natal, where it is known as the “Lory” <hi
                    rend="italic">(cf.</hi> vol. xv. p. 7, note 1), and, though figured by Daubenton
                    and others, first differentiated in 1841 by Strickland <hi rend="italic">(Ann.
                    Nat. History,</hi> vii. p. 33) as <hi rend="italic">Turacus albicristatus—</hi>
                    its crest having a conspicuous white border, while the steel-purple of <hi
                    rend="italic">T. persa</hi> is replaced by a rich and glossy bluish-green of no
                    less beauty. In nearly all the species of this genus the nostrils are almost
                    completely hidden by the frontal feathers; but there are two others in which,
                    though closely allied, this is not the case, and some systematists would place
                    them in a separate genus <hi rend="italic">Gallirex;</hi> while another species,
                    the giant of the Family, has been moved into a third genus as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Corythaeola cristata.</hi> This differs from any of the foregoing by the
                    absence of the crimson coloration of the primaries, and seems to lead to another
                    group, <hi rend="italic">Schizorrhis,</hi> in which the plumage is of a still
                    plainer type, and, moreover, the nostrils here are not only exposed but in the
                    form of a slit, instead of being oval as in all the rest. This genus contains
                    about half a dozen species, one of which, <hi rend="italic">S. concolor,</hi> is
                    the Grey Touraco of the colonists in Natal, and is of an almost uniform
                    slaty-brown. A good deal has been written about these birds, which form the
                    subject of one of the most beautiful monographs ever published <hi rend="italic"
                    >—De Toerako's afgebeld en beschreven,—</hi> by Schlegel and Westerman, brought
                    out at Amsterdam in 1860; while the latest collected information is contained in
                    an elaborate essay by Herr Schalow <hi rend="italic">(Jour. f.
                    Ornithologie,</hi> 1886, pp. 1-77). Still, much remains to be made known as to
                    their distribution throughout Africa, and their habits. They seem to be all
                    fruit-eaters, and to frequent the highest trees, seldom coming to the ground.
                    Very little can be confidently asserted as to their nidification, but at least
                    one species of <hi rend="italic">Schizorrhis</hi> is said to make a rough nest
                    and therein lay three eggs of a pale blue colour. An extraordinary peculiarity
                    attends the crimson coloration which adorns the primaries of so many of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Musophagidae.</hi> So long ago as 1818, Jules Verreaux observed
                    <hi rend="italic">(Proc. Zool. Society,</hi> 1871, p. 40) that in the case of
                    <hi rend="italic">T. albicristatus</hi> this beautiful hue vanishes on exposure
                    to heavy rain and reappears only after some interval of time and when the
                    feathers are dry.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    fact of this colouring matter being soluble in water was incidentally mentioned
                    at a meeting of the Zoological Society by Mr Tegetmeier, and brought to the
                    notice of Prof. Church, who, after experiment, published in 1868 <hi
                    rend="italic">(Student and Intellectual Observer,</hi> i. pp. 161-168) an
                    account of it as “Turacin, a new animal pigment containing copper.” Further
                    information on the subject was given by Monteiro <hi rend="italic">(Chem.
                    News,</hi> xxviii. p. 201; <hi rend="italic">Quart. Jour. Science,</hi> ser. 2,
                    iv. p. 132). The property is possessed by the crimson feathers of all the birds
                    of the Family.</p></note></p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Musophagidae</hi> form a very distinct Family of Prof.
                    Huxley’s <hi rend="italic">Coccygomorphae,</hi> having perhaps the <hi
                    rend="italic">Coliidae</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cuculidae</hi> as their
                    nearest allies. Eyton pointed out <hi rend="italic">(Ann. Nat. History,</hi>
                    ser. 3, ii. p. 458) a feature possessed in common by the latter and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Musophagidae,</hi> in the “process attached to the anterior edge
                    of the ischium,” which he likened to the so-called “marsupial” bones of
                    Didelphian Mammals. J. T. Reinhardt has also noticed (<hi rend="italic">Vidensk.
                    Meddels. Naturhist. Forening,</hi> 1871, pp. 326-341) another Cuculine character
                    offered by the <hi rend="italic">os uncinatum</hi> affixed <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n507/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0507-0488"/> to the lower side of the ethmoid in the
                    Plantain-eaters and Touracos; but too much dependence must not be placed on
                    that, since a similar structure is presented by the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Frigate-bird</hi> (vol. ix. p. 786) and the <hi rend="smallcaps">Petrels</hi>
                    (vol. xviii. p. 711). A corresponding process seems also to be found in <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Trogon</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi> The bill of nearly
                    all the species of <hi rend="italic">Musophagidae</hi> is curiously serrated or
                    denticulated along the margin, and the feet have the outer toe reversible. No
                    member of the Family is found outside of the continental portion of the
                    Ethiopian Region. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
