<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0426-0407-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TIRYNS (9th edition, volume 23, page 407)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m29x">Dorians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896967">Dorians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938950">Gates</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n426/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TIRYNS</label>, the Típws τ∈ιχι&lt;feσ&lt;rα, of Homer (77.,
                    ii. 559), was a small Peloponnesian city, in the prehistoric period of the
                    Achaean race, long before the Dorian immigration. It stood on a small rock in
                    the marshy plain of Argolis, about 3 miles from the sea, and was fabled to have
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n427/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0427-0408"/> been founded by King Praetus, the brother of
                    Acrisius, who was succeeded by the hero Perseus. It was the scene of the early
                    life of Heracles, who is hence called Tirynthius. The massive walls were said to
                    have been the work of Cyclopean masons. Its period of greatest splendour was
                    during the 11th and 10th centuries B.c.; but the city continued to exist till
                    about 468 B.c., when it was destroyed through the jealousy of the inhabitants of
                    the neighbouring Argos,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Homer (Il., ii. 559) speaks of the Tirynthians as subject to
                    Argos.</p></note> who had not assisted in the final defeat of the Persians at
                    Plataea.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Dιod., iv.
                    10; Paus., ii. 25; and Herod., vi. 83, ix. 28. Schliemann <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Tiryns,</hi> London, 1886) and Mahaffy (in <hi rend="italic">Hermathena,</hi>
                    Dublin), however, deny the truth of this statement, believing that Tiryns ceased
                    to exist some centuries earlier, in spite of the strong evidence given by the
                    inscription on the bronze column (now in Constantinople), formed by three
                    twisted serpents, which once supported the golden tripod dedicated to Apollo out
                    of the spoils from Plataea. Tiryns occurs in the list of allied states present
                    at that battle; moreover, recent discoveries have brought to light remains of an
                    important building of about 600 B.c.</p></note></p>
                <p>Excavations made in 1884-85 by Schliemann and Dörpfeld over part of the rock on
                    which Tiryns stood have exposed a most interesting building, quite unique as an
                    example of a Greek palace of the 11th or 10th century B.C., and of special
                    interest from the way in which it closely illustrates the Homeric palaces of
                    Alcinous and Odysseus, and throws a new light on scenes such as the slaughter of
                    the suitors <hi rend="italic">(Od.,</hi> xxi. and xxii.).</p>
                <p>The rock on which Tiryns is built is of an irregular oval shape, about 330 yards
                    long by 112 at the widest part, and is surrounded by a very massive wall,
                    varying from 30 to 40 feet in thickness and averaging when complete about 50
                    feet in height, measuring from its base outside. Inside, the wall was probably
                    not more than 10 or 12 feet high above the ground, so the masonry acts as a
                    retaining wall to a considerable depth of earth which covers the rock (see fig.
                    2 below). The wall is built of very large hammer-dressed blocks, some as much as
                    10 feet long by 3 feet 3 inches or 3 feet 6 inches wide, with smaller ones to
                    fill up the interstices. The whole was bedded, not in mortar, but in clay, which
                    has mostly been washed out of the joints; originally the surface was probably
                    protected with a coating of stucco. The only important gateway, which was on the
                    east side, away from the sea, probably resembled the “lion gate” at Mycenae. The
                    other entrances are mere slits in the wall. One of these and the chief gate are
                    shown in fig. 1. Internally the area of the city was divided by cross walls into
                    three parts at successive levels. The lowest and middle divisions have not yet
                    been excavated; the upper part at the south end of the rock was completely
                    exposed in 1884-85 by Schliemann and Dörpfeld, and the almost complete plan of
                    the various structures clearly made out. This division contains the palace of
                    the ruler of Tiryns, a building which shows careful and skilful construction,
                    elaborate decoration, and a well-arranged plan, suitable to the wants of a
                    wealthy autocratic chief, who lived in a manner which partly recalls the luxury
                    of an Oriental king, and also resembled the feudal state of a mediaeval baron,
                    surrounded by a crowd of vassals. From the main gate, which was defended by a
                    tower, a strong passage led between the outer wall and an inner one to an inner
                    gate, thence to a propylaeum or double porch, with two wooden columns on each
                    side,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The arrows in fig.
                    1 show the way from the city gate to the palace court and hall.</p></note>
                    adjoining which were chambers for guards. Then came another similar, but smaller
                    propylaeum, and opposite to that was the entrance to the great court (αύλή),
                    nearly 53 by 70 feet, in which stands the altar to Zeus Herceus, with a circular
                    pit beneath it to catch the victims’ blood. This court was surrounded by wooden
                    columns supporting a roof, like a mediaeval cloister; on the south side are
                    chambers for attendants <hi rend="italic">(θa</hi><hi rend="italic">∖</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dμoιf</hi> On the north side is the great hall <hi rend="italic"
                    >(μtyapov</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    women’s hall is also called the megaron; see <hi rend="italic">Οd.,</hi> xviii.
                    198.</p></note><hi rend="italic">),</hi> with an outer portico supported by two
                    columns <hi rend="italic">(αίθουσα)</hi> and an inner vestibule <hi
                    rend="italic">(πρ6δoμos)</hi> with three doors.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The <hi rend="italic">τrpbδoμos</hi> is
                    mentioned by Homer (ZZ.,ix. 473, and <hi rend="italic">Οd.,</hi> iv. 302); but
                    in the palace of Odysseus the <hi rend="italic">αίθουσα</hi> seems to have been
                    the only vestibule to the megaron. In several respects the palace of Tiryns is
                    more magnificent than that of Odysseus, whose hall was paved with clay, not
                    concrete as at Tiryns; see <hi rend="italic">Οd.,</hi> xxi. 122, where
                    Telemachus <hi rend="italic">άμφί</hi><hi rend="italic">Sé yaîav tvaξe,</hi>
                    after cutting a trench to fix the row of axes.</p></note> The hall is about 40
                    by 30 feet, with a circular hearth-stone in the centre <hi rend="italic"
                    >(eστla</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ίσχάρα).</hi> Four columns supported the roof,
                    the central part of which probably rose above the rest like a mediaeval
                    “lantern”; and in this there was probably a door leading out to the flat roof
                    round it—possibly the <hi rend="italic">όρσοθύρη</hi> of Homer <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Od.,</hi> xxii. '126), through which one of the suitors escaped and so got
                    arms from the treasury or armoury, which was on an upper floor (see <hi
                    rend="italic">Od.,</hi> xxii. 142 and xxi. 5). On the west side of the hall are
                    a number of small chambers <hi rend="italic">(θαλάμοι)</hi> for the unmarried
                    men, and a bath-room about 12 by 10 feet, with its floor formed of one great
                    slab of stone, sloped so as to drain out at one side through a pipe which passes
                    through the wall. The women’s part of the house is of equal importance to that
                    of the men, and has its hall and two open courts with pillars. It is approached
                    in a very circuitous way,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>The way to the harem in a modern Oriental house is similarly made as
                    circuitous as possible, for the sake of privacy.</p></note> either by a passage
                    <hi rend="italic">(λaυon)</hi> leading from a side <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n428/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0428-0409"/> door in the main propylaeum or by another long
                    passage which winds round the back of the men’s hall, and so leads by a long
                    flight of steps, cut in the rock, to the little postern door in the semicircular
                    bastion. The many small rooms in this part of the palace were probably the
                    bedrooms of the women and married couples of the chiefs family. A staircase at
                    16 led to an upper floor, like the <hi rend="italic">κΚΐμαξ υψηλή</hi> of <hi
                    rend="italic">Od.</hi> xxi. 5. The circuit wall round the palace is more
                    strongly constructed than the rest On the south side it is built in two offsets,
                    forming a level platform for the garrison halfway up. In the upper and thinner
                    part of the wall two narrow passages at different levels are formed in its
                    thickness. They are roofed by projecting courses of stone in large blocks. The
                    wall on the east side has a similar intermediate platform, on to which open a
                    series of small chambers formed in the mass of the upper wall (see fig. 2). At
                    the top level the wall was covered by a colonnade of wood pillars resting on
                    circular stone blocks. This supported a flat roof and was open to the inside of
                    the city. The back of the colonnade was built of brick, and is now missing, as
                    are all the brick parts of the city, owing to the bricks having been only
                    sun-dried.</p>
                <p>The methods of construction employed in the Tiryns palace are of the highest
                    interest. The foundations and about 3 feet of the walls above the ground are
                    made of large blocks of stone bedded in clay; above this the wall was of brick,
                    sun-dried, and covered with stucco. The upper story was probably of wood. Some
                    of the thresholds of the doors were massive blocks of stone <hi rend="italic"
                    >(λiιvos</hi> oüðós); others were of wood <hi rend="italic">(δρtivos
                    oiδ6s').</hi> Wood was also used for all the columns, d∞rposts, and antae <hi
                    rend="italic">{πapaστdδes),</hi> and in some cases the walls of the rooms were
                    lined with wood, carefully fixed by dowels, the holes for which still
                    exist.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The marks of the
                    wooden wall linings are specially clear in the little bath-room.</p></note> The
                    doors had pivots of bronze revolving in well-fitted bronze cup-like sockets let
                    into the thresholds. In the megaron and other rooms the floors are of good
                    concrete, decorated with a simple series of incised lines, coloured blue and
                    red. The stucco of the internal wall is decorated with bold and very effective
                    patterns—birds and scroll-work of· semi-Oriental style; in many cases the
                    motives are obviously taken from textile ornaments, as in the most archaic style
                    of vase painting. One example of rich and costly decoration remains,—part of a
                    frieze of white alabaster, sculptured in relief with rosettes and interlacing
                    patterns, and studded with jewel-like pieces of blue glass or enamel, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Θpιyκ0s</hi><hi rend="italic">κυάνοιο</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Od.</hi> vii. 87.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    genuineness of this line has been questioned, but apparently without much
                    reason.</p></note> Further excavations in the lower parts of the city will
                    probably bring to light the dwellings of the citizens who garrisoned the place.
                    The great bulk of the Tirynthians must have lived in houses outside the citadel,
                    but under the shelter of its protection, just as in mediaeval Italy villages
                    grew up round the castles of any powerful lord.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In modern Italian <hi rend="italic"
                    >eastellο</hi> means a “village” as well as a “castle.”</p></note> (J. H.
                    Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
