<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0100-0089-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TAXIDERMY (9th edition, volume 23, page 89)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41834b98">Wards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vs35">Naturalists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7fz12">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5wd2z">Towing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885683">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153292">Towing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825070">Back</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n100/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TAXIDERMY</label>, the art of preserving the integument,
                    together with the scales, feathers, or fur, of animals. Little is known of the
                    beginnings of the practice of the “stuffing” or “setting up” of animals for
                    ornament or for scientific purposes; and it is highly probable, from what we
                    gather from old works of travel or natural history, that the art is not more
                    than some three hundred years old. It was practised in England towards the end
                    of the 17th century, as is proved by the Sloane collection, which in 1725 formed
                    the nucleus of the collection of natural history now lodged in the galleries at
                    South Kensington.</p>
                <p>It was not until the middle of last century that any treatise devoted to the
                    principles of the then little understood art was published in France, Réaumur’s
                    treatise (1749) being probably the first. This was followed at intervals by
                    others in France and Germany, until the beginning of the present century, when
                    the English began to move in the matter, and several works were published,
                    notably those by E. Donovan,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Instructions for Collecting and Preserving Various Subjects
                    of Natural History, <hi rend="italic">London, 1794.</hi></p></note> W.
                    Swainson,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    Naturalist's Guide for Collecting and Preserving Subjects of Natural History and
                    Botany, <hi rend="italic">London, 1822.</hi></p></note> Capt. Thomas Brown,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Taxidermist’s Manual, <hi
                    rend="italic">Glasgow, 1833.</hi></p></note> and others. These works, however,
                    are now inadequate; and since the Great Exhibition of 1851, when the Germans and
                    French taught British taxidermists the rudiments of scientific treatment of
                    natural objects, several works have appeared upon the subject from the pens of
                    American and English authors, such as J. H. Batty,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Practical Taxidermy and Home Decoration, <hi
                    rend="italic">New York, 1880.</hi></p></note> R. Ward,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Sportsman's Handbook of Practical Collecting
                    and Preserving, <hi rend="italic">London, 1880.</hi></p></note> and Montagu
                    Browne.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Practical Taxidermy,</hi> London, 1879; 2d edition,
                    1884.</p></note></p>
                <p>The first principle governing the art is that, after the specimen has been
                    procured, in as fresh and clean a state as may be, it should have the skin
                    stripped from the body in such a manner as not to disturb the scales if a fish
                    or a reptile, the feathers if a bird, or the fur or hair if a mammal. To do this
                    correctly requires a small stock of tools, as well as a great amount of patience
                    and perseverance. The appliances comprise several sharp knives (some pointed and
                    some obtuse), a pair of scissors, a pair of pliers, a pair of nippers or
                    “cutting-pliers,” some tow, wadding, needles and thread, also a “stuffing-iron,”
                    some crooked awls, a pair of fine long flat-nosed pliers, and a camel-hairbrush.
                    The preservative compound is often the original (Bécoeur’s) “arsenical soap,”
                    made by cutting up and boiling 2 lb of white soap, to which 12 oz. of salt of
                    tartar and 4 oz. of powdered lime (or whiting) are added <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n101/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0101-0090"/> when dissolved; to this mixture, when nearly
                    cold, 2 lb of powdered arsenic and 5 oz. of camphor (the latter previously
                    triturated in a mortar with spirits of wine) are added. The mixture is put away
                    in small jars or pots for use. Like all arsenical preparations, this is
                    exceedingly dangerous in the hands of unskilled persons, often causing shortness
                    of breath, sores, brittleness of the nails, and other symptoms; and, as arsenic
                    is really no protection against the attacks of insects, an efficient substitute
                    has been invented by Browne, composed of 1 lb of white curd soap and 3 lb of
                    whiting boiled together, to which is added, whilst hot, 1⅜ oz. of chloride of
                    lime, and, when cold, 1 oz. of tincture of musk. This mixture is perfectly safe
                    to use when cold (although when hot the fumes should not be inhaled, owing to
                    the chlorine given off), and is spoken of as doing its work efficiently.
                    Solutions of corrosive sublimate, often recommended, are, even if efficient,
                    dangerous in the extreme. Powders consisting of tannin, pepper, camphor, and
                    burnt alum are sometimes used for “making skins,” but they dry them too rapidly
                    for the purposes of “mounting.” Mammals are best preserved by a mixture of 1 lb
                    of burnt alum to { lb of saltpetre; this, when intimately mixed, should be well
                    rubbed into the skin. Fishes and reptiles, when not cast and modelled, are best
                    preserved in rectified spirits of wine; but this, when economy is desired, can
                    be replaced by “Möller’s solution” (bichromate of potash 2 oz., sulphate of soda
                    1 oz., distilled water 3 pints) or by a nearly saturated solution of chloride of
                    zinc. The cleaning of feathers and furs is performed by rubbing them lightly
                    with wadding soaked in benzoline, afterwards dusting on plaster of Paris, which
                    is beaten out, when dry, with a bunch of feathers.</p>
                <p>The preparation and mounting of bird specimens, the objects most usually selected
                    by the amateur, are performed in the following manner. The specimen to be
                    operated upon should have its nostrilsand throat closed by plugs of cotton wool
                    or tow; both wing-bones should be broken close to the body, and the bird laid
                    upon a table on its back; and, as birds—especially white-breasted ones—should
                    seldom, if ever, be opened on the breast, an incision should be made in the skin
                    under the wing on the side most damaged, from which the thigh protrudes when
                    pushed up slightly; this is cut through at its junction with the body, when the
                    knife is gently used to separate the skin from this, until the wing-bone is seen
                    on the open side. This is then cut through by scissors, and by careful
                    manipulation the skin is further freed from the back and breast until the neck
                    can be cut off. The other side now remains to be dealt with; from this the wing
                    is cut by travelling downwards, the remaining leg is cut away, and very careful
                    skinning over the stomach and upon the lower back brings the operator to the
                    tail, which is cut off, leaving a small portion of the bone (the coccyx) in the
                    skin. The body now falls off, and nothing remains in the skin but the neck and
                    head. To skin these out properly without unduly stretching the integument, is a
                    task trying to the patience, but it can be accomplished by gradually working the
                    skin away from the back of the head forward, taking care to avoid cutting the
                    eyes or the eyelids, but, by cautious management, to cut the membranous skin
                    over those parts, so that the eyes are easily extracted from the orbits without
                    bursting. The skin should be freed down nearly to the beak, and then the back of
                    the head, with neck attached, should be cut off, the brains extracted, all the
                    flesh cleared from the skull and from the bones of the wings, legs, and tail,
                    the skin painted with the preservative, and ultimately turned into its proper
                    position. When “skins” only are to be made for the cabinet, it is sufficient to
                    fill the head and neck with chopped tow, the body with a false one made of tow,
                    lightly packed or loose according to the genius of the preparer, to sew up the
                    skin of the stomach, and to place a band of paper lightly pinned around the body
                    over the breast and wings, and allow it to remain in a warm position, free from
                    dust, for several days or weeks, according to the size of the specimen. It
                    should then be labelled with name, sex, locality, and date, and put away with
                    insect powder around it.</p>
                <p>When, however, the specimen is to be “mounted,” the operations should be carried
                    up to the point of returning the skin, and then a false body of tightly wrapped
                    tow is made upon a wire pointed at its upper end. This is inserted through the
                    incision under the wing, the pointed end going up the neck and through the skull
                    to the outside. When the imitation body rests within the skin, pointed wires are
                    thrust through the soles of the feet, up the skin of the back of the legs, and
                    are finally clenched in the body. Wires are also thrust into the butts of the
                    wings, following the skin of the under surface, and also clenched through into
                    the body. A stand or perch is provided, and the bird, being fixed upon this, is,
                    after the eyes have been inserted, arranged in the most natural attitude which
                    the skill of the taxidermist can give it.</p>
                <p>Mammals are cut along the stomach from nearly the middle to the breast, and are
                    skinned by working out the hind legs first, cutting them off under the skin at
                    the junction of the femur with the tibia, and carefully stripping the skin off
                    the lower back and front until the tail is reached, the flesh and bones of which
                    are pulled out of the skin, leaving the operator free to follow on up the back
                    and chest until the fore legs are reached, which are cut off* in like manner.
                    The neck and head are skinned out down to the inner edges of the lips and nose,
                    great care being exercised not to cut the outer portions of the ears, the
                    eyelids, the nose, or the lips. The flesh being cleared off, and the brain and
                    eyes extracted, the skull should adhere to the skin by the inner edges of the
                    lips. AU the flesh should be trimmed from the bones of the legs. The head, being
                    shaped, where the flesh was removed, by tow and clay, is returned into the skin.
                    A long wire of sufficient strength is tightly bound with tow, making a long,
                    narrow body, through which wires are thrust by the skin of the soles of the
                    feet. The leg wires and bones being wrapped with tow and clay into shape, the
                    points, of the wires are pushed through the tow body and clenched. They and the
                    body are then bent into the desired position, and modelled up by the addition of
                    more tow and clay, until the contours of the natural body are imitated, when the
                    stomach is sewn up. A board is provided upon which to fix the specimen,
                    artificial eyes are inserted, the lips, nose, and eyelids fixed by means of pins
                    or “needle-points,” and the specimen is then placed in a warm situation to
                    dry.</p>
                <p>Reptiles, when small, have their skin removed by cutting away the attachment of
                    the skull to the cervical vertebrae, and by turning the decapitated trunk out at
                    the mouth by delicate manipulation. When large, they are cut along their median
                    line, and treated in the same manner as mammals.</p>
                <p>Fishes, after being covered on their best side with paper or muslin to protect
                    the scales, are cut along the other side from the tail to the gills, and are
                    skinned out by removing “cutlets,” as large as is possible without cracking the
                    skin, which, indeed, should be kept damp during work. After being cured with a
                    preservative, they are filled with sawdust or dry plaster of Paris, sewn up,
                    turned over on a board, the fins pinned out, and the mouth adjusted, and, when
                    perfectly dry, the plaster may be shaken out.</p>
                <p>A new school of taxidermists, with new methods, whose aim is to combine knowledge
                    of anatomy and modelling with taxidermie technique, are now coming to the front,
                    and the next generation will discard all processes of “stuffing” in favour of
                    modelling. Within the limits of an article like the present it is impossible to
                    do more than glance at the intricate processes involved in this. In the case of
                    mammals, after the skin has been completely removed, even to the toes, a copy is
                    made of the body, posed as in life, and from this an accurate representation of
                    form, including delineation of muscles, &lt;tc., is built up in light materials;
                    the model is then covered with the skin, which is damped, and pinned in to
                    follow every depression and prominence; the study is then suffered to dry; and,
                    models having been made, in the case of large animals, of the mucous membrane of
                    the jaws, palate, tongue, and lips, these are truthfully reproduced in a plastic
                    material. The ordinary glass eyes are discarded, and hollow globes, specially
                    made, are hand-painted from nature, and are fixed in the head so as to convey
                    the exact expression which the pose of the body demands. Birds, if of any size,
                    can be modelled in like manner, and fishes are treated by a nearly identical
                    process, being finally coloured as in a “still life” painting.</p>
                <p>To give a life-like representation, attention is also paid to artistic
                    “mounting.” By this is meant the surrounding of specimens with appropriate
                    accessories, and it is well exemplified by the new work shown in the natural
                    history museum at South Kensington, where, for example, birds are arranged as in
                    a state of nature, feeding or flying to their young, sitting on their eggs,
                    swimming in miniature pools, or preening their feathers whilst perched lovingly
                    side by side, and surrounded by exquisitely modelled <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n102/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0102-0091"/> foliage and flowers. This, with correct modelling
                    of the specimens, which, except in rare instances, is not quite so striking in
                    the new groups, indicates the future of the art, the hope of which lies in the
                    better education of taxidermists as designers, artists, and modellers. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(μ. b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
