<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0502-0483-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TOULON (9th edition, volume 23, page 483)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945091">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933759">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896024">Docks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1056939">Peninsulas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25f3j">Docks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n502/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TOULON</label>, a French fortress of the first class,
                    chef-lieu of an arrondissement in the department of Var, of the 5th naval
                    arrondissement, and of a military subdivision, is situated on the Mediterranean,
                    42 miles east-south-east of Marseilles by the railway to Nice. The bay, which
                    opens to the east, has two divisions, the “grand rade” and the “petite rade”; it
                    is sheltered on the north and west by high hills, closed on the south by the
                    peninsula of Capes Sicié and Cépet, and protected on the east by a huge
                    breakwater,—the entrance, 1300 feet wide, being defensible by torpedoes. A ship
                    coming from the open sea must first pass the forts of St Marguerite, of Cape
                    Brun, of La Malgue, and of St Louis to the north, and the battery of the signal
                    station to the south; before reaching the petite rade it must further pass under
                    the guns of the battery of Le Salut to the east, and of the forts of Balaguier
                    and L’Éguillette to the west. The Bay of La Seyne lies west of the petite rade,
                    and is defended by the forts of Les Six-Fours, Napoleon (formerly Fort Cairo),
                    and Malbous-quet, and the batteries of Les Arenes and Les Gaus. To the north of
                    Toulon rise the defensive works of Mont Faron and Fort Rouge, to the east the
                    forts of Artigues and St Catherine, to the north-east the formidable new fort of
                    Le Coudon, and to the south-east that of La Colle Noire, respectively dominating
                    the highway into Italy and the valley of Hyéres with the Bay of Carqueyranne.
                    The port of Toulon consists of the old dock, of which one-third is reserved for
                    the national navy, a new dock, wholly so devoted, a harbour capable of receiving
                    trading vessels drawing from 16 to 18 feet, but only used for cargoes of wood
                    and wine, and the Castigneau dock. The naval arsenal (including the arsenal of
                    Castigneau, which is contiguous with it, in the direction of La Seyne) extends
                    over 4 miles, has an area of 667 acres, and employs from 12,000 to 13,000 men.
                    It contains the offices connected with the administration of the port, the
                    office of naval construction, a well-stored naval museum, and a great variety of
                    workshops. These last include a rope-work 1050 x 66 feet, covered building
                    yards, careening basins, forges, armourers’ and joiners’ shops, general
                    magazines, reconstructed on a fireproof principle since the conflagration<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n503/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0503-0484"/> of 1793, in which are stored all materials
                    required in the arsenal and on board ship, a park of artillery, a splendid
                    collection of arms, and separate storehouses for various classes of rigging. The
                    Castigneau arsenal contains the navy bakery of twenty ovens, capable of cooking
                    600,000 rations daily, the foundry and boiler-making works, engineers’
                    workshops, forges, three large careening basins, a washing house, a slaughter
                    house, stores of provisions, coals, anchors and machinery, and the like. The
                    Mourillon arsenal, to the south-east of the town, has stores of wood, building
                    yards, and appliances for naval construction in wood and iron. The town,
                    enlarged to the north under the second empire, has on that side a fine new
                    quarter; but in the old town the streets are for the most part narrow, crooked,
                    and dirty, and to their insanitary state the cholera epidemic of 1884 has been
                    attributed. The chief buildings are the old cathedral of St Marie Majeure, the
                    church of St Louis, the town-hall, the theatre (seating 2000 persons), the
                    museum, the library (18,000 volumes), the naval and military hospital, with a
                    natural history collection and an anatomical museum attached, a naval school of
                    medicine, a school of hydrography, and large barracks. The imports are wine
                    (2,470,000 gallons in 1881), corn, wood, coal, hemp, iron, sugar, coffee, and
                    fresh fish; the exports are salt, copper ore, barks for tanning, and oils. In
                    1882 the movement of the port was represented by 280 vessels (41,000 tons). The
                    interesting buildings and gardens of the hospital of St Mandrier stand on the
                    peninsula of Cape Cépet, and near them is the lazaretto. In 1881 the population
                    of Toulon was 48,832, and in 1886 it was 53,941, exclusive of 12,487 soldiers,
                    sailors, &amp;c. (commune 70,122).</p>
                <p>The Roman Telo Martins is supposed to have stood near the lazaretto. The town was
                    successively sacked by Goths, Burgundians, Franks, and Saracens. During the
                    early Middle Ages, and till conquered by Charles of Anjou in 1259, it was under
                    lords of its own, and entered into alliance with the republics of Marseilles and
                    Arles. St Louis, Louis XII., and Francis I. strengthened its fortifications. It
                    was seized by the emperor Charles V. in 1524 and 1536. Henry IV. founded a naval
                    arsenal at Toulon, which was further strengthened by Richelieu, and Vauban made
                    the new dock, a new enceinte, and several forts and batteries. In 1707 the town
                    was unsuccessfully besieged by the duke of Savoy, Prince Eugene, and an English
                    fleet. In 1721 there was an outbreak of the plague. In 1792, after great and
                    sanguinary disorder, the royalists of the town sought the support of the English
                    and Spanish fleets cruising in the neighbourhood. The convention having replied
                    by putting the town “hors la loi," the inhabitants opened their harbour to the
                    English. The army of the republic now laid siege to the town, and it was on this
                    occasion that Napoleon Bonaparte first made his name as a soldier. The forts
                    commanding the town having been taken, the English ships retired after setting
                    fire to the arsenal. The conflagration was extinguished by the prisoners, but
                    not before 38 out of a total of 56 vessels had been destroyed. Under the
                    Directory Toulon became the most important French military fort on the
                    Mediterranean; it was here that Napoleon organized the Egyptian campaign, and
                    the expedition against Algiers set out from Toulon in 1830. The fortifications
                    have been strengthened by Napoleon I., Louis Philippe, Napoleon III., and since
                    1870.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
