<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0324-0307-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THOLUCK, Friedrich August Gottreu (9th edition, volume
                    23, page 307)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vk4z">Orientation</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h10">Sermons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n324/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THOLUCK, <hi rend="smallcaps">Friedrich August
                    Gottreu</hi></label> (1799-1877), German theologian and preacher, was born at
                    Breslau, March 30, 1799, in humble circumstances. He received his education at
                    the grammar school and university of his native town, and early distinguished
                    himself by wonderful versatility of mind, a phenomenal power of acquiring
                    languages, and an omnivorous appetite for books. A romantic love of the East and
                    its literature led him to exchange the university of Breslau for that of Berlin,
                    that he might study Oriental languages to greater advantage, and there he was
                    received into the house of the Orientalist Von Dietz. He was introduced to
                    Pietistic circles in Berlin, and came specially under the influence of Baron Von
                    Kottwitz, who became his “spiritual father,” and of the historian Neander.
                    Before deciding on the career of theological professor, he had in view that of a
                    missionary in the East. Meanwhile he was feeling the influence to a certain
                    degree of the romantic school, and of Schleiermacher and Hegel too, though he
                    never sounded the depths of their systems. At length, in his twenty-first year,
                    he finally decided to adopt the academical calling. From December 1820 to April
                    1826 he was “privat-docent” and “prof, extraordinarius” of theology in Berlin,
                    though he was at the same time most active in the work of home and foreign
                    missions. He lectured on the Old and New Testaments, theology, apologetics, and
                    the history of the church in the 18th century. The first fruit of his Oriental
                    studies and his introduction to his profession was his work <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ssufismus, siυβ Theosophia</hi><hi rend="italic">Persarum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Pantheistica</hi> (1821); following the same line of study he published <hi
                    rend="italic">Blütensammlung aus der morgenländischen Mystik</hi> (1825) and <hi
                    rend="italic">Speculative</hi><hi rend="italic">Trinitätslehre des späteren
                    Orients</hi> (1826). His well-known essay on the nature and moral influence of
                    heathenism (1822) was published by Neander, with high commendation, in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Denkwürdigkeiten·,</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Commentary on
                    the Epistle to the Romans</hi> (1824) secured him a foremost place amongst the
                    most suggestive, if not the most accurate, Biblical· interpreters of that time.
                    Another work, which was soon translated into all the principal European
                    languages, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Lehre von der Sünde und
                    vom Versöhner</hi> (1823), the outcome of his own religious history, procured
                    for him the position which he ever after held of the modern Pietistic apologist
                    of evangelical Christianity. In 1825, with the aid of the Prussian Government,
                    he visited the libraries of England and Holland, and on his return was appointed
                    professor of theology at Halle, the centre of German rationalism. Here he made
                    it his aim to combine in a higher unity the learning and to some extent the
                    rationalism of Sender with the devout and active pietism of Francke; and, in
                    spite of the opposition of the theological faculty of the university, he
                    succeeded in changing the character of its theology. This he effected partly by
                    his lectures, particularly his exegetical courses, but, above all, by his
                    personal influence upon the students, and, after 1833, by his preaching. His
                    theological position was that of a mild and large-hearted orthodoxy, which laid
                    more stress upon Christian experience than upon rigid dogmatic belief. On the
                    two great questions of miracles and inspiration he made great concessions to
                    modern criticism and philosophy. The battle of his life was on behalf of
                    personal religious experience, in opposition to the externality of rationalism,
                    orthodoxy, or sacrament-arianism. He fought this battle with weapons taken in
                    the first instance from his own personal history, but also from the wide world
                    of human culture, ancient and modern. Carl Schwarz happily remarks that, as the
                    English apologists of the 18th century were themselves infected with the poison
                    of the deists whom they endeavoured to refute, so Tholuck absorbed some of the
                    heresies of the rationalists whom he tried to overthrow. As a preacher Tholuck
                    ranked amongst the foremost of his time. He was also one of the prominent
                    members of the Evangelical Alliance, and few men were more widely known or more
                    beloved throughout the Protestant churches of Europe and America than he. He
                    died at Halle, June 10, 1877.</p>
                <p>After his commentaries (on Romans, the Gospel of John, the Sermon on the Mount,
                    and the Epistle to the Hebrews) and several volumes of sermons, his best-known
                    books are <hi rend="italic">Stunden christlicher Andacht</hi> (1839, 8th ed.
                    1870), intended to take the place of Zschokke’s standard rationalistic work with
                    the same title, and his reply to Strauss’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Jesus
                    (Glaubivürdigkeit</hi><hi rend="italic">der evangelischen</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n325/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0325-0308"/><hi rend="italic">Geschichte,</hi> 1837). He
                    published at various times valuable contributions towards a history of
                    rationalism, — <hi rend="italic">Vorgeschichte des Rationalismus</hi> (1853-62),
                    <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Rationalismus,</hi> i. (1865), and a number of
                    essays connected with the history of theology and especially of apologetics. His
                    views of inspiration were indicated in his work <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Propheten und ihre Weissagungen</hi> (1860), in his essay on the
                    “Alte Inspirationslehre,” <hi rend="italic">Deutsche Zeitschrift für christliche
                    Wissenschaft</hi> (1850), and in his <hi rend="italic">Gespräche über die
                    vornehmsten Glaubensfragen der Zeit</hi> (1846, 2d ed. 1867).</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Das Leben Tholucks,</hi> by L. witte, 2 vols., 1884-1886;
                    <hi rend="italic">A.</hi><hi rend="italic">Tholuck, ein Lebensabriss,</hi> by Μ.
                    Kähler (1877), and the same author’s art. “Tholuck,” in Herzog’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Real·Encyklopädie</hi>; “Zur Erinnerung an Tholuck,” by C.
                    Siegfried, <hi rend="italic">Protestantische Kirchzeitung,</hi> 1885, No. 45,
                    and 1886, No. 47; Carl Schwarz, <hi rend="italic">Zur Geschichte der neuesten
                    Theologie</hi> (4th ed., 1869); Nippold’s <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der
                    neuesten Kirchen-geschichie.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
