<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0344-0327-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THUGUT, Franz Maria von (9th edition, volume 23, page
                    327)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n344/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THUGUT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Franz Maria von</hi></label>
                    (1734-1818), foreign minister of Austria, was born of humble parentage at Linz
                    in 1734, placed in the Government school of Oriental studies in 1752, and sent
                    to Constantinople as an interpreter in 1757. At Constantinople he rose from post
                    to post in the embassy, until in 1771 he became internuncius or ambassador. In
                    1776, after the war between Russia and Turkey, he obtained from the latter power
                    the cession of the province of Bukowina to Austria. After thus crowning his long
                    service in the East and gaining the confidence of Maria Theresa, he was sent by
                    her without the knowledge of her son, the emperor Joseph, to Berlin, to avert by
                    a peaceful settlement with Frederick the Great the threatened Bavarian war. In
                    1790 he was employed in the negotiations of Sistova, and his next mission was to
                    Paris, where he entered into close relations with Mirabeau as the friend of
                    Marie Antoinette. On the invasion of France by the allied armies in 1792, Thugut
                    was sent to the scene of operations. It is well known that Kaunitz, the veteran
                    minister of Austria, condemned the terms of the alliance with Prussia, as
                    securing to Prussia the annexation of a great part of Poland, while only holding
                    out to Austria an uncertain prospect of acquiring its equivalent in Bavaria.
                    Thugut, a politician of the same school, viewed the new alliance with even
                    greater hatred. After the failure of the campaign of 1792 he formed the
                    deliberate opinion that persons around the duke of Brunswick had been bribed by
                    the French, and that the retreat had been ordered in consequence. A few months
                    later the anticipations of Kaunitz were realized. Prussia seized western Poland,
                    while Austria remained as far as ever from gaining Bavaria. The emperor Francis
                    now dismissed the ministers responsible for the Prussian alliance, and called
                    Thugut to power. From this critical moment the alliance was doomed, and the
                    allied commanders thwarted rather than assisted one another’s operations on the
                    eastern frontier of France. On the other hand, Thugut drew nearer to Russia, and
                    negotiated at St Petersburg for the seizure of Venice by Austria. With England
                    he desired to stand on a good footing; but, while Pitt’s object was the
                    overthrow of the revolutionary Government, Thugut’s was simply the acquisition
                    of territory for Austria. This discrepancy of aim led to results exasperating to
                    the English ministry, such as the fall of Toulon, to which Thugut neglected to
                    send the troops which he had promised. The evacuation of Belgium in 1794,
                    usually attributed to Thugut’s treachery, was, however, due to the incapacity or
                    intrigues of others. In 1795, after the withdrawal of Prussia from the
                    coalition, Thugut obtained financial help from England, gained from Russia a
                    large share of Poland in the last partition, and prepared to carry on the war
                    against France with the utmost energy. The campaign <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n345/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0345-0328"/> of the archduke Charles in 1796 drove the French
                    from the east of the Rhine, and Bonaparte, who had conquered northern Italy up
                    to Mantua, narrowly escaped destruction before this fortress. But for the genius
                    of the French commander and the wretched character of the Austrian generals and
                    officers, the immense efforts made by Thugut at this time would have turned the
                    tide of the war. Defeat after defeat seemed to make no impression upon his
                    “world-desolating obstinacy and, even when Bonaparte had advanced to within
                    eighty miles of Vienna, it is stated that the empress had to throw herself at
                    her husband’s feet when in conference with his minister, in order to overcome
                    the resistance of the latter to an armistice. The subsequent peace of Campo
                    Formio was hotly condemned by Thugut, who tendered his resignation. Then
                    followed the congress of Rastadt and the murder of the French envoys, long
                    attributed, but without any real ground, to Thugut himself. War was renewed; the
                    French were driven out of Italy by Austrian armies assisted by Suwaroff; and it
                    was determined that the allies should conquer Switzerland, and so invade France
                    where the frontier is most open. Thugut, now at the height of his power, and far
                    more anxious to recover Belgium than to overthrow the republic, took the fatal
                    step of withdrawing a great part of the Austrian forces from Switzerland at the
                    very moment when the Russians were entering it. The result was the destruction
                    of the Russians by Masséna and the total failure of the campaign, followed by
                    the secession of Russia from the coalition. Still full of designs for annexation
                    in Italy, Thugut continued the war with the help of England. On the very day
                    when he renewed his engagements with England the news arrived of the battle of
                    Marengo, which at one blow made an end of all that Austria had won in Italy in
                    the preceding year. Nothing daunted, Thugut continued, during the armistice
                    which followed, his preparation for the struggle with Moreau in the valley of
                    the Danube; and, if he could have inspired his master with his own resolute
                    spirit, the result of the war might have been different. But, while Thugut was
                    actually receiving the British subsidies, the emperor, without the knowledge of
                    his minister, surrendered the fortresses of Ulm and Ingolstadt to Moreau, in
                    return for an extension of the armistice. Thugut’s passionate indignation on
                    learning of this miserable act is impressively described in Lord Minto’s
                    despatches from Vienna. He withdrew from office; but Lord Minto’s protests
                    compelled the emperor again to place in his hands the direction of affairs,
                    which he held until the battle of Hohenlinden made all further resistance
                    impossible. He was then, in deference to French influence, banished from Vienna,
                    and never resumed office. In his retirement he was occasionally consulted, as
                    after the battle of Wagram in 1809, when he recommended the emperor to make
                    peace at any cost, stating that the existence of the Austrian monarchy was at
                    stake and that the dissolution of Napoleon’s empire was not far off. After the
                    overthrow of Napoleon he returned to the capital, where he died May 29, 1818.
                    Thugut possessed many of the qualities of a great man,—indomitable courage,
                    calmness in danger, devotion to public interests, enormous industry; but all
                    this was spoilt by the persistent disregard of obligations towards allies in the
                    greedy pursuit of Austria’s own aggrandizement, and by the intriguing spirit
                    inseparable from this policy. The materials for forming a fair estimate of
                    Thugut’s conduct of affairs from 1793 to 1801 have but recently been given to
                    the world. Of his private life next to nothing is known.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
