<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0402-0383-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TIERRA DEL FUEGO (9th edition, volume 23, page
                    383)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:813089">Archipelagoes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134302">Straits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960336">Horns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1054772">Patagonians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878051">Cooks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j3q">Darwinism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43x83s88">Patagonians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rn70">Snow</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pz6r">Pillars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n402/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TIERRA DEL FUEGO</label>, a large archipelago at the southern
                    extremity of South America, from which it is separated by Magellan Strait, at
                    the Narrows and other points scarcely a mile wide. The group lies between 52°
                    40' and 55° 59' S. lat. and 63° 30' and 74° 35' W. long, stretching nearly in a
                    line with the Patagonian Andes for over 400 miles north-west and south-east,
                    between Capes Pillar and Horn, and for about 270 miles west and east from Cape
                    Pillar to Cape Espiritu Santo (Catherine Point) in the north; southwards it
                    tapers to 120 miles between Capes Horn and St Diego, the latter being continued
                    eastwards to Staten Island, which is not usually included in the group. Although
                    on ordinary maps this region presents to the eye a hopelessly confused aggregate
                    of islands, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n403/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0403-0384"/> channels, and fjord-like inlets, as if it had
                    been submerged sufficiently to convert its deep valleys and gorges into marine
                    passages, bays, and bights, it is nevertheless clearly disposed in three main
                    sections, -which may be conveniently named East, West, and South Fuegia.</p>
                <p>East Fuegia consists of the single island of King Charles’s South Land (eastern
                    Tierra del Fuego), which is very much larger than all the rest of the group
                    together, being considerably over 200 miles long from north to south. It
                    obviously forms a southern extension of the Patagonian pampas, which it greatly
                    resembles in its physical constitution, climate, flora, and fauna. The
                    low-lying, flat or slightly rolling plains are covered with a rich growth of
                    tali herbage, which is frequented by the rhea, guanaco, and other animals common
                    to the adjoining mainland, and also peopled by a branch of the same Tehuelche
                    (Patagonian) family. In the south a long peninsula projects westwards to the
                    Pacific. This western limb assumes a mountainous character, Mount Darwin (6800
                    feet) being situated about midway on its south side and Mount Sarmiento (6900,
                    or perhaps 7000 feet), the culminating point of the archipelago, much nearer the
                    Pacific. Although generally supposed to be volcanic, this peak presents such
                    extremely precipitous, in fact, almost vertical flanks that John Ball considers
                    it more probably “a portion of the original rock skeleton that formed the axis
                    of the Andean chain during the long ages that preceded the great volcanic
                    outbursts that have covered the framework of the western side of South
                    America.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Notes of a Naturalist in South America,</hi> London, 1887, p.
                    245.</p></note> This is altogether an alpine region with numerous snow-clad
                    summits and glaciers descending down to the sea (Darwin).</p>
                <p>Along the south side of East Fuegia flows Beagle Channel, about 55° S. lat.,
                    separating it from South Fuegia, which comprises the islands of Hoste, Navarin,
                    Gordon, Londonderry, Stewart, Wollaston, and numerous islets, disposed in
                    triangular form with the base on Beagle Channel and the apex at the rocky
                    headland of Cape Horn. At its western end Beagle Channel takes the name of
                    Darwin Sound, which leads to the Pacific at Londonderry and Stewart Islands.
                    North of these lies Brecknock Peninsula, the westernmost extension of East
                    Fuegia, cutting off South Fuegia from Clarence Island and Desolation Land, which
                    with Dawson Island and numerous rocks and islets constitute West Fuegia.
                    Desolation Land, so named by Cook, who supposed it to form a continuous mass
                    stretching from the western entrance of Magellan Strait to Cockburn Channel,
                    really consists of at least three, and possibly more islands, separated from
                    each other by very narrow channels flowing between the Pacific and the western
                    branch of Magellan Strait. The name Desolation has been reserved for the
                    northern member of the group terminating at Cape Pillar; the one next to it has
                    been called Santa Inez; the other or others are still unnamed. When Ball passed
                    through the strait, he was shown one of the narrow sounds “which have lately
                    been ascertained to penetrate entirely through what used to be considered a
                    single island” <hi rend="italic">(op. cit.,</hi> p. 241).</p>
                <p>Lying almost in a line with the main Andean axis, both West and South Fuegia are
                    essentially highland regions, conforming in their general characteristics to the
                    intervening western extension of East Fuegia. As compared λvith the great mass
                    of the latter, they are everywhere extremely rugged and mountainous, having a
                    mean elevation of not less than 3000 feet, a much moister climate, and arboreal
                    instead of grassy vegetation. The isothermals of 32° Fahr, for July (winter) and
                    50° Fahr, for January (summer), with a mean annual temperature of 42° Fahr.,
                    show that tolerably mild winters are followed by cool summers, both seasons
                    being accompanied by overcast skies, constant and sudden changes from fair to
                    foul weather; whilst fogs, mists, rains, snows, and high winds (prevailing
                    throughout the year) endanger the navigation of the intricate inland channels,
                    and render· the archipelago one of the dreariest regions on the globe.</p>
                <p>A botanical parting line seems to be constituted by the range of hills running
                    back of Punta Arenas along the east side of Brunswick Peninsula (which, although
                    attached by a narrow neck of land to Patagonia, belongs physically to the
                    insular domain), and terminating at Cape Froward (53° 54' S. lat.), the
                    southernmost point of the American mainland. West and south of this line the
                    pampas are replaced by lofty mountains clothed with a dense forest vegetation
                    from the water’s edge to heights of 1000 and 1200 feet, above which stretches a
                    zone of peaty soil with stunted alpine plants as far as the snow line (3000 to
                    3500 feet). The forest species are chiefly an evergreen beech <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Fagu,s antarctwa,</hi> S.) and the winter bark (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Winteria</hi><hi rend="italic">aromatica),</hi> also evergreen, with tall
                    smooth stem and glossy leaves like the laurel. Wild celery, cress, cochlearia,
                    and other anti-scorbutic plants occur on both sides of Magellan Strait, and the
                    beech nourishes a large yellow mushroom, which, with the berries of a dwarf
                    shrub, is the only vegetable food of the natives.</p>
                <p>In West and South Fuegia the fauna is restricted mainly to two species of fox, a
                    bat, rats, mice, the sea otter, the penguin and other aquatic birds, and various
                    cetaceans in the surrounding waters.</p>
                <p>To the three geographical divisions correspond three well-marked ethnical
                    groups,—the Onas of East, the Yaghans of South, and the Alacalufs of West
                    Fuegia. The first are estimated to number 2000, the others 3000 each, making a
                    total population of some 8000 for the whole archipelago. The Onas are
                    Patagonians who have crossed the strait. The Alacalufs are also immigrants from
                    the mainland, but probably they came at an earlier date, and from the western
                    uplands, being apparently a branch of the Auca (Araucanian) race of the
                    Patagonian and Chilian Cordilleras. They differ altogether in speech both from
                    the Onas, with whom they come scarcely anywhere in contact, and from the
                    Yahgans, who are the true aborigines of the archipelago. These last are in
                    exclusive possession of South Fuegia, and also occupy the north side of Beagle
                    Channel about Mount Darwin and further west. To them alone missionary enterprise
                    has hitherto been extended, and the English station of Ushiwaya on Beagle
                    Channel has for some years been the only centre of civilizing influences in the
                    archipelago. As Lieutenant Bove of the Italian Antarctic expedition has made a
                    special study of this branch,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See Guido Cora’s <hi rend="italic">Cosmos</hi> for May
                    1883.</p></note> they are much better known than either of the neighbouring
                    races. If they represent an earlier Araucanian immigration than that of the
                    Alacalufs, their extremely low social state, on which all observers are
                    unanimous, may be regarded as the result of degradation from a higher condition
                    during their long sojourn in their present inhospitable environment. But it
                    seems more probable that they are the direct descendants of the primitive race
                    by which the archipelago has been occupied from a vastly remote period, as is
                    shown by the very great number of kitchen-middens recently discovered on the
                    coast. Although taller than the Negritoes of the eastern hemisphere (4 feet 10
                    inches to 5 feet 4 inches), the Yahgans present in some respects a more debased
                    type, characterized by low brows, prominent zygomatic arches, large tumid lips,
                    flat nose, loose wrinkled skin (“pelle grinzosa e cadente,” says Bove), black
                    restless eyes very wide apart, coarse black unkempt hair, and head and chest
                    disproportionately large compared with the extremely slender and outwardly
                    curved legs, conveying an impression of top-heaviness like that of the Akkas of
                    equatorial Africa. Their mental qualities are on the same low level, as is
                    indicated by the almost total absence of clothing under such inclement skies, by
                    the brutal treatment of their women, who when old and useless are often eaten,
                    by the lack of human affections or love of offspring, who in rough weather are
                    thrown overboard (Dr Fenton), either as a peace offering to the spirits of the
                    storm or to lighten the canoe, and by many repulsive practices connected with
                    their food and social habits. The tribal organization<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n404/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0404-0385"/> has not yet been reached, each family circle
                    living apart and combining only in small groups against some common enemy, but
                    recognizing no hereditary chief or even any temporary leader. Yet the
                    missionaries, who have reduced the language to writing (Gospel of St Luke,
                    London, 1881), assert that it contains no less than 30,000 words, although the
                    numerals stop at <hi rend="italic">five,</hi> already a compound form <hi
                    rend="italic">{cu-pash-pa),</hi> and although the same word expresses both <hi
                    rend="italic">hand</hi> and <hi rend="italic">finger.</hi> But they have
                    obviously failed to distinguish between distinct terms and the endless
                    grammatical intricacies in which this, like so many other rude forms of speech,
                    is still involved.</p>
                <p>Since 1881 the eastern portion of Fuegia (with Staten Island) has belonged to the
                    Argentine Republic and the western to Chili. The boundary line, which is purely
                    conventional, runs from Cape Espiritu Santo due south to Beagle. Channel.
                    Neither power has hitherto occupied any part of Fuegia, except Punta Arenas
                    (Sandy Point) on the Patagonian side of Magellan Strait, where the Chilians have
                    for some years maintained a convict and coaling station.</p>
                <p>Fuegia was discovered by Magellan in 1520, when he sailed through the strait
                    named after him, and called this region the “Land of Fire,” either from now
                    extinct volcanic flames, or much more probably from the fires kindled by the
                    natives along parts of his course. In 1578 Drake first sighted the point which
                    in 1616 was named Cape Hoorn (Anglicized Horn) by the Dutch navigators Lemaire
                    and Schouten. In 1619 the brothers Nodal first circumnavigated the archipelago,
                    which was afterwards visited at intervals by Wood and Narborough (1670), Gennes
                    and Froger (1696), Byron (1764), Wallis and Carteret (1767), Cook (1768), and
                    Weddell (1822). But no systematic exploration was attempted until the British
                    Admiralty undertook a thorough survey of the whole group by King (1826-28) and
                    Fitzroy (1831-36). The latter expedition <hi rend="italic">{Voyage of the
                    “Beagle")</hi> was accompanied by Charles Darwin, then a young man. To these
                    admirable surveys is due most of the present geographical terminology of the
                    archipelago. Since then the work of exploration has been continued and nearly
                    completed by Dumont d’Urville (1837), Charles Wilkes (1839), Parker Snow (1855),
                    Bove (1883), and various English, American, and Roman Catholic missionaries.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography.—</hi> De Brosses, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">des Navigations</hi><hi rend="italic">aux Terres
                    Australes,</hi> Paris, 1756; J. Burney, <hi rend="italic">History of</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Voyages</hi><hi rend="italic">and Discoveries in the South
                    Sea,</hi> London, 1803-17; J. weddell, <hi rend="italic">A Voyage towards the
                    South Pole and to Tierra del Fuego,</hi> London, 1825; Charles Darwin, <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal of Researches,</hi> &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">during the
                    Voyage of the “Beagle " round the World,</hi> London, 1845; W. Parker Snow, <hi
                    rend="italic">A Two Years' Cruise off Tierra del Fuego,</hi> London, 1857; G.
                    Marguin, “La Terre de Feu," in <hi rend="italic">Bull, de la Soc. de
                    Géogr.,</hi> November 1875; J. G. Kohl, <hi rend="italic">Gesch. d.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Entdeckungsreisen,</hi> &amp;c., <hi rend="italic">zur</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Magellan's Strasse,</hi> Berlin, 1877; “La Terre de Feu et ses
                    Habitants,” in <hi rend="italic">Journal des Missions</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Évangéliques,</hi> August 1876; D. Lovisato, <hi rend="italic">Appunti
                    Etnografici con Accenni Geologici sulla Terra del Fuoco,</hi> Turin, 1884; John
                    Ball, <hi rend="italic">Notes of a Naturalist in South America,</hi> London,
                    1887; R. W. Coppinger, <hi rend="italic">Cruise of the “Alert,"</hi> London, 4th
                    ed. 1885; G. Sergi, <hi rend="italic">Antropologia Fisica della Fuegia,</hi>
                    Rome, 1887; Ramon Lista, “East Fuegia,” in <hi rend="italic">Petermann's</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Mitteilungen,</hi> May 1887; and the works already mentioned. (A.
                    H. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
