<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0238-0221-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THAR AND PÀRKAR, or Thur and Parker (9th edition,
                    volume 23, page 221)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:981259">Jains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104803">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gt9w">Jains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n238/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THAR AND PÀRKAR, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Thur and
                    Parker</hi></label>, a district in the east of Sind, Bombay presidency, India,
                    with an area of 12,729 square miles. It lies between 24° 13' and 26° 15' N. lat.
                    and between 68° 51' and 71° 8' E. long., and is bounded on the N. by Khaipur
                    state, on the E. by the states of Jaisalmir, Malani, and Jodhpur, on the W. by
                    Hyderabad district, and on the S. by the Runn of Cutch. The district is divided
                    into two portions. The western part, called the “Pat,” is watered by the Eastern
                    Nara and the Mithrau canals, which constitute the sole water-system of the
                    district, and the presence of water has created a quantity of jungle and marsh;
                    the other part, called the “Thar,” is a desert tract of rolling sand-hills,
                    running north-east and south-west, composed of a fine but slightly coherent
                    sand. To the south-east of Thar is Pârkar, where there are ranges of rocky
                    hills, rising to 350 feet above the surrounding level, and open plains of stiff
                    clay. The Pârkar portion of the district contains the ruins of several old
                    temples; one of these is a Jain temple, which contained an idol of great
                    sanctity and repute, known under the name of Gorcha. The climate is subject to
                    considerable extremes in temperature, being excessively hot in the summer and
                    very cold in winter, the cold increasing as the sand-hills are approached.</p>
                <p>The census of 1881 returned the population at 203,344 (males 112,400, females
                    90,944); Hindus numbered 43,755, Mohammedans 109,924, and Christians only 14.
                    Umarkot, the birthplace of Akbar, is the chief town, with a population of 2828.
                    The chief products of the district are rice, joâr, bajri, cotton, and oil seeds.
                    It is estimated that only 45 per cent, of the arable area is under cultivation.
                    The exports are chiefly rice, wheat, oil-seeds, cattle, goats, and sheep; the
                    imports consist of cotton, metals, dried fruits, piece goods, sugar, and
                    tobacco. The manufactures are chiefly blankets, camel saddles, and coarse cotton
                    cloth. The imperial revenue in 1885-86 amounted to £44,313, of which the land
                    supplied £32,927.</p>
                <p>Very little is known of the early history of the district. The Soda Rajputs, said
                    to be descendants of Parmar Soda, are supposed, to have come into this part of
                    Sind about 1226, when they quickly displaced the rulers of the country, though,
                    according to other authorities, they did not conquer the country from the
                    Surnras, the dominant race, before the beginning of the 16th century. The local
                    dynasty of the Sodas succumbed to the Kalhoras about 1750, since which period
                    the district has been subject more or less to Sind. The Talpur mirs succeeded
                    the Kalhoras, and built a number of forts to overawe the people, who were
                    lawless and addicted to robbery. On the British conquest of Sind in 1843 the
                    greater part of the district was made over to Cutch; and in 1856 it was wholly
                    incorporated in the province of Sind. In 1859 a rebellion broke out, which was
                    quickly suppressed.</p>
                <p>TΞARRAWADDY, a district in the Pegu division of Burrnah, with an area of 2014
                    square miles. It lies between 17° 30' and 18° 40' N. lat. and between 95° 20'
                    and 96° 10' E. long., and is bounded on the N. by Prome, on the E. by the Pegu
                    Yoma range, on the S. by Hanthawaddy, and on the W. by Henzada. The Pegu Yoma
                    range separates Tharrawaddy from Toungd district, and forms the water-parting
                    between the rivers Irrawaddy and Sittang; there are also many small elevations.
                    The Irrawaddy, which traverses the district for 46 miles, is the principal
                    navigable river. Another important river is the Hlaing, which runs through the
                    district from north to south, receiving from the east, through numerous
                    channels, the drainage of the Pegu Yoma Mountains, which fertilizes the plain on
                    its eastern bank. There are twenty-three teak forests and four fuel reserves in
                    the district, covering an area of 817 square miles. Among the wild animals
                    generally found in the mountains are the elephant, rhinoceros, bison, and
                    various kinds of feathered game.</p>
                <p>In 1881 the population was returned at 278,155 (males 143,413, females 134,742),
                    of whom 1985 were Hindus, 1110 were Mohammedans, 270,552 were Buddhists, whilst
                    Christians and aborigines numbered 2363 and 2135 respectively. The area under
                    cultivation in 1885-86 comprised 323,542 acres, and that available for
                    cultivation 186,002 acres; forests occupied 364,524 acres. The chief products of
                    the district are rice, sesamum, tobacco, sugar-cane, cotton, and fruits. The
                    gross revenue of Tharrawaddy in 1885-86 was £85,254, of which the land yielded
                    £51,523. The history of the district is identical with that of <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Henzada</hi><hi rend="italic">{q.v.</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> y</hi><hi rend="italic">).</hi> Tharrawaddy was formed in 1878 out
                    of that portion of Henzada lying east of the Irrawaddy. Its headquarters are at
                    Thoon-tshay, on the stream of the same name.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
