<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0054-0045-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TANGANYIKA (9th edition, volume 23, page 45)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208387">Michigan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926361">Fishes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n54/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TANGANYIKA</label>, a lake in East Central Africa, called <hi
                    rend="italic">Msaga</hi> (“tempestuous”) by the Wakawendi and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kimana</hi> by the Warungu. The meaning of the name Tanganyika is, according to
                    Cameron, nothing more than “the mixing place.” It is the longest freshwater lake
                    in the world, being about 75 miles longer than Lake Michigan. Although the Arabs
                    had long known of the existence of the lake, the first Europeans who discovered
                    it were Speke and Burton in 1858. It has since been visited by Livingstone,
                    Cameron, Stanley, Thomson, and Hore, who have all added to our knowledge of it.
                    Tanganyika, which is situated some 600 miles as the crow flies from the east
                    coast of Africa, extends from 3° 16' S. lat. to 8° 48' S. lat., and lies between
                    29° 10' E. long, and 32° 30' E. long. Its length is 420 miles, and its breadth
                    varies from 10 to 50 miles. Its area is 12,650 square miles, and its altitude
                    may be taken as 2700 feet above sea-level (Cameron, 2710; Stanley, 2770; Hore,
                    2750; Popelin, 2665). It has a coast-line of 900 miles in extent. Its greatest
                    depth has not yet been determined, but Hore states that a 168-fathom rope often
                    failed to reach the bottom. Tanganyika may be described as an enormous crevasse.
                    It is bordered on all sides by hills and mountains, some of which rise to from
                    5000 to 10,000 feet above its waters. The scenery is marked by exceptional
                    grandeur, and is well calculated to impress the traveller. Burton says :—</p>
                <p>“It filled us with admiration, with wonder, and delight. Beyond the short
                    foreground of rugged and precipitous hill-fold, down which the footpath
                    painfully zigzags, a narrow plot of emerald green shelves gently towards a
                    ribbon of glistening yellow sand, here bordered by sedgy rushes, there clear and
                    cleanly cut by the breaking wavelets. Farther in front stretches an expanse of
                    the lightest, softest blue, from 30 to 35 miles in breadth, and sprinkled by the
                    east wind with crescents of snowy foam. It is bounded on the other side by tall
                    and broken walls of purple hill, flecked and capped with pearly mist, or
                    standing sharply pencilled against the azure sky. To the south lie high bluff
                    headlands and capes; and as the eye dilates it falls on little outlying islets,
                    speckling a sea horizon. Villages, cultivated lands, the frequent canoes of the
                    fishermen, give a something of life, of variety, of movement to the
                    scenery.”</p>
                <p>Tanganyika is fed by numerous rivers and streamlets which flow from the
                    surrounding hills, the yearly rainfall being about 27 inches, but the rainy
                    seasons vary extremely in different years, altering the surface area of the lake
                    accordingly. Hore found that between March 1879 and August 1880 the waters had
                    fallen 10 feet 4∣ inches, as marked by a water-gauge he had erected at Ujiji,
                    and he also saw evident signs of the receding of the waters all round the shores
                    of the lake—belts of dead timber and bleached rock. Some 120 rivers and streams
                    flow into the lake; the most important river is the Malagarasi, near Ujiji. Just
                    below the rapids its width is 500 feet, and the average depth 5 feet. For many
                    years Tanganyika was a riddle to African explorers,—Livingstone, Baker, and
                    others believing that it belonged to the Nile system, and that it was connected
                    w ith the Albert Nyanza. That this theory is incorrect was proved when
                    Livingstone and Stanley explored the north end of the lake in November 1871,
                    finding no outlet. It was Cameron, in March 1874, who first solved the riddle,
                    and found that the outlet of Tanganyika was the river Lukuga, at about the
                    centre of the western shore of the lake, 5° 52' 45" S. lat. In 1876 <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n55/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0055-0046"/> this outlet was visited by Stanley, who found
                    that there was no apparent outflow, and doubt was thrown upon Cameron’s
                    observations, which, however, have been proved to be correct by Hore, who in
                    1880 found a strong current setting unequivocally out of the lake. Not only so,
                    but he obtained good views of the river, which gradually widens soon after the
                    rapids near the lake are passed. He followed the river to 5° 50' S. lat., and,
                    from an altitude of 1100 feet above the river, he saw it flowing far away to the
                    westward. The question is therefore settled that Lake Tanganyika belongs to the
                    Congo system, but it is only an occasional tributary to that mighty river, its
                    contribution depending upon the rainfall. The lake is subject to frequent
                    storms, especially from the S.S.E. and S.W., lasting sometimes for two or three
                    days, and leaving a heavy swell, which proves a great hindrance to navigation.
                    Hore says —“I have never witnessed such wondrous cloud-scenery and majestic
                    effects of thunder and lightning as on Tanganyika.”</p>
                <p>The shores and water of the lake abound in animal life,—crocodiles, the
                    hippopotamus, otters, and many kinds of fish being found in its waters. Flocks
                    of waterfowl abound in the river mouths: gulls, divers, herons, kingfishers,
                    eagles, fish-hawks, and black ibis are very numerous. The shores are very
                    fertile,—rice, manioc, kaffre corn, two kinds of ground nuts, maize, uleysi,
                    pumpkins, sweet potatoes, sugar-cane, castor-oil tree, tamarind, cotton, tomato,
                    and cucumber growing luxuriantly. The oil palm grows at Ujiji, Urundi, and at
                    the south end of the lake, the borassus near the Malagarasi river, the screw
                    palm in Uguha, and the raphra in several localities. The tzetse fly is found on
                    the shores of the lake from Ujiji round the southern end as far as Ubwari on the
                    west coast. Amongst the useful timber trees may be noticed the gigantic mbule,
                    the mininga, lignum vitae, and ebony. The people inhabiting the countries on the
                    borders of the lake form ten distinct tribes, with separate national
                    peculiarities and customs. They live in well-organized villages, in which
                    considerable social order is maintained. They have also learnt, to some extent
                    at any rate, to utilize the products of their country: they work their own iron
                    and copper; salt is prepared for barter; palm oil is collected; and in some
                    places there are large pottery works. Their fishing industry is extensive, and
                    dried fish is exported; boatbuilding is carried on to a small extent; cotton
                    cloth is manufactured at several places, and at others the famous grass or
                    palm-fibre cloth; whilst the dairy farms of Uhha export packages of butter.
                    There are several London Missionary Society stations on Lake Tanganyika, also
                    one belonging to the Roman Catholics; and a station of the African International
                    Association is situated at Karema. Ujiji, an Arab town of some importance,
                    stands on the eastern shore of the lake.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
