<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0268-0251-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THÉNARD (9th edition, volume 23, page 251)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wr3t">Oxygen</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:939255">Gays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136041">Students</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1049655">Oxygenators</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1049616">Oxygen</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100369">Rooms</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n268/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THÉNARD</label>, Louis <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacques</hi>
                    (1777-1857), was born on the 4th of May 1777, at Louptière, near
                    Nogent-sur-Seine, in Champagne. His father, though a poor man, sent him to the
                    academy of Sens, where he received a liberal education. At the age of sixteen he
                    went to Paris to study pharmacy. He attended the lectures of Fourcroy and
                    Vauquelin, and saw that the only way to learn chemistry was to work at it.
                    Vauquelin, himself a poor man, admitted a few students to his laboratory on
                    payment of a fee of 20 francs a month. But this fee was prohibitory to the
                    peasant’s son; the utmost that his father could send him just kept him alive in
                    Paris. Thénard went to Vauquelin and asked to be allowed to do any menial work
                    for him, if only he would let him assist in his laboratory. One of Vauquelin’s
                    sisters had slipped into the room and heard part of the conversation; she said
                    to her brother, “He is a good lad; you should keep him; he will help you in the
                    laboratory, and look after our <hi rend="italic">pot</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >au</hi><hi rend="italic">feu·,</hi> your dandy assistants always let it boil.”
                    Thénard was engaged on these terms. Long afterwards he said that he looked upon
                    the chemistry of the <hi rend="italic">pot</hi><hi rend="italic">au</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">feu</hi> and the process of simmering as of very great importance:
                    they had been the turning-point of his life. Thénard assisted Vauquelin in the
                    laboratory and at his lectures, and, when by starving for a day or two he
                    accumulated sous enough to pay for a seat in the gallery, used to go to the
                    theatre to improve his pronunciation and rub off his rustic accent.</p>
                <p>By and by Vauquelin gave him an opportunity of testing his powers as a lecturer.
                    Having to go for some days to the country, he asked Thénard to take his place.
                    For the first two or three lectures his attention was fixed on his work, and his
                    eyes did not wander from the lecture table. On the fifth day he ventured to look
                    round the room, when to his consternation he saw Fourcroy and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n269/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0269-0252"/> Vauquelin among the audience. They were so
                    satisfied with what they had heard that they obtained for Thénard in 1797 an
                    appointment as teacher of chemistry in a school, and in 1798 the post of
                    répétiteur at the École Polytechnique.</p>
                <p>In 1804 Vauquelin resigned the professorship of chemistry at the Collège de
                    France, and successfully used his influence to have Thénard appointed. In 1810
                    he succeeded Fourcroy both as professor of chemistry at the École Polytechnique
                    and as member of the Academy. He was also appointed professor of chemistry in
                    the faculty of the sciences. ^ He was made a chevalier of the Legion of Honour
                    in 1814, commander in 1837, and grand officer in 1842. In 1825 Charles X. gave
                    him the title of baron; from 1827 to 1830 he represented the department of Yonne
                    in the chamber of deputies. In 1832 Louis Philippe made him a peer of France. As
                    vice-president of the conseil supérieure de l’instruction publique, he exercised
                    a great influence on scientific education in France. He died 21st June 1857, and
                    was buried at La Ferte, near Châlon-sur-Saône. In 1861 a statue was erected to
                    him at Sens, and in 1865 the name of his native village was changed to La
                    Louptière-Thénard. Thénard was tall and strongly built, his hair was thick and
                    black, his eyes bright, and his manner active and prompt. He married, in 1810,
                    Mlle. Humblot, granddaughter of Conté. His wife and several of his children
                    predeceased him. He was survived by his son Paul, who had assisted him in some
                    of his later researches.</p>
                <p>Thénard was above all things a teacher: as he himself said, the professor, the
                    assistants, the laboratory, everything, must be sacrificed to the students. The
                    history of his discovery of the peroxide of hydrogen well illustrates the
                    predominance of the teacher in his character. He was lecturing on the formation
                    of salts, and had told his students that a metal must be oxidized to a certain
                    extent in order that it may combine with an acid to form a salt; if the metal be
                    combined with more than the proper quantity of oxygen, the excess of oxygen will
                    be given off when the oxide is treated with an acid, and, as an illustration, he
                    mentioned the action of acids on peroxide of barium. As he spoke his conscience
                    smote him, for the experiment had not been made. Immediately after lecture he
                    mixed peroxide of barium and nitric acid, keeping the temperature low by means
                    of ice. He was surprised to see the peroxide dissolve without any evolution of
                    gas. He left the mixture standing, and next day, before lecture, noticed small
                    bubbles of gas rising from it. Pouring some of the liquid into a test-tube and
                    warming it, he saw a large amount of gas escape, which he easily recognized as
                    pure oxygen. At first he thought the acid had been oxidized, but he soon saw the
                    true explanation of the phenomena, and discovered the peroxide of hydrogen. His
                    lecture experiments were few, well-chosen, and accurately performed. If any
                    failure occurred he would roundly scold his assistant, often apologizing for his
                    vehemence when the short fit of anger was over. His lecture room, seated for
                    1000, was almost always crowded by eager and attentive students and
                    visitors.</p>
                <p>Like most great teachers, Thénard published a text-book, and perhaps we may say
                    that by his <hi rend="italic">Traité de Chimie Élémentaire, Théorique et
                    Pratique</hi> (4 vols., Paris, 1813-16; 6th ed., 5 vols., 1833-36) he did even
                    more to further the progress of the science than by his numerous and important
                    original discoveries. His first original paper (1799) was on the compounds of
                    arsenic and antimony with oxygen and sulphur. Careful analyses led him to
                    conclusions as to the composition of the metallic oxides contradictory of some
                    of Berthollet’s theoretical views; he also showed (1802) that Berthollet’s
                    “zoonic acid” was impure acetic acid. Berthollet, far from resenting these
                    corrections from a younger man, took this opportunity of introducing himself,
                    and invited Thénard to become a member of the “Société d’Arcueil,” to the
                    proceedings of which Thénard contributed important papers. Soon after his
                    appointment as répétiteur at the École Polytechnique Thénard made the
                    acquaintance of Gay-Lussac, and formed with him a lifelong friendship. Their
                    joint work, and its relation to the discoveries of Davy, have been fully
                    recorded in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Gay-Lussac.</hi> Of his separate
                    investigations perhaps the most important is that on the compound ethers, begun
                    in 1807. He showed that each acid gives its own ether, and that the acid and
                    alcohol can be recovered by decomposing the ether by means of caustic alkali.
                    His discovery of peroxide of hydrogen (1818) has already been described. His
                    researches on sebacic acid (1802) and on bile (1807) also deserve special
                    notice. The blue substance known as Thénard’s blue (essentially aluminate of
                    cobalt) was prepared by him in response to a demand by Chaptai for a cheap blue,
                    as bright ,as ultramarine, and capable of standing the temperature of the
                    porcelain furnace.</p>
                <p>Thénard’s researches were chiefly published in the <hi rend="italic">Annale» de
                    Chimie et de</hi><hi rend="italic">Physique,</hi> in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mémoires de la Société</hi><hi rend="italic">d’Arcueil,</hi> and in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Compte» Rendus</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> of the
                    Academy of Sciences. (A. C. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
