<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0295-0278-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THEOSOPHY (9th edition, volume 23, page 278)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1163799">Valentinians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:943906">Gnosticism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882407">Creationism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882382">Creation</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jm0g">Evil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn01649">Creation</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b853m90">Processions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p29x">Process</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp1x">Gnosticism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k675">Freedom</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n295/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THEOSOPHY</label>, as its derivation implies, is a term used
                    to denote those forms of philosophic and religious thought which claim a special
                    insight into the Divine nature and its constitutive moments or processes.
                    Sometimes this insight is claimed as the result of the operation of some higher
                    faculty or some supernatural revelation to the individual; in other instances
                    the theosophical theory is not based upon any special illumination, but is
                    simply put forward as the deepest speculative wisdom of its author. But in any
                    case it is characteristic of theosophy that it starts with an explication of the
                    Divine essence, and endeavours to deduce the phenomenal universe from the play
                    of forces within the Divine nature itself. It is thus differentiated at once
                    from all philosophic systems which attempt to rise from an analysis of phenomena
                    to a knowledge, more or less adequate, of the existence and nature of God. In
                    all such systems, God is the <hi rend="italic">terminus ad quern,</hi> a direct
                    knowledge of whom is not claimed, but who is, as it were, the hypothesis
                    adopted, with varying degrees of certainty in different thinkers, for the
                    explanation of the facts before them. The theosophist, on the other hand, is
                    most at his ease when moving within the circle of the Divine essence, into which
                    he seems to claim absolute insight. This, however, would be insufficient to
                    distinguish theosophy from those systems of philosophy which are sometimes
                    called “speculative” and “absolute,” and which also in many cases proceed
                    deductively from the idea of God. In a wide sense, the system of Hegel or the
                    system of Spinoza may be cited as examples of what is meant. Both thinkers claim
                    to exhibit the universe as the evolution of the Divine nature. They must
                    believe, therefore, that they have grasped the inmost principles of that nature:
                    so much is involved, indeed, in the construction of an absolute system. But it
                    is to be noted that, though there is much talk of God in such systems, the known
                    universe—the world that now is-—is nowhere transcended; God is really no more
                    than the principle of unity immanent in the whole. Hence, while the accusation
                    of pantheism is frequently brought against these thinkers, the term theosophical
                    is never used in their regard. A theosophical system may also be pantheistic, in
                    tendency if not in intention; but the transcendent character of its Godhead
                    definitely distinguishes it from the speculative philosophies which might
                    otherwise seem to fall under the same definition. An historical survey shows,
                    indeed, that theosophy generally arises in connexion with religious needs, and
                    is the expression of religious convictions or aspirations. Now the specifically
                    religious consciousness is not pantheistic in any naturalistic sense; God is
                    rather regarded as the transcendent source of being and purity, from which the
                    individual in his natural state is alienated and afar off. Theosophy accepts the
                    testimony of religion that the present world lies in wickedness and
                    imperfection, and faces the problem of speculatively accounting for this state
                    of things from the nature of the Godhead itself. Theosophy is thus in some sort
                    a mystical philosophy of the existence of evil; or at least it assumes this form
                    in some of its most typical representatives.</p>
                <p>The name with which it is oftenest coupled is mysticism (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Mysticism).</hi> The latter term has properly a practical rather than a
                    speculative reference; but it is currently applied so as to include the systems
                    of thought on which practical mysticism was based. Thus, to take only one
                    prominent example, the profound speculations of Meister <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Eckhart</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.vf)</hi> are always treated under the head of
                    Mysticism, but they might with equal right appear under the rubric Theosophy. In
                    other words, while an emotional and practical mysticism may exist without
                    attempting philosophically to explain itself, speculative mysticism is almost
                    another name for theosophy. There is still a certain difference observable,
                    however, in so far as the speculative mystic remains primarily concerned with
                    the theory of the soul’s relation to God, while the theosophist gives his
                    thoughts a wider scope, and frequently devotes himself to the elaboration of a
                    fantastic philosophy of nature.</p>
                <p>In the above acceptation of the term, the Neoplatonic doctrine of emanations from
                    the supra-essential One, the fanciful emanation-doctrine of some of the Gnostics
                    (the aeons of the Valentinian system might be mentioned), and the elaborate
                    esoteric system of the Kabbalah, to which the two former in all probability
                    largely contributed, are generally included under the head of theosophy. In the
                    two latter instances there may be noted the allegorical interpretation of
                    traditional doctrines and sacred writings which is a common characteristic of
                    theosophical writers. Still more typical examples of theosophy are furnished by
                    the mystical system of Meister Eckhart and the doctrine of Jacob <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Boehme</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.υ.),</hi> who is known as “the
                    theosophist” <hi rend="italic">par excellence.</hi> Eckhart’s doctrine asserts
                    behind God a predicateless Godhead, which, though unknowable not only to man but
                    also to itself, is, as it were, the essence or potentiality of all things. From
                    it proceed, and in it, as their nature, exist, the three persons of the Trinity,
                    conceived as stadia of an eternal self-revealing process. The eternal generation
                    of the Son is equivalent to the eternal creation of the world. But the sensuous
                    and phenomenal, as such, so far as they seem to imply independence of God, are
                    mere privation and nothingness; things exist only through the presence of God in
                    them, and the goal of creation, like its outset, is the repose of the Godhead.
                    The soul of man, which as a microcosmos resumes the nature of things, strives by
                    self-abnegation or self-annihilation to attain this unspeakable reunion (what
                    Eckhart calls being buried in God). Regarding evil simply as privation, Eckhart
                    does not make it the pivot of his thought, as was afterwards done by Boehme, but
                    his notion of the Godhead as a dark and formless essence is a favourite thesis
                    of theosophy. The followers of Eckhart are either practical mystics, or
                    reproduce at most what may be called their master’s speculative theology, till
                    we come to Boehme.</p>
                <p>Besides mystical theology, Boehme was indebted to the writings of Paracelsus.
                    This circumstance is not accidental, but points to an affinity in thought. The
                    nature-philosophers of the Renaissance, such as Nicholas of Cusa, Paracelsus,
                    Cardan, and others, curiously blend scientific ideas with speculative notions
                    derived from scholastic theology, from Neoplatonism, and even from the Kabbalah.
                    Hence it is customary to speak of their theories as a mixture of theosophy and
                    physics, or theosophy and chemistry, as the case may be. Boehme offers us a
                    natural philosophy of the same sort. As Boehme is the typical theosophist, and
                    as modern theosophy has nourished itself almost in every case upon the study of
                    his works, his dominating conceptions supply us with the best illustration of
                    the general trend of this mode of thought. His speculation turns, as has been
                    said, upon the necessity of reconciling the existence and the might of evil with
                    the existence of an all-embracing and all-powerful God, without falling into
                    Manichaeanism on the one hand, or, on the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n296/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0296-0279"/> other, into a naturalistic pantheism that denies
                    the reality of the distinction between good and evil. He faces the difficulty
                    boldly, and the eternal conflict between the two may be said to furnish him with
                    the principle of his philosophy. It is in this connexion that he insists on the
                    necessity of the Nay to the Yea, of the negative to the positive. Eckhart’s
                    Godhead appears in Boehme as the abyss, the eternal nothing, the essenceless
                    quiet (“Ungrund” and “Stille ohne Wesen” are two of Boehme’s phrases). But, if
                    this were all; the Divine Being would remain an abyss dark even to itself. In
                    God, however, as the condition of His manifestation, lies, according to Boehme,
                    the “eternal nature” or the <hi rend="italic">mysterium</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >magnum,</hi> which is as anger to love, as darkness to light, and, in general,
                    as the negative to the positive. This principle (which Boehme often calls the
                    evil in God) illuminates both sides of the antithesis, and thus contains the
                    possibility of their real existence. By the “Qual” or torture, as it were, of
                    this diremption, the universe has qualitative existence, and is knowable. Even
                    the three persons of the Trinity, though existing <hi rend="italic"
                    >idealiter</hi> beforehand, attain reality only through this principle of nature
                    in God, which is hence spoken of as their <hi rend="italic">matrix.</hi> It
                    forms also the matter, as it were, out of which the world is created; without
                    the dark and fiery principle, we are told, there would be no creature. Hence God
                    is sometimes spoken of as the father, and the eternal nature as the mother, of
                    things. Creation (which is conceived as an eternal process) begins with the
                    creation of the angels. The subsequent fall of Lucifer is explained as his
                    surrender of himself to the principle of nature, instead of dwelling in the
                    heart of God. He sought to make anger predominate over love; and he had his
                    will, becoming prince of hell, the kingdom of God’s anger, which still remains,
                    however, an integral part of the Divine universe. It is useless to follow Boehme
                    further, for his cosmogony is disfigured by a wild Paracelsian symbolism, and
                    his constructive efforts in general are full of the uncouth straining of an
                    untrained writer. In spite of these defects, his speculations have exercised a
                    remarkable influence within the present century, notably upon the later phases
                    of Schelling’s philosophy, upon Franz von Baader, Molitor, and others.</p>
                <p>Schelling’s <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Inquiries into the Nature of Human
                    Freedom</hi> (1809) is almost entirely a reproduction of Boehme’s ideas, and
                    forms, along with Baader’s writings, the best modern example of theosophical
                    speculation. In his philosophy of identity <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Schelling</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.υ.)</hi> had already defined the Absolute as
                    pure indifference, or the identity of subject and object (of the ideal and the
                    real), but without advancing further into theogony. He now proceeded to
                    distinguish three moments in God, the first of which is the pure indifference
                    which, in a sense, precedes all existence—the primal basis or abyss, as he calls
                    it, in agreement with Boehme. But, as there is nothing before or besides God,
                    God must have the ground or cause of His existence in Himself. This is the
                    second moment, called nature in God, distinguishable from God, but inseparable
                    from Him. It is that in God λvhich is not God Himself; it is the yearning of the
                    eternal One to give birth to itself. This yearning is a dumb unintelligent
                    longing, which moves like a heaving sea in obedience to some dark and indefinite
                    law, and is powerless to fashion anything in permanence. But in correspondence
                    to the first stirring of the Divine existence there awakes in God Himself an
                    inner reflexive perception, by means of which—since no object is possible for it
                    but God—God beholds Himself in His own image. In this, God is for the first time
                    as it were realized, although as yet only within Himself. This perception
                    combines as understanding with the primal yearning, which becomes thereby free
                    creative will, and works formatively in the originally lawless nature or ground.
                    In this wise is created the world as we know it. In every natural existence
                    there are, therefore, two principles to be distinguished—first, the dark
                    principle, through which this is separated from God, and exists, as it were, in
                    the mere ground; and, secondly, the Divine principle of understanding. The first
                    is the particular will of the creature, the second is the universal will. In
                    irrational creatures the particular will or greed of the individual is
                    controlled by external forces, and thus used as an instrument of the universal.
                    But in man the two principles are consciously present together, not, however, in
                    inseparable union, as they are in God, but with the possibility of separation.
                    This possibility of separation is the possibility of good and evil. In Boehme’s
                    spirit, Schelling defended his idea of God as the only way of vindicating for
                    God the consciousness which naturalism denies, and which ordinary theism emptily
                    asserts. This theosophical transformation of Schelling’s doctrine was largely
                    due to the influence of his contemporary <hi rend="smallcaps">Baader</hi>
                    (g.v.). Baader distinguishes, in a manner which may be paralleled from Boehme,
                    between an immanent or esoteric process of self-production in God, through which
                    He issues from His unrevealed state, and the emanent, exoteric, or real process,
                    in which God overcomes and takes up into Himself the eternal “nature” or the
                    principle of selfhood, and appears as a Trinity of persons. The creation of the
                    world is still further to be distinguished from these two processes as an act of
                    freedom or will; it cannot, therefore, be speculatively constructed, but must be
                    historically accepted. Baader, who combined his theosophy with the doctrines of
                    Roman Catholicism, has had many followers. Among thinkers on the same lines, but
                    more or less independent, Molitor is perhaps the most important. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Swedenborg</hi><hi rend="italic">{q.vf</hi> is usually reckoned
                    among the theosophists, and some parts of his theory justify this inclusion; but
                    his system as a whole has 1ittle in common with those speculative constructions
                    of the Divine nature which form the essence of theosophy, as strictly
                    understood. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. se.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
