<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0694-0669-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TURPENTINE (9th edition, volume 23, page 669)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35f3t">Rosin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hm52s7v">Production</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tk2p">Resins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925164">Fir</term>
                    <term ref="fast:826212">Balsams</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880392">Corsicans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204694">Alabama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n694/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TURPENTINE</label> consists of the oleo-resins which exude
                    from certain trees, especially from some conifers and from the terebinth tree,
                    <hi rend="italic">Pistacia Terebinthus,</hi> L. It was to the product of the
                    latter, now known as Chian turpentine, that the term was first applied. The
                    terebinth tree <hi rend="italic">(τέρμιvθoς</hi> of Theophrastus) and its resin
                    <hi rend="italic">(ῥητίνη τερμívθιvη)</hi> were well known and highly prized
                    from the earliest times. The tree is a native of the islands and shores of the
                    Mediterranean, passing eastward into Central Asia; but the resinous exudation
                    found in commerce is collected in the island of Scio. Chian turpentine is a
                    tenacious semi-fluid transparent body, yellow to dull brown in colour, with an
                    agreeable resinous odour and little taste. On exposure to the air it becomes
                    dry, hard, and brittle. In their general characters, turpentines are soft solids
                    or semi-fluid bodies, consisting of a mixture of one or more resins with
                    essential oils, which, although differing in physical properties, have a
                    composition corresponding to the formula C <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 16</hi>. They also contain minute quantities of oxygenated
                    oils. Formerly they had considerable reputation in medicine, and they still
                    continue to be employed in plasters and ointments; but their great use is in the
                    arts, for which they are separated by distillation into rosin or colophony (see
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Rosin,</hi> vol. xx. p. 852) and oil or spirit of
                    turpentine.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Crude or common turpentine</hi> is the commercial name which
                    embraces the oleo-resin yielded by several coniferous trees, both European and
                    American. The principal European product, sometimes distinguished as Bordeaux
                    turpentine, is obtained from the sea pine, <hi rend="italic">Pinus
                    maritima,</hi> in the Landes department of France. Crude turpentine is further
                    yielded by the Scotch fir, <hi rend="italic">P. sylvestris,</hi> throughout
                    northern Europe, and by the Corsican pine, <hi rend="italic">P. Laricio,</hi> in
                    Austria and Corsica. In the United States the turpentine-yielding pines are the
                    swamp pine, <hi rend="italic">P. palustris,</hi> and the loblolly, <hi
                    rend="italic">P. Taeda,</hi> both inhabiting North and South Carolina, Georgia,
                    and Alabama. <hi rend="italic">Venice turpentine</hi> is yielded by the larch
                    tree, <hi rend="italic">Larix europaea,</hi> from which it is collected
                    principally in Tyrol. <hi rend="italic">Strasburg turpentine</hi> is obtained
                    from the bark of the silver fir; but it is collected only in small quantities.
                    Less known turpentines are obtained from the mountain pine, <hi rend="italic">P.
                    Pumilio,</hi> the stone pine, <hi rend="italic">P. Cembra,</hi> the Aleppo pine,
                    <hi rend="italic">P. halepensis,</hi> &amp;c. The so-called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Canada balsam,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">Abies balsamea</hi> (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Balsam,</hi> vol. iii. p. 293), is also a true turpentine.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Oil of turpentine</hi> as a commercial product is obtained from
                    all or any of these oleo-resins, but on a large scale only from crude or common
                    turpentine. The essential oil is rectified by redistillation with water and
                    alkaline carbonates, and the water which the oil carries over with it is removed
                    by a further distillation over calcium chloride. Oil of turpentine is a
                    colourless liquid of oily consistence, with a strong characteristic odour and a
                    hot disagreeable taste. Its boiling point ranges from 152° to 172° C. at
                    ordinary temperature; its sp. gr. is between 0∙856 and 0∙870; and in optical
                    properties it rotates the plane of polarized light both to right and left in
                    varying degrees according to its sources. It is soluble in alcohol, ether,
                    benzol, other essential oils, and the fixed oils, and itself is a solvent of
                    resins and caoutchouc. On exposure to the air it dries to a solid resin, and
                    when oxidized in the presence of water gives off peroxide of hydrogen—a reaction
                    utilized in the preparation of a disinfectant called “sanitas.” Oil of
                    turpentine is largely used in the preparation of varnishes, and as a medium by
                    painters in their fiat” colours.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
