<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0648-0627-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TURGOT (9th edition, volume 23, page 627)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136041">Students</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1172973">Wealth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7712k">Wealth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bv7p">Jansenists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n648/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TURGOT</label>. <hi rend="smallcaps">Anne Robert Jacques
                    Turgot, Marquis de l’Aulne</hi> (1727-1781), French statesman and economist, was
                    born at Paris, 10th May 1727. He was the third son of Michel Étienne Turgot and
                    of Madeleine Françoise Martineau. His family, which was ancient and noble, is
                    said to have been originally Scottish, but had long been settled in Normandy.
                    His ancestors early abandoned the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n649/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0649-0628"/> sword for the robe. Both his father and
                    grandfather had been in the civil service of the state: his father was “prévôt
                    des marchands” at Paris, and won a high reputation as a magistrate and
                    administrator. Turgot in his childhood was timid, and showed in company an
                    absent and embarrassed air, from which he never afterwards entirely freed
                    himself, and which in later life was sometimes unjustly attributed to hauteur.
                    His mother, through excessive or injudicious efforts to correct these faults,
                    appears to have aggravated them. He obtained his early education at the Collége
                    Louis-le-Grand, and was afterwards a student of the Collége du Plessis. He then
                    entered the seminary of St Sulpice, and thence passed to the Sorbonne with the
                    view of taking his licence in theology. But he decided finally in 1751 not to
                    follow the ecclesiastical profession. His opinions were inconsistent with that
                    calling, and he said “he could not consent to wear a mask all his life.” He
                    showed at this time an enthusiastic love of literature and powers of memory
                    which are described as “prodigious,” as well as a penetrating intellect and a
                    sound judgment. We have the testimony of the Abbé Morellet, who was then his
                    intimate acquaintance and constant companion, to the singular purity, the
                    simplicity, modesty, and frank gaiety which characterized him.</p>
                <p>As prior of the Sorbonne (an honorary office conferred annually on some
                    distinguished student) he wrote and delivered publicly in 1750 two remarkable
                    pieces,—one <hi rend="italic">On the Benefits which the Christian Religion has
                    conferred on Mankind,</hi> the other <hi rend="italic">On the Historical
                    Progress of the Human Mind.</hi> Having chosen the law as his profession, he was
                    appointed in 1752 “conseiller substitut du procureur général,” and afterwards
                    “conseiller au parlement.” The controversy arising from the refusal of the
                    sacraments to the Jansenists by the archbishop of Paris being then agitated
                    between the parlement and the clergy, Turgot wrote (1753) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters to a Vicar-General on Toleration</hi> and a pamphlet entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Le Conciliateur,</hi> in favour of religious liberty and against
                    the interference of the temporal power in theological disputes. In 1753 he
                    became “maître des requêtes.” He discharged his professional duties with
                    scrupulous purity and conscientious industry. He continued at the same time his
                    studies in ancient and modern literature (including English and German),
                    mathematics, astronomy, chemistry, and natural history, and frequented the
                    salons of Madame de Graffigny (authoress of <hi rend="italic">Les Lettres
                    Péruviennes),</hi> Madame Geoffrin, and Madame du Deffand. Whilst he enjoyed the
                    acquaintance and society of D’Alembert, Baron d’Holbach, Raynal, Marmontel,
                    Morellet, Galiani, Helvétius, and other notabilities of the time, he maintained
                    his intellectual independence and refused to connect himself with any party or
                    political group. About this time he also entered into relations with Quesnay and
                    Gournay—the principal members of the physiocrats. He was attracted to them by
                    the similarity of their sentiments on social questions and their opinions on
                    economic policy to those which he himself entertained. Turgot accompanied
                    Gournay in 1755 and 1756 in his official tours of inspection as intendant of
                    commerce, and on Gournay’s death in 1759 he wrote his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eloge.</hi> He then made a short visit to eastern France and a part of
                    Switzerland. When he arrived at Geneva he went to see Voltaire at Les Délices,
                    and formed with him what proved to be a lasting friendship. He contributed about
                    this period several articles to the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie.</hi> In 1761
                    the controller-general Bertin appointed him intendant of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >généralité</hi> of Limoges. In that district the mass of the people were sunk
                    in poverty and barbarism; the corvées for the construction of roads and the
                    transport of military equipages were oppressive; the country was depopulated by
                    the requisitions for the militia; the taxation was excessive and unfairly
                    distributed; the state of the roads was wretched; and the general condition of
                    agriculture was deplorable. Turgot’s administration of the district lasted for
                    thirteen years, and was marked by a steady pursuit of the public good, and a
                    firm resistance to inertia, prejudice, and corruption. In particular he strongly
                    maintained the cause of the industrious poor, and insisted on a more equitable
                    assessment of the public charges which pressed unduly upon them. With nobly
                    disinterested spirit he refused to be transferred to other <hi rend="italic"
                    >généralités</hi> in which the salary was higher and the administration easier.
                    Rising above the common prejudices of the <hi rend="italic">philosophes,</hi> he
                    sought the cooperation of the clergy, both to inform him of everything relating
                    to the circumstances of the people which it was desirable for him to know, and
                    to explain to their flocks the nature and objects of the measures he proposed to
                    put in operation; and he acknowledges that he found in them earnest and active
                    auxiliaries. But he was not seconded as he ought to have been by the central
                    Government, and had often to remonstrate with the Abbé Terray, minister of
                    finance. During the scarcity of 1770 and 1771, which was particularly severe in
                    Limousin, he devoted himself with untiring assiduity to the relief of the
                    distressed, and, when he had exhausted such public funds as were available,
                    incurred for the same object a personal debt of more than 20,000 livres. Shortly
                    after the accession of Louis XVI. Turgot was appointed by Maurepas (19th July
                    1774) minister of marine, and in that capacity began at once to initiate
                    important reforms and to conceive far-reaching projects. But he filled the post
                    only for five weeks, being then (21st August) promoted to the ministry of
                    finance. In his new office he addressed to the young king a declaration of the
                    principles by which he intended to be guided: “No bankruptcy, no increase of
                    taxation, and no borrowing.” Economy and wise management were to be his only
                    resources. Fearing the opposition he must encounter, he appealed to Louis to
                    support him. By a decree of the 13th September 1774, he re-established free
                    trade in grain within the kingdom, which had been suspended by Terray, and
                    authorized the importation of supplies from abroad; the traffic in other
                    alimentary substances was also relieved of many impediments, and various
                    monopolies and exclusive privileges were abolished; the <hi rend="italic"
                    >octroi</hi> taxation was reformed, public works promoted, and improvements in
                    agriculture encouraged. Some of these measures were made the pretext for
                    disturbances, known as <hi rend="italic">la guerre des farines,</hi> which
                    Turgot always suspected the Prince de Conti of having fomented. The riots had to
                    be suppressed by armed force, and the energetic action of the minister against
                    them was made a ground of attack by his enemies. The parlement had been weakly
                    recalled by Louis from the exile to which in the preceding reign Maupeou had
                    condemned it. It now constituted itself the organ of the resistance of menaced
                    interests to the measures of Turgot, who would gladly have abolished it,
                    providing in its place better political securities and courts of justice on a
                    new plan. In January 1776 he presented to the king a memoir proposing, amongst
                    other things, the abolition of the corvée, to be replaced by a territorial tax,
                    from which the privileged classes were not to be exempt, and the suppression of
                    the <hi rend="italic">jurandes</hi> (exclusive trade corporations). The edicts
                    for these purposes were submitted to Miromesnil, keeper of the seals, a secret
                    enemy of Turgot, who, spurred on by Maurepas, wrote a memoir against them, and
                    opposed them in the king’s council. The courtiers, the nobility, the clergy, and
                    the leading members of the industrial corporations now combined against the
                    minister, and were joined by a large part of the common people, who did not
                    understand his policy. The Count de Provence, afterwards Louis XVIII., wrote a
                    pamphlet, entitled <hi rend="italic">The Dream of M. de</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n650/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0650-0629"/><hi rend="italic">Maurepas,</hi> against Turgot.
                    The parlement refused to register the decrees; but the king held a <hi
                    rend="italic">lit de justice,</hi> which Voltaire proposed to call a <hi
                    rend="italic">lit de bienfaisance,</hi> and compelled the registration. This
                    forced submission only aggravated the rancour of Turgot’s enemies, and the king
                    had not the firmness to sustain his minister against the coalition. A vile
                    conspiracy having poisoned Louis’s mind against him, he addressed to the king an
                    eloquent letter in which he pointed out the grave perils impending over the
                    throne and the state, and warned Louis that princes who are tempted to give
                    themselves up to the direction of courtiers should remember the fate of Charles
                    I. The minister received his dismissal on the 12th of May 1776. He had been in
                    office only twenty months, of which he had lost six in repressing sedition, and
                    for seven more had been confined to his bed by the gout; but he had done during
                    his tenure an extraordinary amount of work. Voltaire, however, nobly avenged
                    Turgot on his enemies in his <hi rend="italic">Épître à un Homme.</hi> The
                    fallen minister devoted his remaining years to his favourite studies, especially
                    to physical science and the ancient poets; he enjoyed the society of Lavoisier,
                    D’Alembert, Condorcet, Bossut, Rochon, and Rouelle, and attended the meetings of
                    the Academy of Inscriptions, of which he was elected vice-director in 1777. He
                    also corresponded with Price and Franklin, and, if we may believe Condorcet,
                    with Adam Smith, whose acquaintance he had made at Paris in 1766.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Dugald Stewart, however,
                    cannot find any evidence of a correspondence between Turgot and Smith. It has
                    also been said that during this period Turgot corresponded with Hume. But little
                    more than three months intervened between his dismissal and the death of Hume
                    (25th August 1776) and there appears to be no trace of letters having passed
                    between them in this interval. They had corresponded, but at a much earlier
                    date; see Burton’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Hume,</hi> ii. 352, 381.</p></note>
                    Turgot died at Paris on 18th March 1781.</p>
                <p>Turgot’s official career is for ever memorable in the history of social politics.
                    Never did a public man give himself to the service of the community with more
                    earnest and unselfish devotion. He made it his object to convince before
                    commanding, in order that his aims might be better understood and his directions
                    more surely obeyed; and, in issuing any instruction, making any decision, or
                    advising any legislative act, he stated fully, by way of preamble, the grounds
                    on which he proceeded. In the documents which he prepared on these occasions we
                    have a body of valuable materials on administrative and economic questions; some
                    of them contain the substance of chapters in the <hi rend="italic">Wealth of
                    Nations.</hi> When he became minister, the finances were in what seemed a
                    desperate condition, and the general state of affairs justified the prediction
                    of Louis XV.—“après moi le déluge.” Turgot framed a vast plan of reform, at once
                    administrative and economic, as the only hope for the salvation of the state. He
                    speaks of his system of measures as intended for “the regulation of the
                    kingdom,” thus showing that he contemplated nothing less than a pacific
                    revolution. But the first condition of success in such an effort was wanting,
                    namely, the entire confidence and unfaltering support of the king, and the
                    energetic exercise of the royal power in carrying out a policy of thorough
                    reform against all adverse influences.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Some have thought that the cardinal error in Turgot’s policy
                    lay in his not having convoked the states-general; that would, however, have
                    been simply to open the flood-gates.</p></note> Turgot’s struggle, though it
                    failed from causes independent of himself, cannot be regarded without profound
                    sympathy and admiration. Nor was it without a large measure of immediate
                    success. Whilst he scrupulously observed all the pecuniary obligations of the
                    state, he greatly diminished the crushing deficit which he found on his
                    accession to office, and re-established the public credit in such a degree that
                    the Dutch bankers offered him a loan of sixty millions of livres at less than 5
                    per cent. His financial and other plans, of course, fell with him, and his most
                    important measures were annulled; but his policy and his writings exercised a
                    lasting influence, and many of his projects were realized by the Revolution.
                    Turgot is altogether one of the most massive and imposing figures of the 18th
                    century. His whole character and public action are marked by an air of austere
                    grandeur. Single-mindedness and veracity were of the very essence of his nature.
                    Absolutely unbiased by selfish ends, he lived only for France, for truth, and
                    for his duty. Believing intensely in a definite system of social and economic
                    principles, which he had early formed by independent study and reflexion, he was
                    prepared to carry them out with dauntless determination, and with a lofty
                    contempt for the interested or prejudiced opposition they were sure to
                    encounter. He has been accused of a doctrinaire rigidity, and it is possible
                    that, as a practical man, he wanted flexibility; yet he was often willing, not
                    indeed to disguise his convictions, but to postpone the realization of his
                    plans. In his public acts he always showed a lively concern for the poor and the
                    suffering; in private life he was humane and benevolent; in his relations with
                    his friends, amiable and affectionate. Malesherbes, the only other minister of
                    his time who was worthy to be his colleague, said of him that "he had the head
                    of Bacon and the heart of L’Hôpital,” and, on the moral side at least, this was
                    no exaggerated estimate.</p>
                <p>Possessed of a many-sided culture, Turgot wrote on a great variety of
                    subjects—philosophic, scientific, and literary—though political economy is the
                    branch of knowledge with which his name must always be most closely associated.
                    Already in 1749, whilst a student at St Sulpice, he addressed to his friend,
                    Abbé de Cicé, afterwards bishop of Auxerre, a <hi rend="italic">Letter on Raper
                    Money,</hi> in which he asserted, in opposition to the views of Law and his
                    followers, doctrines similar to those now accepted by all competent authorities.
                    In one of his discourses at the Sorbonne in 1750, moving into the higher regions
                    of the philosophy of society, he makes a remarkable attempt to work out the
                    pregnant conception, already enunciated by Pascal, of the continuity of the
                    intellectual movement of our race, thus preparing the way for Condorcet’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Esquisse,</hi> and ultimately for the sociology of Comte. In 1753
                    he translated under the title of <hi rend="italic">Questions Importantes sur le
                    Commerce,</hi> a tract of Dr Josiah Tucker on the expediency of naturalizing
                    foreigners. He contributed to the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie</hi> the
                    articles <hi rend="italic">Étymologie, Existence, Expansibility Fondations,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Foires et Marchés.</hi> The first of these contains much
                    that is just as well as interesting, though in the time of Turgot the subject
                    could not yet be treated on genuinely scientific bases. In the second he
                    undertakes a refutation of the Berkeleian theory. The third contains some
                    ingenious suggestions in practical physics. The article on foundations maintains
                    the right of the Government to dispose of them for the public good, suppressing
                    them if hurtful, and directing the funds to more useful objects; the policy
                    advocated in it was afterwards carried into effect by the constituent assembly.
                    In the paper on fairs and markets he argues that these are institutions adapted
                    only for an immature state of commercial relations, and that more good would be
                    done by liberating trade from the legislative fetters which everywhere impeded
                    it than by bestowing special privileges or other encouragements on particular
                    localities as centres of exchange. In the <hi rend="italic">Éloge</hi> of
                    Gournay he combines with his tribute to the memory of his friend a vindication
                    of the principle of industrial freedom, which that friend had condensed in the
                    oft-repeated maxim, “Laissez faire, laissez passer.” To the period of Turgot’s
                    intendance belong his unfinished <hi rend="italic">Valeurs et Monnaies,</hi>
                    intended to form an article in the <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire de
                    Commerce</hi> of Morellet; his <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> (to the Abbé
                    Terray) <hi rend="italic">on the Freedom of the Corn-Trade</hi>; his memoir <hi
                    rend="italic">Sur les Prêts d'Argent,</hi> in which he insists on the necessity
                    of leaving free the interest on loans; and that on the principles which should
                    direct legislation respecting mines and quarries, as well as the work on which
                    his reputation as a systematic economist mainly rests, namely, his <hi
                    rend="italic">Réflexions sur la Formation et la Distribution des Richesses.</hi>
                    This treatise was written for two Chinese youths who had been sent over by the
                    Jesuit missionaries to study in France. The work was first published in 1766 in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Éphémérides du Citoyen,</hi> edited by Dupont de Nemours,
                    and speedily passed through four editions. It gives in brief compass a luminous
                    statement of some of the most important principles relating to the economic
                    constitution of societies—the division of labour, the origin and use of money,
                    the nature of capital and the different modes of its employment, the necessary
                    rise of capitalist chiefs of industry, the legitimacy of interest on loans, and
                    the impossibility of arbitrarily fixing the rate of that interest. It
                    unfortunately contains, along with many truths, the erroneous doctrines of the
                    physiocrats on the exclusive productiveness of agriculture and on the consequent
                    propriety of imposing taxes only on the land of a country. This book was
                    erroneously represented by Condorcet as " the germ of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Wealth of Nations,”</hi> and has been spoken of by others as “anticipating some
                    of the leading principles” of Smith. The truth is, most of what it contains had
                    either been fully set forth by the earlier economists or was familiar to Quesnay
                    and his group. It is, in fact, not a work of research but of exposition, and,
                    regarded in this light, has real originality and may justly be pronounced a
                    masterpiece.</p>
                <p>Fuller information on the life, administrative labours, and writings of Turgot
                    will be found in the following works :—Dupont de Nemours, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Notes et Mémoires sur la Vie, l' Administration, et les Ouvrages de
                    Turgot,</hi> 1782, and enlarged in his edition of Turgot’s works mentioned
                    below; Condorcet, <hi rend="italic">Vie de Turgot,</hi> 1786; A. Batbie, <hi
                    rend="italic">Turgot, Philosophe, Économiste, Administrateur,</hi> 1861; J.
                    Tissot, <hi rend="italic">Turgot, sa Vie, son Administration, ses ouvrages</hi>
                    (a <hi rend="italic">mémoire couronne),</hi> 1862; A. Neymarck, <hi
                    rend="italic">Turgot et ses Doctrines,</hi> 1885. The last-named contains the
                    most complete treatment of the subject. See also an <hi rend="italic">Éloge</hi>
                    by Dupuy (1781) in the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires de l'Académie des Inscriptions
                    et Belles-Lettres,</hi> vol. xlv.; L. de Lavergne, Zes <hi rend="italic"
                    >Économistes Français au Dix-Huitième Siècle,</hi> 1870, and Mr. John Morley s
                    article in his <hi rend="italic">Critical Miscellanies,</hi> 2d series, 1877. A
                    collected edition of Turgot's <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n651/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0651-0630"/> writings was published for the first time by
                    Dupont in 9 vols. (Paris 1808-11); the most complete and in every respect best
                    edition is that contained in the <hi rend="italic">Collection des Principaux
                    Économistes</hi> of Coquelin and Guillaumin, 2 vols., 1844, with a biographical
                    notice by Eugène Daire. An English translation of <hi rend="italic">The
                    formation and Distribution of Wealth</hi> was published in London in 1793, and
                    was reprinted in 1859 in Lord Overstone’s <hi rend="italic">Select Collection of
                    Scarce and Valuable Economical Tracts,</hi> edited by J. R. M'Culloch. (J. K.
                    I.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
