<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0322-0305-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THIRLWALL, Connop (9th edition, volume 23, page
                    305)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wr06">Hares</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:951448">Hares</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1113216">Sermons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n322/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THIRLWALL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Connop</hi></label>
                    (1797-1875), bishop of St David’s, was born at Stepney on 11th January 1797, and
                    was the son of the Rev. Thomas Thirlwall, at the time lecturer at St Dunstan’s,
                    Stepney, and afterwards rector of Bowers Gifford, in Essex. The family were of
                    Northumbrian extraction. Young Connop showed the most remarkable precocity,
                    learning Latin at three, reading Greek at four, and writing sermons at seven.
                    When he was twelve his admiring father published his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Primitiae,</hi> sermons and poems, the thoughts of an imitative boy in the
                    style of a grown man. No especial greatness could have been safely predicted
                    from these performances, which Thirlwall assiduously strove to suppress in after
                    years. He shortly afterwards went to the Charterhouse, where he wrote a number
                    of letters to a friend named John Candler, some of which have been preserved.
                    They display the same extraordinary prematurity, but are barren of anything
                    original except what he himself calls “sensibility to the great and beautiful in
                    morality.” By a curious coincidence his future rival in Greek history, Grote,
                    and Hare, his coadjutor in the translation of Niebuhr, were among his
                    schoolfellows. He took up his residence at Trinity College, Cambridge, in
                    October 1814, and gained the Craven university scholarship, one of three
                    recorded instances of this honour being obtained by freshmen, and the
                    chancellor’s classical medal. In October 1818 he was elected to a fellowship,
                    and immediately went for a year’s travel on the Continent. At Rome he gained the
                    friendship of Bunsen, which had a most important influence on his life. On his
                    return, “distrust of his own resolutions and convictions” led him to abandon for
                    the time his intention of being a clergyman, and he settled down to the study of
                    the law, “with a firm determination not to suffer it to engross my time so as to
                    prevent me from pursuing other branches of knowledge.” This was not the way to
                    become lord chancellor, and, though he afterwards says, “My aversion to the law
                    has not increased,” he adds, “It scarcely could.” How little his heart was with
                    it was shown by the labour he soon imposed upon himself of translating and
                    prefacing Schleiermacher’s essay on the Gospel of St Luke, “very injudiciously,”
                    says Maurice, who seems to think that it may have cost Thirlwall the
                    archbishopric of Canterbury. The translation, nevertheless, marks an era in
                    English theology. He further, probably influenced by Hare, who had already
                    translated Tieck, rendered two of the latter’s most recent <hi rend="italic"
                    >Novellen</hi> into English. In 1827 he at length made up his mind to quit his
                    uncongenial profession, and was ordained deacon the same year. Beyond all
                    question he might have obtained the highest distinction both as jurist and
                    advocate, had law interested him more, or other things less. No one ever
                    possessed a more judicial mind. Of his oratory, Mill, whom he opposed at a
                    debating society, says, “Before he had uttered ten sentences I set him down as
                    the best speaker I had ever heard, and I have never since heard any one whom I
                    placed above him.”</p>
                <p>It is not often that a scholar twice makes an epoch by a translation. Such was
                    Thirlwall’s destiny: he joined with Hare in translating Niebuhr’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Pome j</hi> the first volume appeared in 1828. The
                    translation was attacked in the <hi rend="italic">Quarterly</hi> as favourable
                    to scepticism, and the translators jointly replied. In 1831 the friends
                    established the <hi rend="italic">Philological Museum,</hi> which lived through
                    only six numbers, though among Thirlwall’s contributions was his masterly paper
                    on the irony of Sophocles,—“the most exquisite criticism I ever read,” says
                    Sterling. On Hare’s departure from Cambridge in 1832, Thirlwall became assistant
                    college tutor, which led him to take a memorable share in the great controversy
                    upon the admission of Dissenters which arose in 1834. Dr Turton, the regius
                    professor of divinity, had written a pamphlet objecting to the admission, on the
                    pretext of the apprehended unsettlement of the religious opinions of young
                    churchmen. Thirlwall replied by pointing out that no provision for theological
                    instruction was in fact made by the colleges except compulsory attendance at
                    chapel, and that this was mischievous. This attack upon a time-hallowed piece of
                    college discipline brought upon him a demand for the resignation of his office
                    as assistant tutor. He complied at once; his friends generally thought that he
                    ought to have tested the master’s power. The occurrence marked him out for
                    promotion from a Liberal Government, and in the autumn he received the
                    chancellor’s living of Kirby-under-Dale, in Yorkshire. Though devoted to his
                    parochial<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n323/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0323-0306"/> duties, he found time to begin the book which has
                    remained the principal work of one whose performance, however great, rarely rose
                    to the level of his power. His <hi rend="italic">History of Greece,</hi>
                    unfortunately for him and for us, was a commission from Lardner’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Cabinet Cyclopaedia,</hi> and was originally intended to have been
                    condensed into two or three duodecimo volumes. The scale was enlarged, but
                    Thirlwall always felt cramped. He seems a little below his subject, and a little
                    below himself. Yet, such was his ability that his history is usually allowed to
                    fall only just short of Grote’s, a work undertaken with far greater enthusiasm,
                    and executed with far greater advantages. Sterling pronounces him “a writer as
                    great as Thucydides and Tacitus, and with far more knowledge than they.” The
                    first volume was published in 1835, the last in 1847. A noble letter from
                    Thirlwall to Grote, and Grote’s generous reply, are published in the life of the
                    latter.</p>
                <p>In 1840 Thirlwall was raised to the see of St David’s. The promotion was entirely
                    the act of Lord Melbourne, an amateur in theology, who had read Thirlwall’s
                    introduction to Schleiermacher, and satisfied himself of the propriety of the
                    appointment. “I don’t intend to make a heterodox bishop if I know it,” he said.
                    Thirlwall so little expected the honour that he was absent on a pedestrian tour,
                    and it was some days before he could be found. In most essential points he was a
                    model bishop, and in acquainting himself with Welsh, so as to preach and conduct
                    service in that language, he performed a feat which few bishops could have
                    imitated. It cannot be said that he was greatly beloved by his clergy, who felt
                    their intellectual distance too great, and were alternately frozen by his
                    taciturnity and appalled by his sarcasm. The great monument of his episcopate is
                    the eleven famous charges in which he from time to time reviewed the position of
                    the English Church with reference to whatever might be the most pressing
                    question of the day,—addresses at once judicial and statesmanlike, full of
                    charitable wisdom and massive sense. No similar productions, it may safely be
                    said, were ever so eagerly looked for, or carried with them such weight of
                    authority. His endeavours to allay ecclesiastical panic, and to promote
                    liberality of spirit, frequently required no ordinary moral courage. He was one
                    of the four prelates who refused to inhibit Bishop Colenso from preaching in
                    their dioceses, and the only one who withheld his signature from the addresses
                    calling upon Colenso to resign his see. He took the liberal side in the
                    questions of Maynooth, of the admission of Jews to parliament, of the Gorham
                    case, and of the conscience clause. He was the only bishop who voted for the
                    disestablishment of the Irish Church, though but as a painful necessity.
                    Concurrent endowment would have been much more agreeable to him. For many years
                    he was the only statesman on the bench; it would have been a great benefit to
                    the Church of England had it been possible to have raised him to the primacy
                    upon the death of Archbishop Howley. But such was the complexion of
                    ecclesiastical politics that the elevation of the most impartial prelate of his
                    day would have been resented as a piece of party spirit.</p>
                <p>Thirlwall’s private life was happy and busy. He never married, but found
                    sufficient outlet for his deep affectionateness of nature in his tenderness to
                    the children of others, and to all weak things except weak-minded clergymen. He
                    was devoted to animals, and rivalled Southey and Jeremy Bentham in his love for
                    cats. Perhaps the most durable monument to his memory will be his incomparable
                    volume of letters to a friend, Miss Johnes of Dolaucothy, a young lady in every
                    way worthy to be the correspondent of such a man. Even as letters these rank
                    with the best in the language; but as letters from age to youth, sympathizing
                    with all its feelings, entering into all its pleasures, at once inspiring and
                    amusing, guiding without seeming to direct, and entertaining without seeming to
                    condescend, they are unique in their delightful branch of literature. They are
                    also important as revealing Thirlwall’s mind on numerous subjects which he has
                    not elsewhere treated, and most interesting from their picture of simplicity of
                    character associated with greatness of intellect, and of the multiplicity of his
                    intellectual interests, from which novels and fine art were by no means
                    excluded. During his latter years he took great interest in the revision of the
                    authorized version of the Bible, and was chairman of the revisers of the Old
                    Testament. He resigned his see in May 1874, and retired to Bath, where he died
                    on July 27, 1875.</p>
                <p>As scholar, critic, and ecclesiastical statesman Thirlwall is almost above
                    praise. He was not a great original thinker; he lacked the creative faculty and
                    the creative impulse. The world owes such vestiges of his power as it possesses
                    to a series of fortunate accidents—an importunate editor, vexatious church
                    controversies, and an admirable friend. Though not most fully exerted, the force
                    of his mind is perhaps best appreciated in the volume of his letters edited by
                    Dean Perowne. His treatment of every question is consummate; the largest and the
                    smallest seem alike to him. His character, with its mixture of greatness and
                    gentleness, was thus read by Carlyle :—“a right solid honest-hearted man, full
                    of knowledge and sense, and, in spite of his positive temper, almost timid.”</p>
                <p>Thirlwall’s <hi rend="italic">History of Greece</hi> remains a standard book. His
                    literary and theological remains have been edited by Dean Perowne in three
                    volumes, two of which are occupied by his charges. His letters on literary and
                    theological subjects, with a connecting memoir, have been published by Dean
                    Perowne and the Rev. Louis Stokes. His <hi rend="italic">Letters to α
                    Friend</hi> were originally published by Dean Stanley, and there is a revised
                    and corrected edition. For a general view of Thirlwall’s life and character, see
                    the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review,</hi> vol. exliii.; for a picture of him
                    in his diocese, <hi rend="italic">Temple Bar,</hi> vol. lxxvi. The review of his
                    letters in <hi rend="italic">Blackwood’s Magazine</hi> for 1852 is by the late
                    Rev. W. Lucas Collins. (R. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
