<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-6931-0743-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DEVEREUX, Robert</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 743</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1043068">Occasionalism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1137041">Success</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194756931" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DEVEREUX, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>, Earl of
                    Essex, the son of Walter Devereux, Viscount Hereford, was born at Netherwood, in
                    Herefordshire, in the year 1567. He succeeded to the title of Earl of Essex at
                    the age of ten; and about two years afterwards was sent by his guardian, Lord
                    Burghley, to Trinity College, Cambridge. He took the degree of master of arts in
                    1582, and soon afterwards retired to his seat at Lampsie, in South Wales. He did
                    not, however, continue long in this retreat; for we find him, in his seventeenth
                    year, at the court of Queen Elizabeth, who immediately honoured him with
                    singular marks of her favour. Authors seem very unnecessarily perplexed to
                    account for this young earl’s gracious reception at the court of Elizabeth. But
                    the reasons seem pretty obvious; he was her relation, the son of one of her most
                    faithful servants, the son-in-law of her favourite Leicester, and a very
                    handsome and accomplished youth. Towards the end of the following year, 1585, he
                    attended the Earl of Leicester to Holland; and gave signal proofs of his
                    personal courage during the campaign of 1586, particularly at the battle of
                    Zutphen, where the gallant Sir Philip Sidney was mortally wounded. On this
                    occasion the Earl of Leicester conferred on him the honour of knight
                    banneret.</p>
                <p>In the year 1587, Leicester being appointed lord steward of the household, Essex
                    succeeded him in the honourable post of master of the horse; and the year
                    following, when the queen assembled an army at Tilbury to oppose the Spanish
                    invasion, Essex was made general of the horse, From this time he was considered
                    as the favourite of the queen; and if any mark was yet wanting to fix the
                    opinion of the people in this respect, it was shown by the queen’s conferring on
                    him the honour of the garter.</p>
                <p>It is not to be wondered at that so rapid an elevation should have affected so
                    young a man as the Earl of Essex, who henceforward showed a very high spirit,
                    and often behaved petulantly enough to the queen herself, who yet did not chuse
                    to be controlled by her subjects. His eagerness about this time to dispute her
                    favour with Sir Charles Blount, afterwards Lord Mountjoy and Earl of Devonshire,
                    cost him some blood; for Sir Charles, thinking himself affronted by the earl,
                    challenged him, and after a short contest wounded him in the knee. The queen, so
                    far from being displeased with this occurrence, is said to have sworn a good
                    round oath, that it was fit somebody should take him down, otherwise there would
                    be no ruling him. However, she reconciled the rivals, who, to their credit,
                    continued good friends as long as they lived.</p>
                <p>The gallant Essex, however, was not so entirely captivated with his situation as
                    to become insensible to the allurements of military glory. In 1589, Sir John
                    Norris and Sir Francis Drake having sailed on an expedition against Spain, the
                    young favourite, without the permission or knowledge of his royal mistress,
                    followed the fleet, which he joined as they were sailing towards Lisbon, and
                    acted with great resolution in the repulse of the Spanish garrison of that city.
                    The queen wrote him a very severe letter on the occasion; but, after his return,
                    she was soon appeased. Yet it was not long before he again incurred her
                    displeasure, by marrying the widow of Sir Philip Sidney. In 1591 he was sent to
                    France with the command of 4000 men to the assistance of Henry IV. In 1596 he
                    was joined with the lord high admiral Howard in the command of the famous
                    expedition against Cadiz, the success of which is universally known. In 1597 he
                    was appointed <pb break="no" facs="nls:194756944" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6944-0744"
                    />master of the ordnance, and the same year commanded another expedition against
                    Spain, called the <hi rend="italic">Island Voyage,</hi> the particulars of which
                    are also well known.</p>
                <p>Soon after his return he was created earl marshal of England; and, on the death
                    of the great Lord Burghley in 1598, elected chancellor of the university of
                    Cambridge. This is reckoned one of the last instances of the good fortune of a
                    man who had now advanced too high to sit at ease; and those who longed for his
                    honours and employments very closely applied themselves to bring about his fall.
                    The first great shock he received in the queen’s favour arose from a warm
                    dispute between her majesty and himself, about the choice of some fit and able
                    person to superintend the affairs of Ireland. The affair is related by Camden,
                    who tells us that nobody was present except the lord admiral, Sir Robert Cecil,
                    secretary, and Windebank, clerk of the seal. The queen looked upon Sir William
                    Knolls, uncle of Essex, as the most proper person for the charge; but Essex
                    contended that Sir George Carew was a much fitter man for the situation. When
                    the queen could not be persuaded to approve his choice, he so far forgot himself
                    and his duty as to turn his back upon her in a contemptuous manner; which
                    insolence her majesty not being able to bear, gave him a box on the ear, and bid
                    him go and be hanged. Essex put his hand to his sword and swore revenge. This
                    violent storm, however, soon subsided, and they were again, at least apparently,
                    reconciled.</p>
                <p>The total reduction of Ireland being proposed soon afterwards, the earl was
                    pitched upon as the only man by whom it could be accomplished. This was an
                    artful contrivance of his enemies, who hoped to ruin him, by employing him in a
                    desperate undertaking; nor were their expectations disappointed. He declined
                    this fatal preferment as long as he could; but perceiving that he should have no
                    quiet at home, he accepted it; and his commission as lord lieutenant passed the
                    great seal on the 12th of March 1598. The earl met with nothing in Ireland but
                    ill success and disasters; in the midst of which an army was suddenly raised in
                    England, under the command of the Earl of Nottingham, by the suggestions of the
                    earEs enemies, who insinuated that he meditated an invasion of diis native
                    country, rather than the reduction of the Irish rebels. This and other
                    considerations induced him to quit his post and to come over to England, which
                    he accordingly did without leave. On his arrival he burst into her majesty’s
                    bed-chamber as she was rising, and was received with a mixture of tenderness and
                    severity; but she soon afterwards thought fit to deprive him of all his
                    employments except that of master of the horse; and he was committed to the
                    custody of the lord-keeper, with whom he continued six months. No sooner had he
                    regained his liberty than he plunged into many extravagancies, to which he was
                    instigated by knaves and fools, but perhaps more powerfully by his own passions.
                    He first determined to obtain an audience of the queen by force; he refused to
                    attend the council when summoned; and when the queen sent the lord-keeper, the
                    lord chiefjustice, and two others, to. know his grievances, he confined them,
                    and then marched with his friends into the city, in expectation that the people
                    would rise in his favour. But in this he was completely disappointed. Fie was at
                    last besieged and taken in his house in Essex Street, and being committed to the
                    Tower, he was tried by his peers, condemned, and executed. He was a polite
                    scholar, and a generous friend to literature. The Earl of Essex died in the
                    thirty-fourth year of his age, leaving by his lady one son and two
                    daughters.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
