<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-5241-0613-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DANCE, or Dancing</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 613</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v18f">Princesses</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sn03">Rope</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s11w">Woman</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1033832">Nationalism</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194755241" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DANCE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Dancing</hi></label>, as at
                    present practised, may be defined an agreeable motion of the body, adjusted by
                    art to the measures or tones of instruments, or of the voice. But, according to
                    what some reckon more agreeable to the true genius of the art, dancing is the
                    art of expressing the sentiments of the mind, or the passions, by measured steps
                    or bounds that are made in cadence, by regulated motions of the body, and by
                    graceful gestures; all performed to the sound of musical instruments or of the
                    voice.</p>
                <p>There is no account of the origin of the practice of dancing amongst mankind. It
                    is found to exist amongst all nations whatever, even the most rude and
                    barbarous; and, indeed, however much the assistance of art may be necessary to
                    make any one perfect in the practice, the foundation must certainly lie in the
                    human constitution itself.</p>
                <p>As barbarous people are observed to have the strongest passions, so they are also
                    observed to be the most easily affected by sounds, and the most habitually
                    addicted to dancing. Sounds to us the most disagreeable, the drumming of sticks
                    upon an empty cask, or the noise made by blowing into reeds incapable of
                    yielding one musical note tolerable to us, is agreeable music to them. Much more
                    are they affected by the sound of instruments which have any thing agreeable in
                    them. Mr Gallini informs us, that “The spirit of dancing prevails almost beyond
                    imagination among both men and women in most parts of Africa. It is even more
                    than instinct, it is a rage, in some countries of that part of the globe. Upon
                    the Gold Coast especially, the inhabitants are so passionately fond of it, that
                    in the midst of their hardest labour, if they hear a person sing, or any musical
                    instrument played, they cannot refrain from dancing. There are even
                    well-attested storiee of some negroes flinging themselves at the feet of an
                    European playing on a fiddle, entreating him to desist, unless he had a mind to
                    tire them to death; it being impossible for them to cease dancing while he
                    continued playing.”</p>
                <p>The same thing is found to take place in America, though, as the inhabitants of
                    that continent are found to be of a more fierce and barbarous nature than the
                    African nations, their dances are still more uncouth and barbarous than those of
                    the negroes. “In Mexico” says Gallini, “they have also their dances and music,
                    but in the most uncouth and barbarous style. For their symphony they have wooden
                    drums, something in form of a kettledrum, with a kind of pipe or flageolet made
                    of a hollow cane or reed, but very grating to an European ear. It is observed
                    they love every thing that makes a noise, how disagreeable soever the sound is.
                    They will also hum over something like a tune when they dance thirty or forty in
                    a circle, stretching out their hands, and laying them on each other’s shoulders.
                    They stamp and jump, and use the most antic gestures for several hours, till
                    they are heartily weary. And one or two of the company sometimes step out of the
                    rings to make sport for the rest, by showing feats of activity, throwing their
                    lances up into the air, catching them again, bending backwards and springing
                    forwards with great agility.”</p>
                <p>The origin of dancing amongst the Greeks was most certainly the same as amongst
                    all other nations; but as they proceeded a certain length in civilization, their
                    dances were of consequence more regular and agreeable than those of the more
                    barbarous nations. They reduced dancing into a kind of regular system; and had
                    dances proper for exciting, by means of the sympathy above mentioned, any
                    passion whatsoever in the minds of the beholders. In this way they are said to
                    have proceeded lengths to us absolutely incredible. At Athens it is stated that
                    the dance of the Eumenides or Furies on the theatre had so expressive a
                    character as to strike the spectators with irresistible terror. Men grown old in
                    the profession of arms trembled; the multitude ran out; women with child
                    miscarried; people imagined they saw in earnest those terrible deities
                    commissioned with the vengeance of heaven to pursue and punish crimes upon
                    earth.</p>
                <p>The Greeks had martial dances, which they reckoned useful in keeping up and
                    cherishing the warlike spirit of their youth; but the Romans, though equally
                    warlike with the Greeks, never had any thing of the kind. This may probably be
                    owing to the want of that romantic turn for which the Greeks were so remarkable.
                    The Romans had no heroes among them, such as Hercules, Achilles, or Ajax; nor
                    does the whole Roman history furnish an example of a general who made war after
                    the manner of Alexander the Great. Though their soldiers were as valiant as ever
                    the Greeks could pretend to be, the object with them was the honour of the
                    republic, and not their own personal praise. Hence there was less fury, and much
                    more cool deliberate valour, exercised by the Romans than by any other nation
                    whatsoever. The passions of pride, resentment, obstinacy, and the like, were
                    excited in them, not by the mechanical means of music and dancing, but by being
                    taught that it was their chief honour to fight for the republic. It does not,
                    however, appear that the Romans were at all less capable of being affected in
                    this mechanical manner than the Greeks. When dancing was once introduced, it had
                    the very same effects at Rome as at Athens.</p>
                <p>Amongst the Jews dancing seems to have formed a part of the religious worship on
                    some occasions, as we learn from some passages in the Psalms, though we do not
                    find either saltation or singing positively enjoined by a divine precept. In the
                    Christian churches mentioned in the New Testament, there is no account of
                    dancing being introduced as an act of worship, though it is certain that it was
                    used as such in after-ages. Mr Gallini tells us, that “at Limoges, not long ago,
                    the people used to dance the round in the choir of the church which is under the
                    invocation of their patron saint; and at the end of each psalm, instead of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Gloria</hi><hi rend="italic">Patri,</hi> they sung, <hi
                    rend="italic">St Marcel, pray for us, and we shall dance in honour of you”</hi>
                    Though dancing would now be looked upon as the highest degree of profanation in
                    a religious assembly, yet it is certain that dancing, considered as an
                    expression of joy, is no more a profanation than singing, or than simple
                    speaking; nor can it be thought in the least degree more absurd that a Christian
                    should dance for joy that Jesus Christ is risen from the dead, than that David
                    danced before the ark when it was returned to him after a long absence.</p>
                <p>Plato reduces the dances of the ancients to three classes: first, the military
                    dances, which tended to make the <pb break="no" facs="nls:194755254"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-5254-0614"/>body robust, active, and well disposed for all the
                    exercises of war; secondly, the domestic dances, which had for their object an
                    agreeable and innocent relaxation and amusement; thirdly, the mediatorial
                    dances, which were in use in expiations and sacrifices. Of military dances there
                    were two sorts; the <hi rend="italic">gymnopedic</hi> dance, or the dance of
                    children; and the <hi rend="italic">enoplian,</hi> or armed dance. The Spartans
                    had invented the first as an early excitation of the courage of their children,
                    and in order to lead them on insensibly to the exercise of the armed dance. This
                    children’s dance used to be executed in the public place. It was composed of two
                    choirs, the one of grown men, the other of children; whence, being chiefly
                    designed for the latter, it took its name. They were both of them in a state of
                    nudity. The choir of the children regulated their motions by those of the men,
                    and all danced at the same time, singing the poems of Thales, Alemaeon, and
                    Dionysodotus. The <hi rend="italic">enoplian</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pyrrhic</hi> was danced by young men armed <hi rend="italic">cap-a-pied,</hi>
                    who executed, to the sound of the flute, all the proper movements either for
                    attack or for defence. It was composed of four parts. The first, called the <hi
                    rend="italic">pbdisnι</hi> or footing, consisted in a quick shifting motion of
                    the feet, such as was necessary for overtaking a flying enemy, or for getting
                    away from him when an overmatch; the second, the <hi rend="italic">xiphism,</hi>
                    a kind of mock fight, in which the dancers imitated all the motions of
                    combatants, aiming a stroke, darting a javelin, or dexterously dodging,
                    parrying, or avoiding a blow or thrust; the third part, called the <hi
                    rend="italic">homos,</hi> consisted in very high leaps or vaultings, which the
                    dancers frequently repeated for the better accustoming themselves occasionally
                    to leap over a ditch, or spring over a wall; the <hi rend="italic"
                    >tetvacoìnos,</hi> or the fourth and last part, was a square figure, executed by
                    slow and majestic movements, but it is uncertain whether this was everywhere
                    executed in the same manner.</p>
                <p>Of all the Greeks, the Spartans were those who most cultivated the Pyrrhic dance.
                    Athenaeus relates, that they had a law by which they were obliged to exercise
                    their children in it from the age of five years. This warlike people constantly
                    retained the custom of accompanying their dances with hymns and songs. The
                    following was sung for the dance called <hi rend="italic">trichoria,</hi> said
                    to be instituted by Lycurgus, and which had its name from its being composed of
                    three choirs, one of children, another of young men, and the third of old. The
                    old men opened the dance, saying, “In time past we were valiant.” The young men
                    answered, “We arc so at present.” “We shall be still more so when our time
                    comes,” replied the chorus of children. The Spartans never danced except with
                    real arms. In process of time, however, other nations came to use only weapons
                    of wood on such occasions. Nay, it was only so late as the days of Athenaeus,
                    who lived in the second century, that the dancers of the Pyrrhic, instead of
                    arms, carried only flasks, and ivy-bound wands (thyrsus) or reeds.. But, even in
                    Aristotle’s days, they had begun to use thyrsuses instead of pikes, and lighted
                    torches instead of javelins and swords. With these torches they executed a dance
                    called the <hi rend="italic">conflagration of the world.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Of</hi> the dances for amusement and recreation, some were simply gambols, or
                    sportive exercises, which had no character of imitation, and of which the
                    greater part exist to this day. The others were more complex, agreeable,
                    figured, and were always accompanied with singing. Amongst the first or simple
                    ones was the <hi rend="italic">ascoliasmus.</hi> which consisted in jumping with
                    one foot only, on bladders filled with air or wine, and rubbed on the outside
                    with oil. The <hi rend="italic">dy-podium</hi> was jumped with both feet close.
                    The <hi rend="italic">hybeslesis</hi> was what is called in this country the <hi
                    rend="italic">somerset.</hi> Of the geçond kind were that called the <hi
                    rend="italic">wine-press,</hi> of which there is a description in Longinus, and
                    the Ionian dances. These last, in the original of their institution, had nothing
                    but what was decent and modest; but, in time, their movements came to be so
                    depraved, as to be employed in expressing nothing except voluptuousness, and
                    even the grossest obscenity.</p>
                <p>Amongst the ancients there were no festivals nor religious assemblies but what
                    were accompanied with songs and dances. It was not held possible to celebrate
                    any mystery, or to be initiated, without the intervention of these two arts. In
                    short, they were looked upon as so essential in these kinds of ceremonies, that
                    to express the crime of such as were guilty of revealing the sacred mysteries,
                    they employed the word <hi rend="italic">hheistae,</hi> signifying to be out of
                    the dance. The most ancient of these religious dances is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bacchic,</hi> which was not only consecrated to Bacchus, but to all the deities
                    whose festival was celebrated with a kind of enthusiasm. The most grave and
                    majestic was the <hi rend="italic">lap pordιematic,</hi> which was executed to
                    the lyre, and accompanied with the voice. On his return from Crete, Theseus
                    instituted a dance, at which he himself assisted at the head of a numerous and
                    splendid band of youths, round the altar of Apollo. The dance was composed of
                    three parts; the <hi rend="italic">strophe, antistrophe,</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">stationary.</hi> In the strophe, the movements were from the right
                    to the left; in the antistrophe, from the left to the right; and in the
                    stationary, they daneed before the altar; so that the stationary did not mean an
                    absolute pause or rest, but only a more slow or grave movement. Plutarch is
                    persuaded that in this dance there is a profound mystery. He thinks, that by the
                    strophe is indicated the motion of the world from east to west; by the
                    antistrophe, the motion of the planets from the west to the east; and by the
                    stationary, the stability of the earth. To this dance Theseus gave the name of
                    <hi rend="italic">geranos,</hi> or the crane, because the figures which
                    characterised it bore a resemblance to those described by cranes in their
                    flight.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Stage-<hi rend="smallcaps">DANCES.</hi></hi> The Greeks were
                    the first who united the dance to their tragedies and comedies; not indeed as
                    making part of those spectacles, but merely as an accessary.</p>
                <p>The Romans, as usual, copied from the Greeks; but in the reign of Augustus they
                    left their instructors far behind them. At that time two very extraordinary men
                    made their appearance, who invented a new species of entertainment, and carried
                    it to an astonishing degree of perfection. Nothing was then talked of but the
                    wonderful talents and amazing performances of Pylades and Bathylus, who were the
                    first to introduce among the Romans what the French call the <hi rend="italic"
                    >ballet d’action,</hi> in which the performer is both actor and dancer.</p>
                <p>Pylades undertook the difficult task of representing, with the assistance of the
                    dance alone, strong and pathetic situations. He succeeded perhaps beyond his own
                    expectation, and may be called the father of that style of dancing which is
                    known to us by the name of <hi rend="italic">grave</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >serious pantomime.</hi> Bathylus, an Alexandrian, and a freeman of Meccnas,
                    took upon himself to represent such subjects as required a certain liveliness
                    and agility. He was handsome in his person; and the two great scourgers of Roman
                    follies, Persius, and especially Juvenal, speak of him as the gallant of every
                    woman in Rome. The latter, in his cynic style, even goes so far as to say, that
                    when Bathylus performed the dance called, after the name of a celebrated female
                    dancer, <hi rend="italic">Cheromenos-Leda,</hi> the gravest matron was turned
                    off her guard, and the young virgin longed for the dancer’s addresses.</p>
                <p>Nature had been exceedingly partial to these two men. They were endowed with
                    genius, and with all the exterior accomplishments which could captivate the eye.
                    By their study, application, and the desire to establish a lasting<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194755267" xml:id="kp-eb0707-5267-0615"/> reputation, they displayed
                    to the greatest advantage all the resources which the art of dancing could
                    supply. But, like two phenomena, they disappeared, and the world did not look
                    upon their like again. Government withdrew its protection; the art gradually
                    sunk into obscurity, and, on the accession of Trajan to the empire, became even
                    entirely forgotten.</p>
                <p>Thus buried with the other arts in entire oblivion, dancing remained uncultivated
                    till about the fifteenth century, when ballets were revived in Italy at a
                    magnificent entertainment given by a nobleman of Lombardy at Tortona, on account
                    of the marriage between Galeas Duke of Milan and Isabella of Aragon. Every
                    resource that poetry, music, dancing, and machinery could supply, was employed
                    and exhausted on the occasion. The description given of so superb an
                    entertainment excited the admiration of all Europe, and roused the emulation of
                    several men of genius, who improved the hint by introducing amongst their
                    countrymen a kind of spectacle equally pleasing and novel.</p>
                <p>It would seem, however, that at first the women had no share in the public or
                    theatrical dance; at least we do not find them mentioned in the various
                    entertainments given at the opera in Paris till the 21st of January 1681, when
                    the then dauphiness, the Princess of Conti, and some other ladies of the first
                    distinction in the court of Louis XIV. performed a ballet in the opera called
                    <hi rend="italic">Le Triomphe de</hi><hi rend="italic">l’Amour.</hi> This union
                    of the two sexes served to enliven and render the spectacle more pleasing and
                    more brilliant than it ever had been at any other period; and it was received
                    with so much applause, that on the 16th of May following, when the same opera
                    was acted in Paris at the theatre of the Palais Royal, it was thought
                    indispensable for the success of that kind of entertainment to introduce female
                    dancers. They have continued ever since to be the principal support of the
                    opera.</p>
                <p>A ballet perfect in all its parts, says Noverre, in his treatise on this subject,
                    is a picture drawn from life, of the manners, dresses, ceremonies, and customs
                    of all nations. It must therefore be a complete pantomime, and speak, as it
                    were, through the eyes, to the very soul of the spectator. If it wants
                    expression, or if it be deficient in point of situation and scenery, it
                    degenerates into a spectacle equally flat and monotonous.</p>
                <p>A ballet, in whatever style it may be conceived, should, according to Aristotle,
                    be composed, as well as poetry, of two different parts, which he calls parts of
                    quality and parts of quantity. Nothing exists in nature without matter, form,
                    and figure; the ballet therefore becomes a mere nonentity if it be deficient in
                    any of those essential parts which mark and constitute the being of any one
                    thing, animate or inanimate. The matter here is the subject intended for
                    representation; its form consists in the ingenious distribution of the plan, and
                    the various component parts constitute its figure. The form therefore contains
                    the parts of quality, and the extent the parts of quantity.</p>
                <p>Thus it appears that ballets are in some degree subject to the rules of poetical
                    composition. They, nevertheless, differ from tragedies and comedies, in that the
                    former are not subject to the three unities of time, place, and action. Yet they
                    require an unity of plot, in order that the various scenes may meet and
                    terminate on the same point. The ballet, therefore, may be termed the brother of
                    the drama, though not restrained to its stricter rules, which only serve to
                    cramp the imagination, check its flight, and confine genius, and which, if
                    adhered to, must set aside all thought of composition of ballets, by depriving
                    them of their chief ornament, pleasing variety.</p>
                <p>Noverre considers tragedy as the subject most suitable for the art of dancing. It
                    abounds in noble incidents, situations, and character, and these produce the
                    best stage effects. Besides, the passions are more forcibly expressed by great
                    characters than by common men; the imitation is of course less difficult, and
                    the action in the pantomime more significant, natural, and intelligible.</p>
                <p>“The business of a skilful master,” he observes, “is to foresee, as it were at
                    one glance, the general effect that may result from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >ensemble,</hi> and never give the preference to one single part over the whole.
                    The only way for him to bestow his thoughts on the greatest number, is to forget
                    for a while the principal characters of the drama; if his whole attention should
                    entirely be occupied with the parts of his first dancers of both sexes, the
                    action is suspended, the scenes are slow in their progress, and the whole
                    performance must fall short of its desired effect.</p>
                <p>“In the tragedy of Merope by Voltaire, the principal characters are Merope,
                    Polifonte, Egiste, and Narbas. But although the parts of the inferior actors are
                    not of equal importance, yet they all concur to the general action, and to the
                    progression of the drama, which would appear deficient in some parts should
                    either of those characters be wanting in the representation. No useless
                    personage should be obtruded on the stage. Every thing therefore that may tend
                    to weaken the effect of the drama ought to be carefully avoided, and only that
                    number of actors introduced which is barely requisite for the execution of the
                    performance.</p>
                <p>“A ballet is a production of the same kind. It must be divided into acts and
                    scenes, each of which, as well as the act itself, must have its beginning, its
                    middle, and its end; that is, in other words, exposition, plot, and
                    denouement.”</p>
                <p>Noverre, in considering the knowledge necessary for attaining perfection in the
                    present art, observes, that mythology, ancient poetry, and chronology, ought to
                    be the primary study of a ballet-master, who ought also to possess a genius for
                    poetry and painting, since the art borrows all its charms from a perfect
                    imitation of nature. A slight knowledge of geometry cannot but prove very
                    advantageous, as it will help the master to introduce his figures in due
                    proportion, to calculate exactly, and execute with precision. By means of that
                    unerring guide, he will retrench every superfluous accessary, and thus enliven
                    the performance. Taste will introduce elegance, genius create variety, and
                    judgment direct the whole.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Country-<hi rend="smallcaps">Dance</hi>,</hi> commonly so
                    written, and hence seeming to imply a rustic way of dancing borrowed from
                    country people or peasants, is, however, merely a corruption of the French <hi
                    rend="italic">Contre-danse,</hi> where a number of persons placing themselves
                    opposite one to another begin a figure.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Rope-<hi rend="smallcaps">Dancer</hi> (schoenobates),</hi> a
                    person who walks, leaps, dances, and performs several other feats upon a small
                    rope or wire. The ancients had their rope-dancers as well as we, and these had
                    four several ways of exercising their art: the first vaulted or turned round the
                    rope like a wheel round its axis, and there hung by the heels or neck; the
                    second flew or slid from above, resting on their stomachs, with the arms and
                    legs extended; the third ran along a rope stretched in a right line, or up and
                    down; and the fourth not only walked on the rope, but made surprising leaps and
                    turns thereon. They had likewise the <hi rend="italic">cremnobates</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">orobates</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> that is, people who walked
                    on the brinks of precipices. Nay more, Suetonius in his life of Galba, Seneca in
                    one of his Epistles, and Pliny in his eighth book, make mention of elephants
                    which were taught to walk on the rope.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="smallcaps">Dancing</hi>-Girls</hi> are employed all
                    over the East, as affording great diversion at all public entertainments.</p>
                <p>These dancing-girls, whether in a settled or unsettled <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:194755280" xml:id="kp-eb0707-5280-0616"/>condition, live in a band or
                    community, under the direction of some superannuated female of the same
                    profession, under whom they receive a regular education, and are trained up in
                    all the arts of love and pleasing, like scholars in an academy. Thus they
                    acquire the art of captivating the affections of the other sex to such a degree,
                    that nothing is more common than for one of the princes or chief people of the
                    country to take a liking to one of these girls, and waste immense sums on her,
                    though at the same time his own haram maybe stocked with beauties far superior,
                    and who are besides possessed of the natural modesty of the sex, to which the
                    others have not the smallest pretensions. Thus some of these girls acquire
                    immense wealth.</p>
                <p>With regard to the performances of these women as dancers, we have various
                    accounts. The author of a work entitled <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the War in
                    Asia,</hi> acquaints ns, “that their attitudes as well as movements are not
                    ungraceful. Their persons are delicately formed, gaudily attired, and highly
                    perfumed. By the continuation of wanton attitudes, they acquire, as they grow
                    warm in the dance, a frantic lasciviousness themselves, and communicate, by a
                    natural contagion, the most voluptuous desires to the beholders.” Mr Ives seems
                    to have been more cool on this subject. “I could not,” says he, “see any thing
                    in their performance worthy of notice. Their movements are more like tumbling or
                    showing postures than dancing. Their dress is thin and light; and their hair,
                    necks, ears, arms, wrists, fingers, legs, feet, and even their toes, are covered
                    with rings of gold and silver, made after a clumsy manner. They wear two rings
                    in their noses; and, by their staring looks and odd gesticulations, you would
                    rather suspect them to be mad women than morris-dancers. The band of music that
                    attends them is not less singular in its way; it is chiefly composed of three or
                    four men, who hold two pieces of bell-metal in their hand, with which they make
                    an incessant noise; another man beats what he is pleased to call a drum; and
                    that they may not want vocal music to complete the band, there are always two
                    others appointed to sing. These last generally lay in their mouths a good
                    loading of betel-nut before they begin, which, after having been well chewed,
                    tinges the saliva with such a redness, that a stranger would judge them to bleed
                    at the mouth by too violent an exertion of their voice. These gentry are called
                    <hi rend="italic">ticky-taw</hi> boys, from the two words <hi rend="italic"
                    >ticky taw,</hi> which they continually repeat, and chant with great vehemence.
                    The dancing-girls are sometimes made use of in their religious ceremonies, as
                    when the priests bring forth the images of their gods into the open fields on a
                    car ornamented with lascivious figures, these girls dance before the images
                    amidst a great crowd of people; and having been selected for their superior
                    beauty, are very profitable to their masters the priests, who are said to
                    prostitute them to all comers.”</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
