<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-6099-0679-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DELAMBRE, J</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 679</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45717p75">Prizes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194756099" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DELAMBRE, J</label>. B. J. an eminent mathematician and
                    astronomer, was born at Amiens on the 19th September 1749. He studied in the
                    gymnasium of that tow n, and by his intimate acquaintance with the Latin and
                    Greek languages, as well as his amiable disposition and prodigious memory, he
                    drew the attention of his preceptor, the celebrated French poet the Abbé
                    Delisle, who at that time taught in the college. This was the beginning of a
                    friendship between them, which only terminated with the life of the poet.</p>
                <p>Having accomplished his first course of studies, it remained to pursue in Paris a
                    career begun under such favourable auspices; but the expense exceeded his
                    resources. Fortunately, however, his family had formerly founded a gratuitous
                    place for a limited time in one of the great colleges of the University of
                    Paris: the town of Amiens, which appears to have had the disposal of it,
                    bestowed it on Delambre; and thus the benefit of an act of beneficence was
                    reflected back on its source.</p>
                <p>The time during which he was to enjoy the advantage he had obtained passed away,
                    and his family, subjected to . many other kinds of expense, left him to provide
                    for him- self. In this state he passed more than a year in expectation L of a
                    better situation, and supported with constancy very great privations. Itwasthen
                    that he gave himself upto those i historical and literary studies which were the
                    origin of his i future labours. He undertook extensive translations of; works in
                    the Latin, Greek, Italian, and English languages, not for the sake of gain,
                    which, however, he might have <pb break="no" facs="nls:194756112"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-6112-0680"/>got, but solely with a view to complete his
                    studies. From the same motive he entered on the study of the mathematical
                    sciences.</p>
                <p>The great merit of Delambre, the habitual suavity of his character and manners,
                    and the resolution he had taken to begin anew the entire course of his studies,
                    and proceed, by his own efforts alone, engaged the attention of some, who
                    advised him to consecrate a few years to the giving of instruction; and with
                    this view he went to Compiègne; but he soon returned to Paris, a residence in
                    which was now essentially necessary to his studies. There he pursued the same
                    career, but with increased advantages; and this procured him a competent and
                    independent subsistence.</p>
                <p>He now yielded to the natural impulse of his mind in the pursuit of knowledge,
                    studying profoundly the different mathematical theories, as also physics and
                    astronomy; and continuing to cultivate history and general literature. No one
                    could proceed with more system, or show more constancy in exploring the vast
                    field of human knowledge; indeed perseverance was a distinguishing feature of
                    his character. When he presented himself at the College of France to follow the
                    lessons of Lalande, he had already read the works of that astronomer, and had
                    made a complete commentary on them. This was first remarked when, in the course
                    of instruction, an occasion offered to him of citing from memory a passage of
                    Aratus. Lalande immediately foresaw the advantages his pupil was likely to
                    confer on science, and from that moment regarded Dclambre as a fellow-labourer.
                    He entrusted to him the most complicated astronomical calculations, and
                    prevailed on Μ. Dassy, whose son had received lessons from Delambre, to
                    establish an observatory at his house, where Delambre applied himself to
                    astronomical observations. He at the same time undertook the most extensive
                    researches; he formed the design of completing the astronomical tables; and he
                    dedicated his life to the study and the description of the heavens, a resolution
                    he had previously entertained during his stay at Compiègne.</p>
                <p>In the year 1781 the discovery of the Georgium Sidus or Uranus, by Herschel,
                    excited general attention among astronomers; and the Academy of Sciences
                    proposed the determination of its orbit as the subject of one of its annual
                    prizes. Delambre undertook the formation of tables of its motion, and the prize
                    was awarded to him for his labour. His next effort was the construction of solar
                    tables, also tables of the motions of Jupiter and Saturn; he likewise undertook
                    the construction of ecliptical tables of the satellites of Jupiter, and in a few
                    years he completed that laborious and extensive work. He took a part in the
                    sitting of the Academy of Sciences when Laplace communicated his important
                    discoveries on the inequalities of Jupiter and Saturn; and he formed the design
                    of applying the result .of that profound analysis to the completion of tables of
                    the two planets. Delambre applied himself more especially to the satellites of
                    Jupiter, an undertaking of great difficulty and extent. In this he was sustained
                    by two powerful motives, public utility, and the dignity of the subject. He had
                    been engaged for several years in the composition of his ecliptical tables, when
                    the Academy of Sciences proposed the same question as the subject of a prize: it
                    was awarded to his labours, and soon afterwards, viz. in 1792, he was elected a
                    member of the academy.</p>
                <p>The great diversity of weights and measures, and the consequent inconvenience to
                    commerce, engaged the attention of the French nation about the time of the first
                    revolution; and in the year 1790, Tallyrand, then minister of foreign relations,
                    brought the subject before the constituent assembly, where it was resolved that
                    the king should be requested to apply to his Britannic majesty, with the view of
                    getting the English parliament to concur with the national assembly in fixing on
                    some natural unit as a standard. It was proposed that commissioners from the
                    Academy of Sciences should meet an equal number of members of the Royal Society
                    of London, in order to ascertain the length of a pendulum in some determinate
                    latitude, and thence to deduce an invariable model for all weights and measures;
                    and a commission, composed of Borda, Lagrange, Laplace, Monge, and Condorcet,
                    was appointed to consider this grand project. Besides the length of the
                    pendulum, two other units were suggested, namely, a quadrant of the elliptic
                    meridian, and a fourth part of the earth’s circumference at the equator. Of the
                    three, the commission adopted the quadrant of the meridian, and its execution
                    was begun by appointing Delambre and Méchain to measure an arc from Dunkirk to
                    Barcelona. This undertaking, in itself laborious, was, by circumstances which
                    arose out of the revolution, rendered highly dangerous to the personal safety of
                    those engaged in it. Méchain died whilst the work was proceeding, and its
                    successful termination was at last accomplished by the zeal, the talents, the
                    perseverance, and the prudence of Delambre. The details of this grand labour
                    have been consigned to posterity in his work entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Base</hi><hi rend="italic">du Système Métrique</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Decimal,</hi> the first volume of which bears the date of 1806, and the third
                    and last that of 1810. The labours of Delambre and Méchain were followed up by
                    those of Biot and Arago, who have added as a supplement to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Base</hi><hi rend="italic">du Système Métrique</hi> their <hi rend="italic"
                    >Recueil</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Observations Géodesiques,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Astronomiques, et</hi><hi rend="italic">Physiques,</hi> published
                    in 1820, in which the operations are detailed by which the measurement of the
                    meridian was prolonged from Barcelona to Formentera in the Mediterranean.
                    Altogether this work does honour to the nation which produced such
                    mathematicians, astronomers, and artists as were united in the execution of the
                    labours detailed in it, but particularly to Delambre, the great directing mind
                    that in the course of eight years brought them to a successful termination. The
                    opinion of the National Institute of France was solemnly expressed when, having
                    considered what had been the most important application of the mathematical and
                    physical sciences during the preceding ten years, the universal suffrages of the
                    members decreed the prize to the author of the <hi rend="italic">Base</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">du Système Métrique.</hi></p>
                <p>Delambre, who had been chosen as an associate of almost every scientific body in
                    Europe, and a member of the French Board of Longitude, was appointed perpetual
                    secretary for the mathematical sciences in the Institute. He had succeeded
                    Lalande in the chair of astronomy of the College of France, and he was appointed
                    one of the principal directors <hi rend="italic">(titulaires)</hi> of the
                    university. For twenty years he executed the duties of his office in one of the
                    classes of the Institute, and, in doing so, he enjoyed the reputation of being
                    impartial, faithful, and just. His annual reports, his historical éloges, which
                    have been published, and his exposition of the progress of science, are
                    eminently distinguished by profound erudition, a talent for writing formed on
                    the best models, and, above all, by a disposition of mind which inclined him to
                    place in the most favourable light the works of others, as far as was consistent
                    with historical truth. His literary and scientific labours were very numerous,
                    and, in respect to excellence, of the highest order. His History of Astronomy,
                    comprehended in six quarto volumes (a seventh has been promised), is a work of
                    prodigious research. It puts the modern astronomer in possession of all that has
                    been done, and of the methods employed by those who have gone before him.</p>
                <p>His <hi rend="italic">Méthodes Analytique pour la Détermination d’un Are du
                    Méridien,</hi> his numerous memoirs in the additions to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Connaissances</hi><hi rend="italic">des Temps,</hi> and his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Astronomie Théorique et</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:194756125"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-6125-0681"/><hi rend="italic">Pratique,</hi> exhibit the
                    finest applications of the modern analysis to astronomy and geography; in fact,
                    they have given a new turn to these sciences. Astronomers have now laid aside
                    the purely geometrical methods, which, however elegant, always required at last
                    numerical calculations, and instead of these, have expressed every thing to be
                    determined in astronomy by compact analytical formula?, of which a great number
                    are due to Delambre.</p>
                <p>It is a remarkable fact in the life of Delarnbre, that he .did not apply himself
                    to astronomical observations until he was about thirty-five years of age;
                    whereas in general, the particular subject in which a man is destined to excel
                    attracts his attention in early youth. In one respect this was verified in the
                    case of Delambre, for he manifested an early promptitude in the acquisition of
                    languages; but instead of spending his life in the study of mere words, he made
                    his skill in languages the key to knowledge, and rendered it subservient to the
                    elucidation of the history of an important science, astronomy.</p>
                <p>Delambre was appointed a member of the Royal Council of Public Instruction in the
                    year 1814; a place, however, which he lost in 1815. He was in Paris when it was
                    taken by the allied armies; and in a letter written at that time to a friend and
                    pupil, he says, that on the day of the siege, in the hearing of the cannonade,
                    he laboured with tranquillity in his study from eight in the morning till
                    midnight. He had a happier fate than the unfortunate Sicilian geometer
                    Archimedes in a like position, for not only was he not molested by the victors,
                    but no military man was even billeted on him, probably from respect to his high
                    reputation. At the creation of the legion of honour, Delambre was made a member
                    of that order. He was appointed chevalier of St Michael in 1817, an officer in
                    the legion of honour in 1821, but a long time before he was created a hereditary
                    chevalier, with an endowment, which was decreed as a national reward.</p>
                <p>The life of continued and hard study which Delambre led at last affected his
                    health. The disease by which he was cut off became apparent in the month of July
                    1822. His total loss of strength, with frequent and long-continued fainting
                    fits, gave warning of a fatal result. He foresaw what was about to happen, but
                    he preserved to the last moment the unalterable mildness of his character, and
                    the serenity of his mind. At last, on the 19th of August 1822, at the age of
                    seventy-two, he sunk under his disease, not without having suffered, but without
                    having complained, or betrayed any symptoms of impatience.</p>
                <p>The following is a list of his works which appeared separately: 1. Tables de
                    Jupiter et de Saturn, 1789; 2. Tables du Soleil, de Jupiter, de Saturn,
                    d’Uranus, et des Satellites de Jupiter, pour servir à la 3me edition
                    l’Astronomie de Lalande, 1792; 3. Méthodes Analytiques pour la Détermination
                    d’un Arc du Méridien, 1799; 4. Tables Trigonométriqués Décimales, par Borda,
                    revues, augmentées, et publiées par Μ. Delambre, 1801; 5. Tables du Soleil
                    (publiées par le Bureau des Longitudes), 1806; 6. Base du Système Métrique
                    Décimal, &amp;c. 3 vols. in 4to, 1806-1810; 7. Rapport Historique sur les
                    Progrès des Sciences Mathématiques depuis 1789, &amp;c. 1810; 8. Abrégé
                    d’Astronomie, ou Leçons Elémentaires d’Astronomie Théorique et Pratique, in 8vo;
                    9. Astronomie Théorique et Pratique, 3 vols. in 4to, 1814; 10. Tables
                    Ecliptiques des Satellites de Jupiter, 1817; 11. Histoire de l’Astronomie
                    Ancienne, 2 vols. in 4to; 12. Histoire de l’Astronomie du Moyen Age, 1819, 1
                    vol. in 4to; 13. Histoire de l’Astronomie Moderne, 1821, 2 vols. in 4to; 14.
                    Histoire de l’Astronomie au Dixhuitiême Siècle, 2 vols. in 4to, 1827 (only one
                    yet published, 1833).</p>
                <p>In addition to these, he furnished a very considerable number of memoirs (about
                    twenty-eight) on various points of astronomy, to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Connaissances</hi><hi rend="italic">de Temps,</hi> beginning with the year
                    1788. He also contributed to the Memoirs of the Academies of Stockholm,
                    Petersburg, Berlin, and Turin, and to those of the first class of the French
                    Institute; and he composed éloges on many of his predeceased contemporaries,
                    among which may be noticed one on our highly distinguished countryman Dr
                    Maskelyne, the astronomer-royal of England.</p>
                <p>In conclusion, we may remark, that Delambre has rendered essential service to
                    true knowledge by the pains he took to dispel a delusion which had been
                    propagated by his friend Bailly regarding the antiquity of the Indian astronomy.
                    Almost every one is now satisfied that the Indian tables, so far from having
                    been composed from observations made at so remote a period as 3000 years ago,
                    are probably not older than about 700 years. This was the decided opinion of
                    Delambre, and in this he has been supported by the authority of Laplace.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
