<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6229-0689-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">DELPHI</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 689</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b40v89n0g">Goat</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:939002">Gauls</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:993639">Laurel</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194756229" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">DELPHI</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Ancient Geography,</hi>
                    a town of Phocis, situated on the south-western extremity of Mount Parnassus. It
                    was famous for the temple and oracle of Apollo, the origin of which is ascribed
                    to an accidental discovery. A number of goats which were feeding on Mount
                    Parnassus happened, it is said, to approach a place which had a long and deep
                    perforation. The vapour which issued from the cavity seemed to inspire the
                    goats, and they played and frisked about in such an uncommon manner that the
                    goatherd was tempted to lean over the aperture, in order to see what mysteries
                    the place contained. But he was immediately seized with a fit of enthusiasm; his
                    expressions were wild and extravagant, and passed for prophecies. This
                    circumstance soon became known throughout the country, and many experienced the
                    same enthusiastic inspiration. The place was revered; a temple was soon
                    afterwards erected in honour of Apollo; and a city was built, which became the
                    most illustrious in Phocis. The influence of this oracle afterwards controlled
                    the councils of states, directed the course of armies, and decided the fate of
                    kingdoms. The ancient history of Greece is full of its energy, and an early
                    register of its authority. The circumjacent cities were the stewards and
                    guardians of the god; and their deputies composed the famous Amphictyonie
                    assembly which once guided all Greece.</p><p>The temple of Apollo was at first a kind of cottage covered with boughs of
                    laurel; but the god was early provided with a better habitation. An edifice of
                    stone was erected by Trophonius and Agamedes, and subsisted about seven hundred
                    years, but it was burned in die year 636 after the taking of Troy, and 548
                    before Christ. It is mentioned in the hymn to Apollo ascribed to Homer. An
                    opulent and illustrious family, called Alemaeonidae, having fled from Athens and
                    the tyrant Hippias, contracted with the deputies for the building of a new
                    temple, and far exceeded their agreement. The front was raised with Pa-&gt; rian
                    marble, instead of the stone called <hi rend="italic">porus,</hi> which
                    resembled it in whiteness, but was not so heavy; the pediments were adorned with
                    representations of Diana, and Latona, and Apollo, and the Muses, with the
                    setting of Phoebus or the sun, Bacchus, and the women called Thy-ades; and the
                    architraves were decorated with golden armour, with bucklers suspended by the
                    Athenians after the battle of Marathon, and with shields taken from the Gauls
                    under Brennus. In the porticowere inscribed the celebrated maxims of the seven
                    sages of Greece. There was also an image of Homer; and in the cell was an altar
                    of Neptune, with statues of the Fates, and of Jupiter and Apollo, who were
                    surnamed Leaders of the Fates. Near the hearth, before the altar at which
                    Neoptolemus, the son of Achilles, was slain by a priest, stood the iron chair of
                    Pindar. In the sanctuary stood an image of Apollo. The enclosure was of great
                    extent, and filled with treasures, many cities having consecrated tenths of the
                    spoil taken in war, and with the public donations of renowned states in various
                    ages. It was the grand repository of ancient Greece, in which, by the labours of
                    the sculptor and statuary, gods, heroes, and illustrious persons, were seen
                    collected and arranged; the inequalities of the area of acclivity contributing
                    to give a full display of the noble assemblage.</p><p>The oracles were delivered by a priestess called the Pythoness, who received the
                    prophetic influence in the following manner. A lofty tripod, decked with laurel,
                    was placed over the aperture whence the sacred vapour issued. The priestess,
                    after washing her body, and especially her hair, in the cold water of Castalia,
                    mounted on the stool to receive the divine effluvia. She wore a crown of laurel
                    on her head, and shook a sacred tree which grew near the aperture. Sometimes she
                    chewed the leaves; and the frenzy which followed may probably be attributed to
                    this usage, and the gentler or more violent symptoms to the quantity taken. In
                    one instance the paroxysm was so terrible that the priests and suppliants ran
                    away, and left her alone to expire, as was believed, of the god. Her part was an
                    unpleasant one; but if she declined acting, they dragged her by force to the
                    tripod. The habit of her order was that of virgins. The rules enjoined
                    temperance and chastity, and prohibited luxury in apparel. The season of inquiry
                    was in the spring; after which Apollo was supposed to visit the altars of the
                    Hyperboreans.</p><p>The city of Delphi arose in the form of an amphitheatre, upon the winding
                    declivity of Parnassus, the fantastic tops of which overshadowed it like a
                    canopy on the north, whilst two immense rocks rendered it inaccessible on the
                    cast and west, and the rugged and shapeless Mount Cirphis defended it on the
                    south. The foot of the last-named mountain was washed by the rapid Plistus,
                    which discharged itself into the sea at the distance of only a few leagues from
                    the sacred city. This inaccessible and romantic situation, from which the place
                    derived the name of Delphi, a word signifying <hi rend="italic">solitary,</hi>
                    was rendered still more striking by the innumerable echoes which multiplied
                    every sound, and increased the ignorant veneration of visitants for the divinity
                    of the oracle. The artful ministers of Apollo also collected such objects in the
                    groves and temple as were fitted to astonish the senses of the admiring
                    multitude. The splendour of marble, the magic of painting, and invaluable
                    statues of gold and silver, had not, to use the language of antiquity, the
                    resemblance of an earthly habitation, but rather expressed the image of Olympus,
                    adorned and enlightened by the actual presence of the gods.</p><p>The protection and superintendence of this precious depository of riches and
                    superstition belonged to the Amphictyons. But the inhabitants of Delphi, who, if
                    we may use the expression, were the original proprietors of the oracle, always
                    continued to direct the religious ceremonies, and to conduct the important
                    business of prophecy. It was their province alone to determine at what time, and
                    on what occasion, the Pythia should mount the sacred tripod, in order to receive
                    the prophetic exhalations by which she communicated with Apollo. When
                    overflowing with the heavenly inspiration, she uttered the confused words, or
                    rather frantic sounds, irregularly suggested by the impulse of the god; and
                    these sounds the Delphians collected, reduced them into order, animated them
                    with sense, and adorned them with harmony. The Pythia, being appointed and
                    dismissed at pleasure, was a mere instrument in the hands of those artful
                    ministers, whose character became so venerable and sacred, that they were
                    finally regarded, not merely as attendants and worshippers, but as the peculiar
                    family of the divinity. Their number was considerable, and never exactly
                    ascertained, since all the principal inhabitants of Delphi, claiming an
                    immediate relation to Apollo, were entitled to officiate in the rites of his
                    sanctuary; and even the inferior ranks belonging to that sacred city were
                    continually employed in dances, festivals, and <pb break="no" facs="nls:194756242" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6242-0690"/>processions,
                    and in displaying all the gay pageantry of an airy and elegant superstition.</p><p>Delphi was conveniently situated for t∩e resort of votaries, being in the centre
                    of Greece, and, as was then imagined, also in that of the universe. It was
                    customary for those who consulted the oracle to make rich presents to the god.
                    His servants and priests feasted upon the numerous victims which were sacrificed
                    to him; and the rich magnificence of his temple had become proverbial even in
                    the age of Homer. In after times, Croesus, the wealthiest of monarchs, was
                    particularly munificent in his donations. This sacred repository of opulence
                    therefore often became the object of plunder. Neoptolemus was slain whilst
                    sacrificing, on suspicion of a design of this kind. Xerxes divided his army at
                    Panopeus, and proceeded with the main body through Boeotia into Attica, whilst a
                    party keeping Parnassus on the right, advanced along Schiste to Delphi; but it
                    was seized with a panic when near Ilium, and fled. This monarch, it is related,
                    was as well apprised of the contents of the temple, and the sumptuous offerings
                    of Halyattes and Croesus, as of the effects which he had left behind him in his
                    own palace. The divine hoard was seized by the Phocensians under Philomelus, and
                    dissipated in a long war with the Amphictyons. The Gauls experienced a reception
                    similar to that of the Persians, and manifested similar dismay and superstition.
                    Sylla, wanting money to pay his army, sent to borrow from the holy treasury; and
                    when his messenger would have frightened him, by reporting a prodigy, namely,
                    that the sound of a harp had been heard from within the sanctuary, the Roman
                    replied, it was a sign that the god was happy to oblige him.</p><p>The trade in oracles, after it had flourished for a long period, was affected by
                    the mal-practices of some concerned in the partnership, who were convicted of
                    bribery and corruption, which ruined the character of their principal. The
                    temple in the time of Strabo was reduced to extreme poverty; but the offerings
                    which remained were very numerous. Apollo became silent, except at intervals,
                    when some efforts were made to regain his lost credit. Nero attempted to drive
                    him, as it were, by violence, from the cavern, killing men at the mouth, and
                    polluting it with blood; but he lingered on, and would not entirely forsake it.
                    Answers were reported as having been given by him afterwards, but not without
                    suspicion of forgery. An oracle of Apollo at another place informed those who
                    consulted him that he should no more recover utterance at Delphi, but he
                    enjoined the continuance of the accustomed offerings.</p><p>The city of Delphi became free under the Romans. In the time of Pausanias, who
                    has particularly described it, there still remained an invaluable treasure of
                    offerings within the court of the temple. The number, variety, and beauty of
                    these gifts were prodigious; the store appeared inexhaustible; and the robbery
                    of Nero, who removed no less than five hundred brazen images, was rather
                    regretted than perceived. The holy treasuries, though empty, served as memorials
                    of the piety and glory of the cities which had erected them. The Athenian
                    porticopreserved the beaks of ships and the brazen shields, trophies won in the
                    Peloponnesian war; and a multitude of curiosities remained untouched in other
                    parts of the temple.</p><p>Constantine the Great, however, proved a more fatal enemy to Apollo and to Delphi
                    than either Sylla or Nero. He removed the sacred tripods to adorn the hippodrome
                    of his new city, where these, with the Apollo, the statues of the Heliconian
                    muses, and the celebrated Pan, dedicated by the Greek cities after the
                    conclusion of the war with the Medes, were extant when Sozomen wrote his
                    history. Julian afterwards sent Oribasius to restore the temple; but he was
                    admonished by an oracle to represent to the emperor the deplorable condition of
                    the place. “Tell him the well-built court is fallen to the ground. Phoebus has
                    not a cottage, nor the prophetic laurel, nor the speaking fountain Cassotis; and
                    even the beautiful water is extinct.”</p></div></body></text></TEI>