<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0707-6190-0686-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DELILLE, Jacques</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 686</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:920123">Fame</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194756190" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DELILLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacques</hi></label>, early
                    acquired deserved celebrity as the founder of a new school in French poetry, but
                    unfortunately his ambition extended with his fame, till he left behind him as
                    many didactic poems as Sir Richard Blackmore has epics, and we suspect the
                    greater number of them are already almost as little known. The author of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Jardins,</hi> indeed, will always hold his rank among poets; but
                    it would have been no great misfortune to his memory if he had written little
                    more.</p>
                <p>He was born on the 22d of June 1738, in the neighbourhood of Clermont, in
                    Auvergne. His father was a man of neither fortune nor family; but he was
                    connected by his mother with that of the Chancellor de l’Hôpital. With very
                    slender means of support, he was educated at Paris, and made such progress in
                    his studies as augured well for his future distinction. When his education was
                    completed, he was forced to accept of a very low situation as teacher in the
                    College of Beauvais; but this was soon exchanged for the more honourable station
                    of professor of humanity at Amiens. After returning to Paris, where he likewise
                    obtained a professorship, be speedily acquired a considerable poetical name, and
                    was encouraged, by the younger Racine, to give to the world a translation of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Georgies</hi> of Virgil, which he had begun at Amiens. This
                    translation was a bold attempt for a French poet. The muses of that nation were
                    but little conversant with a country life. They had been reared in courts, and
                    seemed incapable of assuming any other tone than that declamatory one in which
                    kings and princesses might be supposed, however erroneously, to give utterance
                    to their tragic woes, or that elegant and complimentary style in which the
                    interests, the intrigues, and the morality of polite life, find a much truer and
                    more adequate expression. Racine and Boileau, in a word, had fixed the poetry of
                    their nation within the limits which they had prescribed for it; it was perfect
                    in its kind, and this made it appear still more hopeless to attempt to extend it
                    further. Voltaire, indeed, had given a wider compass to the language of tragedy;
                    in his spirit of universal dominion, he had attempted the epic, but had failed.
                    He was more successful in transfusing into the guarded regularity of French
                    poetry some of the wilder graces and eccentricities of the Italian; but even he
                    would have shrunk from the unprecedented audacity of walking his courtly muse
                    over a ploughed field, or bringing her within the steam of a dunghill. We are
                    told, accordingly, that he was greatly struck with the enterprise and the
                    success of Delille; and that, without any personal acquaintance with the poet,
                    he, of his own accord, recommended him and his work to the good graces of the
                    academy. It was not, however, till some years afterwards that Delille became a
                    member of that celebrated body. He now aimed at a higher distinction than even a
                    finished translation of the most finished poem in the world could confer upon
                    him; and in the <hi rend="italic">Jardins,</hi> which he published a few years
                    after his reception into the academy, he made good his pretensions as an
                    original poet. The mantle of the Roman bard still, indeed, seemed to enfold him;
                    and, if we can pardon a few French prettinesses, there is no didactic poem in
                    any language, we believe, which approaches so closely to the polish, the grace,
                    and the tenderness of Virgil, as the <hi rend="italic">Jardins</hi> of
                    Delille.</p>
                <p>It is an unfortunate thing for a poet to become too ambitious, especially if his
                    former success renders him inattentive to the steps by which he was conducted to
                    fame. After his <hi rend="italic">Georgies</hi> had put him at the head of the
                    poets of his country, Virgil, in obedience to the calls of gratitude and of
                    patriotism, rather than of ambition, ventured upon his grand national epic; an
                    arduous effort even for him. Yet by never losing sight for a moment of his own
                    strength and his own weakness, he has been enabled (although his heart never
                    seems to have gone along with it, and he was at last, as is well known, quite
                    dissatisfied with his own work) to complete an undertaking which, in the
                    judgment of posterity, has for ever encircled his modest brows with a glory,
                    second only to that which beams from the divinity of Homer. His French disciple,
                    who seemed for a time to be humbly treading in his steps, wanted, however, the
                    composure of a Roman head. After the success of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Jardins,</hi> Delille appears to have forgotten where the strength of his own
                    genius lay; that he was nothing at all if he was not cautious, select, elegant,
                    and pathetic; that the world did not expect to be deluged by his poetry, but to
                    be refreshed by its gentle and winding streams; that there was no necessity, in
                    a word, for his writing a great deal, but the very greatest for his continuing
                    to write inimitably well. The subject upon which he next laboured was an unhappy
                    one. Without any great portion of <hi rend="italic">Imagination</hi> of his own,
                    he projected a poem on that vague and indeterminate theme. He sets out,
                    accordingly, at a <pb break="no" facs="nls:194756203"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-6203-0687"/>pitch which he cannot keep up; he then loses
                    himself in indistinct metaphysics; and the want of any limit to his subject
                    tempts him into a wandering and interminable style of composition, which is at
                    complete variance with every thing like point, polish, and elegance. Before he
                    had gone far in the composition of this poem, which was not, indeed, published
                    till after many of his other works, he made a voyage to Constantinople in the
                    train of the ambassador Μ. de Choiseul Gouffier. He did not lose this
                    opportunity of visiting Attica and the Troad, and we might have hoped that some
                    glowing sketches of scenes so inspiring to a poet would have relieved the
                    heaviness of his <hi rend="italic">Imagination.</hi> But the following is the
                    only passage in all that long poem which pretends to catch any portion of their
                    divine influence.</p>
                <p>Lorsque de l’univers l’aimable enchanteresse, L’imagination, me porta dans la
                    Grèce,</p>
                <p>Je ne m’attendais pas qu’un jour mes propres yeux Verraient ces belles mers, ces
                    beaux champs, ces beaux cieux; Je les ai vus! Mon coeur a tressailli de
                    joic:</p>
                <p>Homère m’a guidé dans les champs où fut Troie. Pour moi, ses vers divins
                    peuplaient ces lieux deserts, Et ces lieux, à leur tour, m’embellissaient ses
                    vers.</p>
                <p>Un délire charmant, qu’il m’inspirait sans doute, D’enchantements sans nombre
                    avait semé ma route; Je ne demandais plus, pour traverser les flots Ni les
                    secours des vents, ni l’art des matelots; Je disais aux Tritons, aux jeunes
                    Néréides, De pousser mon vaisseau sur les plaines humides. Tout à coup sur ces
                    mers, à mes yeux s’est montré <hi rend="italic">Un stupide Pacha,</hi>
                    d’esclaves entouré;</p>
                <p>Tout s’est désenchanté, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>In spite of this tremendous pasha, whose stupidity appears to have been somewhat
                    infectious, our poet, whilst he resided at Constantinople, was almost in the
                    daily habit of passing over to the coast of Asia, and studying his poem amidst
                    the inspirations of its splendid scenery. Yet we cannot be persuaded that his
                    enthusiasm, amidst these classical regions, was very profound or genuine, if it
                    be true that he stated it as one of his greatest enjoyments, while resident
                    amongst them, that he could go every day to breakfast in Asia, and come back
                    again to dine in Europe.</p>
                <p>On his return to Paris he prelected, in his capacity of professor, on the Latin
                    poets, and was attended by a numerous audience, who were delighted, not only
                    with his critical observations, but with his beautiful recitation. He indulged
                    them, too, with his own verses; and in this way, we believe, the choice <hi
                    rend="italic">morceaux</hi> of his poem on <hi rend="italic">Imagination</hi>
                    were familiar to the public long before it came into their hands. Delille
                    continued to advance in fame and fortune, though without hazarding any more
                    publications, till the period of the Revolution, when he was reduced to poverty,
                    and sheltered himself in retreat from the disasters which surrounded him. He
                    quitted Paris, and retired to St Diez, the native place of Madame Delille; and
                    here he completed, in deep Solitude, his translation of the Aeneid, which he had
                    begun many years before. A residence in France, however, soon became very
                    undesirable, and he emigrated first to Bale, and then to Glairesse in
                    Switzerland, a charming village on the lake of Bienne, opposite Rousseau’s
                    island of St Pierre. Much delighted with this enchanting country, and with the
                    reception which he met from its inhabitants, he occupied himself constantly in
                    the composition of poetry, and here finished his <hi rend="italic">Homme des
                    Champs,</hi> and his poem on the <hi rend="italic">Trois Règnes</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de la Nature.</hi> We have censured Delille for writing too much;
                    but an excuse may be found for him in the horrors of the times, and the
                    necessity of some object to interest his mind, and relieve it from the
                    oppression of his misfortunes. He would probably have adopted a course more
                    favourable to his fame, had not the revolution sent him adrift upon the world.
                    His next place of refuge was in Germany, where he composed his <hi rend="italic"
                    >La Pitié;</hi> and finally, he passed two years in London, chiefly employed in
                    translating <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost.</hi> In 1801, finding that he might
                    return safely to Paris, he did so, carrying with him his immense <hi
                    rend="italic">Poetical Encyclopaedia,</hi> and from that time he sent poem after
                    poem into the world, till at last he himself quitted it on the first of May
                    1813, at the age of seventy-five. In his latter years he had lost, in a great
                    degree, his sight, which gave him an opportunity of opening one of the cantos of
                    his <hi rend="italic">Imagination</hi> with an imitation of that noble passage
                    in which our sublime poet laments a similar misfortune.</p>
                <p>Voilà que le printemps reverdit les coteaux, Des chaines de Thiver dégage les
                    ruisseaux, Rend leur feuillage aux bois, ses rayons à l’aurore; Tout renait;
                    pour moi seul rien ne renait encore.</p>
                <p>Delille appears to have been a person of a very amiable and simple character; his
                    conversation full of a child-like gaiety; his writings always moral and pious.
                    He was a man, too, of courage and firmness. In his voyage to Attica his little
                    vessel was pursued by pirates, and very nearly overtaken. All on board were in
                    consternation. The poet very coolly observed, “These rascals are not aware that
                    I shall make them very ridiculous in an epigram.” A finer instance of his
                    resolution occurred during the tyranny of Robespierre. That wretch ordered him
                    to compose a hymn on occasion of an impious fête, which Delille refused to do,
                    and replied to the threats which were made him, <hi rend="italic">Que la</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">guillotine</hi><hi rend="italic">était</hi><hi rend="italic">fort
                    commode,</hi><hi rend="italic">et fort expéditive.</hi> Being still urged to
                    comply, he did write an ode, in which he took occasion to paint (a theme we may
                    believe not very agreeable to the heroes of the Revolution) the terrors which
                    immortality held out to the guilty, and its consolations to the virtuous under
                    misfortune. This was very noble; but, wearied out afterwards by his long
                    banishment, he does not appear to have been equally sturdy when he put forth his
                    poem of <hi rend="italic">La Pitié,</hi> on his return to Paris. Unfortunately
                    he had already given it to the London booksellers; and, in their edition, there
                    were various attacks on the proceedings of Napoleon, and expressions of great
                    devotion to the exiled family. But when he found himself under the consular
                    government, he made considerable alterations on his poem. It was published in
                    Paris about the same time that it appeared in London; and, like the statue with
                    two faces, it was quite a different thing, according to the side of the channel
                    on which it was contemplated. On a general estimate of the genius of Delille, we
                    must consider him as a poet of much refinement and delicacy, but of no great
                    power or stamina. Upon the pleasing subject of rural life he dilates with great
                    beauty and felicity. There are, too, throughout his poems, very splendid
                    descriptions of all kinds; but he weakens them constantly by diffusion; and
                    there is very little art or elegance in his connections or transitions. He set
                    out well, but he afterwards attempted more than he could accomplish. It is a
                    pity that he was able to read any language but French and Latin, or that he
                    should have ever wandered beyond the precincts of nature and of Virgil. It has
                    occurred to us in reading Delille, that, with all his beauty of versification,
                    and occasional felicity of expression, he yet shows, in his latter works
                    especially, a great ignorance of the line of distinction between prose and
                    poetry. This is a curious subject of discussion; and we know not that it has
                    ever been accurately examined. There may be very eloquent and very animated
                    prose, which yet, if versified, would make but indifferent poetry. Delille very
                    nearly versifies some of the pathetic passages in Rosseau’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Heloiseς</hi> but in his hands they are any thing but poetical. On the other
                    hand, there are poems and subjects<pb break="no" facs="nls:194756216"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0707-6216-0688"/> which are more naturally treated in prose, but
                    which, by the art of the poet, acquire the character of poetry. The satires of
                    Horace, which he himself calls <hi rend="italic">sermoni propiora,</hi> Dryden’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Religio</hi><hi rend="italic">Laid,</hi> and still more the
                    <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi> of Pope and Boileau, have all, doubtless, a
                    poetical character, although there is in them no passion, and very little
                    imagery. Didactic poetry, in general, is an invasion upon the precincts of prose
                    composition; but how wonderfully have some poets invested it with the attributes
                    of the highest inspiration! One half of Lucretius is mere reasoning, yet even in
                    his reasonings we discern the poet. There is the animation, the diction, the
                    rapidity of poetry; and that overflowing of mind with which he is constantly
                    breaking out of his reasonings, and running into the most brilliant conceptions
                    and pictures, is its very soul. Virgil, too, in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Georgies,</hi> is poetical from beginning to end. No man who ever wrote seems
                    to have seen more distinctly than this great master what it is that peculiarly
                    constitutes poetry, or to have been so capable of diffusing it over the most
                    unpromising parts of his subject. Perhaps the charm consists very much in
                    selection. A prose writer accumulates image upon image when he wishes to make a
                    forcible impression; but translate these intoverse,and some of them will appear
                    insignificant, some of them low, and the quantity of them tedious. This is often
                    the effect of Delille’s descriptions. A poet like Virgil, again, fixes upon some
                    one striking feature of the conception which he wishes to impress—some thought
                    that breathes, and word that burns; and giving us these, he not only gives us
                    the image which he expresses, but the full force of many kindred images which
                    are kept behind, yet which our imaginations, when thus seized, can easily body
                    out for themselves.</p>
                <p>Delille has left behind him little prose. His preface to the translation of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Georgies</hi> is an able essay, and contains many excellent
                    hints on the art and the difficulties of translation. He wrote the article <hi
                    rend="italic">La</hi><hi rend="italic">Bruyère</hi> in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Biographie Universelle.</hi> The following is the list of his poetical works:
                    1. <hi rend="italic">Les Georgiques de</hi><hi rend="italic">Virgile, traduites
                    en vers Françaises,</hi> Paris, 1769, 1782, 1785, 1809. 2. <hi rend="italic">Les
                    Jardins, en quatre chants,</hi> 1780; nouvelle edition, Londres, 1800; Paris,
                    1802. 3. <hi rend="italic">L’</hi><hi rend="italic">Hommes des Champs, ou
                    les</hi><hi rend="italic">Georgiques Françaises,</hi> 1800. 4. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Poesies</hi><hi rend="italic">Fugitives,</hi> 1802. A collection given under
                    the title of <hi rend="italic">Poesies</hi><hi rend="italic">Diverses,</hi> 180
                    J, was disavowed by Delille. 5. <hi rend="italic">Dithyrambe sur</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">l</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Immortalité</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >de</hi><hi rend="italic">l’Ame, suivi du passage du Saint</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Gothard</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> poème traduit de l’Anglais de Madame la
                    Duchesse de Devonshire, 1802. 6. <hi rend="italic">La Pitié;</hi> poëme en
                    quatre chants. Londres et Paris, 1803. 7. <hi rend="italic">L'Enéide de Virgile,
                    traduite en vers Françaises,</hi> 1805. 9. <hi rend="italic">EImagination, poème
                    en huit chants,</hi> 1806. 10. <hi rend="italic">Les Trois Règnes de la
                    Nature,</hi> 1809.</p>
                <p>11. <hi rend="italic">La Conversation,</hi> 1812.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
