<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0707-5293-0617-03" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">DANTE, Alighieri</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 617</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:833880">Blacks</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:833576">Black</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1174597">White</term><term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4804p">Fairs</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term><term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194755293" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">DANTE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Alighieri</hi></label>, one of
                    the first poets of Italy, was born at Florence in May 1265, being descended of
                    an ancient and honourable family. The name he received at his birth was Durante,
                    which was abbreviated into Dante, in which form it has descended to posterity.
                    Boccacio, who lived at the same period, has left a very curious and entertaining
                    treatise on the life, studies, and manners of this extraordinary poet, whom he
                    regarded as his master, and for whose memory he cherished the highest
                    veneration. This biographer relates, that Dante, before he was nine years old,
                    conceived a passion for the lady whom lie has immortalized in his singular poem.
                    Her age was nearly the same as his own, and her name was Beatrice, the daughter
                    of Folco Portinari, a noble citizen of Florence. The passion of Dante, however,
                    like that of his successor Petrarch, seems to have been of the chaste and
                    Platonic kind, according to the account he has given of it in one of his early
                    productions in prose, entitled <hi rend="italic">Vita Nuova,</hi> in which he
                    mentions both the origin of his affection and the death of his mistress, who,
                    according to Boccacio, died at the age of twenty-four. The same author asserts
                    that Dante, in consequence of this event, fell into a deep melancholy, from
                    which his friends endeavoured to rouse him, by persuading him to marry. After
                    some time he followed their advice, and repented it; for he unfortunately made
                    choice of a lady named Gemma, of the house of Donati, who bore a considerable
                    resemblance to Xan-tippe; and the poet, not possessing the patience of Socrates,
                    separated himself from her with such vehement expressions of dislike, that he
                    never afterwards admitted her to his presence, though she had borne him several
                    children. In the early part of his life he acquired some credit in a military
                    character, having distinguished himself by his bravery in an action where the
                    Florentines obtained a signal victory over the citizens of Arezzo. But he became
                    still more eminent by the acquisition of civil honours; and at the age of
                    twenty-five he rose to be one of the chief magistrates of Florence, when that
                    dignity was conferred by the suffrages of the people. From this exaltation,
                    however, the poet himself dated his principal misfortunes, as appears by the
                    fragment of a letter quoted by Leonardo Bruni, one of his early biographers, in
                    which Dante speaks of his political failure with that liberal frankness which
                    integrity inspires. Italy was at that time distracted by the contending factions
                    of the Gibelines and the Guelfs; and the latter, with whom Dante took an active
                    part, were again divided into the Blacks and the Whites. Dante, as Gravina
                    informs us, exerted all his influence to unite these inferior parties; but his
                    efforts proved ineffectual, and he had the misfortune to be unjustly persecuted
                    by those of his own faction. A powerful citizen of Florence, named Corso Donati,
                    had taken measures to terminate these intestine broils, by introducing Charles
                    of Valois, brother of Philip the Fair, king of France. But Dante, with great
                    vehemence, opposed this disgraceful project, and obtained the banishment of
                    Donati and his partizans. The exiles, however, applied to the pope, Boniface
                    VIII. and by his assistance succeeded in their design. Charles of Valois entered
                    Florence in <pb break="no" facs="nls:194755306" xml:id="kp-eb0707-5306-0618"/>triumph, and those who had opposed his admission
                    were banished in their turn. Dante had been dispatched to Rome as the ambassador
                    of his party, and was upon his return when he received intelligence of the
                    revolution in his native city. His enemies, availing themselves of his absence,
                    had procured an iniquitous sentence against him, by which he was condemned to
                    banishment, and his possessions were confiscated. His two enthusiastic
                    biographers, Boccacio and Manetti, express the warmest indignation against the
                    injustice of his country. Dante, on receiving this intelligence, took refuge in
                    Sienna, and afterwards in Arezzo, where many of his party had assembled. An
                    attempt was then made to surprise the city of Florence by a small army which
                    Dante is supposed to have attended; but the design miscarried, and the poet is
                    conjectured to have wandered throughout various parts of Italy, until he found a
                    patron in Candella Scala, prince of Verona, whom he has celebrated in his poem.
                    The high spirit of Dante was ill suited to courtly dependence, and he is said to
                    have lost the favour of his Veronese patron by the rough frankness of his manner
                    and bearing. From Verona, according to Manetti, he retired to France; and
                    Boccacio affirms that he disputed in the theological schools of Paris with great
                    reputation. Bayle questions his visiting Paris at this period of his life, and
                    thinks it improbable, that a man who had been one of the chief magistrates of
                    Florence should have condescended to engage in the public disputations of the
                    Parisian theologists. But the spirit both of Dante and the times in which he
                    lived sufficiently accounts for this exercise of his talents; and his residence
                    in France at the period in question is confirmed by Boccacio, in his life of the
                    poet, which Bayle seems to have had no opportunity of consulting.</p><p>The election of Henry count of Luxemburg to the empire in November 1308, afforded
                    Dante a prospect of being restored to his native city, as he had attached
                    himself to the interest of the new emperor, in whose service he is supposed to
                    have written his Latin treatise <hi rend="italic">De AIonarcliia</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> in which he asserted the rights of the empire
                    against the encroachments of the papacy. In the year 1311 he instigated Henry to
                    lay siege to Florence, an enterprise in which he did not appear in person, from
                    motives of respect towards his native city. But the emperor was repulsed by the
                    Florentines; and his death, which happened in the following year, deprived Dante
                    of all hopes of ever being re-established in Florence. After this
                    disappointment, he is supposed to have passed some years in roving about Italy
                    in a state of poverty and distress, until he found an honourable establishment
                    at Ravenna, under the protection of Guido Novello da Polenta, lord of that city,
                    who received the illustrious exile with the most endearing liberality, continued
                    to protect him during the few remaining years of his life, and extended his
                    munificence even to the ashes of the poet.</p><p>Eloquence was one of the many talents which Dante possessed in an eminent degree.
                    On this account he is said to have been employed, in the course of his life, on
                    fourteen different embassies, and to have succeeded in most of them. His patron
                    Guido having occasion to try his abilities in a service of this nature,
                    dispatched him as his ambassador to negociate a peace with the Venetians, who
                    were preparing for hostilities against Ravenna. But Manetti asserts that he was
                    unable to procure a public audience at Venice, and returned to Ravenna by land,
                    from apprehension of the Venetian fleet; when the fatigue of his journey, and
                    the mortification of having failed in his attempt to preserve his generous
                    patron from the impending danger, threw him into a fever, which terminated in
                    death on the 14th of September 1321. He died, however, in the palace of his
                    friend; and the generous Guido paid the most tender regard to his memory. This
                    munificent patron commanded the body to be adorned with poetical ornaments, and,
                    after being carried on a bier through the streets of Ravenna by the most
                    illustrious citizens, to be deposited in a marble sarcophagus. He himself
                    pronounced the funeral oration, and expressed his design of erecting a splendid
                    monument in honour of the deceased; a design which his subsequent misfortunes
                    rendered him unable to accomplish. At his request many epitaphs were written on
                    the poet, the best of which were by Giovanni del Virgilio of Bologna, a
                    celebrated author of that time, and the intimate friend of Dante. Boccacio then
                    cites a few Latin verses, not worth transcribing, six of which are quoted by
                    Bayle, on the authority of Paul Jovius, as the composition of Dante himself. In
                    1483 Bernardo Bembo, the father of the celebrated cardinal, raised a handsome
                    monument over the neglected ashes of the bard.</p><p>Before this period the Florentines had vainly endeavoured to obtain from the city
                    of Ravenna the bones of their great poet. In the age of Leo X. they made a
                    second attempt, by a solemn application to the pope for that purpose; and Michel
                    Angelo, an enthusiastic admirer of Dante, very liberally offered to execute a
                    magnificentmo-nument to the poet. But the hopes of the Florentines were again
                    disappointed. The particulars of their singular petition may be found in the
                    notes of Codivi’s Life of Michel Angelo.</p><p>At what time, and in what place, he executed the great and singular work which
                    has rendered him immortal, hisnu∙ merous commentators have been unable to
                    determine. Boccacio asserts that he began it in his thirty-fifth year, and had
                    finished seven cantos of his <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi> before his exile;
                    and that in the plunder of his house on that occasion the beginning of his poem
                    was fortunately preserved, but remained for some time neglected, till its merit
                    being accidentally discovered by an intelligent poet named Dino, it was sent to
                    the Marquis Marcello Malespina, an Italian nobleman, by whom Dante was then
                    protected. The marquis restored these papers to the poet, and entreated him to
                    proceed with a work which opened in so promising a manner. To this incident we
                    are probably indebted for the poem of Dante, which he must have continued under
                    all the disadvantages of an unfortunate and agitated life. It does not appear at
                    what time he completed it; perhaps before he quitted Verona, as he dedicated the
                    <hi rend="italic">Paradise</hi> to his Veronese patron. The critics have
                    variously accounted for his having called his poem <hi rend="italic">Commedia.</hi> He gave it the title, said one of his sons, because it opens
                    with distress and closes with felicity. The very high estimation in which this
                    production was held by his country appears from a singular institution. The
                    republic of Florence, in the year 1373, assigned a public salary to a person
                    appointed to read lectures on the poem of Dante, and Boccacio was the first
                    person engaged in this office; but his death happening about two years after his
                    appointment, his comments extended only to the seventeen first cantos of the <hi rend="italic">Inferno.</hi> The critical dissertations which have been written
                    on Dante are almost as numerous as those to which Homer himself has given birth;
                    the Italian, like the Grecian bard, having been the subject of the highest
                    panegyric and of the grossest invective.</p><p>The most ancient Italian commentary extant on the <hi rend="italic">Divina</hi><hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> is that of Boccacio, which, however, was not
                    printed until 1724, at Naples. Specimens of other commentaries will be found in
                    the first volume of Muratori’s <hi rend="italic">Antiquitates</hi><hi rend="italic">Italicae.</hi> The first edition of the text without commentaries
                    is that of 1472, in folio, without the name of any place, but printed at Foligno
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">La</hi><hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi><hi rend="italic">di Dante Alighieri,</hi><hi rend="italic">delle</hi><hi rend="italic">pene e</hi><hi rend="italic">punizioni</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    Vizj, e premj</hi><hi rend="italic">delle</hi><hi rend="italic">Virtu.</hi>
                    The same year <pb break="no" facs="nls:194755319" xml:id="kp-eb0707-5319-0619"/>another appeared at Mantua, in folio, bearing the
                    Latin title of <hi rend="italic">Dantis</hi><hi rend="italic">Capitula,</hi><hi rend="italic">Italice</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but the most valuable of
                    all these editions is that of Naples, 1477, in folio, which is now very scarce
                    and high priced. The first of the old editions with commentaries is that of
                    Milan, 1478, in folio, entitled <hi rend="italic">Dantis</hi><hi rend="italic">Comoedia cum</hi><hi rend="italic">Commentariis,</hi> by Martin Paul Nidobeato
                    de Navarre, printed, the text in beautiful characters, and the commentaries in
                    Gothic. This edition is highly esteemed on account of the purity of the text,
                    and the excellent lessons which it affords. The principal editions accompanied
                    with commentaries are those of Florence, 1481, folio; Venice, 1491, folio;
                    Venice, 1554, in 4to; Lyons, 1547, in 16to; Venice, 1568, in 4to; Padua, 1727,
                    in 3 vols. 8vo; Venice, 1739, in 3 vols. 8vo; Verona, 1749; and Venice, 1757,
                    1758, 3 vols. large 4to. The most esteemed editions of the text alone since the
                    fifteenth century, are those of Venice, Aldus, 1502. in 8vo; Aldus and Andrea d’
                    Assola, 1515, in 8vo; Florence, Juntes, 1506, in 8vo; Florence, 1595, in 8vo,
                    being the Della-Cruscan edition, which was reprinted at Naples in 1716, in 12mo;
                    Paris, Prault, 1768, in 2 vols. 12mo; Parma, Bodoni, 1796, in 3 vols. 4to; Pisa,
                    1804, in 3 vols. folio; Milan, Mussi, 1809, in 3 vols. large atlas folio. The
                    best French translation of Dante’s works is that of Artaud, published at Paris
                    in 1811, 1812, 1813. In English there are two translations, both excellent, the
                    one by Carey and the other by Wright. The <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi> has
                    given rise to a good deal of speculation, of which some account will be found in
                    die <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review,</hi> vol. lv. The lyric productions or
                    <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> of Dante, though inferior to his great poem, are not
                    unworthy of him. They are to be found in the Venetian editions of his works,
                    published by Pasquali in 1741 and by Zatta in 1758. These two editions also
                    contain the prose works of Dante, the most interesting of which is his <hi rend="italic">Vita Nuova.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Convivio</hi><hi rend="italic">di Dante</hi> is a commentary in prose on three of his Canzoni.
                    The treatise <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Monarchia,</hi> written
                    in Latin, had for its object to support the rights of the Emperor Henry VII. by
                    whose means Dante hoped to be restored to his country in spite of the pope, who
                    had been the cause of his disgrace and exile; and though the style is devoid of
                    elegance, it nevertheless displays considerable vigour. In the treatise <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Vulgari Eloquentia,</hi> also written in
                    Latin, Dante proposed to examine the state of the Italian language about a
                    century after its origin, to indicate the idioms formed nearly at the same time
                    in different parts of Italy, which ought to prevail, and to point out the
                    different species of composition in which the language had been employed with
                    success, as well as the authors who had most distinguished themselves by their
                    writings in that language. The edition of Zatta above mentioned also contains
                    paraphrases of the seven penitential psalms, of the <hi rend="italic">Credo,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Pater Noster,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Ave Maria,</hi> pieces which have nothing in common with his great poem, except
                    the form of the verses and the interlacement of the rhymes.</p></div></body></text></TEI>