<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6008-0672-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">DEFOLIATION</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 672</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1042610">Oak</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:840438">Buds</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1130905">Spring</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1130935">Springs</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn5g">Oak</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ht2gc4x">Buds</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4901zk6v">Springs</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194756008" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">DEFOLIATION</label> (from <hi rend="italic">de, and
                    folium,</hi> a leaf), the fall of the leaves. A term opposed <hi rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="italic">frondescentia,</hi> the annual renovation of the
                    leaves, produced by the unfolding of the buds in spring.</p><p>Most plants in cold and temperate climates shed their leaves every year. This
                    happens in autumn, and is generally announced by the flowering of the common
                    meadow saffron. The term is only applied to trees and shrubs; for herbs perish
                    down to the roots every year, losing stem, leaves, and all.</p><p>All plants do not drop their leaves at the same time. Amongst large trees, the
                    ash and walnut, although the latest in unfolding, are soonest divested of them.
                    The latter seldom carries its leaves above five months. On the oak and hornbeam
                    the leaves die and wither as soon as the colds commence; but they remain
                    attached to the branches until they are pushed off by the new ones, which unfold
                    themselves the following spring. These trees are doubtless a kind of evergreens.
                    The leaves are probably destroyed only by cold; and perhaps would continue
                    longer on the plant, but for the force of the spring sap joined to the
                    moisture.</p><p>In mild and dry seasons the liiach, privet, yellow jessamine of the woods, and
                    maple of Crete, preserve their leaves green until spring, and do not drop them
                    till the new leaves are beginning to appear. The fig-tree, and many other trees
                    that grow between the tropics, are of this particular class of evergreens. The
                    trees in Egypt, says Dr Hasselquist, cast their leaves in the latter end of
                    December and beginning of January, having young leaves ready before all the old
                    ones have fallen off; and, to forward this operation of nature, few of the trees
                    have buds; the sycamore and willow, indeed, have some, but with few and quite
                    loose <hi rend="italic">stipula</hi> or scales. Nature did not conceive buds to
                    be so necessary in the southern as in the northern countries; and this occasions
                    a great difference between them.</p><p>Lastly, some trees and shrubs preserve their leaves constantly throughout the
                    whole year, and are not in the least influenced by the clemency or inclemency of
                    seasons. Such are the firs, juniper, yew, cedar, cypress, and many other trees,
                    hence denominated <hi rend="italic">evergreens.</hi> These preserve their old
                    leaves a long time after the formation of the new, and do not drop them at any
                    determinate time. In general the leaves of evergreens are harder and less
                    succulent than those which are renewed annually. The trees are generally natives
                    of warm climates; as the alaternuses of France and Italy, and the evergreen oak
                    of Portugal and Suabia.</p><p>Some herbaceous perennials, as the house-leeks and navel-worts, enjoy the same
                    privilege with the evergreen trees, and resist the severities of winter; some
                    even can dispense with the earth for a time, being replete with juices, which
                    the leaves imbibe from the humidity of the atmosphere, and which in such plants
                    are of themselves sufficient for effecting the purposes of vegetation. It is for
                    this reason that, unless in excessive hot weather, gardeners seldom water fat
                    succulent plants, as the aloes, which rot when they are moistened, if the sun
                    does not quickly dry them up.</p><p>The leaves of all the evergreen shrubs and trees have a thin compact skin or
                    cover over their surface, as is easily discovered by macerating them in water,
                    in order to separate the parenchyma or pulp from the vessels of the leaves,
                    which cannot be effected in any of these evergreens till a thin parchment-like
                    colour is taken off. These trees and shrubs are found by experiment to perspire
                    but little, when compared with others which shed their leaves; and it is perhaps
                    principally owing to this close covering, as also to the small proportion of
                    moisture contained in their vessels, that they retain their verdure, and
                    continue through the winter on the trees. The nutritive juices of these plants
                    always abound more or less with an oily quality, which secures them from being
                    injured by severe frosts; so that many of these evergreen trees are adapted to
                    grow in the coldest parts of the habitable world.</p><p>With respect to deciduous trees, the falling off of the leaves seems principally
                    to depend on the temperature of the atmosphere, which likewise serves to hasten
                    or retard the appearance in question. An ardent sun contributes to hasten the
                    dropping of the leaves; and hence in hot and dry summers the leaves of the
                    lime-tree andhorse-chesnut turn yellow about the first of September, whilst in
                    other years the yellowness does not appear till the beginning of October.
                    Nothing, however, contributes more to hasten the fall of the leaves than
                    immoderate cold or moist weather in autumn; but, on the other hand, moderate
                    droughts serve to retard it. As a proof of this position, Mr Adanson relates,
                    that in the year 1759, the leaves of the elm-tree, which generally fall off
                    about the twenty-fifth of November, continued in verdure and vigour at Paris,
                    where the autumn was remarkably dry, till the tenth of the following month.</p><p>It deserves to be remarked, that an evergreen grafted upon a deciduous tree,
                    determines the latter to retain its leaves. This observation is confirmed by
                    repeated experiments, particularly by grafting the laurel, or cherry-bay, an
                    evergreen, on the common cherry; and the ilex, or evergreen oak, on the oak.</p></div></body></text></TEI>