<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6814-0734-02" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">DERBYSHIRE</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 7, page 734</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="19" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term><term n="14" ref="fasttopic:845230">Canals</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1047551">Ores</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1053705">Parks</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z08r">Doves</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term><term n="19" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:194756814" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">DERBYSHIRE</label> was, in the time of the Britons, <hi rend="italic">a</hi> portion of the district which constituted the kingdom of
                    the Co-ritani. During the government of the Romans, it formed a part of
                    Britannia Prima, and under the Heptarchy it was included in the kingdom of
                    Mercia. It is situated nearly in the centre c∙f England, and is bounded on the
                    cast by the county of Nottingham and a part of Leicestershire; on the west it is
                    divided from Staffordshire and Cheshire by the rivers Trent, Dove, the Etlierow,
                    and Goyt; on the north it has Yorkshire and a part of Cheshire, and on the south
                    is Leicestershire. Its figure is very irregular, but approaches nearest to that
                    of a triangle. The greatest length from south-east to north-west is about
                    fifty-six miles, and its width from east-north-east to west-south-west
                    thirty-three. It contains 972 square miles, or 622,080 statute acres.</p><p>This county is divided into the hundreds of High Peak, Scarsdale, Appletree,
                    Repton and Gresley, Morleston and Littchurch, and the wapentake of Wirksworth.
                    It contains sixteen market-towns, viz. Alfreton, Ashbourne, Ash-</p><p>over, Bakewell, Belper, Buxton, Chapel-en-le-Frith, Chesterfield, Crich,
                    Cromford, Derby, Heanor, Ilkeston, Sideswell, Winster, and Wirksworth, lt
                    consists of 117 parishes, is included as an archdeaconry in the diocese of
                    Lichfield and Coventry, and is divided into six deaneries, viz. High Peak,
                    Chesterfield, Ashbourne, Castíllar, Derby, and Repington. By the reform act this
                    county returns four members to the House of Commons, and for that purpose it has
                    been formed into two divisions. The northern part comprehends the whole of the
                    hundreds of High Peak and Scarsdale, and so much of the wapentake of Wirksworth
                    as is comprised in Bakewell division, and the polling-place is the town of
                    Bakewell. The southern part comprehends the hundreds of Appletree, of Repton and
                    Gresley, of Morleston and Littchurch, and the remainder of the wapentake of
                    Wirksworth; and the polling-place for the division is the town of Derby. Derby
                    gives the title of earl to the noble family of Stanley, Chesterfield the same to
                    that of Stanhope, and Hartington affords the title of marquis to his Grace the
                    Duke of Devonshire.</p><p>There is no English county which presents such a variety of scenery as
                    Derbyshire. The surface of the southern district is, for the most part, pretty
                    level, containing nothing remarkable in its hills, and consequently little of
                    the picturesque. But the northern part abounds in hill and dale, and the scenery
                    is in many places romantic and sublime. The county rising gradually from the
                    south to the town of Wirksworth, and thence to the north, assumes a mountainous
                    appearance, which it continues to possess to its extremity. These elevations are
                    the commencement of that mountainous ridge which from thence divides the island
                    and extends into Scotland. The highest points in the mountainous tract of
                    Derbyshire are, Ax Edge, about three miles south-west of Buxton; Lord’s Seat,
                    near Castleton; and Kinderscout, near the north-western extremity of the county.
                    About the town of Derby, and to the south of it, the country is flat and low. In
                    the hilly districts some of the valleys are very beautiful, particularly those
                    of Castleton and Glossop; but what constitutes the most picturesque and singular
                    scenery of this county is the great number and variety of smaller valleys or
                    dales with which the limestone district abounds. These may differ in extent and
                    some particular circumstances, but the general characteristics of them are
                    precipitous rocks, of very singular and picturesque forms, with mountain streams
                    and rivulets running through the lower parts of the dales, the sides of which
                    are generally well wooded. The most celebrated of these are, Matlock-Dale, on
                    the river Derwent; Monsal-Dale, the upper part of which is called Millers-Dale,
                    on the river Wye; Middleton-Dale, Eyam-Dale, and Dove-Dale. In Matlock-Dale is a
                    stupendous rock, called the High-Tor, rising almost perpendicularly from the
                    river to the height of about 300 feet.</p><p>The soils of Derbyshire consist chiefly of clay, loam, sand, and peat, very
                    irregularly intermixed. The southern part, which has been distinguished by the
                    appellation of the fertile district, consists principally of a red loam, on
                    various subsoils, which approaches to marl, clay, loam, sand, grit or gravel,
                    according to the nature of the substratum, or its exposure to the atmosphere.
                    Peat mosses are abundant in the northern part of the county denominated High
                    Peak. The substrata of most of the southern portion of the county consist of
                    gravel, intermixed with large portions of red marl of very irregular forms, in
                    several parts of which are beds of gypsum of considerable extent. The substrata
                    of the other parts of Derbyshire consist of limestone of various kinds, and
                    toadstone; shale and gritstone; coal and indurated clay resting on each other,
                    in alternate layers.</p><p>Derbyshire is a well-wooded county, and several of the <pb break="no" facs="nls:194756827" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6827-0735"/>noblemen’s
                    parks afford fine oak of very noble appearance. Those of Kedlestone Park, the
                    seat of Lord Scarsdale, are supposed to be the largest and oldest in the
                    kingdom, several being thought to be eight hundred years old.</p><p>The atmosphere and climate of Derbyshire vary very much in different parts. From
                    its northern situation, even the southern part of the county is colder, and more
                    frequently visited with rain, than many of the more central .counties. In
                    summer, cold and thick fogs are frequently seen hanging over the rivers, and
                    surrounding the bases of the hills, and hoar-frosts are not unfrequent even in
                    the months of June and July. Owing to the great elevation of the northern parts,
                    some kinds of grain will not grow at all in the Peak, and even that which is
                    sown in the more sheltered places is seldom cut till late in the year. The
                    winters are, in general, very severe, and the mountains attracting the clouds in
                    their passage over them, cause this region to be distinguished from the others,
                    by the greater quantity of rain which falls upon it.</p><p>The chief rivers arc, the Trent, the Derwent, the Wye, the Dove, the Etherow, the
                    Earwash, and the Rother. The Trent does not intersect the county, but forms the
                    boundary between it and Staffordshire on the south. The Derwent rises at the
                    northern extremity of the county; its whole length is forty miles. It was
                    formerly navigable from Wylne-Ferry up to Derby, but the navigation was
                    abandoned when the Derby Canal was completed in 1795. The Wye has its origin a
                    little to the north of Buxton, and falls into the Derwent near Rowsley. The
                    Dove, which has its source in the High Peak, a few miles to the south of Buxton,
                    is for many miles the boundary between Derbyshire and Staffordshire; it falls
                    into the Derwent near Newton-Sol-ney. The Wye and the Dove are celebrated for
                    their trout and grayling fishing. The river Rother rises near Padley, and, after
                    running by Chesterfield, enters Yorkshire near Killamarch. The Earwash flows
                    from the skirts of Sherwood Forest in Nottinghamshire, and falls into the Trent
                    near Long Eaton. The Etherow rises amongst the hills at the northern boundary of
                    the county, flows nearly due south, dividing Derbyshire from Cheshire, and,
                    meeting the Groyt near Marple, assumes the name of Mersey. The lesser rivers
                    are, the Amber, Barbrook, Burbage, Ecclesburn, Goyt, Lathkill, Maese, and the
                    Morledge.</p><p>Derbyshire has several canals intersecting it in different directions. The Trent
                    and Mersey, or Grand Trunk Canal, communicating between Liverpool and London,
                    and also with Bristol and Hull, was begun in 1776, by the celebrated Brindley, a
                    native of the county, and completed in 1777, under his able successors Smeaton
                    and Rennie. It passes through Derbyshire, from Burton to its termination at
                    Wilden-Ferry, following the course of the Trent. The Chesterfield Canal was
                    begun in 1771 by Brindley, and completed by his brother-in-law Mr Henshall in
                    1776. It enters the county at Killamarsh, and terminates at Chesterfield. The
                    Langley Bridge, or Earwash Canal, begun in 1777 by Mr Jessop, commences in the
                    Trent navigation, near Sawley, and terminates at Langley Mill. It runs parallel
                    to the little river Earwash, and opens into the Cromford Canal. The Peak Forest
                    Canal was commenced in 1794, and finished in 1800. It proceeds from the
                    Ashton-under-Line Canal, near Dukinfield Bridge, and terminates at Chapel
                    Milton, Derbyshire. The Cromford Canal was begun in 1789. Its line is wholly in
                    Derbyshire, commencing at Langley Mill, where the Earwash terminates, and ending
                    at Cromford. It was completed in 1794 by Mr Jessop. The Ashby-de-la-Zouch Canal,
                    begun in 1793, but not finished until 1805, is connected with the southern part
                    of Derbyshire; its line passing by Willesley and Measham. The line of the Derby
                    Canal is entirely in this county; commencing in the Trent and Mersey Canal,
                    north of Swarkstone, passing by Derby, with a branch to Little Eaton, and
                    terminating in the Earwash Canal, half a mile south of Sandiacre. The Nutbrook
                    Canal was made in 1793. It commences in the Earwash Canal, and, after running
                    four miles and a half, finishes at Shipley Wharf.</p><p>This county is celebrated for its abundance of metals and minerals. They are
                    various and plentiful, particularly in the limestone strata. Lead ore is found
                    in several forms, but most commonly in galena or sulphuret of lead. That species
                    called slickenside, having a smooth glossy surface, is found in the Odin and
                    Castleton Mines. The portion of silver united to the Derbyshire lead is not
                    sufficient to be worth while separating it. A carbonate of lead sometimes
                    occurs. Calamine, or native oxide of zinc, is found at Castleton, Cromford,
                    Bonsall, and Wirksworth. It occurs in various colours and of different
                    qualities; sometimes in nodules, in the form of grapes, and in the ochreous
                    state. Blende, or black-jack, another ore of zinc, is also obtained. Copper has
                    been found in small quantities only. Pieces of considerable size, detached from
                    any vein, have frequently been met with at Matlock and Bonsall; and a slender
                    vein has been discovered between Tideswcll and Buxton.</p><p>Iron ore is found in very great abundance in all those tracts of the country
                    where coal has been discovered. It lies at different depths; and frequently,
                    from the great dip of the strata, appears upon the surface of the ground. The
                    beds of ore are from two to twelve inches thick, producing generally that of the
                    argillaceous kind; but the calcareous, or sparry iron ores, of a fine brownish
                    red colour, sometimes bright yellow, scaly, or dirty brown, are found in
                    amorphous masses near the surface, and filling insulated places. The principal
                    founderies and forges are, Butterley, Codnor, Morley Park, Wingerworth,
                    Chesterfield, Riddings, and Stavely.</p><p>The ore of manganese appears in various forms. The ores of arsenic and antimony
                    are found in small quantities, united with lead ore, quartz crystals, various
                    crystals of calcareous spar, and of fluor or fluate of lime, gypsum, selenite,
                    and barytes, here called cauk. The most beautiful among the fossils of this
                    county is that much admired fluor known by the name of Blue John, or Derbyshire
                    spar, found in the fissures of the limestone, in the neighbourhood of Castleton.
                    This substance, when polished, exhibits an infinite variety of blue, purple,
                    red, and yellow shades; and its being transparent shows the colours to greater
                    advantage. The red however is not natural, but produced by an artificial
                    process, chiefly by the agency of fire. Petroleum, or rock oil, is found in the
                    black marble at Ashford. Elastic bitumen, a substance peculiar to this county,
                    resembling in appearance the common Indian rubber, is also found in the cavities
                    of the Odin mine.</p><p>Coal is very plentiful, abounding in large fields in several districts. It is of
                    different degrees of hardness, comes out of the pit in long stratified pieces of
                    shining fracture, burns with a brilliant flame and crackling noise, and leaves a
                    reddish-white ash. The limestone of this county is of various colours, white,
                    gray, yellowy blue, and black; and is of various qualities, some being soft, and
                    some sufficiently hard to be polished into beautiful marble. A new variety, of a
                    deep red colour, similar to Rosa antiquo, has lately been found near New Haven.
                    The Duke of Devonshire preserves it for particular purposes. Fine freestone,
                    toadstone, shale, clunch, stalactitical concretions, and fuller’s earth, are
                    also found in different parts. Impressions of leaves and plants, a great variety
                    of coralline bodies, fossil shells, and even a small alligator, have been found
                    imbedded in the limestone of this county.</p><p>The warm mineral and other springs have long been celebrated. The principal are
                    those of Buxton and Matlock.</p><pb break="no" facs="nls:194756840" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6840-0736"/><p>The heat of the Buxton water is 82°, never varying on account of the temperature
                    of the atmosphere. The water is remarkably pure, being very slightly impregnated
                    with saline particles. It is used both for bathing and drinking, and is chiefly
                    recommended for gout, rheumatism, derangement of the biliary and digestive
                    organs, and diseases of the urinary passages, for all of which it is of
                    considerable efficacy. There are several public and private baths, both for
                    ladies and gentlemen, and one open gratis to the poor. It appears from several
                    remains discovered at different times that these waters were known to the
                    Romans; and from their time to the present they have been resorted to by
                    invalids.</p><p>Matlock water is not so warm as the Buxton, the thermometer seldom rising to more
                    than 68° of Fahrenheit. The springs issue from between fifteen and thirty yards
                    above the level of the river; higher or lower the springs are cold, differing in
                    nothing from common water. The water is very pure, and less impregnated with
                    mineral substances than that of Buxton. There are also several baths at Matlock,
                    which are much resorted to.</p><p>There is a tepid chalybeate spring at Bakewell, the temperature of which is about
                    59 degrees. It is tonic, and recommended for indigestion, debility, and chronic
                    rheumatism. Here there is one bath. At this place there is also a spring, which
                    has been found to contain in sixty quarts thirteen cubic inches of sulphuretted
                    hydrogen. The tepid spring at. Stony-Middleton much resembles that of Matlock,
                    but it is not so warm, being only 63 degrees. There are several other tepid
                    springs in the county. Among the sulphureous springs, that of Kedleston is the
                    strongest. It is like the Harrowgate water, and is used externally for most
                    cutaneous diseases, particularly for those of an ulcerous nature; while it is
                    taken internally as an antiscorbutic and diuretic. There are cold and warm
                    baths. Other sulphureous springs are also found in many districts. The most
                    celebrated chalybeate water is at Quarndon, three miles from Derby, which is a
                    good deal frequented.</p><p>Among the wonders of Derbyshire, all authors mention the intermitting spring at
                    Barmoor, near Tideswell. It is generally called the Ebbing and Flowing Well; but
                    the intermission is not regular, for in dry seasons the ebbing and flowing
                    ceases for several weeks, and in wet weather it often ebbs and flows every ten
                    minutes.</p><p>The southern and south-eastern parts of this county are the best cultivated; for
                    great quantities of excellent wheat and barley are grown there. The arable lands
                    in the northern parts are chiefly cultivated for oats, of which grain there is a
                    great consumption, oaten bread leavened being the principal food of the lower
                    classes. The dairy country is around Ashbourne and the south-western side of the
                    county, whence not less than 2000 tons of cheese are annually exported. In the
                    neighbourhood of Chesterfield there are about eighty acres of land employed in
                    the growth of chamomile. This useful plant was introduced into the county about
                    1740; and it produces from three to six hundredweight per acre, and is chiefly
                    consumed at home and in America. Valerian and elecampane are cultivated in
                    Ashover and North Wingfield in small quantities.</p><p>The breed of cows in this county has been very much improved of late years. They
                    are in general horned, large, and handsome; yielding upon an average ten quarts
                    of milk a day. They are most commonly speckled, with large well-turned horns,
                    though of late the short-horned Lancashire breed has been introduced. Nature
                    seems to have adapted the horses in Derbyshire to the different regions in which
                    she designed them to labour. In the northern districts the breed is small, of
                    light and slender make; in the southern parts they are in general of a strong
                    and heavy kind; and in the stables of the country gentlemen this beautiful
                    animal may be found in the full perfection of its symmetry. The sheep also vary
                    in size; those that are bred on the borders of Leicestershire differ but little
                    in weight from that county breed; but they gradually diminish in size as we
                    proceed northwards, till they get as small as any in the kingdom. The parks in
                    the county are well stocked with fallow-deer.</p><p>The woollen manufactories, for which this county was formerly celebrated, are now
                    confined to the worsted-spinning at Derby, Melbourne, and Tideswell, and to the
                    weaving a few blankets at Chesterfield. The first silk-mill established in this
                    kingdom was introduced into Derby in the beginning of the last century, and the
                    improved machinery of it was brought from Italy by the celebrated John Lombe.
                    This mill is still worked with the original machinery; but very great
                    improvements have been made of late years in the construction of the spinning
                    apparatus; and the facility attained in working the several articles of silk
                    manufacture has contributed to the extension of this branch of business in a
                    very eminent degree. The manufacture of stockings was introduced into Derbyshire
                    about 1717; and this acquired additional celebrity by the ingenious discovery of
                    Strutt, who introduced a machine for making ribbed stockings about the year
                    1755.</p><p>The manufacture of cotton was introduced in the year 1771, when Sir Richard
                    Arkwright, the inventor, established one of the first cotton-mills on the
                    improved principles; and in 1773 he, in conjunction with Mr Jedediah Strutt and
                    Mr Need, made at Derby the first successful attempt to establish the manufacture
                    of calicoes in this kingdom. This county, therefore, is the cradle of the most
                    important branches of the cotton trade; and, at the present moment, an immense
                    capital is employed in the business, which is carried on to a great extent.</p><p>There are in several places manufactures of linen, and flax-spinning is carried
                    on in others, but upon a small scale. White and red-lead works, various
                    manufactures connected with the iron trade, marble and spar works, a long
                    established and celebrated porcelain manufactory,and grindstone mills, are found
                    in different parts of the county. In the town of Derby there is a considerable
                    quantity of jewellery goods prepared, of good taste and quality.</p><p>Among the singular customs of Derbyshire may be mentioned that of rush-bearing, a
                    ceremony of strewing the churches on a certain day with rushes. It usually takes
                    place on the anniversary of the dedication of the church, or on midsummer eve.
                    The ancient custom of hanging up in the churches garlands of roses, with a pair
                    of gloves cut out of white paper, which had been carried before the corpses of
                    unmarried women at their funerals, still prevails in many parishes of the Peak;
                    and that of dressing wells and fountains with flowers is still preserved at
                    Tissington, and Holy Thursday is devoted to the festival. The country wakes are
                    generally observed here, on the Sunday following the day of the dedication of
                    the church or chapel, or on the day of the saint to whom it is dedicated.</p><p>The British antiquities of this county are druidical circles, tumuli of earth and
                    stones, rocking-stones, rock-basins, and some rude military works in the
                    uncultivated parts of the county. The Roman remains deserving of notice are, the
                    altar preserved in Haddon-Hall, the inscribed pigs of lead now in the British
                    Museum, and the silver plate found in Risley Park. Several Roman roads, the
                    remains of which are still visible, passed through the county; and many stations
                    of consequence may be easily traced.</p><p>The ecclesiastical edifices of this county exhibit the taste of different ages.
                    Of the Saxon period is the crypt under Repton Church, which is supposed to be
                    the remains<pb break="no" facs="nls:194756853" xml:id="kp-eb0707-6853-0737"/> of the conventual church, destroyed by the Danes
                    in the year 874. Melbourne church is a very perfect specimen of the massive
                    style of architecture which prevailed in the eleventh century. The desecrated
                    church of Steetly exhibits a very complete specimen of the latter and more
                    enriched style of Saxon architecture on a small scale. Other and numerous
                    remains of Saxon architecture are to be found in this county.</p><p>Specimens of the early Gothic style are not frequent; and those of the fifteenth
                    and sixteenth centuries are inconsiderable, except the tower of All-Saints at
                    Derby, which has been generally and deservedly admired: it is about 150 feet
                    high, and richly ornamented with Gothic tracing.</p><p>The only monastic buildings in this county, of which any remains at present
                    exist, are Dale Abbey, the arch of the east window of which still stands;
                    Beauchief Abbey, now used as a church; part of the original Saxon monastery of
                    Repton, and an ancient brick tower, which formed part of the prior’s
                    lodging.</p><p>The ancient castles of Derbyshire whose ruins now remain are those of Castleton,
                    Codnor, Horsley, and Melbourne. Castleton was most probably erected by William
                    Peverell, to whom the manor was given by William the Conqueror; Codnor was the
                    ancient seat of the Grey family; Horsley was built in the beginning of the
                    thirteenth century, by Ferrers, earl of Derby; and Melbourne existed as early as
                    the time of Edward the Third.</p><p>The most remarkable mansion-house in this county, in point of antiquity, is
                    Haddon Hall, belonging to the Duke of Rutland. It has been erected at various
                    times, but no part later than the middle of the sixteenth century. Hardwick
                    Hall, belonging to the Duke of Devonshire, is another pile of the above
                    description, exhibiting a complete specimen of the domestic architecture which
                    prevailed among the upper ranks during the reign of Queen Elizabeth. Balborough
                    Hall is another handsome mansion of the sixteenth century. The manor-house of
                    South Wingfield, a very splendid and spacious edifice, erected by Lord Cromwell
                    in the reign of Henry VI., is now a mere ruin, having been suffered to fall into
                    decay soon after the civil war in the seventeenth century.</p><p>The noblemen’s seats are, Chatsworth, the chief seat, and Hardwicke, the
                    occasional residence, of the Duke of Devonshire; Elvaston, the seat of the Earl
                    of Harrington; Sudbury, that of Lord Vernon; Kedleston, the elegant mansion of
                    Lord Scarsdale; Bretby, the seat of the Chesterfield family; Doveridge, that of
                    Lord Waterpark; and Hassop, that of the Earl of Newburgh. The baronets’ seats
                    are, Ashbourne Hall, that of Sir Brooke Boothby; Wingerworth, that of Sir Henry
                    Hunloke; Egginton, that of Sir Henry Every; Tissington, that of Sir H.
                    Fitzherbert; Chaddesden, that of Sir R. Wilmot; Osmaston, that of Sir R. Wilmot;
                    Foremark, that of Sir F. Burdett; and Stretton, that of Sir W. C. Browne. There
                    are several elegant and extensive mansions belonging to the gentry of the
                    county, the principal of which are, Sutton and Willersley, both the property of
                    R. Arkwright, Esq.; Markeaton, of F. Mundy, Esq.; Longford, of E. Coke, Esq.;
                    Radborne, of E. S. C. Pole, Esq.; Bridge Hill, of G. B. Strutt, Esq.; Hopton, of
                    P. Gell, Esq.; Shipley, of E. Μ. Mundy, Esq.; Norton, <hi rend="italic">of
                    S.</hi> Shore, Esq.; and Alfreton, of H. C. More-wood, Esq.</p><p>By some ancient returns, of doubtful authority, it appears that the inhabitants
                    were in 1377 only 24,289, but in 1789 they amounted to 124,465. By the more
                    correct later returns they were found to amount in 1801 to 161,142, in 1811 to
                    185,487, in 1821 to 213,333, and in 1831 to 236,900. The value of the landed
                    property, as assessed by the property tax of 1815, appeared to be L.887,659
                    annually.</p></div></body></text></TEI>