<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-7474-0744-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KLOPSTOCK, Frederic Theophilus</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1017422">Messiah</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950757">Hamburgers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043867">Odes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p104">Messiah</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688q84">Odes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192947474?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">KLOPSTOCK, <hi rend="smallcaps">Frederic
                            Theophilus</hi></label>, was born at Quedlinburg in 1724, and one of the
                    most celebrated of the German poets. His father was a man of an elevated
                    character, and a magistrate of that place, who afterwards farmed a bailiwick in
                    the Brandenburg part of Mansfield. Klopstock was the oldest of eleven children,
                    and having received the rudiments of education at home, he was put to the public
                    school of Quedlinburg, where he soon became conspicuous both for bodily and
                    mental exercises. He went to the college of the same place at the age of
                    sixteen, where, under the tuition of an able teacher, he obtained a knowledge
                    of, and taste for, the beauties of the best classical authors. He composed some
                    pastorals in verse; and even at this early period he conceived the bold design
                    of writing an epic poem, fixing at length, after much deliberation, on the
                    Messiah, by which he has rendered his name immortal.</p>
                <p part="N">He commenced the study of theology at the University of Jena, in the
                    year 1745, although in his retirement he was constantly ruminating on his great
                    projected work already mentioned, sketching out the three first cantos. They
                    were first written in prose, as the common measure of German verse did not
                    accord with his own sentiments. Transported with the melody of Homer’s and
                    Virgil’s strains, he determined to make trial of German hexameters, in which he
                    succeeded so entirely to his own satisfaction, that he fixed upon this majestic
                    verse for the whole of his poem. By his removal from Jena to Leipzig in 1746, he
                    became acquainted with a number of young votaries of the muses, who occasionally
                    published their essays in a paper called the <hi rend="italic">Bremen
                        Contributions,</hi> in which appeared the three cantos of Klopstock’s
                    Messiah, and a number of his odes, for which he was so applauded as to animate
                    him to persevere.</p>
                <p part="N">He quitted Leipzig in 1748, and resided at Langensalza, where he carried
                    on a fruitless correspondence with a beautiful young lady, who discovered no
                    inclination to return his passion, which for some time threw a gloom over his
                    mind. He now published ten books of his Messiah, by which he came to be known
                    and admired all over Germany. It was an extremely popular work amongst all those
                    who were at once the lovers of poetry and devotion. It was quoted from the
                    pulpit by young divines, whilst others of a more stern deportment found fault
                    with the author, as indulging too much in fiction on sacred topics.</p>
                <p part="N">He travelled into Switzerland in 1750, to pay a visit to Bodmer of
                    Zurich, in consequence of an invitation, and was received with every token of
                    respect. The sublime scenery of that country, the simplicity of its inhabitants,
                    and the freedom they enjoyed, were admirably suited to the taste and sentiments
                    of Klopstock. Here in all probability he would have breathed his last, had not
                    Baron Bernstorff, who was charmed with bis poetry, engaged Count Molke, after
                    returning from France to Copenhagen, to invite him to that city, with assurances
                    of such a pension as would make him independent. Our author accordingly set out
                    for Copenhagen in the year 1751, by the way of Brunswick and Hamburg, at which
                    latter place he became acquainted with a young lady, Miss Moller, of literary
                    abilities, and a heart susceptible of tender impressions. They were soon
                    afterwards married, and seemed destined by Providence to be one of the happiest
                    couples upon earth; but he was early deprived of her, for she died in childbed,
                    and her memory was sacred to Klopstock to the last hour of his existence. He
                    lived for the most part at Copenhagen till the year 1771, after which he resided
                    at Hamburg in the capacity of royal Danish legate, and counsellor of the
                    margrave of Baden, who gave him a pension, and engaged him to pass the year 1775
                    at his palace of Carlsruhe. Such was the diffidence of our poet, that it
                    required the most extraordinary condescension on the part of the great to make
                    him easy in their presence.</p>
                <p part="N">The decline of his health made no change on the habitual tranquillity of
                    his mind; he contemplated his approaching dissolution without any dismay, and
                    his pious fortitude continued unshaken amidst the severest sufferings. He died
                    at Hamburg in March 1803, being then seventy-nine years of age, and his funeral
                    was attended with such honours as justly belonged to the greatest poet of the
                    country.</p>
                <p part="N">The character of Klopstock as a poet is that of exuberance of
                    imagination and sentiment. His sublimity, which is nearly unparalleled, makes
                    him almost lose himself in mystical extravagance. A great critic claims for the
                    author of the Messiah a rank amongst the very first class of poets. His odes and
                    lyric poems are much admired by his countrymen; and his dramatic works display
                    great force and dignity, but are thought to be better adapted to the closet than
                    the theatre. He was also an excellent prose writer, as is fully evinced by his
                        <hi rend="italic">Grammatical Dialogues.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
