<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-6577-0675-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">KANT, Immanuel</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:954113">Heaven</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tb93">Heaven</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192946577?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">KANT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Immanuel</hi></label>, a
                    very eminent metaphysician, and the author of that theory which has been
                    distinguished by the name of the <hi rend="italic">Critical</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">Transcendental Philosophy,</hi> was born at Königsberg, in
                    Prussia, on the 22d of April 1724. Of his paternal ancestors little is known
                    with certainty; but tradition represents them as having sprung from an emigrant
                    Scotchman of the name of Cant; and the philosopher himself, who frequently
                    alluded to this traditionary extraction, is said to have been the first of his
                    family who changed the initial letter of his name to K, with a view to adapt it
                    to the German pronunciation.</p>
                <p part="N">The father of Kant, who exercised the humble profession of a saddler or
                    harness-maker, in the suburbs of Königsberg, was distinguished rather for his
                    integrity and respectability than for his wcaltb. His mother appears to have
                    been a woman of considerable talent, and of a more decided character. She was
                    exceedingly pious, and much attached to the strict religious tenets and
                    discipline of Dr Schultz, a divine who at that period enjoyed a high reputation
                    for learning, eloquence, and piety.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p part="N">He was professor of theology at the university
                            of Königsberg, and the author of several works which were much esteemed
                            in their day; amongst others, of a work on the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Elements of Metaphysical Science.</hi></p></note> Kant uniformly
                    spoke of both his parents, but especially of his mother, with feelings of the
                    warmest affection.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p
                            part="N">Kant had several sisters, and an only brother several years
                            younger than himself, who took orders, and had a living in Courland,
                            where he continued to reside until his death.</p></note></p>
                <p part="N">Although far from being in affluent circumstances, his parents resolved
                    to bestow upon their son Immanuel every advantage that could result from a
                    liberal education. Accordingly, after having been taught to read and write at
                    the charity school of the suburbs, he was sent, in the year 1732, to the <hi
                        rend="italic">Collegium Fridericianum,</hi> at the suggestion, it is
                    believed, of Dr Schultz, who, even at that early period, had the penetration to
                    discover the talents of the boy. At this school he contracted an intimate
                    friendship with Ruhnkenius, afterwards so celebrated for his philological
                    attainments, which was maintained by occasional correspondence during the
                    remainder of their lives, and which, in their early years, may naturally be
                    supposed to have had a salutary influence on the studies of both. They were both
                    indefatigable students; and they not only mutually assisted each other in their
                    school exercises, but read together, during their leisure hours, whatever books
                    their inclination led them to peruse, or their circumstances permitted them to
                    purchase. It is rather a remarkable circumstance, however, that at this early
                    period Kant devoted his attention principally to philological studies; whilst
                    his friend Ruhnkenius seemed to be attracted, by an apparently natural tendency
                    of disposition, to the cultivation of philosophy. In their maturer years, as is
                    well known, these early predilections were precisely reversed.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Throughout every
                            period of his life, however, Kant retained a great fondness for
                            classical literature. He was particularly partial to the study of the
                            Roman writers; and, even in his old age, he delighted to have an
                            opportunity of reciting and applying passages from the works of his
                            favourite authors.</p></note></p>
                <p part="N">Having completed his preliminary education, he repaired, in the year
                    1740, to the university of his native town, where he applied himself with great
                    ardour to the study of the mathematical, philosophical, and theological
                    sciences. Amongst the professors of Königsberg, several of whom were men of
                    considerable talents and attainments, he appears to have attached himself
                    particularly to Professor Martin Knutzen, well known, at that period, as the
                    author of several useful works, to whose instructions in mathematics and
                    philosophy Kant acknowledged himself to have been greatly indebted.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Knutzen died in
                            the year 1756, as extraordinary professor of philosophy at
                            Königsberg.</p></note> To the great diligence and success with which he
                    prosecuted his studies at this period, his early writings bear ample testimony.
                    The youth who, at the age of twenty-two, could boldly and successfully impugn
                    the doctrines of Leibnitz and Wolf, and skilfully wield the weapons of
                    dialectics against the authority of the most eminent metaphysicians of his day,
                    must have bestowed no common pains in the acquisition of scientific knowledge,
                    and in cultivating the powers of his understanding. From the earliest period of
                    his career, too, he was left almost entirely to the resources of his own talents
                    and prudence, and compelled, at every step, to struggle against the depressing
                    influence of poverty. When scarcely arrived at manhood, he had the misfortune to
                    lose both his parents, who had not the satisfaction of living to witness the
                    fruits of their son’s talents and industry. They, indeed, had never been able to
                    afford him much pecuniary assistance; but he was fortunate in meeting with some
                    relations of his family, who were in more affluent circumstances, and by whose
                    liberality, combined with his own exertions and economy, he was enabled to
                    continue the prosecution of his studies.</p>
                <p part="N">After a residence of about three years at the university, he acted in
                    the capacity of private tutor in several families, and lived about nine years
                    with the Count de Hüllesen at Arnsdorf. During this period he embraced the
                    opportunities which his retirement afforded him, of collecting a vast store of
                    general knowledge in almost every department of science and literature, and of
                    sketching the outlines of several of those philosophical treatises, which were
                    soon afterwards published in rapid succession.</p>
                <p part="N">It is rather unfortunate that no record seems to have been preserved of
                    the course of his studies during this most interesting period of his life; nor
                    has he himself, so far as we know, left any memorials which might enable us to
                    trace the gradual progress of his mind in the acquisition of knowledge. It is
                    certain, however, that he both read and thought much. According to his own
                    confession, he was not particularly well qualified to discharge the duties of a
                    tutor; being always too deeply engaged in acquiring and digesting knowledge in
                    his own mind, to be capable of communicating the rudiments of it to others. His
                    mind seems to have originally entertained a strong bias towards mathematical and
                    physical researches; and <pb break="no" facs="nls:192946590?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0712-6590-0676"/>he exhibited some specimens of knowledge,
                    acuteness, and originality of investigation, in the latter branch of science,
                    from which much eminence might have resulted had his views been exclusively
                    confined to that department.</p>
                <p part="N">It was probably during the period of his retirement at Arnsdorf that he
                    was led to engage in a laborious investigation of the various metaphysical
                    theories or ancient and modern times. With this view, he made himself master of
                    the living languages, especially the French and English, the latter of which he
                    acquired without the aid of a master, in order to enable him to examine into the
                    merits of the British philosophers, particularly Lockc, Berkeley, and Hume. To
                    the sceptical conclusions of the last-mentioned writer, according to Kant’s own
                    confession, the world is indebted for the <hi rend="italic">Critical
                        Theory.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">Having attained his thirtieth year, and already distinguished himself as
                    the author of several tracts, exhibiting great originality of thought, Kant
                    resolved to devote himself to the profession of public teacher. With this view,
                    he returned to the university of Königsberg, and took his degree of master of
                    arts, according to the usual forms, in the year 1755. It was upon this occasion
                    that he produced, in the form of an inaugural dissertation, his tract entitled
                        <hi rend="italic">Principiorum primorum Cognitionis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Metaphysicoe nova dilucidatio</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> the first of his
                    works, it is believed, which contained any hints respecting his peculiar views
                    of metaphysical science. In the same year he published his celebrated treatise
                    on the <hi rend="italic">Universal Natural History and Theory of the
                        Heavens</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">or an Essay on the
                        Constitution and Mechanical Structure of the ιvhole Globe, according to the
                        Newtonian System.</hi> In this treatise, by follow-ingout the principles of
                    Newton, he was led to anticipate, in theory, some of the subsequent discoveries
                    of the great practical astronomer Herschel.</p>
                <p part="N">Soon after he had taken his degree, he began to avail himself of the
                    privilege attached to the character of a <hi rend="italic">Doctor</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">docens,</hi> by delivering lectures publicly on logic,
                    metaphysics, mathematics, and natural philosophy; to which, at a subsequent
                    period, he added the law of nature, moral philosophy, natural theology, and
                    physical geography. He had not long commenced the discharge of his duties as a
                    public teacher, when the concourse of students, whom the reputation of his
                    profound and extensive learning attracted, was so great, that his <hi
                        rend="italic">auditorium,</hi> or lecture-room, although large and
                    commodious, could scarcely contain the numbers who eagerly flocked to hear him.
                    His affable manners and social talents, at the same time, rendered him a most
                    acceptable guest at the tables of the most respectable inhabitants of
                    Königsberg, with several of whom he lived on habits of intimate friendship.</p>
                <p part="N">But notwithstanding his acknowledged talents as a philosopher, and his
                    popularity as a lecturer on scientific subjects, it was long before Kant
                    obtained any preferment. With a mind constantly and intensely engaged in the
                    pursuit of knowledge, he appears to have possessed no ambition beyond that of
                    being useful in the sphere he had chosen for the exercise of his abilities; and
                    he had too much simplicity of character to resort to any of those arts by which
                    other men, more emulous of distinction, frequently endeavour to advance their
                    worldly interests. Upon the death of Knutzen, in the month of April 1756, he
                    solicited the vacant extraordinary professorship of philosophy, but without
                    success. The ordinary professor of logic and metaphysics having died in 1758, Dr
                    Schultz, who, as we have already observed, discovered at an early period the
                    talents of Kant, and continued to patronise him so long as he lived, exerted all
                    his influence to obtain that situation for <hi rend="italic">his protege'.</hi>
                    But Kant was again disappointed. Not discouraged, however, by the repeated
                    failure of his attempts to attain independence, he continued to deliver his
                    lectures, and to meditate his writings. In the month of February 1766 he
                    accepted the unsolicited situation of second keeper of the royal library, to
                    which a small salary was attached; and at the same time he undertook the
                    management of a private cabinet of curiosities. But these offices he resigned in
                    1772, on account of the interruptions to which he was exposed in showing the
                    books and rarities to strangers.</p>
                <p part="N">In the year 1770, Kant at length attained the highest object of his
                    ambition, on his advancement to the ordinary professorship of logic and
                    metaphysics in the university of Königsberg; a situation which, while it placed
                    him far above the fear of want, afforded him, at the same time, the best
                    opportunity of employing his talents in a manner satisfactory to himself and
                    advantageous to his country. Upon this occasion, he produced his celebrated
                    inaugural dissertation, <hi rend="italic">De Mundi</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Sensibilis atque</hi><hi rend="italic">Intelligïbilis Forma</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">et Principiis,</hi> in which he propounded some of the
                    fundamental principles of that metaphysical theory to which he was afterwards
                    indebted for his great reputation.</p>
                <p part="N">From this period, the life of Kant affords no very remarkable incidents
                    for the pen of the biographer. His time appears to have been chiefly occupied in
                    the faithful and zealous discharge of the duties of his office; in the
                    composition of those philosophical works, by w hich he hoped to accomplish an
                    important and beneficial reform in metaphysical science; and in cultivating the
                    society of a select number of friends. At this time, too, he maintained a
                    philosophical correspondence with several of the first literary characters of
                    the age, and particularly with the celebrated Lambert, then president of the
                    Royal Academy of Sciences at Berlin, whose views of philosophy were, in some
                    respects, coincident with his own. His letters to Lambert, indeed, are
                    peculiarly interesting, as they contain frequent allusions to the gradual
                    development of his metaphysical ideas.</p>
                <p part="N">In the year 1780, he became a member of the <hi rend="italic">Senatus
                        Academicus</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and in 1787 he w as admitted a
                    member of the Royal Academy of Sciences at Berlin. Never, perhaps, did there
                    exist a mind so ardently and so entirely devoted to the cultivation of science,
                    and so utterly divested of all interested motives in the pursuit of know ledge.
                    Having once attained independence, his ambition, as to worldly objects, seems to
                    have aspired no higher. Although he received, at different times, various
                    invitations, with most advantageous proposals, to induce him to transfer his
                    talents and his reputation to other universities, he could never be prevailed
                    upon to leave his native town; being perfectly satisfied with the advantages he
                    already enjoyed, and with the sphere of usefulness which had been assigned him.
                    For many years previous to his death, he was the senior professor of Königsberg;
                    and he enjoyed that high degree of respect and veneration which was due alike to
                    his advanced age, his eminent talents, and conspicuous virtues. He died, by a
                    gradual decay of nature, on the 12th of February 1804, in the eightieth year of
                    his age. His funeral was attended by, the most respectable inhabitants of
                    Königsberg, and by a numerous train of his friends and disciples; and, to
                    express the public regret for the loss of so distinguished a character, the
                    whole city put on mourning. On his coffin there was placed a sepulchral urn,
                    with the inscription, <hi rend="italic">Cineres mortales immortalis</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Kantii.</hi> A beautiful commemorative medal was also executed
                    upon this occasion, by Μ. Abramson of Berlin. On one side is a striking likeness
                    of the philosopher, with the inscription, <hi rend="italic">Immanuel Kant,
                        nat.</hi> 1724. On the reverse, the artist has attempted to express the
                    services of Kant in assigning limits to the province of speculative philosophy,
                    by representing a Minerva seated, and holding an owl in her right hand, which
                    she prevents from flying, with the inscription, <hi rend="italic">Altins</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">volantem arcuit.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">In his person, Kant w as rather below the middle stature, of a slender
                    and delicate form, and. with a very narrow and <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:192946603?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0712-6603-0677"/>flat chest.
                    His bodily frame, indeed, did not seem to pro. mise longevity; nor would he, in
                    all probability, have attained so great an age, had not his constitution been
                    preserved by his regular and temperate mode of living. In his external
                    appearance, strangers found nothing prepossessing, or indicative of any uncommon
                    talents; on the contrary, his features are represented by a gentleman who
                    visited him at Königsberg, as <hi rend="superscript"> ii</hi> a reproach to
                    physiognomy.” Others, however, describe his countenance as full of dignity, and
                    expressive of benevolence. His natural disposition was cheerful and social, and
                    his manners were polite and affable. He exhibited none of that awkwardness or
                    reserve which is frequently generated or increased by habits of recluse
                    meditation, and which is often thought to be characteristic of the scholar and
                    man of science. He loved company, and was both inquisitive himself, and fond of
                    communicating his own knowledge and opinions upon all subjects. There was
                    nothing, however trifling it might appear at first sight, which did not suggest
                    to his mind some interesting reflections; and he could talk as fluently with a
                    lady on the minutiae of female dress, the mjsteries of the kitchen, or the
                    common occurrences of the day, as he could with a philosopher on the most
                    abstruse points of science. He was very regular in his habits. He rose early,
                    and his mornings were generally devoted to study and professional duties, his
                    evenings to society. As he never entered into the married state, he was not
                    encumbered with the cares of a family. He used to say, that when he would have
                    married, he had not fortune sufficient to maintain a wife; and when he possessed
                    the requisite fortune, he had no inclination to marry. It has been remarked that
                    he was fond of society; and during the earlier part of his life, when otherwise
                    disengaged, he used to dine at the ordinary of the principal tavern, by which
                    means he had an opportunity of acquiring an extensive knowledge of human
                    character, and, at the same time, of gratifying his inquisitive disposition, by
                    eliciting from travellers of different countries many curious and valuable
                    observations on the manners, habits, and literature of various nations. He
                    possessed an intimate knowledge of geography, and even of minute topography,
                    probably in a great measure derived from this last-mentioned source, as w ell as
                    from his private reading of books of travels, to which he was always extremely
                    partial; and he frequently entered into local details with a degree of
                    correctness which could not fail to astonish those who learned that he had never
                    moved fifty miles from his native town. At a later period of his life, when more
                    easy in his circumstances, he generally invited a few of his friends to dinner,
                    with whom he relaxed from his graver studies, frequently enlivening his
                    discourse with sallies of wit and humour, of which he possessed no small share,
                    and occasional irony and satire, of that good-natured species which inflicts no
                    wound on the object against whom it is directed.</p>
                <p part="N">Kant’s intellectual faculties were of a high order. He had a wonderful
                    power of reflection, which enabled him to unfold the most abstruse principles,
                    and to pursue, in his own mind, a long train of conclusions. He possessed great
                    quickness of observation, and clearness of conception; insomuch that, in
                    conversation, he could describe any object which he had seen, or of which he had
                    read, with admirable precision and accuracy. His memory was exceedingly
                    retentive. He kept no library, but made a contract with a bookseller to send him
                    all new publications, which he perused, and afterwards returned; and the
                    knowledge thus acquired he had always at his command. The most remarkable
                    feature in the moral character of Kant was an utter abhorrence of every species
                    of falsehood, however in nocent, and a love of perfect honesty and sincerity in
                    word and action, flowing no less from his natural disposition, than from those
                    high principles which he had early imbibed, of the value of truth, and the
                    dignity of man. In this respect he was ever consistent with himself; and the
                    whole tenor of his long life may be regarded as a practical commentary on his
                    writings, and an exemplification of his moral maxims.</p>
                <p part="N">The peculiar doctrines of the critical or transcendental philosophy were
                    not the offspring of impressions accidentally received, and hastily adopted, but
                    the fruit of long, patient, and systematic investigation. Kant, indeed, was well
                    advanced in years before he attempted that reform in metaphysical science which
                    he seems to have long meditated. In several of his earlier productions, and in
                    his letters to Lambert, he evidently appears to have been dissatisfied with the
                    prevailing theories; and his inaugural dissertations, as already mentioned,
                    exhibited some of those peculiar views, which were afterwards more fully
                    developed in his great work, the <hi rend="italic">Critïk der reinen
                        Vernunft.</hi> This work was published in 1781. For several years it appears
                    to have attracted little or no attention; and the publisher, it is said, was on
                    the point of destroying the sheets as waste paper, when a sudden demand rapidly
                    carried off several impressions. From that period, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Transcendental Theory</hi> began to excite an extraordinary sensation, and
                    to be regarded as a new and wonderful discovery in metaphysical science; the
                    philosophers of Germany were divided into professed partisans and determined
                    antagonists of the doctrines of Kant; and a multitude of publications issued
                    yearly from the press, for the purpose of confirming or refuting the new
                    principles.</p>
                <p part="N">It was not long, however, before the <hi rend="italic">Critical
                        Philosophy</hi> bore down all opposition, and obtained a complete ascendency
                    over the theories inculcated by its adversaries. It was publicly taught in the
                    schools, to the almost total exclusion of the doctrines of Aristotle, Descartes,
                    Locke, Leibnitz, and Wolf; it gave a fresh impulse to the spirit of metaphysical
                    inquiry; and men of the first note in the scientific world felt a conscious
                    pride in being able to comprehend, to explain, to illustrate, to apply, or to
                    extend its principles. It not only effected an entire revolution in German
                    metaphysics, but exerted a powerful influence on works of taste, and the lighter
                    literature of the country. It is impossible, indeed, to comprehend, or to
                    relish, many passages in the works of the more recent poets, novelists, and
                    fugitive writers of Germany, without some previous acquaintance with the
                    doctrines of Kant.</p>
                <p part="N">Owing to what has been already said upon the subject in another part of
                    this work,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">See
                                <hi rend="italic">Dissertation First,</hi> Part Second, Section
                            Seventh.</p></note> we shall avoid entering into any discussion
                    respecting the merits of the <hi rend="italic">Critical Philosophy</hi> in the
                    present article; but we shall present our readers with a very concise abstract
                    of its objects and results.,.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Hume proved very satisfactorily, that our ideas of <hi rend="italic"
                        >cause and effect</hi> are not derived from experience ;^but he rashly
                    concluded, as Kant observes, “that they^are the spurious offspring of the
                    imagination impregnated by custom.” Kant discovered that Hume had been led to
                    this hasty inference in consequence of having taken too limited a view of the
                    great problem which he had thus partially attempted to solve. He perceived that
                    the idea of <hi rend="italic">cause and effect</hi> is by no means the only one
                    which the mind makes use of with the consciousness of its necessity, yet without
                    being derived from experience; but that the science of metaphysics is altogether
                    founded on ideas of a similar nature. He endeavoured, therefore, to ascertain
                    the precise number of these abstract or transcendental ideas; and having
                    succeeded in this to his own satisfaction, he <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:192946616?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0712-6616-0678"/>found
                    himself in possession of the whole of those connecting acts of the mind, which
                    constitute the very elements of the understanding itself, which are
                    indispensable to its exercise, and without which the whole of our experience
                    would exhibit nothing but a number of insulated facts, without order or
                    consistency.</p>
                <p part="N">The three original faculties, through the medium of which we acquire
                    knowledge, are, <hi rend="italic">sense, understanding,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">reason. Sense</hi> is a passive or receptive faculty. In the
                    objects presented to our senses, we distinguish <hi rend="italic">matter</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">form.</hi> The forms or conditions of sense are <hi
                        rend="italic">space</hi> and <hi rend="italic">time</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> the former of the external, the latter of the internal sense. All
                    our knowledge is limited by space and time; for we can perceive nothing that
                    does not exist under these conditions.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Understanding</hi> is an active or spontaneous
                    faculty, and consists in the power of forming conceptions. In every conception
                    of the understanding, also, we distinguish the <hi rend="italic">matter</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">form</hi>. The matter is the sensible intuition; the form
                    is the unity, or connection, established by means of the synthetic powers of the
                    understanding, or the categories. Kant was at great pains in endeavouring to
                    ascertain the number of these synthetic powers or categories; and he found them
                    to be all comprehended under the four classes of <hi rend="italic">quantity,
                        quality, relation,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">modality.</hi> The categories
                    themselves are twelve in number. Under the first head are comprised <hi
                        rend="italic">unity, multitude, totality</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> under
                    the second, <hi rend="italic">reality, negation, limitation</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> under the third, <hi rend="italic">substance</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">accident, cause</hi> and <hi rend="italic">effect,
                        action</hi> and <hi rend="italic">re-action</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    under the fourth, <hi rend="italic">possibility, existence, necessity.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">This synthetic power of the understanding is called, in the critical
                    philosophy, its <hi rend="italic">original</hi> use. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >logical</hi> use, both of understanding and reason, is to be found in the
                    faculty of <hi rend="italic">judgment.</hi> Logic, however, has only to do with
                    the form of our conceptions, and not with their matter; which last inquiry
                    belongs to transcendental philosophy, or metaphysics.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Reason</hi> is the third or highest degree of mental
                    spontaneity, and consists in the power of forming ideas. As it is the province
                    of the understanding to form the intuitions of sense into conceptions, so it is
                    the business of reason to form conceptions into ideas. The ideas of reason are
                    absolute and unconditional, and totally independent of space or time;
                    consequently, we can neither obtain nor extend our knowledge by means of reason
                    alone. For these ideas are nothing more than certain representations of the
                    unconditional, that is, of the highest unity and totality, which spring from the
                    essential constitution of our reason, which serve to render the field of
                    experience a comprehensible whole, and which, therefore, arc merely conditions
                    of the exercise of our reason, and not real external objects of which it is
                    possible to acquire any knowledge by intuition.</p>
                <p part="N">The results of the critical theory may be stated, we conceive, in a very
                    few words. The first principles, or conditions, of our speculative knowledge,
                    are mere <hi rend="italic">subjective</hi> forms, or forms derived from the
                    constitution of the thinking being: First, the forms of sense, or pure
                    intuitions (space and time); and, secondly, the forms or notions of the
                    understanding (the categories). These intellectual forms or notions, however,
                    only acquire reality by their application to our perceptions, with reference to
                    possible experience, and therefore we can have no speculative knowledge of
                    things beyond the sphere of experience.</p>
                <p part="N">Besides the critical investigation of pure reason in its speculative
                    exercise, Kant instituted a similar inquiry into the nature and laws of our <hi
                        rend="italic">practical reason,</hi> and of the faculty <hi rend="italic">ç£
                        judgment</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and, in the spirit of his own theory,
                    he published the <hi rend="italic">Metaphysical Elements of Natural
                        Philosophy,</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Law,</hi> and of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ethics.</hi> His <hi rend="italic">Logic, Physical Geography,</hi> and some
                    other works, were published by his friends, from his papers, and the marginal
                    notes to his textbooks. Towards the latter end of his life, he meditated a work,
                    which was intended to be the key-stone of his whole system, and which was to
                    have been entitled <hi rend="italic">The Transition from Metaphysics to
                        Physics</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> in which he proposed tq demonstrate the
                    general application of the principles of the transcendental theory. The decline
                    of his faculties, however, prevented the execution of this projected work.</p>
                <p part="N">We shall close this article with a list of Kant’s publications.</p>
                <p part="N">Gedanken von der wahren Schätzung der lebendigen Kräfte, &amp;c.
                    (Thoughts on the true estimation of the animal powers, with strictures on the
                    proofs advanced by Leibnitz and others.) Königsberg, 1746.</p>
                <p part="N">Allgemeine Naturgeschichte und Theorie des Himmels, &amp;c. (Universal
                    Natural History and Theory of the Heavens, &amp;c.) Ibid. 1755.</p>
                <p part="N">Principiorum primorum Cognitionis Metaphysicae nova dilucidatio. A
                    Dissertation on taking his master’s degree, in 1755.</p>
                <p part="N">Betrachtungen über den Optimism. (Refleetions on Optimism.) Königsberg,
                    1759.</p>
                <p part="N">Von der falschen Spitzfindigkeit der vier syllogistischen Figuren. (On
                    the sophistical subtilty of the four syllogistic figures.) 1763.</p>
                <p part="N">Einzig möglicher Beweisgrund zu einer Demonstration des Daseyns Gottes.
                    (The only possible evidence for demonstrating the existence of the Deity.)
                    Königsberg, 1763.</p>
                <p part="N">Beobachtungen über das Gefühl des Schönen und Erhabenen. (Observations
                    on the feeling of the Beautiful and Sublime.) 1764. This tract is remarkable on
                    account of the spirit of humour and pleasantry which pervades it.</p>
                <p part="N">Träume eines Geistersehers, erläutert durch Träume der Metaphysik.
                    (Dreams of a Ghost-seer, illustrated by the dreams of Metaphysics.) Riga, 1766.
                    This publication was occasioned by the visions of the famous Emanuel
                    Swedenborg.</p>
                <p part="N">De Mundi Sensibilis atque Intelligibilis Forma et Principiis.
                    Königsberg, 1770. An inaugural dissertation on obtaining his professorship.</p>
                <p part="N">These, along with a number of other tracts, in which the author
                    displayed an intimate acquaintance with the principles of the sciences,
                    remarkable quickness of observation, great depth of thought and acuteness of
                    reasoning, will be found incorporated in the following collections.</p>
                <p part="N">Kant’s Sämmtliche kleine Schriften. (Kant’s Smaller Tracts collected.) 3
                    vols. 8vo. Königsberg and Leipsic, 1797.</p>
                <p part="N">Kant’s Vermischte Schriften, mit Anmerkungen, von Tieftrunk. (Kant’s
                    Miscellaneous Writings, with Notes, published by Tieftrunk.) 3 vols. 8vo. Halle,
                    1799. A fourth volume was added, Königsberg, 1807.</p>
                <p part="N">The early and anonymous essays of Kant were collected and published by
                    F. T. Rink, Königsberg, 1800. In the following works, his peculiar views of
                    metaphysical science, as constituting what has been called the Critical
                    Philosophy, are more fully and systematically developed.</p>
                <p part="N">Critik der Reinen Vernunft. (Critical inquiry into the Nature of Pure
                    Reason.) Riga, 1781; 3d ed. 1791, 8vo.</p>
                <p part="N">Prolegomena zu einer jeden künftigen Metaphysik, &amp;c. (Prolegomena to
                    every Future System of Metaphysics, &amp;c.) 1783. In the Critik der reinen
                    Vernunft, the author had proceeded synthetically; in this other work he adopts
                    the analytical method, with the view of rendering his theory more intelligible
                    to students.</p>
                <p part="N">Metaphysische Anfangsgründe der Naturwissenschaft. (Metaphysical
                    Elements of Natural Philosophy,) 1786. This is a systematic text-book on pure
                    physics, in which the author treats of those principles in natural philosophy of
                    whose truth we are conscious <hi rend="italic">a priori, i. e.</hi>
                    independently of experience. The subject is treated under the four <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:192946629?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0712-6629-0679"
                    />heads of Phoronoîny, Dynamics, Mechanics, and Phenomenology.</p>
                <p part="N">Grundlegung zur Metaphysik der Sitten. (Fundamental Principles of the
                    Metaphysics of Morals.) 1785.</p>
                <p part="N">Critik der Practischen Vernunft. (A Critical Inquiry into the Nature and
                    Laws of Practical Reason.) 1788.</p>
                <p part="N">Critik der Urtheilskraft. (A Critical Inquiry into the Faculty of
                    Judgment.) 1790. In this work the author develoρes his views of the principles
                    of taste.</p>
                <p part="N">Metaphysische Anfangsgründe der Rechtslehre. (Metaphysical Elements of
                    Legal Science.) 1797.</p>
                <p part="N">Metaphysische Anfangsgründe der Tugendlehre. (Metaphysical Elements of
                    Ethics.) 1797.</p>
                <p part="N">Anthropologie, in Pragmatischer Hinsicht. (A Pragmatical Treatise on
                    Anthropology.) 1798.</p>
                <p part="N">The following works were published from his papers by his friends:</p>
                <p part="N">Logik (Logic), published by G. B. läsche, 1801.</p>
                <p part="N">Physische Geographie (Physical Geography), of which, we believe, there
                    have been several editions by different editors.</p>
                <p part="N">Pädagogik (Paedagogics, or the Art of communicating Instruction.)
                    Published by F. T. Rink, 1803. (κ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
