<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0364-0343-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PASSOVER and (9th edition, volume 18, page 343)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hm8r">Bread</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n36h">Pentateuch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s51p">Harvesters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b8s">Harvesting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tk26">Sabbath</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10v74">Easter</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1089603">Rajab</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102941">Sabbath</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1060090">Pharaohs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:991032">Lambs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838229">Breading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198482">Bread</term>
                    <term ref="fast:951762">Harvesting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n364/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PASSOVER <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi></label> FEAST OF
                    UNLEAVENED BREAD. It is explained in the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Pentateuch</hi> (p. 511) that the ancient Israelites were accustomed to open
                    the harvest season by a religious feast. No one tasted the new grain, not even
                    parched or fresh ears of corn, till the first sheaf had been presented to
                    Jehovah, and then all hastened to enjoy the new blessings of divine goodness by
                    eating unleavened cakes, without waiting for the tedious process of fermenting
                    the dough. This natural usage became fixed in custom, and at a comparatively
                    early date a new significance was added to it by a reference to the exodus from
                    Egypt, when, as tradition ran, the people in their hasty departure had no time
                    to leaven the dough already in their troughs. The two elements of a thankful
                    recognition of God’s goodness in the harvest, which every one was eager to taste
                    the moment that Jehovah had received His tribute at the sanctuary, and of
                    grateful remembrance of the first proof of His kingship over Israel, went very
                    fittingly together. A similar combination is found in the thanksgiving of Deut
                    xxvi. 5 <hi rend="italic">sq,</hi> in the law, Deut, xxiv. 19-22, and elsewhere;
                    the yearly blessings of the harvest were the proof of the continued goodness of
                    Him who brought Israel forth from Egypt to set him in a fruitful and pleasant
                    land</p>
                <p>The feast of unleavened bread (Hebrew ∏W, <hi rend="italic">maççõth),</hi> with
                    the presentation of the harvest sheaf, which is its leading feature, presupposes
                    agriculture and a fixed residence in Canaan. In the pastoral life the same
                    religious feelings find their natural expression in thank-offerings for the
                    increase of the flocks and herds, consisting of sacrifices “of the firstlings of
                    the flock and the failings thereof,” such as Gen. iv. 4 makes to date back from
                    the very beginnings of human history. The firstlings answer to the first fruits;
                    the increase of cattle falls mainly in the spring; and spring is also the time
                    of the best pasture in a climate where the harvest-tide lies between Easter and
                    Whitsunday, the time therefore when a fat sacrifice can be selected and when
                    vows would generally be fulfilled; especially as the latter, among the pastoral
                    Hebrews as among the Arabs, would frequently have reference to the
                    multiplication of the flock. Abel’s sacrifice of firstlings and fatlings
                    corresponds in fact exactly to the old Arabic <hi rend="italic">fara</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic superscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic">atιra,</hi> the former of
                    which was the firstborn of the herd and the latter a sacrifice offered in the
                    spring month Rajab in fulfilment of a vow conditional on the good increase of
                    the herd.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Zúzení on
                    Hárith’s <hi rend="italic">Μo'αU.,</hi> 1. 69; Bokhari,vi. 207 (Bulak vocalized
                    edition).</p></note> The accumulation of the sacrifices of firstlings and
                    fatlings at one season of the year would readily give rise to a spring feast,
                    and it appears from the Jehovist that something of this kind existed before the
                    exodus (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Pentateuch),</hi> and gave occasion to the
                    request of Moses for leave to lead the people out into the wilderness to
                    sacrifice to Jehovah. Pharaoh’s refusal was appropriately punished by the
                    destruction of the firstborn of man and the firstlings of beasts in Egypt. The
                    recollection of this fact reacted on the old Hebrew usage, and supplied a new
                    reason for the sacrifice of all male firstlings after the Israelites were
                    settled in Canaan (Exod. xiii. 11 <hi rend="italic">sqf).</hi> Up to the time of
                    Deuteronomy this sacrifice was not tied to any set feast (contrast Exod. xxii.
                    30 with Deut. χv. 20); the old sacrificial spring feast, like the Arabic feast
                    of Rajab, was not wholly dependent on the firstlings, but might also be derived
                    from vows. But when Israel was thoroughly united under the kings the tendency
                    plainly lay towards a concentration of acts of cultus in public feasts at the
                    great sanctuaries; and the final result of this tendency, which appears to some
                    degree in earlier laws, but reached its goal only through the Deuteronomic
                    centralization of all sacrifices at the one sanctuary, was that the spring
                    pastoral feast coalesced with the agricultural <hi rend="italic">Mαζc</hi><hi
                    rend="italic subscript"> i</hi><hi rend="italic">oth,</hi> and that its
                    sacrifices were swollen by the prohibition of continued private sacrifices of
                    the male firstlings. This is the form of the Deuteronomic passover (Deut. xvi. 1
                    <hi rend="italic">sqf).</hi> The passover is a sacrifice drawn from the flock or
                    the herd, presented at the sanctuary and eaten with unleavened bread. It is
                    slain on the evening of the first day of the feast, so that the sacrificial
                    feast is nocturnal; and the pilgrims may return to their homes next morning, but
                    the abstinence from leaven lasts seven days, and the seventh day, observed as a
                    day of rest, is the <hi rend="italic">*asereth</hi> or closing day of the feast.
                    The passover is now viewed specially as a commemoration of the Exodus; and by
                    and by, in Exod. xii. 27, its name (Heb. ∏P.P, Gr. ττdσχα, Lat. <hi
                    rend="italic">pascha)</hi> is explained from Jehovah “passing over” the
                    Israelites when he smote Egypt. That this was the original meaning is by no
                    means clear; there is no certain occurrence of the name before Deuteronomy (in
                    Exod. xxxiv. 25 it looks like a gloss), and the corresponding verb denotes some
                    kind of religious performance, apparently a dance, in 1 Kings xviii. 26. A
                    nocturnal ceremony at the consecration of a feast is already alluded to in Isa.
                    xxx. 29, who also perhaps alludes to the received derivation of ∏D0 in ch. xxxi.
                    5. But the Deuteronomic passover was a new thing in the days of Josiah (2 Kings
                    xxiii. 21 <hi rend="italic">sqf).</hi> It underwent a farther modification in
                    the exile, when sacrifices in the proper sense of the word were impossible, but
                    the commemorative side of the feast was perpetuated in the household meal of the
                    paschal lamb, eaten with unleavened bread and bitter herbs (Exod. xii.—from the
                    Priestly Code). The paschal lamb is quite different from the paschal <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n365/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0365-0344"/> sacrifices of Deuteronomy and from the ancient
                    firstlings. In Deuteronomy, for example, the sacrifices may be either from the
                    flock or from the herd, and are boiled, not roasted (A.V. in Deut, xvi. 7
                    mistranslates); the paschal lamb is necessarily roasted, and the only traces of
                    sacrificial character that remain to it are the sprinkling of the blood on the
                    lintel and door-posts,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>The sprinkling of blood on a tent in order to put it under divine protection
                    appears also among the Arabs; Wákidí, ed. Kremer, p. 28.</p></note> and the
                    burning of what is not eaten of it. After the restoration the passover seems to
                    have retained its domestic character, for, though the feast at the sanctuary was
                    renewed, its public features now con sisted of a series of holocausts and
                    sin-offerings continued for seven days (Num. xxix. 16 <hi rend="italic">sqf</hi>
                    The feast is now exactly dated.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>In everything that has to do with sacrifice a day means the
                    daytime with the following night; in other words, the feast days do not begin in
                    the evening. Compare Reland, <hi rend="italic">Ant.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Heb.,</hi> iv. § 15.</p></note> The paschal lamb is chosen on the tenth day of
                    the first month (Abib or Nisan) and slain on the even ing of the fourteenth.
                    Next day—that is, the fifteenth— is now the first day of the feast proper (a
                    change from the Deuteronomic ordinance naturally flowing from the fact that the
                    properly paschal ceremony is now not festal but domestic), so that the seven
                    days end with the twenty first and close with a “holy assembly” at Jerusalem.
                    The old ceremony of presenting the first sheaf had been fixed, in Lev. xxiii.
                    11, for the “morrow after the Sabbath.” This naturally means that the solemn
                    opening of harvest was to take place on a Sunday. But when the feast was fixed
                    to set days of the month the “Sabbath” was taken to mean the first day of the
                    feast or of unleavened bread (Nisan 15), and the sheaf was presented on the
                    sixteenth.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This exegesis
                    and practice are as old as the LXX. version of Leviticus. The passage of
                    Leviticus has given rise to much controversy; see the commentaries and
                    Lightfoot’s <hi rend="italic">llorae</hi> on Luke vi. 1, Acts ii. 1.</p></note>
                    As the feast was now again a great pilgrimage occasion, there was a natural
                    tendency to restore to the paschal lamb a more strictly sacrificial character.
                    This tendency does not appear as yet in the Pentateuch, where the latest
                    provisions are those put in historical form in Exod. xii.; but in 2 Chron.
                    xxxv., which must be taken as describing the practice of the author’s own time,
                    the paschal lamb is slain before the temple, the blood is sprinkled and the fat
                    burned (î verse 14) on the altar; and at the same time we find the Deuteronomic
                    paschal sacrifices existing side by side with the paschal lamb of the later law
                    as subsidiary sacrifices. The later Jewish usage followed this practice; the
                    Deuteronomic sacrifices in their new subsidiary form constituted the so-called
                    <hi rend="italic">hagiga.</hi> The pre-eminent importance which the passover
                    (with the feast of unleavened bread) acquired after the exile, from the fact
                    that its rites, like those of the Sabbath and of circumcision, could be in great
                    part adapted to the circumstances of the dispersion, was still further increased
                    by the fall of the second temple, and the ritual of the Mishna (Pesãhïm) was
                    supplemented by the later paschal Haggãda. The lamb, however, not being slain at
                    the temple, is not in later praxis regarded as strictly the paschal lamb of the
                    law. Some of the post-Biblical features are of interest in connexion with the
                    New Testament, and especially with the last supper. The company for a single
                    lamb varied from ten to twenty; the bitter herbs and unleavened cakes were
                    dipped in a kind of sweet sauce called haróseth; and the meal was accompanied by
                    the circulation of four cups of wine and by songs of praise, particularly the
                    Hallel (Ps. cxiii.-cxviii.).</p>
                <p>The history of the passover is one of the most complicated subjects in
                    Hebrew-archaeology, and has been a great battlefield of Pentateuch criticism.
                    The present article should therefore be read with the article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Pentateuch.</hi> The older books on Hebrew archaeology are of
                    little use, except for the later Jewish practice; on this full details will be
                    found in Bartolocci’s <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Rabbi</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >∣</hi><hi rend="italic">ιicd,</hi> or in Bodenschatz’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kirchliche Verfassung der Juden.</hi> The Biblical data can only be understood
                    in connexion with a critical view of the Pentateuch, and have been discussed in
                    this connexion by Kueuen <hi rend="italic">(Godsdienst),</hi> Wellhausen <hi
                    rend="italic">(Prolegomena),</hi> and others. The present position of those who
                    oppose the Gratian hypothesis may be gathered from Delitzsch’s art. ‘ ‘ Passah
                    ’’ in Kiehm’s <hi rend="italic">Handwörterbuch,</hi> and from Dillmann’s
                    commentary on Exodus and Leviticus. Hunfeld, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vera et primitiva Festorum</hi><hi rend="italic">. . .</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ratione,</hi> 1852-65, and Ewald’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Antiquities,</hi> may also be consulted. (W. R. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
