<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0875-0840-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHOTOMETRY, Celestial (9th edition, volume 18, page
                    840)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26q69g">Bonds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086357g">Stars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cj23">Sun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2df3t">Moon</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1131648">Stars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:835887">Bonds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960068">Hope</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205614">Argentina</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n875/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHOTOMETRY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Celestial</hi></label>. The
                    earliest records that have come down to us regarding the relative positions of
                    the stars in the heavens have always been accompanied with estimations of their
                    relative brightness. With this brightness was naturally associated the thought
                    of the relative magnitudes of the luminous bodies from whence the light was
                    assumed to proceed. Hence in the grand catalogue of stars published by Ptolemy
                    (e. 150 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.),</hi> but which had probably been formed
                    three hundred years before his day by Hipparchus, the 1200 stars readily visible
                    to the naked eye at Alexandria were divided into six classes according to their
                    lustre, though instead of that term he uses the word <hi rend="italic"
                    >pdyeθoς</hi> or “magnitude”; the brightest he designates as being of the first
                    magnitude, and so downwards till he comes to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >minimum</hi><hi rend="italic">visibile,</hi> to which he assigns the sixth.
                    These magnitudes he still further divides each into three. To those stars which,
                    though ranged in any particular order of brightness, nevertheless exceed the
                    average of that order in lustre he attaches the letter ∕χ, the initial letter in
                    <hi rend="italic">μHfwν</hi> (greater), and to those in the same order which
                    exhibit a lustre inferior to that of the average he affixes the letter ∈, the
                    initial letter of <hi rend="italic">iλajcrσωv.</hi> With this sort of
                    subdivision he passes through all the six orders of magnitude. He does not,
                    indeed, tell us the precise process by which these divisions were estimated, but
                    the principle involved is obvious. The eye was here made the natural photometer,
                    and it is certain that even in the instances where modern instrumental
                    appliances are called into requisition the ultimate appeal is made to perception
                    by the eye. Moreover, it is one of the many remarkable instances of the
                    acuteness and precision of the Greek mind that for upwards of 1500 years no real
                    improvement was made in these estimations of lustre by any of Ptolemy’s numerous
                    successors in this field of research. Flamsteed was the first astronomer who
                    extended the estimation of magnitude to stars visible only by the telescope, and
                    he improved Ptolemy’s notation by writing 4 ’ 3 instead of δ, <hi rend="italic"
                    >μ</hi> —indicating thereby an order of magnitude brighter than the average of a
                    fourth, but inferior to that of a third—and 3 ’ 4 for δ, ∈, and so on. Later
                    astronomers have sometimes adopted a more precise nomenclature by subdividing
                    the several orders decimally, but it does not appear that by any immediate and
                    unaided effort the eye can estimate subdivisions of lustre exceeding the thirds
                    adopted by the Greek philosopher.</p>
                <p>It was not till the year 1796 that any real advance was made in stellar
                    photometry. Sir W. Herschel, instead of assigning a particular magnitude to
                    stars, arranged them in small groups of three or four or five, indicating the
                    order in which they differed from each other in lustre at the time of
                    observation. This method was admirably adapted to the discovery of any
                    variations in brightness which might occur in the lapse of time among the
                    members of the group. Sir William observed in this way some 1400 stars,
                    published in catalogues scattered through the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                    Transactif/ns</hi> from 1796 to 1799; but he discontinued the work before its
                    conclusion. It might be urged that such a work touches on no human interests,
                    but it rightly seemed otherwise to the philosophic mind of the great astronomer.
                    He remarked that the sun is, after all, only one among the stars, and that what
                    befalls them in the way of varying light as time proceeds may also befall the
                    sun. He puts the question, “Who would not wish to know what degree of permanency
                    we ought to ascribe to the lustre of our sun? Not only the stability of our
                    climates, but the very existence of the whole animal and vegetable creation
                    itself, is involved in the question. Where can we hope to receive information
                    upon the subject but from astronomical observations ?”<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1796, p.
                    184.</p></note> These researches of the elder Herschel were in due time followed
                    by those of his son, Sir John, about the year 1836 at the Cape of Good Hope. He
                    both extended and improved the methods adopted by his father at Slough, and by a
                    method of estimated sequences of magnitude he hoped to arrange all the stars
                    visible to the naked eye at the Cape or in England in the order of their
                    relative lustre, and then to reduce his results into the equivalent magnitudes
                    adopted by the universal consent of astronomers. Sir John, however, like his
                    father, left this important labour incomplete. Not only is the work one of great
                    and continuous effort, but the effects of ever-varying meteorological conditions
                    greatly impede it. Moreover, there is an unsatisfactory indefiniteness attending
                    all estimations made by the unaided eye; numerical or quantitative comparisons
                    are out of the question, and hence we find Sir John, in the very midst of
                    establishing his “sequences,” adopting also an instrumental method which might
                    lead him to more definite results.</p>
                <p>In the year when Sir John Herschel concluded his photometric work at the Cape
                    (1838) Dr Argelander commenced, and in 1843 completed, his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Uranometria Nova,</hi> in which the magnitudes of all stars visible to the
                    unaided eye in central Europe are catalogued with a precision and completeness
                    previously unknown. It contains 3256 stars, and although it will probably be
                    superseded by instrumental photometry it must ever remain a monument of
                    intelligent patience. Argelander’s labours were confined to stars visible to the
                    naked eye; by the aid of his assistants, Dr Schönfeld and Dr Krüger, a catalogue
                    of magnitudes and celestial coordinates was ultimately published in their
                    well-known <hi rend="italic">Durchmusterung,</hi> extending to the enormous
                    number of 324,000 stars.</p>
                <p>Dr Gould also, in his <hi rend="italic">Uranometria Argentina,</hi> has done
                    similar work for stars visible only in the southern hemisphere, and with the aid
                    of his colleagues has attained to an exactness and precision in his estimations
                    of stellar lustre certainly not hitherto surpassed. There have been other worthy
                    labourers in the same field, each of whom has rendered efficient service, such
                    as Dr Heis and M. Houzeau; but it is chiefly to the labours of Argelander and
                    Gould that astronomers at present make their appeal.</p>
                <p>It is to Sir John Herschel that we are indebted for the first successful attempt
                    at stellar photometry by what may <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n876/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0876-0841"/> be termed “artificial” means. By the aid of
                    appliances of the simplest kind he deflected the light of the moon (by means of
                    the internal reflexion of a rectangular prism) through a small lens 0Ί2 inches
                    in diameter and of very short focus, 0 ’ 2253 inches, so as to form a sort of
                    artificial star in its focus. By the instrumentality of strings and a wooden
                    pole he could move this artificial star of comparison so as to be in the same
                    line of sight with any actual star whose light he proposed to measure. Other
                    strings enabled him to remove this microscopic lunar image to such a distance
                    from the eye that its light was adjudged to be sensibly the same as that of the
                    star compared. The distance of the short focused lens with the image contiguous
                    to it was measured by a graduated tape, and the inverse squares of these
                    distances afforded relative numerical measures of the brightness of the several
                    stars thus brought into ocular juxtaposition with the equalized light of the
                    tiny lunar image. In this way he proceeded with the observations of a
                    considerable number of stars, and these, by appropriate methods, were reduced so
                    as to afford the means of the comparison of their relative brightness when set
                    side by side with results obtained by means of his “sequences,” and with the
                    estimated magnitudes of preceding astronomers. Sir John, however, did not go on
                    to the formation of a complete “uranometria.” While he was thus busy at the Cape
                    of Good Hope, Steinheil at Munich had completed for Dr Seidel an instrument
                    nearly the same in principle but more manageable in form. He divided the small
                    object-glass of a telescope into two halves, one of which was movable in the
                    direction of its axis. The images of two stars whose light he desired to compare
                    were formed by the intervention of prismatic reflexion, nearly in the same line
                    of sight, and one of the lenses was then moved until the light of the two stars
                    near the respective foci of the semi-lenses seemed equal to the judgment of the
                    observer’s eye. The distance through which it was necessary to bring the movable
                    lens furnished the data for comparing the relative lustre of the two stars in
                    question. A large amount of work was thus achieved by Seidel, which for a
                    considerable time has been, with greater or less reason, regarded as worthy of
                    confidence in regard to precision <hi rend="italic">(Trans. Mun. Acad.,</hi>
                    vol. ii.). Dr Zöllner substituted the deflected and reduced image of a lamp for
                    one of SteinheiΓs stars, and the intensity of this light, or artificial star, he
                    could by means of double refraction reduce in any measurable proportion he
                    pleased according to the well-known relations of polarized light. In this way he
                    could equalize the light of the artificial lamp-star with that of the real star
                    with which he compared it; and the division of the lens was thus dispensed with,
                    but a new difficulty was introduced in the impossibility of maintaining the
                    constancy of the flame. Dr Zöllner also availed himself of the effects of double
                    refraction in altering at will the colour of his artificial star of comparison.
                    This ingenious form of photometer has enjoyed considerable reputation, but no
                    astronomer has yet persevered in producing a complete “uranometria” by its aid.
                    The most recent and probably the most successful device for a stellar photometer
                    on the <hi rend="italic">principle of equalizing lights</hi> is that invented by
                    Professor Pickering of Harvard College. He deflects the light of Polaris, or of
                    some other star such as λ Ursae Minoris, by means of prismatic reflexion, and he
                    contrives to form an image of it contiguous to the image of any other star
                    selected on the meridian. The equalization of the lights is then effected by the
                    intervention of a polarizing apparatus, such as that adopted by Zöllner. Thus
                    the artificial and in many respects objectionable lamp-star of Zöllner is
                    dispensed with. Professor Pickering, with singular inventive power, has devised
                    many other forms of stellar photometers on virtually the same principle; for a
                    detailed account of these labours the reader is referred to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Annals of the Harvard College Observatory</hi> (vol. xi.). Unlike
                    his eminent predecessors, the American astronomer is persevering in the
                    formation of a complete catalogue of starmagnitudes.</p>
                <p>It has been already stated that mere estimations of relative brightness by the
                    unaided eye are inadequate to the production of numerical quantitative results.
                    In the instrumental devices explained, whether by means of the alteration of
                    distances or by the known alteration of planes of polarization, no such defect
                    exists. By their means it is possible to obtain a fairly exact numerical
                    expression for the ratio of the intensities of the two lights measured. On
                    applying a photometric measurement it is found that the ratio of the intensities
                    of the lights in passing from one magnitude to the next, even in the
                    conventional magnitudes of Argelander and Gould, is not by any means constant,
                    and even hardly definite. At the suggestion of Mr Pogson it is now generally
                    accepted by astronomers that the adopted and conventional ratio of the intensity
                    of light in passing from one magnitude to another shall be 2'512, a convenient
                    number because its logarithm is '4, which is easily remembered, and still more
                    so because on the whole it agrees better than any other number with the varying
                    light-ratio existing among the hitherto received orders of magnitude obtained by
                    eye-estimation alone.</p>
                <p>There remains still another principle on which a stellar photometer may be
                    successfully formed, and which has been recently largely applied to the
                    determination of starmagnitudes at the university observatory, Oxford. It is
                    constructed on the principle that the absorption of light in passing through a
                    uniform medium depends, <hi rend="italic">caeteris paribus,</hi> upon the
                    thickness. On this principle a thin wedge is constructed of homogeneous and
                    nearly neutral-tinted glass, through which the images of stars formed in the
                    focus of a telescope are viewed. Simple means are contrived for measuring with
                    great exactness the several thicknesses at which the light of these telescopic
                    star-images is extinguished. In this way the light of any star can be readily
                    compared with that of Polaris (or any other selected star) at the moment of
                    observation, and thus a catalogue of star-magnitudes can be formed. This method
                    has been already applied by Professor Pritchard to all the brighter stars north
                    of the equator; the results are published in the forty-seventh volume of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs of the Royal Astronomical Society,</hi> and are to be
                    speedily followed by a complete catalogue, extending to all the stars in
                    Argelander’s <hi rend="italic">Uranometria Nova</hi> north of the equator, and
                    to a few others beyond. For the details of the processes adopted the reader must
                    here, as in all other cases, consult the original researches.</p>
                <p>Even in a rapid sketch of so extensive a subject some notice must be taken of the
                    application of photometry to the determination of the relative amount of light
                    received on the earth from the sun, the moon, and the planets. The methods by
                    which these ratios have been obtained are as simple as they are ingenious; and
                    for them we are mainly indebted to the labours of Bouguer and Bond. The former
                    philosopher compared the light received from the sun with that from the moon in
                    the following fashion in 1725. A hole one-twelfth of a Paris inch was made in
                    the shutter of a darkened room; close to it was placed a concave lens, and in
                    this way an image of the sun 9 inches in diameter was received on a screen.
                    Bouguer found that this light was equal to that of a candle viewed at 16 nches
                    from his eye. A similar experiment was repeated with the light of the full moon.
                    The image now formed was only two-thirds of an inch in diameter, and he found
                    that the light of this image was comparable with that of the same candle viewed
                    at a distance of 50 feet. From <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n877/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0877-0842"/> these data and a very simple calculation it
                    followed that the light of the sun was about 256,289 times that of the moon.
                    Other experiments followed, and the average of all the results was that the
                    light of the sun was about 300,000 times the average light of a full moon, both
                    being viewed in the heavens at the same altitudes. The details will be found in
                    Bouguer’s <hi rend="italic">Traite</hi><hi rend="italic">&lt;T</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Optique.</hi> Wollaston in 1829 tried a series of experiments in
                    which the ratio 801,072 was obtained; but the omission of certain necessary
                    precautions vitiates the result <hi rend="italic">{Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1829).
                    Bond <hi rend="italic">{Mem. Amer. Acad.,</hi> 1851, p. 295) adopted a different
                    process. He formed the image of the sun on a silvered globe of some 10 inches
                    diameter; the light of this image was reflected on to a small mercurial
                    thermometer bulb; and then this second image was compared with a Bengal light so
                    moved that the lights appeared to be equal. The same process was adopted with
                    the full moon instead of with the sun. The result was that the sun’s light was
                    470,980 times that of the moon. Seidel long before this date had compared the
                    light of the mean full moon with that of Jupiter in mean opposition; his result
                    is 6430. So also this light of Jupiter was found to be ’ 4864 times that of
                    Venus at her brightest; and Jupiter was found to give 8 ’ 2 times the light of α
                    Lyrae. If, then, these numbers could be accepted with confidence, we should have
                    the means of comparing the light received from the sun with that received from
                    any of the stars. Adopting these precarious numbers on the authorities of Bond
                    and Seidel we have the following results—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>Sun’s light = 470,980 that of the full moon.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>,, = 622,600,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>,, Venus at her brightest.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>„ = 302,835,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="subscript"> l</hi>, Jupiter at mean
                            opposition.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>„ =5,970,500,000</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>,, Sirius.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Lastly, Bouguer, by comparing the light of the full moon viewed at different
                    altitudes with an artificial light, found that the atmosphere absorbs '1877 of
                    the light incident on it at the zenith of any place. Professor Pritchard, from
                    photometric-measures taken at Cairo, found this number to be <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 157. At Oxford it was '209. Thus Bouguer’s
                    determination indicates an absorptive capacity in the atmosphere of Brittany
                    just midway between those of Oxford and Cairo. Seidel at Munich expresses
                    “surprise” at finding his own results so nearly accordant with Bouguer’s. These
                    numbers, therefore, may be regarded as close approximations to fact.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Since this article was put in
                    type, Professor Pickering at Harvard College has published his concluded
                    results. Professor Pritchard at Oxford has also completed his photometric
                    measures of some 2000 of the same stars. Taken as a whole, and as comprising the
                    first complete and systematic efforts in a new and difficult line of research,
                    the agreements of the two catalogues may fairly be regarded as very
                    satisfactory, not to say surprising.</p></note> (c. p.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
