<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0250-0233-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PARÁ, or Santa Maria (9th edition, volume 18, page
                    233)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c55w">Amazons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx4522p">Peruvian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vs35">Naturalists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:806706">Amazons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174597">White</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174816">Whites</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838162">Brazilians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n250/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PARÁ, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Santa Maria</hi></label><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">de Belem</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">do Grao Para,</hi> one of the
                    most flourishing cities of Brazil, capital of the province of Pará or Gräo Pará,
                    lies on a point of land with sandy porous soil at the junction of the Guamâ with
                    the Rio Pará or eastern arm of the Amazons, about 75 miles from the sea. The
                    main river is about 20 miles wide opposite the town, but is broken by numerous
                    islands. Pará is regularly built, well-paved, and well-lighted. The houses,
                    which seldom exceed two or three stories in height, are usually substantial
                    structures of stone; and a general brightness of aspect is produced by red-tiled
                    roofs and white, yellow, or even pink and blue coloured walls relieved by dense
                    tropical foliage. The Estrada das Mon-gubeiras, running about a mile from the
                    river to Largo da Polvora in the east end of the city, has long been famous for
                    its magnificent cotton trees <hi rend="italic">(Bombax</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Monguba, B. Ceiba');</hi> but the grand old trees are dying out, and the finest
                    avenue in Pará is now the Estrada de Sâo José, with its colonnade of tall “royal
                    palms <hi rend="italic">” (Oreodoxa regia).</hi> In the outskirts of the city
                    the wealthy merchants have villas with very extensive grounds, and a little way
                    beyond these begins the dense swamp-forest. Pará has a wonderfully pleasant and
                    healthy climate, with a temperature extremely equable throughout the year. “The
                    mornings are cool. From 10 till 2 the heat increases rapidly, commonly reaching
                    90° or 91°. A little later great black clouds appear in the east and spread
                    quickly over the sky; the temperature falls suddenly, the wind blows in varying
                    gusts, the rain pours down, and ere one is aware the sun leaps out. Sometimes
                    the first shower is followed by a second or even a third. By sunset the ground
                    is dry.” This is the rule all the year round; only in the height of the dry
                    season a week may pass without any showers. The Brazilians have a proverb, “Who
                    came to Pará was glad to stay: who drank assai went never away.” The <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n251/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0251-0234"/> assai referred to is a beverage made by squeezing
                    the black grape-like berries of the assai palm <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Euterpe</hi><hi rend="italic">edulis)</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> it is
                    largely drunk by all classes in Parâ. The importance of the city is due to its
                    being the great emporium of the rapidly-developing trade of the Amazons. The
                    trade is carried on by several steamboat companies; the most important, the
                    Amazonian Steamboat Company, receives a subsidy from the Brazilian Government.
                    Two lines of steamers run between Liverpool and Paré,; there are also a French
                    line and a German line. A large trade is transacted with the United States, but
                    mainly through English, French, German, and Portuguese houses. The principal
                    exports are cocoa, Brazil nuts, hides, deer-skins, isinglass, balsam of copaiba,
                    tonka beans, and Peruvian bark. In 1863 the total value of the imports was about
                    £500,000 and of the exports about &lt;£525,000; by 1882 the duties paid to the
                    custom-house amounted to £864,396.</p>
                <p>Population has been growing faster than the supply of houses. In 1819 the
                    inhabitants were estimated at 24,500, but by 1850 they had declined to 15,000;
                    in 1866 they were 36,000 (about 5000 slaves); and they are now (1884) nearly
                    40,000. Besides a vast cathedral (1720) and the president’s palace, usually
                    considered one of the best buildings of its kind in Brazil, Parâ contains an
                    episcopal palace (formerly the Jesuit college), a handsome theatre, a large
                    market building, a custom-house (formerly a convent, with two great towers),
                    naval and military arsenals (the first of some size, with shipbuilding yards and
                    a gridiron), a botanical garden, &amp;c. About a mile from the city is the
                    chapel of Our Lady of Nazareth, the most celebrated shrine in northern
                    Brazil.</p>
                <p>In 1615 Francisco Caldeira de Castello Branco, sent out by the Portuguese at
                    Maranhao, built the fort of Santo Christo and founded the settlement of Nossa
                    Senhora de Belem. By 1641 it was a place of 400 inhabitants, with four
                    monasteries. A premature declaration of independence was made at Para in 1823,
                    and soon after Captain Grenfell, sent by Lord Cochrane, brought the city over to
                    the Brazilian party; but for many years it was subject to political disturbance.
                    In 1835 “every respectable white was obliged to leave the city” by the
                    anarchical proceedings of the so-called “Liberals” Gomes, Vinagre, and
                    Rodriguez.</p>
                <p>See Bates, <hi rend="italic">Naturalist on the River Amazons,</hi> 1863; H. H.
                    Smith, <hi rend="italic">Brazil,</hi> 1879.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
