<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0205-0188-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PALLAS, Peter Simon (9th edition, volume 18, page
                    188)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078723">Progress</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vs35">Naturalists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w744">Progress</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n205/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PALLAS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Peter Simon</hi></label>
                    (1741-1811), naturalist and traveller, was born in Berlin, September 22, 1741,
                    the son of Simon Pallas, surgeon in the Prussian army, and professor of surgery
                    in Berlin. Pallas was carefully educated by his father, being accustomed from
                    boyhood to the use of several languages, among them English and French. He was
                    intended for the medical profession, and his progress was such that in 1758 he
                    lectured publicly on anatomy. Pallas studied at the universities of Berlin,
                    Halle, Göttingen, and Leyden. He early displayed a strong leaning towards
                    natural history investigations, which by the time he reached manhood almost
                    monopolized his attention. In 1761 he came to England, where he spent a year,
                    devoting himself to a thorough study of the collections he found there, and to a
                    geological investigation of part of the English coast; and at the age of
                    twenty-three he was elected a foreign member of the Royal Society. Pallas spent
                    some time in Holland, where he found ample scope for investigation in his
                    special subjects, the results of which appeared at the Hague in 1766 in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Elenchus</hi><hi rend="italic">Zoophy</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >torum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Miscellanea Zoologica,</hi> and in 1767-1804
                    in his well-known <hi rend="italic">Spicilegia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Zoologica</hi> (Berlin). In 1768 he gladly accepted the invitation of the
                    empress Catherine to fill the professorship of natural history in the Imperial
                    Academy of Science, St Petersburg, and from that time until within a year of his
                    death his home was in Russia. The great event of his life, and that by which he
                    will be permanently remembered, was the expedition through Russia and Siberia in
                    1768-74, in which he acted as naturalist, in company with Falk, Lepechen, and
                    Güldenstadt, the immediate object being the observation of the transit of Venus
                    in 1769. In this leisurely journey Pallas went by Kasan to the Caspian, spent
                    some time among the Calmucks, crossed the Urals to Tobolsk, visited the Altai
                    Mountains, traced the Irtish to Kolyvan, went on to Tomsk and the Yenissei,
                    crossed Lake Baikal, and extended his journey to the frontiers of China. Few
                    explorations have been so fruitful as this six years’ journey. Pallas’s
                    collections included all departments of natural history, and his observations
                    extended to every point of interest in the region traversed and its inhabitants.
                    The leading results were given in his <hi rend="italic">Reisen durch
                    verschiedene Provinzen des Russischen Reichs</hi> (3 vols. 4to, St Petersburg,
                    1771-76), richly illustrated with coloured plates. A French translation in
                    1788-93, in 8 vols., with 9 vols, of plates, contained, in addition to the
                    narrative, the natural history results of the expedition; and an English
                    translation in three volumes appeared in 1812. As special results of this great
                    journey may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">Sammlungen historischer Nachrichten
                    über die Mongolischen Völkerschaften</hi> (2 vols. 4to, St Petersburg,
                    1776-1802); <hi rend="italic">Novae</hi><hi rend="italic">Species</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Quadrupedum,</hi> 1778-79; Pallas’s contributions to the
                    dictionary of languages of the Russian empire, 1786-89; <hi rend="italic">Icones
                    Insectorum,</hi><hi rend="italic">praesertim Rossiae Siberiaeque</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">peculiarium,</hi> 1781-1806; <hi rend="italic">Zoographia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Rosso-</hi><hi rend="italic">Asiatica</hi> (3 vols., 1831);
                    besides many special papers in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> of the
                    academies of St Petersburg and Berlin. The empress bought Pallas’s natural
                    history collections for 20,000 roubles, 5000 more than he asked for them, and
                    allowed him to keep them for life. He spent a considerable time in 1793-94 in
                    visiting the southern provinces of Russia, and was so greatly taken with the
                    Crimea that he determined to take up his residence there. The empress gave him a
                    large estate at Simpheropol, and 10,000 roubles to assist in equipping a house.
                    Though disappointed with the Crimea as a place of residence, Pallas continued to
                    live there, devoted to constant research, especially in botany, till the death
                    of his second wife in 1810, when he removed to Berlin, where he died September
                    8, 1811. The results of his journey in southern Russia were given in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Bemerkungen auf einer Reise durch die südlichen
                    Statthalterschaften des Russischen Reichs</hi> (Leipsic, 1799-1801; English
                    translation by Blagdon, vols. 5-8 of <hi rend="italic">Modern Discoveries,</hi>
                    1802, and another in 2 vols., 1812). Pallas also edited and contributed to <hi
                    rend="italic">Neue Nordische Beiträge zur physikalischen Erd-und
                    Völkerbeschreibung, Naturgeschichte, und Oekonomie</hi> (1781-96), published <hi
                    rend="italic">Illustrationes Plantarum imperfecte vel nondum cognitarum</hi>
                    (Leipsic, 1803), and contributed to Buffon’s <hi rend="italic">Natural
                    History</hi> a paper on the formation of mountains, and to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Transactions</hi> of various learned societies a great number of special
                    papers.</p>
                <p>The solid value and great extent of Pallas’s contributions to natural science
                    have been long admitted; his name is inseparably associated with the geography
                    (in its varied branches) of Siberia and a large part of European Russia. That he
                    had a marked influence on the progress of zoology there is no doubt; some
                    authorities even hold that he changed the face of the science; while his
                    geological investigations and speculations, if they did not revolutionize the
                    young science (as has been maintained), greatly helped its progress. Though not
                    in any sense brilliant either as an investigator or as a writer, Pallas is
                    certainly one of the most important figures in the science of the latter half of
                    the 18th century.</p>
                <p>See the Essay of Rudolphi in the <hi rend="italic">Transactions</hi> of the
                    Berlin Academy for 1812; Cuvier’s Ëloge in his <hi rend="italic">Recueil des
                    Éloges Historiques,</hi> vol. ii.; and the Life in Jardine's <hi rend="italic"
                    >Naturalists’ Library,</hi> vol. iv., Edin., 1843.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
