<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0834-0799-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHOCION (9th edition, volume 18, page 799)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n834/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHOCION</label>, an Athenian statesman, whose private virtues
                    won him the surname of “the Good,” but whose mistaken policy fatally contributed
                    to the downfall of Athens, was born about 402 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> His
                    father, Phocus, was a pestlemaker, but would seem to have been a man of means,
                    for Phocion in his youth was a pupil of Plato. If Plutarch is right in saying
                    that he afterwards studied under Xenocrates, this implies that he kept up his
                    philosophical studies in later life, for Xenocrates was his junior and did not
                    succeed to the headship of the Academy until 339. As men of kindred character,
                    they may well have been friends; we find them on one occasion serving on the
                    same embassy. It was perhaps from the Academic philosophy that Phocion learned
                    that contempt for luxury and that truly Socratic simplicity and hardiness which
                    characterized him throughout life. From Plato too he may have caught that scorn
                    for the Athenians of his day which he often betrayed—a scorn harmless, perhaps,
                    in the study, but fatal in the council and the camp. His words, though few, were
                    pithy and forcible, his wit keen and caustic. Many of his trenchant sayings have
                    been preserved by Plutarch. He was the only orator whom Demosthenes feared; when
                    Phocion rose to speak Demosthenes used to whisper to his friends, “Here comes
                    the chopper of my speeches.” Gruff in manner, he was kind at heart, ever ready
                    to raise the fallen and succour those in peril, even when they were his enemies.
                    Being once reproached for pleading the cause of a bad man, he replied that the
                    good had no need of help. When other generals were sent by Athens to the allies,
                    the people closed their gates against them and prepared for a siege, but if it
                    was Phocion they went out to meet him and conducted him in joyful procession
                    into their midst. In his youth he saw service under the distinguished general
                    Chabrias, whose temper, by turns sluggish and impetuous, he alternately
                    stimulated and repressed. He thus won the regard of his good-natured commander,
                    and was introduced by him to public notice and employed on important services.
                    When Chabrias defeated the Spartans in the sea-fight off Naxos (September 376)
                    Phocion commanded with distinction the left wing of the Athenian fleet. After
                    the death of Chabrias (357) Phocion cared for the relatives of his patron,
                    patiently endeavouring to train to virtue his wild and wayward son. A consistent
                    advocate of peace, he was yet a good officer, and held the annual office of
                    general no 1ess than forty-five times, though he never sought election.</p>
                <p>He was amongst the last of the Athenian leaders who combined the characters of
                    statesman and soldier. In 351 Phocion and Evagoras, lord of the Cyprian Salamis,
                    were sent by Idrieus, prince of Caria, with a military and naval force to put
                    down a revolt which had broken out against the Persians in Cyprus. The task was
                    successfully accomplished. Next year<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Diodorus (xvi. 46) speaks of Phocion as still in Cyprus iu
                    350. But this can hardly be true if Phocion led the expedition to Eubaea in
                    Anthesterion (end of February and beginning of March) 350. See next
                    note.</p></note> Phocion commanded a force which the Athenians sent to Eubaea in
                    support of the tyrant Plutarch of Eretria. For a time the Athenians were in a
                    dangerous position, but Phocion extricated himself and defeated the enemy on the
                    heights above Tamynae. After the battle he humanely dismissed all his Greek
                    prisoners, fearing the vengeance which the Athenians too often wreaked on their
                    fallen foes. In 341 he returned to the island and put down Clitarchus, whom
                    Philip, king of Macedonia, had set up as tyrant of Eretria. Demosthenes had long
                    warned the Athenians against Philip, but there is nothing to show that in this
                    he was backed by Phocion. On the contrary, from the opposition which he so often
                    offered to Demosthenes, as well as from his subsequent policy, we may infer that
                    Phocion discredited rather than corroborated the warnings of his contemporary.
                    But, when Philip laid siege to Byzantium, the Athenians, at last thoroughly
                    aroused to their danger, sent Chares with an expedition to relieve it. He failed
                    to do so, and Phocion took his place (340). The Byzantines had refused to admit
                    Chares into their city, but they welcomed Phocion. Athenians and Byzantines
                    fought side by side, and Philip was compelled to raise the siege and retire from
                    the Hellespont. Phocion afterwards retaliated on the king’s territory by raids,
                    in one of which he was wounded. When the Megarians appealed to Athens for
                    help,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The dates and even
                    the order of the events from the Cyprian down to the Megarian expedition are
                    variously given by modern writers. The order in the text is that of Plutarch and
                    Diodorus. The dates assigned to the Cyprian, second Eubaean, and Megarian
                    expeditions are those of Diodorus. The first expedition to Eubaea (as to the
                    date of which see Clinton’s <hi rend="italic">Fasti Helleniei,</hi> vol. ii. )
                    and that to Megara are not mentioned by Diodorus. Plutarch mentions the Megarian
                    after the Byzantine expedition. But the siege of Byzantium was not raised till
                    the earlier half of 339, and Phocion afterwards spent some time in Macedonian
                    waters. Thus he could hardly have been at Megara before midsummer 339. But
                    Elatea was seized by Philip iu the winter of 339/338, and its seizure was the
                    occasion of a league between Athens and Thebes. Hence, as the motive assigned
                    for the Megarian expedition was distrust of Thebes, that expedition cannot have
                    taken place after the seizure of Elatea. But the six months between midsummer
                    and winter 339 would hardly suffice for the construction of the Long Walls.
                    Perhaps, then, Plutarch has misplaced the expedition to Megara, and it ought to
                    be dated earlier. Thirlwall assigns it to 343.</p></note> Phocion promptly
                    marched to their aid, fortified the port Nisaea, and connected it with the
                    capital by two long walls, thus securing Megara and its port against attacks by
                    land.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Athenians had
                    rendered the same service to the Megarians more than a century before, but these
                    first Long Walis had been destroyed by the Megarians themselves in the
                    Peloponnesian War (424).</p></note> In spite of the successful issue of his
                    expedition to Byzantium Phocion advised the Athenians to make peace with Philip.
                    But the war party led by Demosthenes prevailed, and the battle of Chaeronea
                    (August 338), in which Philip overthrew the united armies of Athens and Thebes,
                    converted Greece into a province of Macedonia. This brought Phocion and the
                    peace party into power, but Phocion consulted the dignity of Athens so far as to
                    advise the people not to take part in the congress of the Greek states summoned
                    by Philip to meet at Corinth until they knew what terms Philip meant to propose.
                    The Athenians soon had reason to regret that they did not follow this advice.
                    Wüen the <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n835/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0835-0800"/> news of Philip’s assassination reached Athens
                    (336) Phocion vainly dissuaded the people from publicly expressing what he
                    termed a dastardly joy.</p>
                <p>After the revolt of Thebes and its destruction by Philip’s son and successor
                    Alexander the Great, Athens, having been implicated in the movement, was called
                    on by Alexander to surrender the orators of the anti-Macedonian party, including
                    Demosthenes (335). Phocion advised the men to give themselves up, but
                    nevertheless by his intercession he induced the conqueror to relent.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>So Plutarch, <hi
                    rend="italic">Phooion,</hi> c. 17. But Diodorus (xvii. 15) and Plutarch himself
                    elsewhere <hi rend="italic">(Demosth.,</hi> c. 23) ascribe to Demades the credit
                    of having mollified Alexander. Phocion’s name is not mentioned in this connexion
                    by Arrian <hi rend="italic">(Anab.,</hi> i. 10) nor by Justin (xi.
                    4).</p></note> Alexander conceived a high opinion of Phocion, and ever
                    afterwards treated him with marked respect. He would have loaded him with
                    presents, but Phocion steadily declined them, the only favour he asked being the
                    release of some prisoners. When Harpalus, a Macedonian officer who had betrayed
                    the confidence reposed in him by Alexander, fled for refuge to Athens, Phocion,
                    though he contemptuously refused the bribes which Harpalus offered him,
                    nevertheless resisted the proposal to surrender the fugitive (324); and, after
                    the death of Harpalus, Phocion and his son-in-law cared for his infant daughter.
                    The wild joy which the death of Alexander (323) roused at Athens was not shared
                    by Phocion, and he had nothing better than scorn for that heroic effort to shake
                    off the Macedonian yoke known as the Lamian War (323-322). When the news of
                    Leosthenes’s victory over Antipater, the regent of Macedonia, was greeted at
                    Athens with enthusiasm (323), Phocion sneeringly asked, “When shall we have done
                    conquering?” Still, when a body of Macedonian and mercenary troops under Micion
                    landed in Attica and ravaged the country, Phocion led out a force and defeated
                    them with loss. After the battle of Crannon (322) Phocion’s personal influence
                    induced the victorious Antipater to spare Attica the misery of invasion, but he
                    could not prevent the occupation of Munychia (one of the ports of Athens) by a
                    Macedonian garrison. However, Menyllus, the commander of the garrison, was a
                    friend of Phocion and respected the feelings of the Athenians. Further, the
                    Athenians were required by Antipater to surrender the chief members of the
                    anti-Macedonian party, amongst them Demosthenes and Hyperides, and to restrict
                    their franchise by a property qualification. In consequence Hyperides was
                    executed, Demosthenes died by his own hand, and over 12,000 citizens lost the
                    franchise, many of them going into exile. These disfranchised citizens had
                    afterwards an important influence on Phocion’s fate. For some years Athens dwelt
                    in peace, if not in honour, under the shadow of Macedonia. Phocion had the
                    direction of affairs and filled the magistracies with respectable men. By his
                    intercession with Antipater he procured for many of the exiles a repeal or
                    mitigation of their sentence, but he declined to petition Antipater to withdraw
                    the garrison from Munychia. The presents offered him by Antipater and Menyllus
                    he refused. In 318 Antipater died, leaving as his successor in the regency of
                    Macedonia the veteran general Polysperchon, instead of his own son Cassander.
                    The new regent, finding himself isolated and wishing to strengthen himself
                    against his enemies, tried to attach the Greeks to his cause by proclaiming in
                    the name of the young king Philip Arrhidaeus that the oligarchies established by
                    Antipater in the Greek cities should be abolished and the democracies restored,
                    and that all exiles, with a few exceptions, should be allowed to return. A
                    special letter to Athens in the king’s name announced the restoration of the
                    democracy. But Cassander was not to be set aside lightly; he was naturally
                    supported by all who had benefited by his father’s measures, <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> by the oligarchical and Macedonian party in the Greek states. Before
                    the news of the death of Antipater got abroad Cassander sent Nicanor, an
                    adherent of his own, to relieve Menyllus of the command in Munychia. Menyllus
                    unsuspectingly resigned the command to him, and Nicanor held the place for
                    Cassander. When, a few days later, the death of Antipater became known, there
                    were angry murmurs at Athens that Phocion had been a party to the deception.
                    Phocion heeded them not, but, following his usual policy, propitiated Nicanor in
                    favour of Athens. But the people were excited by the promises of Polysperchon
                    Phocion could no longer hold them in. In a public assembly at which Nicanor was
                    present an attempt was made to seize the obnoxious Macedonian, but he escaped.
                    Warnings now poured in on Phocion to beware of him, but he confided in Nicanor’s
                    good intentions and would take no precaution. So Nicanor was enabled to seize
                    and intrench himself in Piraeus, the chief port of Athens. The irritation
                    against Phocion was intense. An attempt to treat with Nicanor failed; he simply
                    referred the envoys, of whom Phocion was one, to Cassander. The arrival in
                    Attica of Alexander, son of Polysperchon, revived the hopes of the Athenians. He
                    came at the head of an army and brought in his train a crowd of the exiles, and
                    it was thought that, along with the constitution, he would restore Munychia and
                    Piraeus to Athens. Far from doing so, it soon appeared that his intention was to
                    seize and hold these ports for Polysperchon, and rumour said that to this step
                    he was instigated by Phocion. The people were furious. In a public assembly they
                    deposed the existing magistrates, filled their places with the most pronounced
                    democrats, and sentenced all who had held office under the oligarchy to exile or
                    death. Among these was Phocion. With some of his companions in misfortune he
                    fled to Alexander, who received the fugitives courteously and sent them to
                    Polysperchon and the king, who were with an army in Phocis. Thither, too, came
                    an embassy from Athens to accuse Phocion and his fellows before the king and to
                    demand the promised independence. Polysperchon resolved to propitiate the
                    Athenians with blood <hi rend="italic">; so,</hi> after an audience disgraceful
                    to all who took part in it except to Phocion, the refugees were packed in carts
                    and sent to Athens to be tried by what Polysperchon called the now free people.
                    A savage mob filled the theatre where the trial was to take place; the returned
                    exiles mustered in force, and with them were women, aliens, and slaves. The
                    prisoners were charged with having betrayed their country in the Lamian War and
                    overturned the democracy. Every attempt Phocion made to defend himself was
                    drowned in a storm of hooting. At last, renouncing the attempt, he was heard to
                    say that for himself he pleaded guilty, but the rest were innocent. “Why,” he
                    asked, “will you kill them?” He was answered with a great shout, “Because they
                    are your friends.” Then Phocion was silent. All were condemned to die, the
                    multitude rising to their feet like one man to give the verdict. A howling
                    rabble followed them with curses to the prison. Phocion was the last to die
                    (317), for he allowed his best friend Nicocles, as a last token of regard, to
                    die before him. His old disdainful wit did not desert him. When his turn came
                    there was not poison enough left, and he had to pay for more, remarking that at
                    Athens a man could not even die for nothing. His body was cast out of Attic
                    territory, but his faithful wife<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The story that this service was rendered by a Megarian woman
                    rests on a false reading in Plutarch, <hi rend="italic">Phoc.,</hi> c. 37,
                    Meγαpjκ⅛ before <hi rend="italic">yυviι</hi> being the interpolation of an
                    ignorant copyist who mistook the preceding <hi rend="italic">τηs
                    'Meγapικηs.</hi></p></note> secretly brought back his bones and interred them by
                    the hearth. Afterwar&lt;⅛ the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n836/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0836-0801"/> repentant Athenians buried them with public
                    honours and raised a bronze statue to his memory.</p>
                <p>The chief authorities for the life of Phocion are Diodorus (xvi. 42, 46, 74,
                    xvii. 15, xviii. 18, 64-67) and the biographies of Plutarch and Nepos. (J. G.
                    FR. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
