<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0361-0340-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PASQUIER, Étienne (9th edition, volume 18, page
                    340)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n361/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PASQUIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Étienne</hi></label>
                    (1529-1615), one of the glories of the French bar, and one of not the least
                    remarkable men of letters of the 16th century, was born at Paris on the 7th June
                    1529 by his own account, according to others a year earlier. Nothing is known of
                    his family, and hardly anything of his youth, but he seems to have inherited a
                    small property at Châtelet in the district of Brie. He certainly studied law
                    early, and in 1547 was a pupil of the famous Cujas at Toulouse. Thence, like
                    many of his contemporaries, he went to finish his studies in Italy. He was
                    called to the Paris bar in November 1549, having not yet (or at most barely)
                    reached his majority. He practised diligently and with success, but by no means
                    neglected literature. Some of his work both at this time and later is light and
                    almost frivolous. A treatise on love, the <hi rend="italic">Mono-ρhile,</hi>
                    appeared in 1554, and not a few similar publications followed it, one of them,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Ordonnances</hi><hi rend="italic">d'Amour,</hi> being
                    somewhat Rabelaisian in character. Pasquier, however, though not a stoic, was a
                    man of perfectly regular life, and he married early; his wife, who was of his
                    own age, affluent, and, it is said, handsome, being a widow for whom he had
                    gained a lawsuit. The next year he had the misfortune to eat some poisonous
                    mushrooms and very nearly died of them; indeed he did not recover fully for two
                    years. This lost him his practice for the time, and he again betook himself to
                    general literature, publishing in 1560 the first book of his great work the <hi
                    rend="italic">Recherches</hi><hi rend="italic">de la France.</hi> Before very
                    long, however, clients once more came to him, and in 1565, when he was
                    thirty-seven, his fame was established by a great speech still extant, in which
                    he pleaded the cause of the university of Paris against the Jesuits, and won it.
                    He was thenceforward constantly employed in the most important cases of the day,
                    and his speeches, many of which we possess, displayed a polished eloquence which
                    was new in his time. But he did not neglect general literature, pursuing the <hi
                    rend="italic">Recherches</hi> steadily, and publishing from time to time much
                    miscellaneous work. His literary and his legal occupations coincided in a
                    curious fashion at the Grands Jours of Poitiers in 1579. These Grand Jours (an
                    institution which fell into desuetude at the end of the 17 th century, with bad
                    effects on the social and political welfare of the French provinces) were a kind
                    of irregular assize in which a commission of the parlement of Paris, selected
                    and despatched at short notice by the king, had full power to hear and determine
                    all causes, especially those in which seignorial rights had been abused. At the
                    Grands Jours of Poitiers of the date mentioned, and at those of Troyes in 1583,
                    Pasquier officiated; and each occasion has left a curious literary memorial of
                    the kind of high jinks with which he and his colleagues relieved their graver
                    duties. The Poitiers work was the celebrated collection of poems on a flea, of
                    which English readers may find a full account in Southey’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Doctor.</hi> Up to this time Pasquier had held no regular office except the
                    lieutenant-generalship of Cognac, where his wife had property; but in 1535 Henry
                    III. made him advocate-general at the Paris Cours des Comptes, an important body
                    having political as well as financial and legal functions. Pasquier
                    distinguished himself here <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n362/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0362-0341"/> particularly by opposing, sometimes successfully,
                    the mischievous system of selling hereditary places and offices, which more
                    perhaps than any single thing was the curse of the older French monarchy. He was
                    present at the famous States of Blois, where Guise was assassinated, and he met
                    Montaigne there. The civil wars brought him much personal sorrow. His wife and
                    children had remained in Paris much harassed by the Leaguers; Madame Pasquier
                    Was even imprisoned, and, though she regained her liberty, she died shortly
                    afterwards, in 1590. Her youngest son was killed fighting on the royalist side
                    the year before. For some years Pasquier lived at Tours, working steadily at his
                    great book, but he returned to Paris in Henry IV.’s train on the 22d March 1594.
                    He continued until 1604 at his work in the Chambre des Comptes; then he retired.
                    He survived this retirement more than ten years, producing much literary work,
                    and died after a few hours’ illness on September 1, 1615, at the age of at least
                    eighty-six.</p>
                <p>In so long and so laborious a life Pasquier’s work was naturally considerable,
                    and it lias never been fully collected or indeed printed. The standard edition
                    is that of Amsterdam, 1723, 2 vols, folio. But for ordinary readers the
                    selections of Μ. Léon Feugère, published at Paris in 2 vols. 8vo, 1849, withan
                    elaborate introduction, are most accessible. As a poet, though very far from
                    contemptible, Pasquier is chiefly interesting as a minor menlber of the Pléiade
                    movement. As a prose writer he is of much more account. The three chief
                    divisions of his prose work are his <hi rend="italic">Recherches,</hi> his
                    letters, and his professional speeches. All are of much value as important
                    documents in the history of the progress of French style. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Recherches</hi> and the letters have a value independent of this. The letters
                    are of much biographical interest and historical importance, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Recherches</hi> contain in a somewhat miscellaneous fashion
                    invaluable information on a vħst variety of subjects, literary, political,
                    antiquarian, and other.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
