<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0713-0682-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PERUZZI, Baldassare (9th edition, volume 18, page
                    682)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p65z">Architects</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vd69">Medusae</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:813114">Architects</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1005463">Magi</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n713/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PERUZZI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Baldassare</hi></label>
                    (1481-1536), architect and painter of the Roman school, was born at Ancajano, in
                    the diocese of Volterra, and passed his early life at Siena, where his father
                    resided. While quite young Peruzzi went to Rome, and there studied architecture
                    and painting; in the latter he was at first a follower of Perugino. The
                    choir-frescos in San Onofrio on the Janiculan Hill, usually attributed to
                    Pinturicchio, are by his hand. One of the first works which brought renown to
                    the young architect was the villa on the banks of the Tiber in Rome now <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n714/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0714-0683"/> known as the Farnesina, originally built for the
                    Sienese Agostino Chigi, a wealthy banker. This villa, like all Peruzzi’s works,
                    is remarkable for its graceful design and the delicacy of its detail. It is best
                    known for the frescos painted there by Raphael and his pupils to illustrate the
                    stories of Psyche and Galatea. One of the <hi rend="italic">loggie</hi> has
                    frescos by Peruzzi’s own hand,—the story of Medusa, a work of considerable
                    decorative beauty. On account of his success in this building Peruzzi was
                    appointed by Leo X. in 1520 architect to St Peter’s at a salary of 250 scudi, a
                    handsome sum for that time; his design for its completion was not, however,
                    carried out. During the sack of Rome in 1527 Peruzzi was taken prisoner, and
                    barely escaped with his life, on condition of his painting the portrait of
                    Constable de Bourbon, who had been killed during the siege (see Vasari). From
                    Rome he escaped to his native city Siena, where he was made city architect, and
                    designed fortifications for its defence, a great part of which still exist. Soon
                    afterwards he returned to Rome, where he made designs for a palace for the
                    Orsini family, and built the palaces Massimi and Vidoni, as well as others in
                    the south of Italy. He died in 1536, and was buried by the side of Raphael in
                    the Pantheon.</p>
                <p>Peruzzi was an eager student of mathematics and the science of perspective; he
                    was also a fair classical scholar, and was much influenced by the treatise of
                    Vitruvius. Like many of the great artists of his time, he was remarkable for the
                    varied extent of his knowledge and skill. A most able architect, a fair painter,
                    and a scientific engineer, he also practised minor arts, such as stucco-work in
                    relief, sgraffito, and the decorative painted arabesques which the influence of
                    Raphael did so much to bring into use. His best existing works in fresco are in
                    the Castel di Bel-caro and the church of Fontegiusta in Siena. For Siena
                    cathedral he also designed a magnificent wooden organcase, painted and gilt,
                    rich with carved arabesques in friezes and pilasters; he also designed the high
                    altar and the Cappella del Battista.</p>
                <p>His chief pupil was the architect Serlio, who, in his work on architecture,
                    gratefully acknowledges the great debt he owed to Peruzzi’s instruction. The
                    English National Gallery possesses an interesting drawing by his hand (No. 167).
                    The subject is the Adoration of the Magi, and it is of special value, because
                    the heads of the three kings are portraits of Michelangelo, Raphael, and Titian.
                    The Uffizi and the library at Siena contain a number of Peruzzi’s designs and
                    drawings, many of which are now of priceless value to the student of Roman
                    antiquities, as they show ancient buildings which have been destroyed since the
                    16 th century.</p>
                <p>Vasari, <hi rend="italic">Vita di Baldassare Peruzzi</hi> (Milanesi’s ed., vol.
                    iv. p. 489, 1882); Milizia, <hi rend="italic">Memοrie degli Arehitetti</hi>
                    (1781, vol. i. pp. 210-215); Della Valle, <hi rend="italic">Lettere Sancsi</hi>
                    (1782-86); Gaye, <hi rend="italic">Carteggio</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >inedito</hi><hi rend="italic">d’</hi><hi rend="italic">Artisti</hi> (1839-40);
                    Lanzi, <hi rend="italic">Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">Pittorica</hi> (1804); and
                    Plainer, <hi rend="italic">Beschreibung der Stadt Rom</hi> (1830-42).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
