<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0209-0192-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PALMER, Edward Henry (9th edition, volume 18, page
                    192)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q77g">Desertion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90f3q">Deserts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c62w">Bedouins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206063">Lebanon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891230">Deserts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048144">Orientalists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n209/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PALMER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edward Henry</hi></label>
                    (1840-1882), Orientalist, was born at Cambridge, August 7, 1840. He lost his
                    parents when he was a mere child, and was then brought up by an aunt. As a
                    schoolboy he showed the characteristic bent of his mind by picking up the Romany
                    tongue and a great familiarity with the inner life of the Gipsies. He was not,
                    however, remarkably bookish, and from school was sent to London as a clerk in
                    the City. Palmer disliked this life, and varied it by learning French and
                    Italian, mainly by frequenting the society of foreigners wherever he could find
                    it. He had a peculiar gift for making himself at home with all manner of strange
                    people, which served him throughout life, and was as effective with Orientals as
                    with Europeans. His linguistic faculty was in fact only one side of a great
                    power of sympathetic imitation. He learned always from men rather than from
                    books, and by throwing his whole flexible personality into unison with those
                    from whom he was learning. In 1859 Palmer returned to Cambridge, apparently
                    dying of consumption. He had an almost miraculous recovery, and in 1860, while
                    he was thinking of a new start in life, fell in at Cambridge with a certain
                    Sayyid Abdullah, a teacher of Eastern languages. Under his influence he resolved
                    to give himself to Oriental studies, in which he made very rapid progress. He
                    now attracted the notice of two fellows of St John’s College, became an
                    undergraduate there, and in 1867 was elected a fellow on the ground of his
                    attainments, especially in Persian and Hindustani. He was soon engaged to join
                    the survey of Sinai, and followed up this work in 1870 by exploring the
                    Wilderness of the Wandering along with Drake. After a visit to Palestine and the
                    Lebanon he returned to England in 1870, and next year published his <hi
                    rend="italic">Desert of the Exodus.</hi> In the close of the year 1871 he became
                    Lord Almoner’s Professor of Arabic at Cambridge, married, and settled down to
                    teaching work. Unhappily his affairs were somewhat straitened, mainly through
                    the long illness of his wife, whom he lost in 1878; he was obliged to use his
                    pen for Oriental and other work in a way that did not do full justice to his
                    talents, and at length he became absorbed in journalism. In 1881, two years
                    after his second marriage, he finally left Cambridge and ceased to teach. In the
                    following year he was asked by the Government to go to the East and assist the
                    Egyptian expedition by his knowledge and his great influence over the Arabs of
                    the desert Al-Tih. It was a hazardous task, but Palmer rightly judged that he
                    could not refuse his country a service which no one else was able to render. He
                    went to Gaza, and without an escort made his way safely through the desert to
                    Suez—an exploit of singular boldness, which gave the highest proof of his
                    capacity for dealing with the Bedouins. From Suez he was again sent into the
                    desert with Captain Gill, to procure camels and do other service of a very
                    dangerous kind, and on this journey he and his companion were attacked and
                    murdered (August 1882). Their remains were recovered after the war, and now lie
                    in St Paul’s Cathedral.</p>
                <p>Palmer’s highest qualities appeared in his travels, especially in the heroic
                    adventures of his last journeys. His brilliant scholarship is also seen to
                    advantage in what he wrote in Persian and other Eastern languages, but not so
                    much so in his English books, which were generally written under pressure. His
                    scholarship was wholly Eastern in character, and lacked the critical qualities
                    of the modern school of Oriental learning in Europe. All his works show a great
                    linguistic range and very versatile talent; but he was cut off before he was
                    able to leave any permanent literary monument worthy of his powers. His chief
                    writings are <hi rend="italic">The Desert of the Exodus,</hi> 1871.; <hi
                    rend="italic">Poems of Behd ed Din</hi> (Ar. and Eng., 2 vols.), 1876-77; <hi
                    rend="italic">Arabic Grammar,</hi> 1877; <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Jerusalem,</hi> 1871 (by Besant and Palmer—the latter wrote the part taken from
                    Arabic sources); <hi rend="italic">Persian Dictionary,</hi> 1876, and <hi
                    rend="italic">English and Persian Dictionary</hi> (posthumous, 1883);
                    translation of the <hi rend="italic">Qu’rân</hi> (unsatisfactory), 1880. He also
                    did good service in editing the <hi rend="italic">Name Lists</hi> of the
                    Palestine Exploration.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
