<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0731-0700-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PETERBOROUGH and MONMOUTH,Charles Mordaunt, Earl of
                    (9th edition, volume 18, page 700)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kk48">Arm</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150446">Thrones</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026940">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947579">Green</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n731/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PETERBOROUGH <hi rend="smallcaps">and MONMOUTH,Charles
                    Mordaunt, Earl of</hi></label> (<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1658-1735), a man
                    whose whole life was passed in the turmoil of excitement, was born about 1658.
                    His father, John Mordaunt, was created Baron Mordaunt of Reigate, Surrey, in
                    1659; his mother was Elizabeth, the daughter and sole heiress of Thomas Cary,
                    the second son of Robert Cary, earl of Monmouth. He entered upon a long career
                    of warfare when only about sixteen years of age by joining Sir John Narborough’s
                    fleet in the Mediterranean, and won his first distinction in arms in Cloudesley
                    Shovel’s destruction of the dey’s fleet under the very guns of Tripoli. On two
                    subsequent occasions— the first in September 1678, the second in June 1680—he
                    embarked in expeditions for the relief of Tangier, but the adventure met with
                    little success, and that troublesome possession was soon after abandoned. His
                    father died 5th June 1675, and Charles Mordaunt succeeded to the peerage. On his
                    return from the second expedition to Tangier he plunged into active political
                    life as a zealous Whig and an unswerving opponent of the duke of York. But his
                    continued hostility to James II. forced him to retire to Holland, when he
                    proposed to William of Orange to invade England. The disposition of the cold and
                    cautious William had little in common with the fierce and turbulent English
                    peer. His plan was rejected, though the prudent prince of Orange deemed it
                    judicious to retain his fiery adherent by his side. When William sailed to
                    Torbay his friend accompanied him, and when the Dutch prince was safely
                    established on the throne of England honours without stint were showered upon
                    Lord Mordaunt. He was sworn of the privy council 14th February 1689, made a lord
                    of the bedchamber in the same month, created lord-lieutenant of Northamptonshire
                    shortly after, and in April of the same year appointed first lord of the
                    treasury and advanced in the peerage to be earl of Monmouth. In less than a year
                    he was out of the treasury, but he still remained by the person of his monarch.
                    He was with William in his dangerous passage to Holland in January 1691; and in
                    June 1692, when crossing from England to the same country, he narrowly escaped
                    shipwreck. Although the English king had refused his consent to α bill for
                    triennial parliaments in the previous session, Lord Monmouth did not shrink from
                    reintroducing it in December 1693. This led to a disagreement with the court,
                    though the final breach did not take place until January 1697, when Monmouth was
                    accused of complicity in Sir John Fenwick’s conspiracy and of the use of
                    “undutiful words” towards the king. He was committed to the Tower, staying in
                    confinement until April 1697, and deprived of his employments. Some consolation
                    for these troubles came to him in June of the same year, when he succeeded to
                    the earldom of Peterborough. The four years after his release from the Tower
                    were mainly passed in retirement at Parson’s Green, Fulham, at a house long
                    since pulled down, but famous for its “extraordinary good rooms” and its
                    spacious gardens. At the close of William’s reign Lord Peterborough emerged from
                    his suburban retreat for a time to take part in the prosecution of Lord Somers,
                    and on the accession of Anne he [dunged into political life again with avidity.
                    His first act was to draw down on himself in February 1702 the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n732/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0732-0701"/> censure of the House of Commons for the part
                    which he took in the attempt to secure the return of his nominee for the borough
                    of Malmesbury.- In the same year he was appointed governor of Jamaica, but he
                    never visited the island over which he ruled, preferring to remain in a part of
                    the world where he could play a more active part in the government of affairs.
                    Through the fear of the ministry that his restless spirit would drive him into
                    opposition to its measures if he stayed at home, he was appointed early in 1705
                    to command an expedition of English and Dutch troops in Spain. He was created
                    sole commander of the land-forces and joint-commander with Sir Cloudesley Shovel
                    of the fleet, and at the same time was reinstated a member of the privy council.
                    His first exploit was to seize Dénia in Valencia; then, with all the impetuosity
                    of his character, he urged upon the Austrian claimant to the throne the
                    expediency of dashing for Madrid, less than 250 miles distant, only to find that
                    he was overruled by his colleagues in council. After this repulse he sailed for
                    Barcelona (August 1705) and commenced to besiege that town. For three weeks the
                    siege languished, until, by a sudden night-attack on 14 th September,
                    Peterborough seized the outworks of Montjuich, and three nights later captured
                    the citadel itself. On 14th October the city was his. This was his greatest
                    feat, and in this enterprise he showed, what was usually wanting in his
                    character, both tact and conciliation. After this victory Catalonia declared for
                    the Austrian prince, and Peterborough advanced into Valencia with the object of
                    reducing it to subjection. By threats, cajolements, intrigues, and plots he
                    obtained possession of its chief towns, but the prince for whom he was fighting
                    allowed himself to be surrounded in Barcelona, Peterborough’s advice, that
                    Charles should travel by sea to Lisbon and march against Madrid with the allied
                    force of 25,000 men, was disregarded, and the English commander with his little
                    body of 2000 foot and 600 horse then advanced towards Barcelona, which was
                    besieged by a greatly superior force of the enemy. The city was on the point of
                    being captured, when Peterborough, warned of the approach of the English
                    fleet—it is said that the signal of its arrival was a blank sheet of paper—put
                    off in an open boat, and, after journeying to and fro, met with his country’s
                    vessels. On 8th May he brought the leading ships into the port of Barcelona, and
                    three days later the French beat a retreat. Again did the English commander urge
                    upon the Austrian claimant of the Spanish throne the expediency of immediately
                    advancing to Madrid, and again was the advice rejected, although the capital was
                    occupied by the allied forces under Galway and Das Minas. Charles remained at
                    Barcelona for some weeks, and when at last he did move towards Madrid it was by
                    a route which Peterborough disapproved of. When difficulties beset Charles on
                    his way the earl joined him, but he soon retired to Valencia in disgust, and
                    then left the country to raise money at Genoa. In a short time he returned to
                    Spain once more, but during his absence the prospects of the allied forces had
                    passed from bad to worse. The leaders of the army differed in their views, and
                    Lord Peterborough quitted the country for ever (March 1707).</p>
                <p>On his return to England he allied himself with the Tories, and received his
                    reward in being contrasted, much to his advantage, with the Whig victor of
                    Blenheim and Malplaquet. The differences between the three peers, Peterborough,
                    Galway, and Tyraλvley, who had served in Spain, formed the subject of angry
                    debates in the Lords, when the majority declared for Peterborough; after some
                    fiery speeches the resolution that he had performed many great and eminent
                    services was carried, and votes of thanks were passed to him without any
                    division. His new friends were not desirous of detaining him long on English
                    soil, and they sent him on a mission where he characteristically engaged the
                    ministry in pledges of which they disapproved. His resentment at this
                    disagreement was softened by the command of a cavalry regiment, and by his
                    appointment as a Knight of the Garter. A few months before the close of Queen
                    Anne’s reign (November 1713) he was despatched as ambassador-extraordinary to
                    the king of Sicily, but was recalled by the Whigs as soon as they obtained the
                    reins of power. With the accession of George I. Lord Peterborough’s influence
                    was gone. Hatred of Marlborough became the ruling passion of his mind. His last
                    twenty years of life were passed with the recollection of disappointed hopes and
                    with the continual presence of disease. Worn out with suffering, he died at
                    Lisbon, 25th October 1735. His remains were brought to England and buried at
                    Turvey in Bedfordshire, 21st November.</p>
                <p>Lord Peterborough was short in stature and spare in habit of body. His activity
                    knew no bounds. He was said to have seen more kings and postilions than any man
                    in Europe, and the whole point of Swift’s lines on “Mordanto” consisted in a
                    description of the speed with which he hastened from capital to capital. Nature
                    had bestowed many gifts upon him, but had denied him more. He was eloquent in
                    debate and intrepid in war, but his influence in the senate was ruined through
                    his inconsistency, and his vigour in the field was wasted through his want of
                    union with his colleagues. He could do nothing like other men. His first wife,
                    Carey, daughter of Sir Alexander Fraser of Mearns, died 13th May 1709, and was
                    buried at Turvey 20th May. Some years later he married Anastasia Robinson, a
                    dramatic singer of great beauty and sweetness of disposition; but she was
                    unrecognized as his wife, and lived apart from him at her mother’s house at
                    Parson’s Green. Nor was it until a few months before his death that she was
                    introduced to society as the countess of Peterborough. (W. P. C. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
