<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0792-0757-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHILLIP, John (9th edition, volume 18, page
                    757)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cs84">Mercerization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dp40">Artists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3cd37">Windows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:918096">Exhibitionism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1016921">Mercerization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984249">Joy</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817559">Artists</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n792/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHILLIP, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1817-1867),
                    subject and portrait painter, was born at Aberdeen, Scotland, on 19 th April
                    1817. His father, an old soldier, was in humble circumstances, and the son
                    became an errand-boy to a tinsmith of the place, and was then apprenticed to a
                    painter and glazier. Meanwhile he was employing in the pursuit of art all the
                    time he could spare from his daily duties, and, having received some technical
                    instruction from a local artist named William Mercer, he began, at the age of
                    about fifteen, to paint portraits. In 1834 he was enabled to make a very brief
                    visit to London, where he studied with delighted interest in the Royal Academy
                    Exhibition and the National Gallery. At this time, or shortly afterwards, he
                    became assistant to James Forbes, an Aberdeen portrait-painter, under whose
                    tuition he made considerable progress. Previously, however, he had gained a
                    valuable patron. Having been sent to repair a window in the house of Major P. L.
                    Gordon, his interest in the works of art which hung on the walls attracted the
                    attention of their owner. He brought the young artist under the notice of Lord
                    Panmure, who bought several of his productions, and in 1836 sent the lad to
                    London, promising to bear the cost of his art-education. At first Phillip was
                    placed under T. Μ. Joy, but he soon entered the schools of the Royal Academy,
                    where he worked diligently, but with no exceptional promise or success, for two
                    years. In 1839 he figured for the first time in the Royal Academy Exhibition
                    with a portrait and a landscape, and in the following year he was represented by
                    a more ambitious figure-picture of Tasso in Disguise relating his Persecutions
                    to his Sister. For the next ten years he supported himself mainly by portraiture
                    and by painting subjects of national incident, such as Presbyterian Catechizing,
                    Baptism in Scotland, and the Spaewife. His productions of this period, as well
                    as his earlier subjectpictures, are reminiscent of the practice and methods of
                    Wilkie and the Scottish genre-painters of his time, often possessing
                    considerable grace of form, executed in a thin delicate style of painting,
                    inclining to brownish tones of colour, and with the more powerful pigments
                    introduced cautiously and with reserve The Letter-writer of Seville, shown in
                    the Royal Academy of 1854, marks a distinct change of both style and subject.
                    Three years previously the artist’s health had shown signs of delicacy, and his
                    medical advisers had recommended a residence in a warmer climate. Spain was
                    selected, and a fresh potency came to· his art as well as to his physical frame.
                    He was brought face to face for the first time with the brilliant sunshine and
                    the splendid colour of the South, and it was in coping <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n793/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0793-0758"/> with these that he first manifested his artistic
                    individuality and finally displayed his full powers. In the Letterwriter,
                    commissioned by the Queen at the suggestion of Sir Edwin Landseer, who had been
                    greatly impressed by some of Phillip’s Spanish sketches, we see the change of
                    method in its initial stages rather than in its complete triumph. The artist is
                    struggling -with new difficulties in the portrayal of unwonted splendours of
                    colour and light, the draperies are somewhat crude and textureless, and the
                    picture may justly be charged with a want of complete harmony and of a due sense
                    of the finer gradations of nature. In 1857 Phillip was elected an associate of
                    the Royal Academy, and in 1859 a full member. In 1855 and in 1860 other two
                    visits to Spain were made, and in each case the painter returned with fresh
                    materials to be embodied with increasing power and subtlety in the long series
                    of works with which his name is exclusively associated in the popular mind, and
                    which has won for him the title of “Spanish Phillip.” His highest point of
                    execution is probably reached in the La Gloria of 1864 and a smaller
                    single-figure painting of the same period entitled El Cigarillo. These Spanish
                    subjects were varied in 1860 by a rendering of the Marriage of the Princess
                    Royal with the Crown Prince of Germany, executed by command of the Queen, and in
                    1863 by a picture of the House of Commons, subjects presenting extreme artistic
                    difficulties, but treated with much skill and dexterity. During his last visit
                    to Spain Phillip occupied himself in a careful study of the art of Velazquez,
                    and the copies which he made after that artist fetched large prices after his
                    death, examples having been secured by the Royal and the Royal Scottish
                    Academies. The year before his death he visited Italy and devoted much attention
                    to the works of Titian. The results of this study of the old masters are visible
                    in such of Phillip’s works as La Loteria Nacional, left uncompleted at his
                    death. This and several other of his later works exhibit symptoms of a fresh
                    change of method, and show signs that his art was again about to take a fresh
                    departure. During this period he resided much in the Highlands, and seemed to be
                    returning to his first love for Scottish subjects, painting several national
                    scenes, and planning others that were never completed. His health had been
                    always delicate, and his strength had been taxed by severe domestic affliction
                    and by the very exceptional rapidity and quantity of his artistic production. In
                    the end of 1866 his excessive application to work for the next year’s exhibition
                    induced an attack of bilious fever, which was succeeded by paralysis, and the
                    genial and talented artist expired at London on 27 th February 1867 at the age
                    of fifty.</p>
                <p>In execution Phillip was singularly direct, forcible, and rapid. He was a noble
                    colourist, a painter in the first and simplest sense of the word, concerning
                    himself mainly with the visible and sensuous beauties of his subjects, their
                    purely artistic problems of colour, tone, lighting, and texture. His art dealt
                    with the appearances of things, a sufficiently legitimate sphere for the
                    painter, and was seldom permeated with any very deep human or dramatic interest.
                    His works were collected in the International Exhibition of 1873, aud many of
                    them have been excellently reproduced by the engravings of T. Oldham Barlow. In
                    addition to the paintings which we have already specified the following are
                    among the more important:—Life among the Gipsies of Seville (1853), El Paseo
                    (1855), Collection of the Offertory in a Scotch Kirk (1855), a Gipsy
                    Water-carrier in Seville (1855), the Prayer of Faith shall save the Sick (1856),
                    the Dying Contrabandist (1856), the Prison Window (1857), a Huff (1859), Early
                    Career of Murillo (1865), a Chat round the Brasero (1866).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
