<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0736-0705-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PETRA (9th edition, volume 18, page 705)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vq1n">Fountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40000538">Islam</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933357">Fountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n736/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PETRA</label> (τ) ∏∈τpα, in ecclesiastical writers also <hi
                    rend="italic">αι</hi> ∏eτpαι), the capital city of the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Nabataeans</hi><hi rend="italic">(g.vf),</hi> and the great centre of their
                    caravan trade, is described by Strabo (xvi. p. 779) as lying in a level place,
                    well supplied with water for horticulture and other uses, but encircled by a
                    girdle of rocks, abrupt towards the outer side. The surrounding country was
                    barren, especially towards Judaea; the distance from Jericho was three to four
                    days’ journey, and from Phaenicum on the Red Sea coast five (see plate VI., vol.
                    vii.). According to Pliny (W. <hi rend="italic">H.</hi>, vi. 144) the little
                    valley of Petra is not quite 2 miles across, and lies at the junction of two
                    roads, from Palmyra and Gaza respectively, 600 miles from the latter. These and
                    other ancient notices leave no doubt as to the identity of the site with the
                    modern Wády Músá in the mountains which form the eastern wall of the great
                    valley between the Dead Sea and the Gulf of Akaba. Wády Músá lies just north of
                    the watershed between the two seas, in 30° 19' N. lat. and 35° 31' E. long.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The latitude and longitude
                    are taken from De Luynes’s map. Ptolemy, who, according to Olympiodorus, spent
                    some time in Petra, and doubtless owes to this fact his excellent information
                    about the caravan-routes in Arabia, gives the latitude, with surprising
                    accuracy, as 30° 20′.</p></note> Travellers coming up the Arabah usually
                    approach the ruins of Petra from the south-west by a rough path, partly of
                    artificial construction<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Compare Diod., xix. 97, who describes the Nabataean fortress— it was not a
                    town at the time in question (312 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> for the
                    Nabataeans were still nomads when they were attacked by Antigonus—as ascended to
                    by a single artificial path.</p></note>; but the natural entrance is from the
                    east down a narrow defile more than a mile long, called the Sík (“shaft”). The
                    Sík is a contraction in the valley of a stream which comes down from the east,
                    rising in a spring now known as the Fountain of Moses ('Ain Músá),<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This seems to be the fountain
                    mentioned by Nowairi, ap. Quatremère’s <hi rend="italic">Mélanges,</hi> p. 84,
                    which flowed with blood and was changed to water by Moses. The name Od-demá,
                    which gave rise to this legend, may possibly be a relic of the old name of
                    Edom.</p></note> and passing between the villages of Eljí and 'Aireh (Palmer).
                    Both these places are ancient; the latter is the fortress Wo'aira of Yákút,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Perhaps also the Iram, □∏T,
                    of Gen. xxxvi. 43.</p></note> while Eljí, mentioned by Edrisi, is the “Gaia urbs
                    juxta civitatem Petram” of the <hi rend="italic">Cnomasticon.</hi><note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Tuch’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Genesis,</hi> 2d ed., p. 271, note.</p></note> Below these and above the ravine
                    the characteristic rockcut tombs and dwellings of the Nabataeans begin to
                    appear. But to reach the city proper from these upper settlements one must
                    traverse the whole length of the defile, which is simply a narrow waterway, in
                    some places not more than 10 or 12 feet broad, and walled in by rich brown or
                    red precipices rising from 60 to 120 feet (De Luynes; Stanley doubles this
                    height) above the stream. In ancient times there was a paved path beside the
                    channel, and remains of an arch spanning it are seen high in the air near the
                    entrance. Towards the lower end of the gorge, a turn in the dark path and the
                    descent of a side valley admit a sudden flood of light, and here stands the most
                    famous ruin of Petra, the so-called Khazna, or “treasury of Pharaoh,” with a
                    rich façade of late Roman style, not built but hewn out of the rose-coloured
                    limestone. The next turn gives room for a rock-cut theatre, and from this point
                    the gorge begins to open out into the little plain described by Strabo, and
                    gives perhaps the most striking view of the multiplicity of grottoes with
                    elaborate classical façades which line the enclosing mountain-wall. The plain
                    itself is strewn with ruins of temples and other buildings, and stairs once led
                    up the rocky walls to higher structures, of which the most notable is now called
                    the “convent” (Al-Deir). The grottoes are inhabited in cold weather by the
                    Liyá-thina Felláhín, who also hold the upper part of the valley, and are so
                    troublesome and extortionate that no thorough exploration of the district has
                    yet been carried out. It is not even known where the torrent-bed leads on
                    leaving the plain of Petra. De Luynes describes the water as wholly absorbed by
                    the sands near the theatre, but there is an unexplored gorge to the south-west
                    which is the continuation of the valley.</p>
                <p>The Nabataeans, as we see from Diodorus, used Petra as a place of refuge and a
                    safe storehouse for their treasures of frankincense, myrrh, and silver before
                    they gave up their nomadic habits. But Petra was not only safe and well <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n737/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0737-0706"/> watered, it lay close to the most important lines
                    of trade. The modern pilgrim-road from Damascus to Mecca, which has taken the
                    place of the old incense-route, passes indeed a little to the east by Ma'án. But
                    to touch Petra involves no great detour even on this line, and in ancient times,
                    when Gaza was the great terminus of the Arabian trade, Petra was the place where
                    the Gaza road branched off from that to Bostra, Palmyra, and north Syria. The
                    route from Egypt to Damascus is also commanded by Petra, and from it too there
                    went a great route direct through the desert to the head of the Persian Gulf.
                    Thus Petra became a centre for all the main lines of overland trade between the
                    East and the West, and it was not till the fall of the Nabataean kingdom that
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Palmyra (⅛</hi><hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> ,</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">.v.)</hi> superseded it as the chief emporium of north Arabia.
                    Many Roman and other foreign merchants were settled here even in the time of
                    Strabo, and he describes the caravans which passed between it and Leuce Come on
                    the Red Sea coast as comparable to armies.</p>
                <p>Petra<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Arabia Petraea is
                    not properly Stony Arabia, but the Arabia of which Petra is the centre— <hi
                    rend="italic">ή κατά</hi><hi rend="italic">∏lτρaν</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >’Αραβία</hi> of Agathemerus.</p></note> is a Greek name which cannot have been
                    that used by the Semitic inhabitants, and from Josephus <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Ant.,</hi> iv. 7, 1; 4, 7) and the <hi rend="italic">Onomastica</hi> (ed.
                    Lag., p. 286 <hi rend="italic">sqj)</hi> it may be concluded that the natives
                    called the place Rekem (Cpl), a designation probably derived from the variegated
                    colours of the rocks about Wády Müsá, to which all travellers refer with
                    admiration.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    rock-hewn city of Rakím (Istakhrí, 64; <hi rend="italic">Géogr. d'Abulf.,</hi>
                    Fr. tr., ii. 2, 5), which Schultens <hi rend="italic superscript"> l</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dnd. Geog. in</hi><hi rend="italic">Vit.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sal.)</hi> proposes to identify with Petra, is a different place, close to
                    'Amman (Mokaddasí, p. 175).</p></note> But Petra had yet another ancient name
                    familiar from the Bible. The Biblical Sela (generally with the article p⅛∏), a
                    city of Edom (2 Kings xiv. 7; Isa. xvi. 1; also Judges i. 36, where E.V. has
                    “the rock”; perhaps also Isa. xlii. 11), appears to be identified with Petra by
                    the LXX., and certainly is so by the <hi rend="italic">Onomastica.</hi> Petra,
                    in fact, or the “rock,” seems to be simply a translation of Sela, but a somewhat
                    loose one,—for the Hebrew name, corresponding to the Arabic SaΓ, is properly a
                    hollow between rocks, just such a place as Petra is. The fortress of Edom,
                    according to Obadiah 3, lay “in the clefts of the Sela,” and seemed impregnable.
                    And that the name of Sela survived the Nabataean occupation is known from Yákút,
                    who places a fortress SaΓ in Wády Músá (comp. Nöldeke in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Z.Ι).MH.,</hi> XXV. 259). Petra, therefore, was a city before theNabataeans,
                    and, occupying one of the few cultivable spots in the district, probably never
                    wholly ceased to be inhabited. This identification disposes of another which was
                    accepted alike by the Jewish and Christian Aramaic versions of the Old
                    Testament, and, passing from the Aramaeans to the Arabs, has given rise to the
                    modern names Fountain and Wády of Moses (comp. Yákút, iv. 879). According to
                    these versions Rkém, Rkám, or more precisely Rkém of Gaiá (that is, Eljí), is
                    Kadesh Barnea, where flowed the waters of Strife or “well of judgment” (Gen.
                    xiv. 7; Num. xx. 1 <hi rend="italic">sq.,</hi> xxvii. 14), where Moses struck
                    the rock. This view is ably supported by Greene <hi rend="italic">(The Hebrew
                    Migration from EgypC)',</hi> others identify Kadesh with 'Ain Kadis (Kudais) on
                    the south border of Judaea.</p>
                <p>Petra survived the fall of the Nabataean kingdom, and indeed most of the
                    buildings may be dated from the 2d and 3d centuries. It appears from coins that
                    Hadrian took it into favour and gave it his name. But Palmyra absorbed its trade
                    with the Persian Gulf, and long before Islam the great incense-route was
                    deserted and left Petra, like the more southern Nabataean city of Egra (Hijr),
                    to fall into ruin. The ruins were an object of curiosity in the Middle Ages, and
                    were visited by Sultan Bibars (Quatremère, Z.c.). The first European to describe
                    them was Burckhardt, and since his time they have often been visited. See the
                    descriptions, plans, and views of Laborde and Linant, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Arabie</hi><hi rend="italic">Petrée</hi> (Paris, 1830-34); the Duc de Luynes,
                    <hi rend="italic">Voyage d'exploration</hi> à <hi rend="italic">la mer
                    morte,</hi> &amp;c., Paris, s.a.; Palmer, <hi rend="italic">Desert of the
                    Exodus,</hi> vol. ii., 1871; Stanley, <hi rend="italic">Sinai and
                    Palestine</hi>; Guérin, <hi rend="italic">Terre</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sainte,</hi> 1883. (W. R. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
