<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0499-0478-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PELLICO, Silvio (9th edition, volume 18, page
                    478)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vs7f">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62623">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dq6d">Esters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mq8d">Moros</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897549">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:920123">Fame</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n499/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PELLICO, <hi rend="smallcaps">Silvio</hi></label>
                    (1788-1854), Italian dramatist, was born at Saluzzo in Piedmont on 24th June
                    1788, the earlier portion of his life being passed at Pinerolo and Turin under
                    the tuition of a priest named Manavella. A taste for the drama, fostered by
                    private theatrical recitals, showed itself at the age of ten in the composition
                    of a tragedy under the inspiration of Caesarotti’s translation of the Ossianic
                    poems. On the marriage of his twin sister Rosina with a maternal cousin at Lyons
                    he went to reside in that city, devoting himself during four years to the study
                    of French literature. His patriotism having been re-awakened by the reading of
                    Foscolo’s <hi rend="italic">Dei Sepolcm,</hi> he returned in 1810 to Milan,
                    where he became professor of French in the Collegio degli Orfani Militari. The
                    appearance of Carlotta Marchionni on the Milan stage induced him to compose for
                    her the tragedy <hi rend="italic">Francesca da Rimini,</hi> which, despite the
                    adverse criticism of Foscolo, was brought out with success on the return of the
                    actress to the city a few years later. Its publication was followed by that of
                    the tragedy <hi rend="italic">Eufemio</hi><hi rend="italic">da Messina,</hi> but
                    the representation of the latter was forbidden. Pellico had in the meantime
                    continued his work as tutor, first to the unfortunate son of Count Briche, and
                    then to the two sons of Count Porro Lambertenghi. In this capacity he was
                    brought into contact with many of the foremost men of the day and threw himself
                    heartily into an attempt to weaken the hold of the Austrian despotism by
                    indirect educational means. Of the powerful literary executive which gathered
                    about Counts Porro and Confalonieri, Pellico was the able secretary,—the
                    management of the <hi rend="italic">Conciliatore,</hi> which appeared in 1818 as
                    the organ of the association, resting largely upon him. But the paper, under the
                    relentless censorship of the Austrian officials, ran for a single year only, and
                    the society itself was broken up by the more vigorous action of the Government
                    consequent upon the formation of the constitution of Naples. In October 1820
                    Pellico was arrested on the charge of carbonarism and conveyed to the Santa
                    Margherita prison. Occupied at first in preparing his defence and in religious
                    meditation, he found means, after his removal to the Piombi at Venice in
                    February 1821, to resume literary work, composing there several <hi
                    rend="italic">Cantiche</hi> and the tragedies <hi rend="italic">Ester
                    cfEngaddi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Iginia TAsti.</hi> The sentence of death
                    pronounced on him in February 1822 was finally commuted to fifteen years <hi
                    rend="italic">carcere duro,</hi> and in the following April he was placed in the
                    Spielberg at Brünn. His chief work during this part of his imprisonment was the
                    tragedy <hi rend="italic">Leoniero da</hi><hi rend="italic">Dertona,</hi> for
                    the preservation of which he was compelled to rely on his memory. After his
                    release in 1830 he commenced the publication of his prison compositions, of
                    which the <hi rend="italic">Ester</hi> was played at Turin in 1831, but
                    immediately suppressed. In 1832 appeared his <hi rend="italic">Gismonda da
                    Mendñzio, Erodiade,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Leoniero,</hi> under the
                    title of <hi rend="italic">Tre nuovi</hi><hi rend="italic">Tragédie,</hi> and in
                    the same year the work which gave him his European fame, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Mie Prigioni.</hi> The last gained him the friendship
                    of the Marchesa di Barolo, the reformer of the Turin prisons, and in 1834 he
                    accepted from her a yearly pension of 1200 francs. His tragedy <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tommaso Moro</hi> had been published in 1833, his most important subsequent
                    publication being the <hi rend="italic">Opere Inedite</hi> in 1837. On the
                    decease of his parents in 1838 he was received into the Casa Barolo, where he
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n500/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0500-0479"/> remained till his death, assisting the marchesa
                    in her charities, and writing chiefly upon religious themes. Of these works the
                    best known is the <hi rend="italic">Dei Doveri degli Uomini,</hi> a series of
                    trite maxims which do honour to his piety rather than to his critical judgment.
                    A fragmentary biography of the marchesa by Pellico was published in Italian and
                    English after her death. He died 31st January 1854, and was buried in the Campo
                    Santo at Turin. His writings, whether in prose or verse, are chaste and
                    graceful, but defective in virility and breadth of thought, and his tragedies
                    display neither the insight into character nor the constructive power of a great
                    dramatist. It is in the simple narrative and naive egotism of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Mie Prτgioni</hi> that he has established his
                    strongest claim to remembrance, winning fame by his misfortunes rather than by
                    his genius.</p>
                <p>Cf. Piero Maroncelli, <hi rend="italic">Addizioni</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >alle</hi><hi rend="italic">Mie Prigioni,</hi> Paris, 1834; the biographies by
                    Latour; Gabriele Rosselli; Didier, <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes,</hi>
                    September, 1842; De Loménie, <hi rend="italic">Galerie</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Contemp. Illustr.,</hi> iv., 1842; Chiala, Turin, 1852; Nollet-Fabert, 1854;
                    Giorgio Briano, 1854; Bourdon, 1868; and the life of the Marchesa di Barolo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
