<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0918-0757-0726-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PHAeDRUS (9th edition, volume 18, page 726)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2s98r">Augustinians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rz2q">Cistercians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3cb0w">Parties</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sh3p">Consolation</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n757/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PHAeDRUS</label>, the author of five books of Latin fables in
                    verse, lived in the reigns of Augustus, Tiberius, Caligula, and Claudius. To his
                    literary vanity we owe most of our scanty knowledge of his life. He was born on
                    the Pierian Mountain in Macedonia, but seems to have been brought at an early
                    age to Italy, for he mentions that he read a verse of Ennius as a boy at school.
                    According to the heading of the chief MS. he was a slave and was freed by
                    Augustus. He incurred the wrath of Sejanus, the powerful minister of Tiberius,
                    but on what grounds is not known. Devoting himself to literature, he lived in
                    poverty and died at an advanced age. The first two books of his fables were
                    published together; the third, fourth, and fifth appeared later, each by itself.
                    The third book is dedicated to Eutychus, a wealthy man of business and probably
                    a freedman, to whom the poet appeals for promised help. The fourth book is
                    dedicated to Parti-culon, who seems to have dabbled in literature. From the fact
                    that Seneca, writing in 43 or 44 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(Consol, ad Polyb.,</hi> 27), knows of no Latin writer of fables we may infer
                    that Phaedrus published his fables after that time, but the exact date is
                    unknown. His work shows little or no originality; he simply versified (in iambic
                    trimeters)· the fables current in his day under the name of “Aesop,'”
                    interspersing them with anecdotes drawn from daily life, history, and mythology.
                    He tells his fable and draws the moral with business-like directness and
                    simplicity; his language is classical, neat, and clear, but thoroughly prosaic,
                    though it occasionally attains a dignity bordering on eloquence. He is fond of
                    abstract words. From a literary point of view Phaedrus is far inferior to those
                    masters of fable-writing, Babrius and La Fontaine; he lacks the quiet
                    picturesqueness and pathos of the former, and the exuberant vivacity and humour
                    of the latter. Though he frequently refers to the envy and detraction which
                    pursued him, Phaedrus seems to have attracted little attention in antiquity. He
                    is mentioned by Martial (iii. 20, 5), who imitated some of his verses, and by
                    Avianus. Prudentius must have read him, for he imitates one of his lines (Prud.,
                    <hi rend="italic">Cath.,</hi> vii. 115; cp. Phaedrus, iv. 6, 10).</p>
                <p>The first edition of the five books of Phaedrus was published by Pithou at Troyes
                    in 1596. But, from the gaps in the books as well as from the disproportionate
                    shortness of some of them, it is plain that this collection is incomplete. In
                    the beginning of the 18th century there was discovered at Parma a MS. of Perotti
                    (1430-1480), archbishop of Siponto, containing sixty-four fables of Phaedrus, of
                    which thirty-two were new. These new fables were first published at Naples by
                    Cassitto in 1808, and afterwards (much more correctly) by Jannelli in 1811. Both
                    editions were superseded by the discovery of a much <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit18newyrich/page/n758/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0918-0758-0727"/> better preserved MS. of Perotti in the Vatican,
                    which was published by Angelo Mai in 1831. For some time the authenticity of
                    these new fables was disputed, but they are now generally accepted, and with
                    justice, as genuine fables of Phaedrus. They do not form a sixth book, for we
                    know from Avianus that Phaedrus wrote five books only, but it is impossible to
                    assign them to their original places in the five books. They are usually printed
                    as an appendix. Even thus it is probable that we have not the whole of
                    Phaedrus.</p>
                <p>In the Middle Ages Phaedrus exercised a considerable influence through the prose
                    versions of his fables which were current, though his own works and even his
                    name were forgotten. Of these prose versions the oldest existing seems to be
                    that known as the “Anonymus Nilantianus,” so called because first edited by
                    Nilant at Leyden in 1709 from a MS. of the 10th or beginning of the 11th
                    century. It approaches the text of Phaedrus so closely that it was probably made
                    directly from it. Of the sixty-seven fables which it contains thirty are derived
                    from lost fables of Phaedrus. But the largest and most influential of the prose
                    versions of Phaedrus is that which bears the name of “Romulus.” It contains
                    eighty-three fables, is as old as the 10th century, and seems to have been based
                    on a still earlier prose version, which, under the name of “Aesop,” and
                    addressed to one Rufus, may have been made in the Cariovingian period. The
                    preface of Romulus, in which he professes to have translated the fables from the
                    Greek, is a mere fiction of the copyist; no such Romulus as this ever existed,
                    although in the Middle Ages he was sometimes thought to have been a Roman
                    emperor, and has still a place in the <hi rend="italic">Biographie
                    Universelle</hi><hi rend="italic">(1863).</hi> The collection of fables in the
                    Weissenburg (now Wolfenbüttel) MS. is based on the same version (the <hi
                    rend="italic">Aesopus ad</hi><hi rend="italic">Rufum)</hi> as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Romulus.</hi> These three prose versions contain in all one hundred distinct
                    fables, of which fifty-six are derived from the existing and the remaining
                    forty-four presumably from lost fables of Phaedrus. Some modern scholars, as
                    Burmann, Dressier, and L. Müller, have tried to restore these lost fables by
                    versifying the prose versions.</p>
                <p>The collection bearing the name of Romulus became in its turn the source from
                    which, during the second half of the Middle Ages, almost all the collections of
                    Latin fables in prose and verse were wholly or partially drawn. A version of the
                    first three books of <hi rend="italic">Romulus</hi> in elegiac verse enjoyed a
                    wide popularity, even into the Renaissance. Its author (generally referred to
                    since the edition of Névelet in 1610 as the Anonymous of Névelet) was long
                    unknown, but Hervieux has lately shown grounds for identifying him with Walther
                    of England, chaplain to Henry II. and afterwards archbishop of Palermo. The
                    version dates from the latter part of the 12th century. It was especially
                    popular in Italy, where the Italian translation of Accio Zuccho (Verona, 1479)
                    was frequently reprinted. Another version of <hi rend="italic">Romulus</hi> in
                    Latin elegiacs was made by Alexander Neckam, born at St Albans in 1157, and
                    towards the end of his life (early part of 13th century) abbot of the
                    Augustinian monastery at Exeter. Neckam knew and copied Walther’s version, but
                    his Oλvn never had the same popularity. Amongst the collections partly derived
                    from <hi rend="italic">Romulus</hi> the most famous is probably that in French
                    verse by <hi rend="smallcaps">Marie de France</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi>
                    About 1200 a collection of fables in Latin prose, based partly on <hi
                    rend="italic">Romulus,</hi> was made by the Cistercian monk Odo of Sherrington;
                    they have a strong mediaeval and clerical tinge. In 1370 Gerard of Minden wrote
                    a poetical version of <hi rend="italic">Romulus</hi> in Low German.</p>
                <p>Since the first edition of Phaedrus by Pithou in 1596 the editions and
                    translations have been very numerous; among the editions may specially be
                    mentioned those of Burmann (1718 and 1727), Bentley (1726), Schwabe (1806),
                    Berger de Xivrey (1830), Orelìi (1832), Eyssenhardt (1867), L. Müller (1877),
                    Hervieux, in his work <hi rend="italic">Les Fabulistes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Latins</hi><hi rend="italic">depuis le siècle d’Auguste jusqu’à la fin du
                    moyen</hi><hi rend="italic">age,</hi> Paris, 1884. For the mediaeval versions of
                    Phaedrus and their derivatives see L. Roth, in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Philologus,</hi> i. p. 523 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>; H. Oesterley, <hi
                    rend="italic">Romulus</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Paraphrasen</hi><hi rend="italic">des Phaedrus</hi><hi rend="italic">und
                    die</hi><hi rend="italic">aesopische</hi><hi rend="italic">Fabel im
                    Mittelalter,</hi> 1870 (untrustworthy); E. Grosse, in <hi rend="italic">Jahrbb.
                    f</hi><hi rend="italic">class. Philol.,</hi> vol. cv. (1872); and especially the
                    learned work of Hervieux, who gives the Latin texts of all the mediaeval
                    imitators (direct and indirect) of Phaedrus, some of these texts being now
                    edited for the first time. (J. G. FR.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
