<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0023-0014-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ATHOS (9th edition, volume 3, page 14)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978609">Ionians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1056939">Peninsulas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159314">Turkeys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:813089">Archipelagoes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jw08">Servians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn8z">Synods</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222rc91">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892j89">Turkeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n23/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ATHOS</label> is, strictly speaking, the terminal peak of the
                    most eastern of the three peninsular promontories which stretch south from the
                    coast of Turkey <hi rend="italic">(Macedonia),</hi> like the prongs of a
                    trident, into the Archipelago. The name is, however, frequently extended to the
                    whole peninsula which was formerly known as Acte. The peak rises like a pyramid,
                    with a steep summit of white marble, to a height of 6780 feet, and can be seen
                    at sunset from the plain of Troy on the one hand, and on the other from the
                    slopes of Olympus. The whole peninsula is remarkable for the beauty of its
                    scenery, with rocky heights and richly-wooded flanks, ravines “embowered from
                    the light,” and glimpses or free outlook over the surrounding sea. The climate
                    is for the most part healthy and pleasant, though the western side is perhaps
                    too much exposed to the heats of summer; and Lucian assures us that in ancient
                    times the inhabitants were famous for longevity. Several towns, such as Sane,
                    Dium, Olophyxus, Cleonae, are mentioned by Greek and Latin writers as existing
                    in the Peninsula; but none of them seem to have attained any great importance,
                    and the most remarkable event in the ancient history of Athos is the
                    construction by Xerxes of a ship-canal across the isthmus between the outer sea
                    and the Singitic gulf. Traces of this canal, which was regarded by Juvenal as a
                    Greek myth, have been found almost right across the neck of land, and leave no
                    doubt of the truth of the story. In more modern times the district of Athos has
                    been famous for the number of hermits and monks that have found shelter in its
                    retreats. No fewer than 935 churches, chapels, and oratories are said to exist,
                    and many of the communities possess considerable wealth. It is believed that,
                    with the exception of the dwellings of Pompeii, some buildings in</p>
                <p>Athos are the oldest specimens of domestic architecture in Europe; the shrines
                    are in many cases richly decorated with goldsmith’s work of great antiquity; the
                    wealth of the monastic libraries in illuminated manuscripts has long been
                    celebrated; and nowhere, according to Mr Tozer, can the Byzantine school of
                    painting be studied with equal advantage. The date of the oldest religious
                    foundation in the peninsula is not clearly ascertained, and the traditional
                    chronology of the monks themselves can hardly be trusted. A bull of Romanus
                    Lecapenus speaks of the restoration of the monastery of Xeropotamu in 924, and
                    as early as 885 a rescript of Basil the Macedonian forbids the molestation of
                    the “holy hermits.” Lavra, on Mount Athos proper, was founded by St Athanasius
                    in 960; the village of Caryes or “The Hazels,” was appointed as the seat of
                    government about the same time; and shortly afterwards there followed the
                    establishments Iveron (τών Ι∕3rjpωv), Vatopedi (∕3ατo7τeδi,ov), and Sphigmenu
                    (τoυ Εσφtγju∈voυ). The family of the Comneni (1056-1204) bestowed great
                    privileges on the existing monastaries, and added to their number. In the reign
                    of Alexius the first purely Slavonic monastery (that of Chilandari) was founded
                    by the Servian prince Stephen Nemenja. The taking of Constantinople by the
                    Latins in 1204 brought persecution and pillage on the monks; this reminded them
                    of earlier Saracenic invasions, and led them to appeal for protection to Pope
                    Innocent III., who gave them a favourable reply. Under the Palaeologi they
                    recovered their prosperity, and were enriched by gifts from various sources. In
                    the 14th century the peninsula became the chosen retreat of several of the
                    emperors, and the monasteries were thrown into commotion by the famous dispute
                    about the mystical Hesychasts. Their numbers were gradually increased by the
                    foundation of St Dionysius, Simopetra, Constamonitu, Russico, St Paul. In the
                    15th century the monks made terms with the Turkish conqueror Amurath, and have
                    since been molested by none of the sultans, except Soliman the Magnificent, who
                    laid waste some parts of the peninsula. In 1545 Stavroniceta, the last
                    monastery, was added to the list. The hospodars of Wallachia, who were
                    recognised as the protectors of Athos, enriched the communities with lands; but
                    a process of secularisation was commenced by <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n26/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0903-0026-0015"/> Capodistrias, who confiscated their holdings
                    in Greece; and more recently they have been stripped of theiι possessions in the
                    Danubian principalities. They still retain some property in parts of the
                    Archipelago. A Turkish official resides at Caryes, and collects the taxes, which
                    amount to about ten shillings a head; but for the most part the peninsula is
                    autonomous, being governed by an administrative body of four presidents
                    (ότιστάται), one of whom bears the title of “First Man of Athos,” and a
                    representative body called the Holy Synod, which consists of twenty members, one
                    from each of the monasteries proper. These twenty communities are partly
                    Ccenobitic, with a common stock and a warden, and partly Idiorrhyth-mic, with a
                    kind of republican government and great individual liberty. Besides these
                    regular monasteries, there are a number of <hi rend="italic">ασκητήρια,</hi> or
                    sketes, which consist of several small associations gathered round a central
                    church, and numerous little communities known as <hi rend="italic"
                        >καθίσματα,</hi> or retreats, as well as genuine hermitages. Harmony is not
                    always maintained between the different establishments, as was shown by a bitter
                    dispute about a water-course between Cutlumusi and Pantocratoros, which led to
                    the interference of the British consuls of Salonica and Cavalia, in answer to an
                    appeal from some Ionian monks who were British subjects (1853). For the most
                    part, however, the inhabitants of Athos are quiet and moderately industrious.
                    They are said to number about 3000, all men; for no female, even of the lower
                    animals, is permitted to desecrate the precincts of the Holy Mountain.</p>
                <p>“Descriptio Montis Atho et xxii. ejusMonast., <hi rend="superscript"> ,,</hi> by
                    Jo. Comnenus in Montfaucon’s <hi rend="italic">Palaeographia Graeca;</hi>
                    Georgirenes, <hi rend="italic">Description of Present State of Samos, Patmos,
                        Nicaria, and Mount Athos,</hi> Lond. 1678; Lieut. Webber Smith, “On Mount
                    Athos,” &lt;⅛c., in <hi rend="italic">Journ. Roy. Geog. Soc.,</hi> 1837; Curzon,
                        <hi rend="italic">Visits to Monasteries in the Levant,</hi> 1849;
                    Falimerayer, <hi rend="italic">Fragmenta</hi><hi rend="italic">aus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">dem Orient,</hi> 1845; Gass, <hi rend="italic">Commentatio
                        Historica,</hi> &amp;c., and <hi rend="italic">Zur Geschichte,</hi> tc.,
                    1866; Ramner’s <hi rend="italic">Hist.</hi><hi rend="italic">Taschenbuch,</hi>
                    1860 (art. by Pischon); Report by Μ. Minoide Minas, 1846; J. Miiller, <hi
                        rend="italic">Denkmäler</hi><hi rend="italic">in</hi><hi rend="italic">den
                        Klöstern</hi><hi rend="italic">von Athos;</hi> Langlois, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Athos,</hi> Ac.; Didron’s <hi rend="italic">Iconographie Chrétienne,</hi>
                    1844; <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi><hi rend="italic">Asiatique,</hi> 1867;
                    Tozer’s <hi rend="italic">Highlands of Turkey,</hi> 1869.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
