<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0062-0051-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ATTACHMENT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 51</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1078061">Processions</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1078016">Process</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4b853m90">Processions</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4930p29x">Process</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n62/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ATTACHMENT</label>, in <hi rend="italic">English Law,</hi> is
                    a process from a court of record, awarded by the justices at their discretion,
                    on a bare suggestion, or on their owm knowledge, and is properly grantable in
                    cases of contempt. It differs from arrest, in that he who arrests a man carries
                    him to a person of higher power to be forthwith disposed of; but he that
                    attaches keeps the party attached, and presents him in court at the day
                    assigned, as appears by the words of the writ. Another difference is, that
                    arrest is only upon the body of a man, whereas an attachment is often upon his
                    goods. It is distinguished from distress in not extending to lands, as the
                    latter does; nor does a distress touch the body, as an attachment does. Every
                    court of record has power to fine and imprison for contempt of its authority.
                    Attachment being merely a process to bring the defendant before the court, is
                    not necessary in cases of contempt in the presence of the court itself.
                    Attachment will be granted against peers and members of Parliament, only for
                    such gross contempts as rescues, disobedience to the Queen’s writs, and the
                    like. Attachment will not lie against a corporation. The County Courts in this
                    respect are regulated by the 9 and 10 Vict. c. 95, § 113, and the 12 and 13
                    Vict. c. 101, § 2. They can only punish for contempts committed in presence of
                    the court. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Contempt of Court.)</hi> Attachments are
                    granted on a rule in the first instance to show cause, which must be personally
                    served before it can be made absolute, except for non-payment of costs on a
                    master’s allocatur, and against a sheriff for not obeying a rule to return a
                    writ or to bring in the body. The offender is then arrested, and when committed
                    will be compelled to answer interrogatories, exhibited against him by the party
                    at whose instance the proceedings have been had; and the examination when taken
                    is referred to the master, who reports thereon, and on the contempt being
                    reported, the court gives πιdgment according to its discretion, in the same
                    manner as upon a conviction tor a misdemeanour at common law. Sir W. Blackstone
                    observes that “this method of making the defendant answer upon oath to a
                    criminal charge is not agreeable to the genius of the common law in any other
                    instance,” and it may be added that the elasticity of the legal definitions of
                    contempt of court, especially with respect to comments on judicial proceedings,
                    is the subject of much complaint.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Attachment out of</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Chancery</hi>
                    enforced answeιs and obedience to decrees and orders of that court, now merged
                    in the High Court of Justice under the Judicature Act, 1873, and was made out
                    without order upon an affidavit of the due service of the process, &amp;c., with
                    whose requirements compliance was sought. A corporation, however, is proceeded
                    against by distringas and not by attachment. It was formerly competent to the
                    plaintiff to compel the appearance of a defendant in Chancery by attachment, but
                    the usual course was to enter appearance for him in case of default. By the
                    proposed rules under the Judicature Act, 1873, a writ of attachment is to have
                    the same force and effect as the old attachment out of Chancery. It is one of
                    the modes of execution allowed for the recovery of property other than land or
                    money.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Attachment of tπe Forest</hi> is the proceeding in the
                    Courts of Attachments, Woodmote, or Forty Days’ Courts. These courts have now
                    fallen into absolute desuetude. They were held before the verderers of the royal
                    forests in different parts of the kingdom once in every forty days, for the
                    purpose of inquiring into all offences against <hi rend="italic">“vert</hi> and
                    venison.” The attachment is by the bodies of the offenders, if taken in the very
                    act of killing venison, or stealing wood, or preparing so to do, or by fresh and
                    immediate pursuit after the act is done; else they must be attached by their
                    goods. These attachments were received by the verderers and enrolled, and
                    certified under their seals to the Court of Justice seat, or Sweinmote, which
                    formed the two superior of the forest courts.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Attachment, Foreign,</hi> is an important custom prevailing
                    in the city of London, whereby a creditor may attach money owing to his debtor,
                    or property belonging to him in the possession of third parties. The person
                    holding the property or owing the money must be within the city at the time of
                    being served with the process, but all persons are entitled to the benefit of
                    the custom. The plaintiff having commenced his action, and made a satisfactory
                    affidavit of his debt, is entitled to issue attachment, which thereupon affects
                    all the money or property of the defendant in the hands of the third party, who
                    in these proceedings is called the <hi rend="italic">garnishee.</hi> The
                    garnishee, of course, has as against the attachment all the defences which would
                    be available to him against the defendant, his alleged creditor. The garnishee
                    may plead payment under the attachment, if there has been no fraud or collusion,
                    in bar to an action by the defendant for his debt or property. The court to
                    which this process belongs is the Mayor’s Court of London, the procedure in
                    which is regulated by 20 and 21 Vict. c. 157. This custom, and all proceedings
                    relating thereto, are expressly exempted from the operation of the Debtor’s Act,
                    1869. Similar customs exist in Bristol and a few other towns in England, and
                    also in Scotland. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Arrest</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Arrestment.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Attachment of Debts.—</hi> It was
                    suggested by the common law commissioners in 1853 that a remedy analogous to
                    that of Foreign Attachment might be made available to creditors, after judgment,
                    against debts due to their debtors. Accordingly, the Common Law Procedure Act,
                    1854, enacted that any creditor, having obtained judgment in the superior
                    courts, should have an order that <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n63/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0063-0052"/> the judgment debtor might be examined as to any
                    debts due and owing to him before a master of the court. On affidavit that the
                    judgment was still unsatisfied, and that any other person within the
                    jurisdiction was indebted to the judgment debtor, the judge was empowered to
                    attach all debts due from such third person (called the <hi rend="italic"
                    >garnishee)</hi> to the judgment debtor, to answer the judgment debt. This order
                    binds the debts in the hands of the garnishee, and if he does not dispute his
                    liability execution issues against him at once. If he disputes his liability the
                    question must be tried. Payment by the garnishee or execution against him is a
                    complete discharge as against the judgment debtor. These provisions were, by an
                    order in Council of 18th Nov. 1867, extended to the County Courts. (By 33 and 34
                    Vict. c. 30, it is enacted that no order for the attachment of the wages of any
                    servant, labourer, or workman shall be made by the judge of any court of record
                    or inferior court.) The proposed rules and regulations under the Judicature Act,
                    1873, retain the process for attachment of debts as established by the Procedure
                    Act of 1854.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
