<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0158-0143-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">AVA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 143</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:841747">Burgundians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:939025">Gautamas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:881894">Cousins</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:919522">Face</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210322">Laos</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n158/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AVA</label>, the former capital of the Burman empire, lies in
                    21° 52' N. lat., and 96° 1' E. long. It is situated on the Irawadi, which is
                    here 3282 feet broad, and which, making a bend out of its ordinary course, flows
                    past the city on the north. On the east it has the river Myt-nge, a rapid stream
                    450 feet broad, which flows into the Irawadi close under its walls. From this
                    river a canal has been dug, through which its waters flow on the south-east
                    angle of the city, and are again brought into the same river. On the south flows
                    the deep and rapid torrent of the Myt-tha, an offshoot of the Myt-nge, which,
                    falling into the Irawadi, forms the defence both of the south and of the west
                    face of the town. It is divided into the upper and lower, or the lesser and the
                    larger town, both of which are fortified.</p>
                <p>The brick wall that surrounds the city is 15⅜ feet in height and 10 feet in
                    thickness, on the inside of which is thrown up a bank of earth, forming an angle
                    of 45 degrees. There is a ditch round the outer wall which is inconsiderable,
                    and in the dry season fordable in every part. The lesser town is chiefly
                    occupied by the royal palace, the hall of justice, the council chamber, the
                    arsenal, and the habitations of a few courtiers of distinction. A strong
                    well-built wall of more solid construction than the outer wall of the city, and
                    about 20 feet high, encloses the square in which these buildings are situated,
                    and on the outside is a teak-wood stockade of the same height. The ditch which
                    surrounds the lesser town is, moreover, deeper and broader than that of the
                    city, and when full is not to be forded. There are, however, three causeways
                    across, which communicate with the adjacent country. The circumference of the
                    city, excluding the suburbs, is about 5⅛ miles, but over this extensive area the
                    houses are but thinly scattered; some quarters are, indeed, wholly destitute of
                    habitations, and have the appearance merely of neglected commons. In general the
                    dwellings of the inhabitants are of the most miserable sort, being mere huts
                    thatched with grass. Wretched as are such habitations to European eyes, the
                    poorer classes are perhaps as well lodged here as in any other parts of Asia.
                    Their sleeping-places are elevated 2 or 3 feet from the ground. Some of the
                    houses of the chiefs are constructed of planks, and tiled; but there are not,
                    according to Mr Crawford, more than half-a-dozen edifices built of brick and
                    mortar. Ava, like all the other Burmese towns, is adorned with numerous temples,
                    of which the gilded spires, rising aloft, present on a distant view of the place
                    a splendid and imposing appearance, which is far from being realised on a nearer
                    inspection. The largest of these temples contains two distinct edifices, one in
                    the ancient, the other in a modern form; the former containing an image of
                    Gautama, not of marble, as Symes supposes, but of sandstone. It is in a sitting
                    posture, and is 24 feet in height. The head is 8 feet in diameter. There is
                    another very large temple, and a third named the “Beautiful.” The one called
                    Maong-Ratna is of great celebrity; it is the one in which the public officers of
                    the government take, with the most solemn forms, the oath of allegiance. The
                    temple called Maħa-mrat-muni had an addition made to it some years ago, of which
                    Mr Crawford mentions that the numerous and richly-gilded pillars and splendid
                    ceiling exceeded anything that was to be seen without the palace. Ava contains
                    eleven markets or bazars, composed of thatched huts and sheds, which, however,
                    are well supplied with all that is necessary for the wants of the people.
                    Besides native commodities, there are exposed in these markets the produce of
                    China and Lao, with British cottons, woollens, glass, and earthenware. The
                    Burman monasteries are mostly built of wood; and of those composed of more solid
                    materials, a few ancient ones are nearly all that are to be seen. The only
                    exception is a monastery, built some years ago by the queen, adjoining the
                    palace— an unshapely fabric of immense size, but a very conspicuous object.</p>
                <p>This former capital of the Burman dominions comprehends, according to the
                    political divisions of that empire, the town of Sagaing, on the opposite shore
                    of the Irawadi, and the town of Amarapura, 4 miles to the east. The town of
                    Sagaing extends along the Irawadi for more than a mile and a half, but is of
                    inconsiderable breadth. It consists of mean houses thinly scattered among
                    gardens and orchards, the principal trees in the latter consisting of fine old
                    tamarinds. Over the site of the town and its environs are scattered innumerable
                    temples, some of them <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n159/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0159-0144"/> old and ruinous, others modern. On the river face
                    it has a brick wall about 10 feet in height, with parapet and embrasures like
                    that of Ava, and extending for above half a mile along the river. Amarapura is a
                    large place, and was formerly the capital; but Ava, which was twice before the
                    capital, was again made so in 1822. It continued to be so till 1853, when the
                    present king, on his accession, transferred the capital to Mandalay. To each of
                    the towns of Ava, Sagaing, and Amarapura, are attached districts, the two former
                    of which extend 12 miles along the river, and are of equal breadth. The district
                    of Amarapura is of equal size, so that Ava must be considered as not only the
                    name of the former capital, but of a large district, which includes an area of
                    288 miles, containing, according to the most accurate estimate, 354,200
                    inhabitants; but the city of Ava is not supposed to contain more than 50,000
                    inhabitants, and, according to Mr Crawford, half that number w ould be nearer
                    the truth. The place, taken altogether, affords few indications of industry or
                    commercial enterprise.</p>
                <p>A VALLON, a town of France, in the department of Yonne, finely situated on a
                    granite rock, at the foot of which flows the river Voisin or Cousin. The church
                    of St Lazare, which dates from the 12th century, is a good specimen of
                    Burgundian Gothic. Manufactures of cloth, hats, hosiery, leather, and paper are
                    carried on, and there is a considerable traffic in firewood, which is conveyed
                    by the Voisin, the Yonne, and the Seine to Paris. The town was long an object of
                    dispute between Burgundy and France, but was finally united to the crown on the
                    death of Charles the Bold. It was pillaged by the Leaguers in 1594. Population,
                    6070. Long. 3° 56' E., lat. 47° 30' N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
