<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0903-0180-0165-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AYRER, Jacob (9th edition, volume 3, page 165)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897468">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897549">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:912699">Enthusiasm</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62623">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vs7f">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dj58k71">Enthusiasm</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk98">Devil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jm23j5b">Hell</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n180/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AYRER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jacob</hi></label>, one of the
                    earliest dramatists of Germany, was born in 1560, probably at Nuremberg,—at
                    least he resided there when a mere boy. His first occupation was keeping an
                    iron-store, which he did with considerable success. After studying law for some
                    time at Bamberg, where he attained a good position as a lawyer, he returned to
                    Nuremberg, and continued to practise there, acquiring the freedom of the city in
                    1594, and ultimately becoming an imperial notary. He died 26th March 1605.
                    Ayrer’s works consist of numerous small poems, and of the series of dramas on
                    which his fame rests. Like other dramas of the time, his productions are, for
                    the most part, spectacular displays, with laboured dialogue, and vary in length
                    from five to twenty-eight acts. The plots are plainly taken from the Latin and
                    Italian tales which supplied material to nearly all the early European
                    dramatists. The chief interest of Ayrer’s works for English readers arise from
                    their connection with Shakespeare. Ayrer adopted several of Shakespeare’s plots,
                    as well a3 his method of representing the characters on the stage after life,
                    “and so produced,” says his editor, “according to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >neιυ</hi> English manner and art, that all can be personally acted and
                    placed so that it shall seem to the spectators to be really happening.” In
                    Ayrer’s time the dramatic spirit in England was strong, and good plays and
                    players abounded. Some of the latter took circuits through Germany, and though
                    performing in their native tongue, excited enthusiasm by their vivacity. Ayrer
                    caught this enthusiasm, and adapted several of the English dramas to the German
                    stage. The <hi rend="italic">Opus</hi><hi rend="italic">Theatricum,</hi> in one
                    folio volume of 1262 pages, was published posthumously in 1618. It contained
                    thirty plays and thirty-six carnival interludes. A second volume to contain
                    forty more, though promised, did not appear. Of the comedies and tragedies of
                    Ayrer, six have been reproduced with an English translation in Cohn’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare in Germany.</hi> These contain respectively plots
                    resembling <hi rend="italic">The Tempest, Much Ado about Noticing, The Two
                        Gentlemen of Verona, Titus</hi><hi rend="italic">Andronicus,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Hamlet.</hi> In
                    1601, a comic prose work by Ayrer was published, giving an account of an <hi
                        rend="italic">Imaginary Suit of the Devil against Jesus Christ for
                        Destroying Hell.</hi> Some of his plays were published prior to 1585, but
                    these are not now to be had, and even the folio of 1618 is extremely rare.
                    Further information about Ayrer may be gained from Tieck’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Deutsches Theater,</hi> vol. i.; Wolff’s <hi rend="italic">Encyc.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">der Deutschen Nationalliteratur,</hi> vol. i.; Cohn’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Shakespeare in Germany;</hi> Dr Bell’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Shakespeare's Puck, and his Folklore;</hi> Dr Latham’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Two Dissertations on “Hamlet</hi> W. J. Thom’s <hi rend="italic">Three
                        Notelets on Shakespeare.</hi></p>
                <p>ΑΥΤΟΝ, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Robert</hi> (1570-1638), a Scottish lyrical poet,
                    the second son of Andrew Ayton of Kinaldie in Fifeshire, was educated at the
                    University of St Andrews, and seems afterwards to have resided for several years
                    in France, where he gained considerable reputation as a poet and scholar. On the
                    accession of James VI. in 1603, Ayton published a very elegant Latin panegyric,
                    which at once brought him into notice and favour at court. He was knighted by
                    the king, and held various important offices, particularly that of private
                    secretary to the queen. He was of an exceedingly amiable disposition, and was
                    much beloved by his contemporaries; even Ben Jonson, w ho criticised all other
                    poets so severely, seems to have made an exception in his favour, for he told
                    Drummond that Sir Robert loved him dearly. Ayton’s extant works consist of some
                    Latin poems, and of a few pieces in the English dialect, which are distinguished
                    by smoothness of rhythm and delicacy of fancy. His best ode, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Inconstancy Reproved,</hi> beginning, “I do confess thou’rt smooth and
                    fair,” may take rank w ith the finest pieces of Herrick or Suckling, while a few
                    others are but little inferior. His poems have been collected and published by
                    C. Rogers (Edin. 1844).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
