<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0084-0073-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">AUGUSTAN HISTORY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 73</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205669">Jordan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n84/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">AUGUSTAN HISTORY</label> is the title bestowed upon a
                    collection of the biographies of the Roman emperors, from Hadrian to Carinus,
                    written under Diocletian and Constantine<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n85/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0085-0074"/>, and usually regarded as the composition of six
                    authors,—Aelius Spartianus, Julius Capitolinus, Aelius Lampridius, Vulcatius
                    Gallicanus, Trebellius Pollio, and Flavius Vopiscus. Upon investigation,
                    however, there appears good reason for reducing these writers to four. The
                    distribution of the respective biographies among them, according to the
                    arrangement of the MSS., is supported by no extraneous authority, and depends
                    upon no intelligible principle. Without entering into detail, for which space
                    fails us, it must suffice to state that up to and including the biography of
                    Alexander Severus, the authorship of the various memoirs is interchanged among
                    Spartianus, Lampridius, and Capitolinus, in a manner only explicable upon the
                    hypothesis of a division of labour among these writers, or on that of their
                    having selected their subjects entirely at random. The latter is contradicted by
                    their own affirmations, and no trace of any mutual concert is discoverable,
                    neither is there any perceptible difference of style. When, therefore, we find
                    the excerpts in the Palatine MS. assigning all the biographies preceding that of
                    Maximin to Spartianus alone, and remark that his praenomen and that of
                    Lampridius are alike given as Aelius, we cannot avoid suspecting with Casaubon
                    and Salmasius that the full name was Aelius Lampridius Spartianus, and that two
                    authors have been manufactured out of one. We further find Spartianus observing,
                    at the commencement of his life of Aelius Verus, that having written the lives
                    of all the emperors who had borne the title of Augustus from Julius Caesar down
                    to Hadrian, he purposes from that point to comprise the Caesars also. This
                    excludes the idea of his having written without a plan, or in concert with any
                    colleague. His biographies are regularly dedicated to Diocletian down to that of
                    Pescennius Niger, after which, with one exception, probably due to the
                    corruption of the MSS., they are inscribed to Constantine, as would naturally be
                    the case with a work continued under this prince’s reign after having been
                    commenced under his predecessor’s. We may also with probability ascribe to
                    Spartianus the life of Avidius Cassius, attributed in the MSS. to Vulcatius
                    Gallicanus, but whose author describes his undertaking in terms almost identical
                    with those employed by Spartianus. No biography subsequent to that of Alexander
                    Severus is attributed to Spartianus by any MS., and the next series, comprising
                    the Maximins, the Gordians, and Maximus and Balbinus, is undoubtedly the
                    production of Julius Capitolinus, who addresses his work to Constantine, and
                    professedly proceeds, in some respects, upon a different plan from his
                    predecessor. The work of Spartianue must have remained incomplete, and
                    Capitolinus must have proposed to fill up the interval between him and
                    Trebellius Pollio, who dedicates his life of Claudius Gothicus to Constantius
                    Chlorus, and whom we know, from the testimony of Vopiscus, to have written the
                    lives of the Philippi and their successors up to Claudius, some years before 303
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> In that year (and not 291 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.d.,</hi> as supposed by Salmasius and Clinton) Vopiscus was solicited by the
                    urban prefect, Junius Tiberianus, to undertake the life of Aurelian; this
                    biography appears from internal evidence to have been published by 307 A.D., and
                    the live3 of Aurelian’s successors down to Carinus were added before the death
                    of Diocletian in 313. We may therefore reduce the Augustan historians from six
                    to four, and assign their respective shares as follows: To Spartianus, the
                    biographies from Juliu3 Caesar to Alexander Severu3, all anterior to Hadrian
                    being lost; to Capitolinus, those from Maximin to the younger Gordian; to
                    Trebellius Pollio, the lives of Valerian, Gallienus, the “Thirty Tyrants,” and
                    Claudius Gothicus, those of the Philippi, the Decii, Gallus, Aemilianus, and
                    part of Valerian’s being lost; to Vopiscus, the remainder, from Aurelian to
                    Carinus. Some difficulty iβ created by the mention of Capitolinus, the latest
                    biographer in order of composition, by his predecessor Vopiscus, but the passage
                    may be an interpolation, or may refer to some other work.</p>
                <p>The importance of the Augustan history as a repertory of information is very
                    considerable, but its literary pretensions are of the humblest order. The
                    writers’ standard was confessedly low. “My purpose,” says Vopiscus, “has been to
                    provide materials for more eloquent persons than myself.” Considering the
                    perverted taste of the age, it is perhaps fortunate that the task fell into the
                    hands of no showy declaimer, who measured his success by his skill in making
                    surface do duty for substance, but of homely, matter-of-fact scribes, whose sole
                    concern was to record what they knew. Their narrative is most unmethodical and
                    inartificial; their style is tame and plebeian; their conception of biography is
                    that of a collection of anecdotes; they have no notion of arrangement, no
                    measure of proportion, and no criterion of discrimination between the important
                    and the trivial; they are equally destitute of critical and of historical
                    insight, unable to sift the authorities on which they rely, and unsuspicious of
                    the stupendous social revolution comprised within the period which they
                    undertake to describe. Their value, consequently, depends very much on that of
                    the sources to which they happen to have recourse for any given period of
                    history, and on the fidelity of their adherence to these when valuable. Marius
                    Maximus and Junius Cordus, to whose qualifications they themselves bear no
                    favourable testimony, were their chief authorities for the earlier lives of the
                    series. For the later they have been obliged to resort more largely to public
                    records, and have thus preserved matter of the highest importance, rescuing from
                    oblivion many imperial rescripts and senatorian decrees, reports of official
                    proceedings and speeches on public occasions, and a number of interesting and
                    characteristic letters from various emperors. Their incidental allusions
                    sometimes cast vivid though undesigned light on the circumstances of the age,
                    and they have made large contributions to our knowledge of imperial
                    jurisprudence in particular. Even their trivialities have their use; their
                    endless anecdotes respecting the personal habits of the subjects of their
                    biographies, if valueless to the historian, are most acceptable to the
                    archaeologist, and not unimportant to the economist and moralist. Their errors
                    and deficiencies may in part be ascribed to the contemporary neglect of history
                    as a branch of instruction. Education was in the hands of rhetoricians and
                    grammarians; historians were read for their style, not for their matter, and
                    since the days of Tacitus, none had arisen worth a schoolmaster’s notice. We
                    thus find Vopiscus acknowledging that when he began to write the life of
                    Aurelian, he was entirely misinformed respecting the latter’s competitor Firmus,
                    and implying that he would not have ventured on Aurelian himself if he had not
                    had access to the MS. of the emperor’s own diary in the Ulpian library. The
                    writers’ historical estimates are superficial and conventional, but report the
                    verdict of public opinion with substantial accuracy. The only imputation on the
                    integrity of any of them lies against Trebellius Pollio, who, addressing his
                    work to a descendant of Claudius, the successor and probably the assassin of
                    Gallienus, has dwelt upon the latter versatile sovereign’s carelessness and
                    extravagance without acknowledgment of the elastic though fitful energy he so
                    frequently displayed in defence of the empire. The caution of Vopiscus’s
                    references to Diocletian cannot be made a reproach to him.</p>
                <p>No biographical particulars are recorded respecting any of these writers. From
                    their acquaintance with Latin and Greek literature they must have been men of
                    letters by profession, and very probably secretaries or librarians to persons of
                    distinction. They appear particularly versed in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n86/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0086-0075"/> law. Spartianus’s reference to himself as
                    “Diocletian’s own” seems to indicate that he was a domestic in the imperial
                    household. They address their patrons with deference, acknowledging their own
                    deficiencies, and seem painfully conscious of the profession of literature
                    having fallen upon evil days.</p>
                <p>The first edition of the <hi rend="italic">A ugustan History</hi> was printed at
                    Milan in 1475, by Bonus Accursius, along with Suetonius. Being based upon the
                    best MSS. it is superior to any of its successors until Casaubon’s (1603).
                    Casaubon manifested great critical ability in his notes, but for want of a good
                    MS. left the restoration of the text to Salmasius (1620), whose notes are a most
                    remarkable monument of erudition combined with acuteness in verbal criticism and
                    general vigour of intellect. Little has since been done for the improvement of
                    the text, which is still in a very unsatisfactory state. The most accurate
                    edition is that by Jordan and Eyssenhardt (Berlin, 1863), grounded on a
                    collation of the Bamberg MS. with the Palatine (now the Vatican) used by
                    Salmasius. The most important separate dissertations on the Augustan historians
                    are that on the sixth volume of Heine’s <hi rend="italic">Opuscula</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Philologica</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Brocks’s essay on the
                    first four of them (Königsberg, 1869); Dirksen’s elucidation of their references
                    to Roman jurisprudence (Leipsic, 1842); Peter’s critical emendations (Posen,
                    1863); Brunner’s monograph on Vopiscus in the second volume of Biidinger’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Untersuchungen zur Römischen Kaiser</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >geschichte,</hi> and J. Muller’s disqui ∙ition in the third (Leipsic, 1868-69).
                    There is no English translation. (R. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
