<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0903-0021-0012-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ATHLETIC SPORTS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 3, page 12</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:806694">Amateurism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1130432">Sports</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1025265">Money</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1086436">Race</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn54">Sports</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n21/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ATHLETIC SPORTS</label>. Although this term is undoubtedly
                    derived from the ancient <hi rend="italic">άθληταί,</hi> the derivation does not
                    exactly indicate its present meaning, inasmuch as our modern athletes are
                    distinctly defined to be amateurs, in contradistinction to professionals. In
                    fact, the former pursue the agonistic art, and should be styled “agonistics,” if
                    we may be allowed to invent such a word, rather than athletes. How the pastime
                    came to be thus named in Britain some fifteen years ago it is hard to say. Till
                    about 1860, all exercises wherein the feet played the principal part were
                    rightly styled “pedestrianism.” Up to that period all prizes, whether contended
                    for by amateurs or professionals, were invariably in money. As the practice of
                    the pastime, however, rapidly spread amongst the former, it was naturally found
                    they were loth to compete on the same terms with, and for similar trophies as,
                    the latter. Hence arose the modern definition of an amateur athlete, viz., “Any
                    person who has never competed in an open competition, or for public money, or
                    for admission money, or with professionals for a prize, public money, or
                    admission money; nor has ever at any period of his life, taught, or assisted in
                    the pursuit of athletic exercises as a means of livelihood; nor is a mechanic,
                    artisan, or labourer.” The moment this definition was brought into force a wide
                    barrier arose between the two classes, and amateurs ceased to. compete for money
                    prizes amongst themselves, or against professionals, on any terms, unless they
                    were willing to forfeit their status. À generic term was required for the new
                    pastime, and in lieu of a better it was entitled “athletic sports,” and its
                    votaries “athletes.” Hence the haphazard origin of the name. The birthplace of
                    the modem pastime was undoubtedly the great universities and the military and
                    public schools. Cricket has always been justly considered the national game of
                    Great Britain during the summer months, and football fills the same position in
                    the winter. For a month or six weeks in spring and autumn the weather and
                    condition of the ground are in a transition state, and fit for neither of these
                    pastimes, and athletic sports step in and appropriately fill the vacuum. About
                    the year 1812 the Royal Military College at Sandhurst inaugurated modern
                    athletic sports; but the example was not followed till about 1840, when Rugby
                    School, Eton College, Harrow School, Shrewsbury Royal School, and the Royal
                    Military Academy, Woolwich, came to the front. Fifteen years later college
                    meetings had become pretty general both at Oxford and Cambridge. Kensington
                    Grammar School had founded the first annual series of gatherings held in London,
                    whilst Cheltenham College led the van amongst English public schools. After a
                    few months’ negotiations the first Oxford <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Cambridge
                    annual meeting was held in 1864, and is justly considered the premier <hi
                    rend="italic">réunion</hi> of the whole year, the interest shown and the
                    attendance of spectators being little, if anything, less than at the annual boat
                    race between the same two seats of learning. Two years later the annual amateur
                    championship meeting was founded in London, when the Oxford and Cambridge
                    victors meet representatives from all parts of the United Kingdom, and contend
                    for the “blue ribands” of the various events. The principal athletic society at
                    present in existence is undoubtedly the “London Athletic Club,” which takes the
                    lead in all matters pertaining to athletics throughout the United Kingdom. In
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit03newyrich/page/n22/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0903-0022-0013"/> England, moreover, there is now scarcely a
                    country town, sea-side watering-place, cricket, rowing, or football club of
                    importance, and probably not a single university or school, which does not hold
                    its annual gathering for athletic purposes. Across the border the professional
                    still far eclipses the amateur element, and there is no meeting of amateurs
                    which can by any means be compared with the autumn Highland gatherings at
                    Braemar and elsewhere. Until recently the two classes contended indiscriminately
                    together, and the prowess displayed by such amateurs as the late Professor
                    Wilson affords ample testimony that gentlemen were quite capable of holding
                    their own against professionals. The number of annual amateur gatherings held in
                    Scotland is, however, extremely limited, and scarcely extends beyond the
                    universities and chief schools connected with Edinburgh, St Andrews, Glasgow,
                    and Aberdeen. In Ireland the origin of the pastime is again attributable to the
                    leading university, viz., Trinity College, Dublin, where the decision of
                    isolated events, from about the year 1845, has given rise to the meetings now
                    annually held in the picturesque College Park at Dublin. The Irish civil service
                    meeting was inaugurated in 1867, since which time the pastime has made
                    marvellous strides in the island, as is testified by important meetings now held
                    annually in Belfast, Cork, and Galway; whilst the recently formed Irish Champion
                    Athletic Club takes the lead, and stands in the same relation to Ireland as the
                    London Athletic Club does to the whole of Great Britain. Athletic sports are
                    also now extending on the Continent, at many great watering-places where
                    Englishmen are in the habit of congregating. Our great colonies of India,
                    Australia, New Zealand, and Canada, too, as well as the United States of
                    America, Buenos Ayres, China, and even Japan, are not without their annual
                    gatherings for competitors of the Anglo-Saxon race. The contests now classified
                    under the name “athletic sports” are, walking, running, leaping, throwing the
                    hammer, and putting the weight. Leaping and running are respectively identical
                    with the dλ∕zα and δρό/χος of the ancient pentathlon; whereas throwing the
                    hammer and putting the <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> weight bear some
                    resemblance to throwing the δίσκος. Spear-hurling, <hi rend="italic"
                    >άκόντιον,</hi> is never practised but by a few gymnastic societies; and
                    wrestling, <hi rend="italic">πάλη,</hi> between amateurs is rarely witnessed.
                    Running and leaping, however, are nearly always combined on every occasion in
                    two descriptions of contests, viz., steeplechasing and hurdle-racing.
                    Race-walking finds most votaries in London, the northern counties of England,
                    and in Ireland, all distances, from 1 mile to 7, being in vogue amongst
                    amateurs. Running comprises all distances from 100 yards up to 4 miles. Leaping
                    may be divided into three principal heads, viz., running high-leaping, running
                    wide-leaping, and running pole-leaping, which are found to be included in nearly
                    every athletic programme. Adjuncts to these are the running hop-step-and-jump,
                    standing high-leaping, and standing wide-leaping, all of which are favourite
                    pastimes in the northern and midland counties of England. Vaulting, too, is
                    sometimes practised, but belongs rather to the gymnasium than outdoor athletic
                    arena. Steeplechasing proper can only be practised over natural courses across
                    country. Its home is to be found at Rugby School, and amongst members of
                    hare-and-hounds’ clubs, who keep themselves in exercise thereby during the
                    winter months. Artificial steeplechase courses are often made on athletic
                    grounds; but the leaps are generally far too sensational, and constructed rather
                    to afford merriment to the spectators than a fair test of the competitors’
                    leaping powers. A prettier sight than a well-contested hurdle race can scarcely
                    be imagined; but few first class hurdle racers are met with outside the
                    universities and public schools. Scotland is undoubtedly the birthplace both of
                    hammer throw ing and putting the weight, yet they are now practised at nearly
                    every English and Irish meeting. 16 lb is the usual weight of the missile except
                    in Ireland, where a 42-lb, and sometimes a 56-lb weight are put, though in a
                    very unsatisfactory fashion. Athletic sports may be practised in a well-rolled
                    grass field, but the best arena is an enclosure, with a regularly laid down
                    running track, the foundation made of clinkers and rubble, and the surface of
                    well-rolled fine cinder ashes. <hi rend="smallcaps">(h. f. w.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
