<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0843-0814-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MORE, Hannah (9th edition, volume 16, page 814)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897468">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kr4b">Falsehood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62623">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n843/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MORE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Hannah</hi></label> (1745-1833),
                    who was born at Stapleton near Bristol in 1745, may be said to have made three
                    reputations in the course of her long life: first, as a clever verse-writer and
                    witty converser in the circle of Johnson, Reynolds, and Garrick; next, as an
                    animated writer on moral and religious subjects on the Puritanic side; and
                    lastly, as a practical philanthropist. She was the youngest but one of the five
                    daughters of Jacob More, a scion of a landed Norfolk family, who taught a school
                    at Stapleton in Gloucestershire. The sisters established a boarding-school at
                    Bristol in 1767. Hannah’s first literary efforts were pastoral plays, suitable
                    for young ladies to act, published in 1773 under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >A Search after Happiness.</hi> Metastasio was one of her literary models; on
                    his opera of <hi rend="italic">Regulus</hi> she based a drama, <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Inflexible Captive,</hi> published in 1774. An annuity from a wealthy
                    admirer set the young lady free for literary pursuits. Some verses on Garrick’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Lear</hi> led to an acquaintance; Miss More was taken up by
                    the great female Maecenas, Mrs Montague; and her unaffected enthusiasm,
                    simplicity, vivacity, and wit won the hearts of the whole Johnson set, the great
                    lexicographer himself being especially fascinated. Miss More was petted,
                    complimented, and encouraged to write. Her ballad, <hi rend="italic">Eldred of
                    the Bower,</hi> was praised and quoted by the highest living authorities; and
                    she wrote for Garrick the tragedy <hi rend="italic">Percy,</hi> which was acted
                    with great success in 1777. Another drama, <hi rend="italic">The Fatal
                    Falsehood,</hi> produced in 1779 after Garrick’s death, was less successful. In
                    these dramas she borrows from Shakespeare situation, imagery, and phraseology
                    with greater freedom than modern criticism would tolerate; but they are written
                    with great vigour, freshness, and effect. Her <hi rend="italic">Sacred
                    Dramas</hi> appeared in 1782. These and the sprightly octosyllabic poems <hi
                    rend="italic">Bas-Bleu</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Florio</hi> (1786) mark her
                    gradual transition to more serious views of life, which were fully expressed in
                    prose in her <hi rend="italic">Thoughts on the Manners of the Great</hi> (1788),
                    and <hi rend="italic">An Estimate of the Religion of the Fashionable World</hi>
                    (1790). She had never been overpowered by the flattering reception given her in
                    fashionable society; she had received its attentions with misgivings and
                    reservations, never touching cards, keeping Sunday strictly, and preferring
                    company where she could have serious conversation; and finally, soon after
                    Garrick’s death, she set herself against theatre-going under any pretence. There
                    is great uniformity of tone and topic in her ethical books and tracts :— <hi
                    rend="italic">Strictures on Female Education</hi> (1799), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hints towards forming the Character of a Young Princess</hi> (1805), <hi
                    rend="italic">Ccelebs in Search of a Wife</hi> (only nominally a story, 1809),
                    <hi rend="italic">Practical Piety</hi> (1811), <hi rend="italic">Christian
                    Morals</hi> (1813), <hi rend="italic">Character of St Paul</hi> (1815), <hi
                    rend="italic">Moral Sketches</hi> (1818). The tone is uniformly animated; the
                    writing fresh and vivacious; her favourite subjects the minor immoralities, the
                    thoughtless self-indulgences and infirmities which are rather indirectly than
                    directly harmful. She was a rapid writer, and her work is consequently
                    discursive and formless; but there was an originality and force in her way of
                    putting commonplace sober sense and piety that fully accounts for her
                    extraordinary popularity. An interesting episode in her literary life was her
                    three years’ labour in writing spirited rhymes and prose tales in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Cheap Repository</hi> series (1795-1798) to counteract the
                    doctrines of Tom Paine and the influence of the French Revolution. Two millions
                    of these rapid and telling sketches were circulated in one year, teaching the
                    poor in rhetoric of most ingenious homeliness to rely upon the virtues of
                    content, sobriety, humility, industry, reverence for the British constitution,
                    hatred of the French, trust in God and in the kindness of the gentry. Perhaps
                    the noblest testimony to Hannah More’s sterling worth was her indefatigable
                    philanthropic work—her long-continued exertions to improve the condition of the
                    children in the benighted districts in the neighbourhood of her country
                    residences at Cowslip Green and Barley Wood. She limited her aims strictly, as a
                    good churchwoman and anti-Revolutionist, to teaching them to read good books and
                    trying to raise their moral tone; but no philanthropist ever laboured at greater
                    self-sacrifice or with purer motives. In her serene old age, philanthropists
                    from all parts of the world made pilgrimages to see the bright and amiable old
                    lady, and she retained all her faculties till within two years of her death,
                    dying at Clifton on 7th September 1833, at the mature age of eighty-seven.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
