<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0213-0204-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MEURTHE-ET-MOSELLE (9th edition, volume 16, page
                    204)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825021">Baccarat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:943029">Glass</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kn24">Glass</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n213/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MEURTHE-ET-MOSELLE</label>, a department in the northeast of
                    France, formed in 1871 out of those parts of the old departments of Meurthe and
                    Moselle which continued French, and deriving its name from the two principal
                    rivers which water it. Prior to 1790 it belonged to ancient Lorraine, or to one
                    or other of the bishoprics of Toul, Metz, and Verdun. It lies between 5° 25' and
                    7° 5' E. long, and 48° 25' and 49° 5' N. lat., and is bounded on the E. by
                    Alsace-Lorraine, on the N. by Belgium and the grandduchy of Luxemburg, on the W.
                    by the department of Meuse, and on the S. by that of Vosges. The superficial
                    area is 2020 square miles. Geologically Meurthe-et-Moselle has five well-marked
                    regions following each other in regular succession from east to north-west. On
                    the frontier of Alsace are the Vosges mountains, of Trias sandstone <hi
                    rend="italic">{grès</hi><hi rend="italic">Vosgiens),</hi> with a maximum
                    elevation of 3000 feet. Ä narrow band of variegated sandstone divides the Vosges
                    from the second region, formed of shelly limestone, which extends as far as the
                    Meurthe on the north and the Moselle on the west. The third region is formed by
                    the variegated marls which cover the rich saline strata of the neighbourhood of
                    Nancy. The Jura limestones of the Lias and Oolite, to the north-west and west of
                    the department, form the last two regions. Here there is a maximum elevation of
                    1400 feet, and the plateau of Briey stretches out towards that of the Ardennes.
                    Between the Vosges and the Ardennes the valley of the Moselle runs from south to
                    north, forming the main artery of the department; the lowest level (570 feet)
                    occurs where the river leaves it. Only a small part of the drainage of
                    Meurthe-et-Moselle flows into the Meuse. The Moselle runs north-west from its
                    entrance into the department as far as Toul; north-east from Toul to Frouard,
                    where it receives its principal affluent, the Meurthe, and becomes navigable;
                    north from Frouard to Pagny-sur-Moselle, passing to Pont à Mousson. The
                    principal affluents of the Moselle are the Madon and the Orne on the left, and
                    on the right, besides the Meurthe, the Seille, which in one part of its course
                    forms the boundary of Alsace-Lorraine. The Meurthe, which flows to the
                    north-west from Raon l’Étape to Frouard, passes on to Baccarat, Lunéville, St
                    Nicholas, and Nancy, and is swelled on the right by the Vezouse and the Sanon,
                    and on the left by the Mortagne. The principal tributary of the Meuse within the
                    department is the Chiers, which takes its course by Longwy and Longuyon.
                    Climatologically Meurthe-et-Moselle belongs to the Vosgian region. Its mean
                    annual temperature is 52° Fahr., being 2° Fahr, lower than that of Paris (which
                    has the same latitude). The thermometer in severe winters falls to 13° Fahr.,
                    while in summer it reaches 100° Fahr. This is to be accounted for by the general
                    elevation of the department, the proximity of the mountains, the arrangement of
                    the valleys (which lie open towards the north), and the distance from the
                    sea.</p>
                <p>More than half of the department consists of culturable land, onefourth of
                    forests, and one-tenth of meadow land. In 1878 there were 54,346 horses, more
                    than 100,000 sheep, 85,000 pigs, 74,000 cattle, 15,000 goats, 21,000 dogs, and
                    17,000 hives of bees. The crops for the same year amounted to 454,192 quarters
                    of wheat, 37,500 quarters of barley, 35,078 quarters of rye, 570,884 quarters of
                    oats, 9,079,125 bushels of potatoes, and 76,868 tons of beet-root. Hops,
                    tobacco, colza, hemp, and flax also occupy a considerable area. The annual yield
                    of the vineyards (56 square miles in extent) exceeds £900,000; the wines of Toul
                    are the best. The most common fruit trees are the pear, the apple, the walnut,
                    the cherry, and the plum. Of forest trees the oak and the wych-elm are most
                    frequent in the west of the department, the beech and the fir in the Vosges. The
                    French school of forestry has its seat at Nancy. The metallurgic industry is
                    highly developed, and has made very rapid progress within the last few years.
                    Even in 1872 there was a consumption of 350,000 tons of coal, four-fifths of
                    which came from Saarbruck, and the remaining fifth from Belgium. In 1877 the
                    iron ore obtained amounted to 1,000,000 tons, of which two-thirds came from the
                    beds near Nancy, the remainder from the neighbourhood of Longwy. In 1880 the
                    department produced a third of the pig-iron made in France (more than 500,000
                    tons).</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n214/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0214-0205"/>
                <p>In 1877 the yield was 43,000 tons. Besides blast-furnaces, forges, and
                    rolling-mills, there are manufactories of files and boring tools, agricultural
                    implements, and furniture. In the production of salt the department holds the
                    first rank in France; the salt-bearing tracts cover more than 150 square miles,
                    the beds having a mean thicknessof 65 feet. The principal salt-working centres
                    (St Nicolas, Varangeville, and Rosières-aux-Salines) lie between Nancy and
                    Lunéville; the annual value of rock-salt and refined salt produced exceeds
                    £500,000; subsidiary to this production is an important manufacture of soda
                    salts. The other chemical products are prussiate of potash, bone-black,
                    wax-candles, soap, and matches. Stone quarrying and the manufacture of plaster
                    and lime are also important branches of industry. The flint-glass manufactory of
                    Baccarat, which employs nearly 1500 workmen, is well known; that of plate-glass
                    at Cirey (with 1000 workmen) produces plates of great size. The faience
                    manufactories of Lunéville, Toul, and Longwy are important. Mention may also be
                    made of the manufacture of window-glass, watch-glasses, and drinking-glasses.
                    The tobacco manufacture at Nancy employs 1000 workmen; tanning, glove-making,
                    hat-making in felt and straw, wool-spinning, and the manufacture of army
                    clothing are also carried on. Nancy is renowned for its embroidery, which is,
                    however, diminishing in importance. It also possesses factories for cotton
                    spinning and cotton stuffs, and for hosiery. The starch manufactories and the
                    breweries, especially that of Tantonville, the largest in France, are highly
                    productive. Nancy also carries on distilleries, grainmills, paper-mills,
                    manufactories of pasteboard objects, and a large printing establishment. The
                    commerce of the department is effectively served by 300 miles of railway (the
                    principal line being that from Paris to Strasburg through Nancy), by a number of
                    good roads, and by several navigable rivers and canals. The main waterway is
                    formed by the canal between the Marne and the Rhine, which runs by Toul and
                    Nancy, and traverses the department from west to east. This canal communicates
                    with the Moselle, which is navigable from Frouard downwards, and with the new
                    eastern canal, which reascends the Moselle as far as Epinal, and which is
                    intended to unite the Meuse and the Moselle with the Saône and the Rhone. The
                    population of Meurthe-et-Moselle in 1881 was 419,317 inhabitants. It constitutes
                    the diocese of Nancy, has its court of appeal at Nancy, and forms a part of the
                    district of the 6th army corps (Châlons-sur-Marne). There are 4 arrondissements
                    (Nancy, Briey, Lunéville, and Toul), 29 cantons, and 597 communes. The capital
                    is Nancy, and the other principal towns are Pont à Mousson, formerly the seat of
                    a university; Longwy (5064), a fortified place; and Baccarat (6013), celebrated
                    for its glass-works.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
