<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0552-0527-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MISTLETOE (9th edition, volume 16, page 527)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1167829">Viscum</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935548">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150454">Thrushes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c21">Thrushes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn5g">Oak</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j6845h">Arboretums</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n552/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MISTLETOE</label><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Greek <hi rend="italic">lξia</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >lξ&lt;fs,</hi> hence Latin <hi rend="italic">viscum,</hi> Italian <hi
                    rend="italic">vischio</hi> or <hi rend="italic">visco,</hi> and French <hi
                    rend="italic">gui.</hi> The English word is the Anglo-Saxon <hi rend="italic"
                    >misteltan,</hi> Icelandic <hi rend="italic">mistelteinn,</hi> in which <hi
                    rend="italic">tan</hi> or <hi rend="italic">teinn</hi> means a twig, and <hi
                    rend="italic">mistel</hi> may be associated either with <hi rend="italic"
                    >mist</hi> in the sense of fog, gloom, because of the prominence of mistletoe in
                    the dark season of the year, or with the same root in the sense of dung (from
                    the character of the berries or the supposed mode of propagation).</p></note><hi
                    rend="italic">(Viscum</hi><hi rend="italic">album,</hi> I..), a species of <hi
                    rend="italic">Viscum,</hi> of the family <hi rend="italic">Loranthaceae.</hi>
                    The whole genus is parasitical, and seventy-six species have been described; but
                    only the mistletoe proper is a native of Europe. It forms an evergreen bush,
                    about 4 feet in length, thickly crowded with (falsely) dichotomous branches and
                    opposite leaves. The leaves are about 2 inches long, obovate-lanceolate,
                    yellowish green; the dioecious flowers, which are small and nearly of the same
                    colour but yellower, appear in February and March; the fruit, which when ripe is
                    filled with a viscous semitransparent pulp (whence birdlime is derived), is
                    almost always white, but there is said to be a variety with red fruit. The
                    mistletoe is parasitic both on deciduous and evergreen trees and shrubs, and “it
                    would be difficult to say on what dicotyledonous trees it does not grow”
                    (Loudon). In England it is most abundant on the apple tree, but rarely found on
                    the oak. The fruit is eaten by most frugivorous birds, and through their agency,
                    particularly that of the thrush (hence missel-thrush or mistle-thrush), the
                    plant is propagated. (The Latin proverb has it that “Turdus malum sibi cacat”;
                    but the sowing is really effected by the bird wiping its beak, to which the
                    seeds adhere, against the bark of the tree on which it has alighted.) The growth
                    of the plant is slow, and its durability proportionately great, its death being
                    determined generally by that of the tree on which it has established itself. See
                    Loudon, <hi rend="italic">Arboretum</hi><hi rend="italic">et Fruticetum
                    Britannicum,</hi> vol. ii. p. 1021 (1838). The mistletoe so extensively used in
                    England at Christmas tide is largely derived from the apple orchards of
                    Normandy.</p>
                <p>Pliny <hi rend="italic">(H. N.,</hi> xvi. 92-95; xxiv. 6) lias a good deal to
                    tell about the <hi rend="italic">viscτvm,</hi> a deadly parasite, though slower
                    in its action than ivy. He distinguishes three “genera.’’ “On the fir and larch
                    grows what is called <hi rend="italic">stelis</hi> in Euboea and <hi
                    rend="italic">hyphcar</hi> in Arcadia." Viscum, called <hi rend="italic">dryos
                    hyphcar,</hi> is most plentiful on the esculent oak (quercus), but occurs also
                    on the robur, <hi rend="italic">Prunus</hi><hi rend="italic">sylvestris,</hi>
                    and terebinth. Hyphear is useful for fattening cattle if they are hardy enough
                    to withstand the purgative effect it produces at first; viscum is medicinally of
                    value as an emollient, and in cases of tumour, ulcers, and the like; and he also
                    notes it “conceptum fceminarum adjuvare si omnino secum habeant.” Pliny is also
                    our authority for the reverence in which the mistletoe when found growing on the
                    robur was held by the Druids. The robur, he says, is their sacred tree, and
                    whatever is found growing upon it they regard as sent from heaven and as the
                    mark of a tree chosen by God. Such cases of parasitism are rare, and when they
                    occur attract much attention (est autem id rarum admodum inventu et repertum
                    magna religione petitur), particularly on ’the sixth (day of the) moon, with
                    which their months and years and, after the lapse of thirty years, their “ages”
                    begin. Calling it in their own language “all heal” (omnia sanantem), after their
                    sacrifices and banquets have been duly prepared under the tree, they bring near
                    two white bulls whose horns are then for the first time bound. The priest
                    clothed with a white robe ascends the tree, cuts [the mistletoe] with a golden
                    hook; it is caught in a white mantle. They then slay the victims, praying God to
                    prosper His gift to them unto whom He has given it. Prepared as a draught, it is
                    used as a cure for sterility and a remedy for poisons. The mistletoe figures
                    also in Scandinavian legend as having furnished the material of the arrow with
                    which Baldur (the sun-god) was slain by the blind god Höder. Most probably this
                    story had its origin in a particular theory as to the meaning of the word
                    mistletoe.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
