<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0040-0031-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MERCURY (9th edition, volume 16, page 31)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1045055">Ointments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795828">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844510">Calomel</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104215">Salt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828986">Bavarians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204928">California</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr9z">Ointments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843x1w">Calomel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw47w7c">Bavarians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n40/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MERCURY</label>, in chemistry, is a metal (symbol Hg) which
                    is easily distinguished from all others by its being liquid at even the lowest
                    temperatures naturally occurring in moderate climates. To this exceptional
                    property it owes the synonyms of <hi rend="italic">quicksilver</hi> in English
                    (with the Germans <hi rend="italic">quecksilber</hi> is the only recognized
                    name) and of <hi rend="italic">hydrargyrum</hi> (from υδωp, water, and άργυρο?,
                    silver) inGraeco-Latin.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n41/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0041-0032"/>
                <p>This metal does not appear to have been known to the ancient Jews, nor is it
                    mentioned by the earlier Greek writers. Theophrastus (about 300 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> mentions it as a derivative of cinnabar. With the
                    alchemists it was a substance of great consequence. Being ignorant of its
                    susceptibility of freezing into a compact solid, they did not recognize it as a
                    true metal, and yet, on the authority of Geber, they held that mercury (meaning
                    the predominating element in this metal) enters into the composition of all
                    metals, and is the very cause of their metalhcity. When, about the beginning of
                    the 16 th century, chemistry and scientific medicine came to merge into one,
                    this same mysterious element of “mercury” played a great part in the theories of
                    pathology; and the metal, in the free as in certain combined states, came to be
                    looked upon as a powerful medicinal agent, which position, on purely empirical
                    grounds, it continues to hold to the present day.</p>
                <p>Mercury occurs in nature chiefly in the form of a red sulphide, HgS, called
                    cinnabar, which, as a rule, is accompanied by more or less of the reguline
                    metal,—the latter being probably derived from the former by some secondary
                    reaction. The most important mercury mines in Europe are those of Almaden in
                    Spain and of Idria in Illyria; these until lately furnished the bulk of the
                    mercury of commerce, but they are now almost eclipsed by the rich deposits of
                    New Almaden in California. Considerable quantities of mercury are said to be
                    produced in China and in Japan; minor deposits are being worked in the Bavarian
                    Palatinate, in Hungary, Transylvania, Bohemia, and Peru. At Almaden the ore
                    forms mighty veins traversing micaceous schists of the older transition period;
                    in Illyria it is disseminated in beds of bituminous schists or compact limestone
                    of more recent date.</p>
                <p>Chemically speaking, the extraction of mercury from its ores is a simple matter.
                    Metallic mercury is easily volatilized, and separated from the gangue, at
                    temperatures far below redness, and cinnabar at a red heat is readily reduced to
                    the metallic state by the action of iron or lime or atmospheric oxygen, the
                    sulphur being eliminated, in the first case as sulphide of iron, in the second
                    as sulphide and sulphate of calcium, in the third as sulphurous acid gas. To the
                    chemical mind a close iron retort would suggest itself as the proper kind of
                    apparatus for carrying out these operations, but this idea is acted upon only in
                    a few small establishments,—for instance, in that of Zweibrücken in the
                    Palatinate, where lime is used as a decomposing agent. In all the large works
                    the decomposition of the cinnabar is effected by the direct exposure of the ore
                    to the oxidizing flame of a furnace, and the mercury vapour, which of course
                    gets diffused through an immense mass of combustion gases, is sought to be
                    recovered in more or less imperfect condensers.</p>
                <p>At Almaden this roasting distillation is effected in prismatic furnaces, which,
                    by a second upper (brick) grating are divided into two flats, the lower one
                    serving for the generation of a wood fire, while the upper accommodates the ore,
                    which is introduced through an opening in the dome-shaped roof. To avoid an
                    excessive dilution of the mercury vapour with combustion gases, part of these
                    are led out laterally into a chimney and the rest allowed to strike up through
                    the heap of ore. The large mass of metalliferous vapour produced passes out
                    through a system of pipes inserted laterally into the dome and so arranged that
                    they follow first a descending and then an ascending plane, to lead ultimately
                    into a condensation chamber which communicates in its turn with a chimney. The
                    pipes are formed each of a large number of elongated pear-shaped earthenware
                    adapters (called <hi rend="italic">aludels),</hi> which are telescoped into one
                    another as in the case of the iodine-distillation apparatus, the joints being
                    luted with clay. The lowest row of aludels, which lie in the line of
                    intersection of the two inclined planes, are pierced with holes below, so that
                    what arrives as liquid mercury there runs out into a gutter leading to a
                    reservoir. What of mercury vapour remains uncondensed in the aludels passes into
                    the chamber, the intention being to have it condensed there; in reality a large
                    proportion of the mercury passes out through the chimney (and through the
                    numerous leaks in the aludels) into the atmosphere to poison the surrounding
                    vegetation and the workmen. Similar furnaces to the Almaden ones are used in
                    Idria and at New Almaden; only the condensation apparatus are a little less
                    imperfect. But in all three places the loss of metal is very considerable; at
                    New Almaden it is said to amount to close upon 40 per cent.</p>
                <p>The mercury obtained is purified mechanically by straining it through dense linen
                    bags, and then sent out into commerce in leather bags, or in wrought-iron
                    bottles provided with screw plugs, each holding about 75 lb avoirdupois.</p>
                <p>According to Balling’s <hi rend="italic">Metallurgische Chemie</hi> (Bonn, 1882),
                    the production of mercury in the years named was as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Austria, exclusive of Hungary (1880)</p><p>Hungary
                            (1879)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>369 tons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>180 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Italy (1877)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>55 ,,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Spain (1873)</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>929 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>United States (1875) .'.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2054 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Assuming the amount to be the same from year to year, this gives a total of 3587
                    tons.</p>
                <p>The price of the metal is subject to immense fluctuations; it generally ranges
                    from 2s. to 7s. 6d. a pound avoirdupois.</p>
                <p>Commercial mercury, as a rule, is very pure chemically, so that it needs only to
                    be forced through chamois leather to become fit for all ordinary applications;
                    but the metal, having the power of dissolving most ordinary other metals, is
                    very liable to get contaminated with these in the laboratory or workshop, and
                    requires then to be purified. For this purpose a great many chemical methods
                    have been proposed, which, however, all come to this, that the base admixtures
                    are sought to be removed by treatment with nitric acid, oil of vitriol, or other
                    agents which act preferably on the impurities. The best of these methods is that
                    of Brühl, who shakes the metal with a solution of 5 grammes of bichromate of
                    potash and a few cubic centimetres of sulphuric acid in one litre of water,
                    until the red chromate of mercury, first produced, has disappeared, and its
                    place been taken by green chromic sulphates. The supernatant liquor and chromic
                    scum are washed away by a powerful jet of water, and the clean metal is dried
                    and filtered through a perforated paper filter. The only really exhaustive
                    method is redistillation out of a glass apparatus. Unfortunately the operation
                    is difficult of execution, as mercury “bumps” badly on boiling; but this can be
                    avoided by distilling the metal in a <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi> vacuum. An
                    ingenious apparatus for this purpose, in which the distilled metal itself is
                    made to keep up the vacuum, was constructed lately by Leonhard Weber. A U-tube,
                    the limbs of which are longer than the height of the barometer, is filled with
                    pure mercury, and inverted, the one limb being made to dip into a vessel with
                    pure, the other into another containing the impure, mercury. This second limb is
                    inflated above so that the meniscus is about the middle of the bulb. This bulb
                    is heated, and the consequence is that the metal there distils over into the
                    first limb to add to the supply of pure metal, the impure rising up in the
                    second by itself to maintain a constant level. Dewar has modified the apparatus
                    so that there is no need of a supply of pure metal to start with. Absolutely
                    pure mercury does not at all adhere to any surface which does not consist of a
                    metal soluble in mercury. Hence the least quantity of it, when placed on a sheet
                    of paper, forms a neatly rounded-off globule, which retains its form on being
                    rolled about, and, when subdivided, breaks up into a number of equally perfect
                    globules. The presence in it of the minutest trace of lead or tin causes it to
                    “draw tails.” A very impure metal may adhere even to glass, and in a glass
                    vessel, instead of the normal convex, form an irregular flat meniscus.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Properties.—</hi> The pure metal is silver-white, and retains
                    its strong lustre even on long exposure to ordinary air. At - 38 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0,</hi> 8 C., <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi>- 37 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 0,</hi> 9 F. (Balfour Stewart), it freezes, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n42/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0042-0033"/> with considerable contraction, into a compact
                    mass of regular octahedra, which can be cut with a knife and be flattened under
                    the hammer. The specific gravity of the frozen metal is 14'39; that of the
                    liquid metal at 0° C. is 13'595 (water of 4°C. = 1). Under 760 mm. pressure it
                    boils at 357° '3 C. (675° 'l Fahr.) (Régnault). At very low temperatures it
                    seems to be absolutely devoid of volatility (Faraday); but from - 13° C. upwards
                    (Régnault) it exhibits an appreciable vapour tension.</p>
                <p>The following table gives the tensions “<hi rend="italic">p”</hi> in millimetres
                    of mercury of 0° C., for a series of centigrade temperatures “i,” according to
                    Régnault :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">t≈</hi> 0’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10’ 20°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>100°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>150°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>200°</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>p='02</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'03 '04</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•11</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>'75</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4'27</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19'90</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">t≈</hi> 250°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>300°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>350°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>400°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>450∙</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>500°</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>p=75'75</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>242'1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>663'2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1588</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3384</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6520</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>According to the same authority, its average coefficient of expansion <hi
                    rend="italic">k</hi> per degree C. is as follows: —</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0-100 <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi> C. <hi rend="italic">k≈</hi>
                            '0001815</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0-200° C. •0001841</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0 -300° C. 0001866</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>or</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1/5510</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1/5432</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1/5359</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Its specific heat in the liquid state is Ό3332; that of the frozen metal (between
                    -78° and -40° C.) is Ό319 (Régnault). Its electric conductivity is <hi
                    rend="subscript"> κ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    τ</hi> of that of pure silver (Matthiesen). Its conductive power for heat is
                    greater than that of water, and is proved (by Herwig) to be perfectly constant
                    from 40° to 160° C. Its vapour density (air of the same temperature and pressure
                    = 1) is 6'976 (Dumas), or 100'93 for hydrogen = 1. Hence its molecular weight (H
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> = 2) is 201'86. The atomic weight, by chemical
                    methods, was found = 200 ’ 0 (Erdmann and Marchand); hence mercury-vapour
                    molecules consist of single atoms. Mercury does not appreciably absorb any
                    chemically inert gas.</p>
                <p>Mercury is in constant requisition in the laboratory. It is used for the
                    collecting and measuring of gases, in the construction of thermometers,
                    barometers, and manometers, for the determination of the capacity of vessels,
                    and many other purposes. In medicine it serves for the preparation of mercurial
                    ointment and of “hydrargyrum cum creta” (the chief component of “blue pills ”);
                    both are obtained by diligently triturating the metal with certain proportions
                    of grease and chalk respectively until it is “deadened,” <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> subdivided into invisibly small globules (see below).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Alloys.—</hi> Mercury readily unites directly with all metals
                    (except iron and platinum) into what are called amalgams. In some cases the
                    union takes place with considerable evolution of heat and large modification of
                    the mean properties of the components. Thus, for instance, sodium when rubbed up
                    with mercury unites with it with deflagration and formation of an alloy which,
                    if it contains more than 2 per cent, of sodium, is hard and brittle, although
                    sodium is as soft as wax and mercury a liquid. Liquid amalgams of gold and
                    silver are employed for gilding and silvering objects of copper, bronze, or
                    other base metal. The amalgam is spread out on the surface of the object by
                    means of a brush, and the mercury then driven off by the application of heat,
                    when a polishable, firmly adhering film of the noble metal remains. Copper
                    amalgam containing from 25 to 33 per cent, of the solid metal, when worked in a
                    mortar at 100° C., becomes highly plastic, but on standing in the cold for ten
                    or twelve hours becomes hard and crystalline. Hence it is used for the stuffing
                    of teeth. A certain amalgam of cadmium is similarly employed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Oxides.—</hi> There are two oxides of mercury, namely, an
                    oxide, Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O, called mercurous, and another, HgO,
                    called mercuric oxide. The latter can be produced directly by keeping the metal
                    for a long time in air at a temperature somewhat below its boiling point, when
                    the oxide is gradually formed as a red powdery solid. This solid has long been
                    known as “red precipitate,” or as <hi rend="italic">mercurius</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">praecipitatus</hi><hi rend="italic">per se.</hi> Priestley made
                    the important discovery that the “precipitate” when heated to dull redness is
                    reduced to metal, with evolution of what has since been known as oxygen gas; but
                    it was reserved for Lavoisier to correctly interpret this experiment, and thus
                    to establish our present views on the constitution of atmospheric air. The oxide
                    is easily prepared by heating any nitrate of the metal as long as nitrous fumes
                    are seen to go off (when it remains as a scaly mass, black when hot, red after
                    cooling), or else by precipitating the solution of a mercuric salt with excess
                    of caustic potash or soda, when it comes down as an amorphous yellow
                    precipitate, which is free of combined water. Mercurous oxide, a black solid,
                    can be obtained only indirectly, by the decomposition of mercurous salts with
                    fixed caustic alkalies. Both oxides are insoluble in water, but dissolve in
                    certain, and combine with all, aqueous acids with formation of mercury salts and
                    elimination of water. Thus, for instance,</p>
                <p>Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> 2HN0 <hi
                    rend="subscript"> s</hi> = H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + Hg <hi
                    rend="subscript"> a</hi> (N0,) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>,</p>
                <p>Mercurous nitrate</p>
                <p>HgO + 2HNO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> = H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + Hg(N
                    O <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>Mercuric nitrate.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Nitrates.—</hi> When metallic mercury is set aside with its
                    own weight of nitric acid of 1'2 specific gravity, at ordinary temperatures, the
                    normal mercurous salt Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (NO <hi rend="subscript">
                    3</hi>) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> is gradually produced, and after a day or
                    two is found to have separated out in colourless crystals. These are soluble
                    (somewhat sparingly) in water acidulated with nitric acid, but are decomposed by
                    the action of pure water, with formation of difficultly soluble basic salts.
                    When this salt (or the metal itself) is treated with excess of nitric acid it is
                    oxidized into mercuric nitrate Hg(NO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>) <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, a white crystalline salt, readily soluble in water
                    without decomposition.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Sulphates. —</hi> Cold aqueous sulphuric acid does not act
                    upon mercury, but the hot concentrated acid converts it first into mercurous and
                    then into mercuric sulphate, with evolution of sulphurous acid.</p>
                <p>Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi> = 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + SO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi> = 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + SO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 2 HgSO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.</p>
                <p>Both salts form white crystalline magmas. The mercurous salt is difficultly
                    soluble in water, and consequently producible by precipitation of the nitrate
                    with sulphuric acid. The mercuric salt, when treated with water, is decomposed
                    with formation of a yellow insoluble basic salt, which has long been known as
                    <hi rend="italic">turpethum</hi><hi rend="italic">minerale.</hi> Its composition
                    is SO <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>. 3HgO when produced by excess of hot water.
                    Mercuric sulphate is of importance chiefly as forming the basis for the
                    manufacture of the two chlorides.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Chlorides. —</hi> These are both extensively used medicinal
                    agents. The mercuric salt, HgCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, known in medicine
                    as corrosive sublimate, is prepared by mixing the sulphate intimately with
                    common salt, and subjecting the mixture to sublimation, a little binoxide of
                    manganese being added to oxidize the mercurous salt, which is generally present
                    as an impurity. The process is conducted in a glass flask buried in a hot
                    sand-bath. When the decomposition is accomplished, the sand is removed from the
                    upper half of the flask and the temperature raised so that the chloride HgCl <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> produced sublimes up and condenses in the upper part as
                    a “sublimate.” The salt, as thus produced, forms compact crystalline crusts,
                    which, when heated, melt into a limpid liquid before volatilizing. It is soluble
                    in water, 100 parts of which at 10°, 20°, 100° dissolve 6'57, 7'39, 54 parts of
                    salt. Corrosive sublimate dissolves in 3 parts of alcohol and in 4 parts of
                    ether. This salt, on account of its solubility in water, is a deadly poison.
                    Mercurous chloride, Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Cl <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>, better known as “calomel” (from <hi rend="italic">κaλos,</hi> fair, and
                    <hi rend="italic">μeλ,as,</hi> black, because it becomes dead-black when treated
                    with ammonia, mercuric chloride yielding a white product), is prepared by mixing
                    corrosive sublimate with the proper proportion of metallic mercury (HgCl <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>: Hg) or mercuric sulphate with salt and mercury in the
                    proportions of HgS0 <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>: Hg: 2NaCl, and subjecting the
                    mixture to sublimation in glass flasks. The salt Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    Cl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> is thus obtained in the form of white, opaque,
                    crystalline crusts, which, when heated, volatilize, without previously melting,
                    into a mixture of HgCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> and Hg vapour, which, on
                    cooling, recombine into calomel. For medicinal purposes the sublimate is reduced
                    to an impalpable powder, washed with water to remove any corrosive sublimate
                    that may be present, and dried. Being insoluble in water, it acts far less
                    violently on the organism than mercuric chloride does. Its action, no doubt, is
                    due to its very gradual conversion in the stomach into mercury and corrosive
                    sublimate. Finely divided calomel can be produced, without trouble, by the
                    precipitation of a solution of mercurous nitrate with hydrochloric acid or
                    common salt; but this preparation is liable to be contaminated with mercurous
                    nitrate, and, even when pure, has been found to act far more violently than
                    ordinary calomel does. Hence its use is not tolerated by the pharmacopoeias.
                    According to Wöhler a mercurous chloride, more nearly equivalent to the sublimed
                    article, is producible by heating corrosive sublimate solution with sulphurous
                    acid—</p>
                <p>2HgCl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 3</hi> + H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O = H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> SO <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> + 2HC1 + Hg <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Cl <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n43/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0043-0034"/>
                <p>The writer is unable to say whether Wöhler’s calomel has ever found its way
                    anywhere into medicinal practice.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Iodides. —</hi> The mercuric salt Hgl <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> is produced in two ways, viz., first by mixing the two elementary
                    components intimately and subjecting the mixture to sublimation, and secondly by
                    precipitating corrosive sublimate solution with its exact equivalent of iodide
                    of potassium. In the first case the salt is obtained in yellow crystals, which,
                    on the slightest touch with a solid body, assume and then permanently retain a
                    rich scarlet colour. The precipitation process at once yields the scarlet salt.
                    The salt is insoluble in water, but soluble in alcohol and in iodide of
                    potassium solution. The mercurous salt Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> I <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> is obtained by precipitating mercurous nitrate with
                    iodide of potassium as a dirty-green powder insoluble in water. Both iodides are
                    used medicinally’.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Sulphides.—</hi> Mercurous sulphide, Hg <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> S, does not seem to exist. The mercuric salt, HgS,
                    exists in two modifications, of which one is amorphous and has a black colour,
                    while the other is crystalline and red. The black one is obtained by
                    precipitation of solutions of mercuric salts with excess of sulphuretted
                    hydrogen, or by direct synthesis. The right proportions of mercury and flowers
                    of sulphur are rubbed together in a mortar until the whole is converted into a
                    jet-black uniform powder. This preparation (the <hi rend="italic"
                    >sethiops</hi><hi rend="italic">mineralis</hi> of the pharmaceutist), however,
                    is apt to be contaminated with uncombined sulphur and mercury. Application of a
                    gentle heat causes exhaustive combination. The red sulphide, HgS, occurs in
                    nature as cinnabar, and can be produced artificially from the black. The
                    artificial preparation, known as vermilion, is highly valued as the most
                    brilliant, stable, and innocuous of all mineral red pigments. Vermilion can be
                    produced from the black sulphide in two ways, viz., first by sublimation, and
                    secondly by treatment of it with fixed alkaline sulphide solution. According to
                    Brunner, 100 parts of mercury are mixed intimately with 38 parts of flowers of
                    sulphur, and the aethiops is digested, with constant agitation, in a solution of
                    25 parts of potash in 150 parts of water at 45° C. (the water lost by
                    evaporation being constantly <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> replaced), until the
                    preparation has come up to its maximum of fire and brilliancy, which takes a
                    good many hours. Purely sublimed vermilion has a comparatively dull colour, and
                    must be manipulated with alkaline sulphide solution to give it the necessary
                    fire. The action of the alkaline sulphide consists probably in this, that it
                    dissolves successive instalments of the amorphous preparation and redeposits
                    them in the crystalline form.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Mercuric Derivatives of Ammonia.—</hi> (1) Recently
                    precipitated oxide HgO is digested, cold, in carbonic-acid-free ammonia, and the
                    mixture allowed to stand for a few days. The liquor is then decanted off, and
                    the precipitate washed with alcohol and then with ether, and dried over
                    sulphuric acid. The product is a yellow solid base (“Millon’s base”) of the
                    composition</p>
                <p>N <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> + 4HgO + H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O = N <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Hg <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi> O.2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O + 2H <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O.</p>
                <p>It is insoluble in alcohol and in ether, and requires 13,000 parts of cold water
                    for its solution. It readily unites with all acids, forming salts, which, as a
                    rule, are insoluble in water. Hence all ordinary salt solutions, when shaken
                    with the base, are decomposed with elimination of the base of the salt. Thus,
                    for instance, even such salts as alkaline nitrates, chlorides, or sulphates are
                    decomposed with formation of solutions of caustic alkali.</p>
                <p>(2) A body N <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Hg <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> I <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O, <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> of the composition of the iodide corresponding to the oxide in (1),
                    is produced as a brown precipitate when ammonia or an ammonia salt is added to a
                    solution of mercuric iodide in iodide of potassium mixed with large excess of
                    caustic potash or soda (“Nessler’s reagent”). In very dilute solutions of
                    ammonia Nessler’s reagent produces only a brown or yellow coloration, which,
                    however, is so intense that <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> 5τ∏⅛γrσ-σth of ammonia
                    in about 50 cubic centimetres of liquid becomes clearly visible.</p>
                <p>(3) The chloride NH <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Hg.Cl of the “ammonium” NH <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> Hg is produced as an insoluble white precipitate when
                    ammonia is added to a solution of corrosive sublimate. This substance is known
                    in medicine as infusible white precipitate, in contradistinction to (4).</p>
                <p>(4) The fusible white precipitate was at one time supposed to be identical with
                    (3), and is obtained by boiling it with sal-ammoniac solution. Its composition
                    is NH <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> HgCl + NH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> Cl=N
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi>. Hg. Cl <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Analysis.—</hi> Any ordinary solid mercury compound, when
                    heated in a sublimation tube with carbonate of soda, yields a sublimate of
                    metallic mercury, which, if necessary, needs only to be scraped together with a
                    wooden spill to unite into visible globules. From any mercury-salt solution the
                    metal is precipitated by digestion with a piece of bright copper-foil. The
                    precipitated mercury forms a coating on the copper, which becomes silvery on
                    being rubbed with blotting paper. When the quicksilvered copper is heated in a
                    sublimation tube, it reassumes its red colour with formation of a sublimate of
                    mercury.</p>
                <p>Solutions of mercurous salts with hydrochloric acid give a white precipitate of
                    calomel, which, after filtration, is easily identified by its becoming jet-black
                    on treatment with ammonia. From mercuric solutions hydrochloric acid
                    precipitates nothing; but stannous chloride, in its twofold capacity as a
                    chloride and a reducing agent, yields a precipitate of calomel. On addition of
                    an excess of reagent the precipitate becomes grey through conversion into finely
                    divided quicksilver. Sulphuretted hydrogen, when added very gradually to an acid
                    mercuric solution, gives at first an almost white precipitate, which, on
                    addition of more and more reagent, assumes successively a yellow, orange, and at
                    last jet-black colour. The black precipitate is HgS, which is identified by its
                    great heaviness, and by its being insoluble in boiling nitric and in boiling
                    hydrochloric acid. A mixture of the two (aqua regia) dissolves it as chloride.
                    (W. D.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Therapeutics of Mercury.</hi></p>
                <p>The use of mercury as a therapeutic agent is of comparatively recent date. To the
                    Greeks and Romans its value was unknown, and the Arabian physicians only used it
                    for skin affections. It was not till the middle of the 16th century that the
                    special properties of mercury were fully appreciated, but since that time the
                    metal has continued to hold a high though fluctuating value as a medicine. At
                    first the metal in a finely divided state or in vapour was used; but very soon
                    its various compounds were found to be endowed with powers even greater than
                    those of the metal itself, and with the discovery of new compounds the number of
                    mercurial medicines has largely increased.</p>
                <p>The preparations now in use may be thus classified. (1) Of the preparations
                    containing metallic mercury the chief members are blue pill (pilula hydrargyri),
                    grey powder (hydrargyrum cum creta), and blue ointment (unguentum hydrargyri).
                    The first consists of mercury, liquorice root, and confection of roses, the
                    second of mercury and chalk, the third of mercury, suet, and lard. The power of
                    the three preparations seems to depend on the fine state of subdivision of the
                    mercury they contain; mercury in its ordinary liquid state seems devoid of
                    medicinal properties. It is thought by some that the fine subdivision of the
                    metal leads to the formation of a little oxide, and that the efficacy of the
                    preparations in part depends on this. (2) Three oxides of mercury are employed
                    in medicine,—the red, from which is made red precipitate ointment (unguentum
                    hydrargyri oxydi rubri), the yellow, an allotropic form of the red, and the
                    black oxide. The yellow and black oxides suspended in lime water form
                    respectively yellow and black wash (lotio flava and lotio nigra). (3) The
                    chlorides of mercury form a very important group: calomel (hydrargyri
                    subchloridum) is a white heavy powder; corrosive sublimate (hydrargyri
                    perchloridum) is a heavy crystalline substance. (4) Two iodides are used
                    medicinally; they are known from their colour as the green and red iodides. (5)
                    Nitrate of mercury enters into the composition of a powerful caustic known as
                    the acid nitrate of mercury. It is also the active principle of citrine ointment
                    (unguentum hydrargyri nitratis). (6) In this class only ammoniated mercury and
                    its ointment commonly known as white precipitate ointment, are contained. Of the
                    many compounds not included in the above classification the oleate and
                    albuminate are the most important.</p>
                <p>Mercurial preparations are largely employed as external applications. Several of
                    them are potent agents for the destruction of the lower forms of animal life,
                    and hence are employed to destroy parasites having their habitat in skin, hair,
                    and clothing. The white and red precipitate ointments are specially effective in
                    the destruction of pediculi, and blue ointment is occasionally used for the same
                    purpose. Corrosive sublimate is, however, the most energetic of the mercurial
                    parasiticides, and recent observations seem to show that it is superior to
                    almost all other substances as a germ destroyer. It is sometimes used to get rid
                    of ringworm. It should be remembered that corrosive sublimate is a powerful
                    irritant to the skin, and also an active poison.</p>
                <p>Acid nitrate of mercury is a caustic, and by it warts and small growths are
                    sometimes removed; it is also one of the caustics occasionally applied to
                    prevent the spread of lupus.</p>
                <p>In skin diseases mercurial preparations are largely used, especially in some
                    forms of eczema. A few grains of the red oxide or of ammoniated mercury in an
                    ounce of zinc ointment are often found of great service in this ailment; citrine
                    ointment is also useful.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n44/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0044-0035"/>
                <p>Calomel ointment is not irritating, but rather tends to soothe. It is therefore
                    sometimes applied to irritable rashes; in pruritus ani it is of special value.
                    Mercurial preparations are not usually found of benefit in scaly eruptions. In
                    acne a weak solution of corrosive sublimate is often most effective.</p>
                <p>Preparations of mercury are often used to heal ulcers, especially those of
                    syphilitic origin. Black wash is one of the commonest applications for this
                    purpose. The red oxide ointment is at times employed to stimulate indolent
                    ulcers, and it is capable of removing exuberant granulations (proud flesh),
                    which sometimes retard the healing of wounds.</p>
                <p>Mercury is largely used externally to promote the absorption of inflammatory
                    products, especially in the neighbourhood of joints. The blue ointment is
                    frequently employed for this purpose, more rarely a plaster containing mercury
                    or a mercurial liniment. For effecting the absorption of goitre (Derbyshire
                    neck) the ointment of the red iodide is often relied on, especially in India,
                    where it is customary to expose the patient’s neck to the sun after rubbing it
                    with the ointment. In enlargements of the liver and spleen the application of
                    mercurial ointment sometimes seems to promote reduction in size.</p>
                <p>Taken internally in continued doses, mercury produces a peculiar effect known as
                    salivation. First a metallic taste is experienced; this is followed by soreness
                    of the gums, an undue flow of saliva, and foetor of the breath. Further
                    administration of the drug may increase greatly the salivary flow, and also lead
                    to swelling of the tongue, ulceration of the mouth, and even disease of the
                    jaw-bone. At the same time the blood becomes impoverished, and feverishness with
                    loss of flesh occurs. A single large dose—rarely too a single small dose—may
                    produce some of the above symptoms. They may also follow the inhalation of the
                    metal or its compounds, or their absorption through the skin. The long-continued
                    inhalation of the vapour of mercury acts likewise on the nervous system, causing
                    a peculiar kind of trembling. Mercurial tremor is sometimes seen in
                    looking-glass makers, often in those who work in quicksilver mines.</p>
                <p>Internally mercury is chiefly given for two purposes—(1) to check inflammation
                    and cause the absorption of the products it gives rise to, and (2) to antagonize
                    the syphilitic virus and remove the evils it causes. Some years ago the belief
                    in the power of mercury to control inflammation was almost universal, and it was
                    largely administered in almost all inflammatory affections, but of late it has
                    been much less used, both because it seems doubtful whether it has really the
                    power it was once supposed to have and because of the possibility of evil
                    results from its continued use. In peritonitis and iritis it is still often
                    employed, small doses of calomel being given. Not unfrequently too it is
                    administered in pericarditis and hepatitis, but in pneumonia, pleurisy, and most
                    other inflammatory affections its use is now discarded by many physicians. As an
                    antidote to the syphilitic poison it is still held in high esteem, though
                    opinions vary much as to the extent of its power. There can be little doubt
                    that, given in an early stage of the disorder, it minimizes the secondary
                    symptoms; but it cannot be relied on to prevent their occurrence. It aids in
                    removing the secondary symptoms, and tends to the avoidance of tertiary
                    manifestations, which nevertheless sometimes occur even when mercury has been
                    freely given. The custom of giving mercury till profuse salivation is
                    established has long been abandoned; the aim now is so to give it as to prevent
                    salivation occurring; for this purpose blue pill, calomel, and corrosive
                    sublimate are given in very small doses, but if the gums become tender the dose
                    is decreased or the administration stopped.</p>
                <p>Mercurial treatment is sometimes carried out by rubbing the blue ointment into
                    the skin, sometimes by exposing the patient to the fumes of calomel; syphilitic
                    eruptions are often treated by such fumigation. More rarely mercury is
                    introduced by injecting the albuminate or some other preparation under the skin
                    or by means of suppositories. In children grey powder is generally used when
                    mercurial treatment is required. Children bear mercury well.</p>
                <p>Blue pill, calomel, and grey powder are often used as purgatives, and a power of
                    promoting the secretion of bile is attributed to them. Experimentally it has not
                    been proved that they stimulate the liver functions, but there is good reason
                    for believing that they promote the expulsion of bile from the body. Grey powder
                    is especially valued as a mild and efficient aperient for children, and is often
                    given in the early stage of diarrhoea to expel the irritating contents of the
                    bowel.</p>
                <p>The use of calomel in tropical dysentery, once very prevalent, has within the
                    last few years been abandoned. (D. J. I.. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
