<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0916-0826-0797-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MONTSERRAT (9th edition, volume 16, page 797)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:982526">Jewelers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:849907">Caves</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10x8h">Jewels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m70n">Jewelers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1211569">Montserrat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n826/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MONTSERRAT</label>. Thirty miles to the north-west of
                    Barcelona in Spain there rises a very remarkable mountain of grey conglomerate,
                    24 miles in circumference, and at its loftiest point (San Geronimo) a little
                    more than 4000 feet in height. From the comparative lowness of the surrounding
                    district, and from its extraordinary configuration, it is a conspicuous object
                    for many miles around. The mountain consists of jagged pinnacles and spires
                    rising abruptly from the base of the mass, which is cloven with many clefts, and
                    abounds with steep precipices. It is the <hi rend="italic">Mons</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Serratus</hi> of the Romans, the <hi rend="italic">Monte
                    Serrado</hi> of the Spaniards, and is thus named either in allusion to its
                    jagged appearance, like the teeth of a saw, or because the eastern face is
                    split, as if sawn,—which occurred, say the Spanish legends, at the time of the
                    crucifixion, when the rocks were rent. The arms of the monastery represent a
                    mountain with a saw resting upon it and penetrating some distance into its mass.
                    Its pinnacles and pyramids and sharp angular masses resemble a mountain of hard
                    crystalline volcanic tuff which occurs between Akureyri and Kalmanstunga in
                    Iceland. The effect of Montserrat may be realized faintly if we place ourselves
                    upon the roof of Milan cathedral, and imagine the forest of spires magnified a
                    thousandfold. The central spire will represent San Geronimo. The result of this
                    varied contour in the case of Montserrat is to make it one of the most
                    picturesque places in Europe. Paths wind along the faces of the precipices,
                    ascending to bare grey summit«, descending to sheltered valleys filled with
                    evergreens and flowers. The Pyrenees are seen in one direction, the sea in
                    another, while the Llobregat winds at the foot of the mountain through the
                    village of Monistrol. Manresa and other villages are seen scattered over the
                    plain; and hills covered with a warm red soil alternate with rich valleys.
                    Street says of Montserrat, — “After much experience of mountains, it strikes me
                    more each time that I see it as among the very noblest of rocks.”</p>
                <p>The monastery, a great pile of buildings, stands upon a narrow platform on the
                    edge of a vast chasm in the eastern face of the mountain. It owes its existence
                    to an image of the Virgin, said to have been carved by St Luke, and brought to
                    Barcelona by St Peter in 30 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> When the Moors
                    invaded the province in 717, the image was taken to Montserrat and hidden in a
                    cave. In 880 Gondemar, bishop of Vich, was attracted to the cave by sweet sounds
                    and smells, and there found the image, which he determined to take to Manresa.
                    But at a certain spot on the mountain the image refused to proceed farther;
                    there it was consequently deposited, and a chapel was erected to contain it. A
                    stone cross near the walls of the monastery still marks the spot where the image
                    refused to move. Round the chapel a nunnery was built, and in 976 this was
                    enlarged <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit16newyrich/page/n827/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0916-0827-0798"/> and converted into a Benedictine monastery.
                    Philip II. built the present church. In 1835 the monastery was suppressed and
                    despoiled of the vast treasures which had accumulated during the Middle Ages.
                    But the buildings were allowed to remain, as well as a few of the fathers to
                    take charge of the Virgin’s shrine. At present they number 19; a hundred years
                    ago there were 76 monks, 28 lay-brothers, 25 singing boys, together with
                    surgeon, physician, and servants. The possessions then consisted of numerous
                    hamlets, besides great quantities of plate and jewels, including 85 silver
                    lamps.</p>
                <p>Nuestra Seftora de Montserrat, Patrona de Cataluna, is one of the most celebrated
                    images in Spain, and her church is visited annually by more than 80,000
                    pilgrims. It is a small carved wooden image, “regularly handsome, but the colour
                    of a negro woman,” and possesses magnificent robes and jewels. It has been
                    visited by numbers of sovereigns and high ecclesiastics, and by millions of
                    Catalonians. In September 1881 it was solemnly crowned by Leo XIII., who sent a
                    croλvn from Rome for that purpose. Quantities of <hi rend="italic">ex</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">votos</hi> are offered at the shrine: wax models of injured or
                    diseased limbs, models of ships, pictures and clothes, jewels and silver hearts.
                    As the celebrity and sanctity of Montserrat increased, so did the number of
                    devotees. Ignatius Loyola laid his sword upon the altar of the Virgin, and,
                    placing himself under her protection, started from Montserrat to commence his
                    new life. Many eminent Spaniards, weary of the world, have retired to this
                    monastery to end their days. Some preferred solitary hermitages perched among
                    the rocks. Of these there were fifteen, eleven of which once formed a <hi
                    rend="italic">via sacra,</hi> ending at the summit of San Geronimo. They were
                    destroyed by the French, but the ruins of some of them still remain. From all
                    the view is magnificent; some are indeed placed on the edges of precipices in
                    almost inaccessible places. There are also caves in the mountain, some of which
                    were formerly occupied by monks. The most celebrated of these are the cave of
                    the Virgin, in which the <hi rend="italic">Santa Imogen</hi> remained hidden
                    until found by Gondemar, and the cave of Fray Juan Garin, a notorious sinner,
                    who ended his days in the practice of revolting penances at Montserrat. At
                    Collbato, on the south-east side of the mountain, near the base, there are also
                    some very curious caves.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
