<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-0941-0758-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PITHOU, Peter</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1008230">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844604">Calvinists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962708">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193500941?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">PITHOU, <hi rend="smallcaps">Peter</hi></label>, a
                    Frenchman of great literary eminence, was descended from an ancient and noble
                    family in Normandy, and born at Troyes in 1539. His taste for li terature early
                    showed itself, and his father cultivated it to the utmost. He first studied at
                    Troyes, and was subsequently sent to Paris, where he became the scholar and
                    friend of Turnebus. Having finished his pursuits in languages and the belles
                    lettres, he was removed to Bourges, and placed under Cujacius to study the civil
                    law. His father was well skilled in his profession, and has left a favourable
                    specimen of his judgment in the advice he gave to his son as to the best method
                    of acquiring a knowledge of law; which was, not to spend his time and labour
                    upon commentators, but to confine his reading chiefly to original writers. The
                    latter made so rapid a progress, that at.the age of seventeen he was able to
                    speak <hi rend="italic">extempore</hi> upon the most difficult questions; and
                    his master was not ashamed to own, that even he himself had learned some things
                    of his pupil. Cujacius afterwards removed to Valence, whither Pithou followed
                    him, and continued to profit by his lectures until the year 1560. He then
                    returned to Paris, and frequented the bar of the parliament there, in order to
                    combine a knowledge of practical forms and usages with his theoretical
                    acquisitions.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1563, being then only twenty-four, Pithou published his <hi
                        rend="italic">Adversaria Subcesiva,</hi> a work highly applauded by
                    Turnebus, Lipsius, and other learned men, and which laid thd foundation of that
                    extensive fame which he subsequently acquired. Soon after this, Henry III.
                    advanced him to some considerable posts, in which, as well as at the bar, he
                    acquitted himself most creditably. Pithou, being a Calvinist, narrowly escaped
                    being involved in the massacre of St Bartholomew in 1572; for he was in Paris
                    when this tragedy took place, and in the same lodgings with several Huguenots,
                    who were all killed. It seems indeed to have frightened him out of his religion,
                    which he soon afterwards abjured, at the same time openly embracing the Catholic
                    faith. At a subsequent period, he attended the Duke of Montmorency into England;
                    and upon his return, his great sagacity, invincible good nature, and amiable
                    manners, rendered him a kind of oracle to his countrymen, and even to
                    foreigners, who consulted him upon all important occasions. An instance of this
                    we have in the conduct of Ferdinand, the Grand Duke of Tuscany, who not only
                    consulted him, but even submitted to his determination in a point contrary to
                    his interests. ' Henry HI. and Henry IV. were greatly indebted to him for
                    combating the League in the most intrepid manner, and for many other services,
                    in which he had recourse to his pen as well as to other means.</p>
                <p part="N">Pithou died upon his birth-day in the year 1596, leaving a wife, whom he
                    had married in 1579, and several children. De Thou says he was the most
                    excellent and accomplished man of the age in which he lived; and all the learned
                    have concurred in speaking well of him. He collected a very valuable library,
                    containing a variety of rare manuscripts, as well as printed books; and he took
                    many precautions, but in vain, to prevent its being dispersed after his death.
                    He published a great number of works upon law, history, and classical
                    literature; and he gave several new and correct editions of ancient writers. He
                    was the first who made the world acquainted with the Fables of Phaedrus, which
                    were utterly unknown till they were published from a manuscript in his
                    possession. His numerous works belong to the civil and the canon law, to
                    history, and to literature properly so called. As a jurisconsult, Lefebvre
                    observed of him, “Cujacius discipulo praeripuit <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193500954?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0717-0954-0759"/>ne primis
                    jurisconsultus esset; ille praeceptori ne solus.” He was closely connected in
                    friendship with Cujacius, and, after the death of the latter, he published his
                    master’s Observations on the Roman Law, accompanied with Remarks and Annotations
                    of his own. We are also indebted to him for the discovery of the laws of the
                    Visigoths, which he published in 1579.</p>
                <p part="N">His principal writings on the canon law are, 1. Corpus Juris Canonici,
                    1687, in two vols, folio; 2. Codex Canonum vetus.ecclesiasticum, in folio; 3.
                    Gallicae Ecclesiaein schismate Status, in 8vo; and, 4. A Treatise on the
                    Liberties of the Gallican Church. Pithou also published an edition of the
                    Capitularies, which has since been surpassed by that of Balzuc; a series of
                    French annalists, from the eighth to the thirteenth century; Memoirs of the
                    Counts de Champagne and de Brie; the Historical Fragments of St Hilarius,
                    containing curious particulars respecting the Council of Rimini; and the
                    writings of several ancient doctors of the Gallican Church, of which several had
                    until then remained inedited. We are likewise indebted to him for editions, from
                    the best manuscripts, of several ancient geographers, the Itinerary from
                    Bordeaux to Jerusalem, the works of Salvian, the Declamations of the Roman
                    rhetoricians, Juvenal and Persius, Petronius, and the moral Distichs attributed
                    to Cato. He enriched literature, as already mentioned, with the Fables of
                    Phaedrus,.the manuscript of which had been discovered by his brother, and also
                    with the <hi rend="italic">Pervigilium Veneris,</hi> both previously unknown.
                    Lastly, he amused himself with paying court to the Latin muses; but his poetry,
                    like his eloquence, had no other ornament than it derived from the thoughts.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
