<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-1435-0796-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PLASTER, or Emplaster</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sn7d">Plaster</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tv8w">Plastering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1066423">Plasterers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066410">Plaster</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066425">Plastering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193501435?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">PLASTER, or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Emplaster</hi></label>, in <hi rend="italic">Pharmacy,</hi> an external
                    application, of a harder consistence than an ointment, and which is, according
                    to the different circumstances of the wound, place, or patient, spread either
                    upon linen or upon leather.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Plaster,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Plαister,</hi>
                    in building, a composition of lime, sometimes with sand, or other substance, to
                    parget or cover the nudities of a building.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">PLASTER of Paris,</hi> a preparation of several
                    species of gypsum dug near Montmartre, a village in the neighbourhood of Paris,
                    and hence the name.</p>
                <p part="N">The best sort is hard, white, shining, and marbly, being known by the
                    name of <hi rend="italic">plaster-stone</hi> or <hi rend="italic">parget of
                        Montmartre.</hi> It will neither give fire with steel, nor ferment with
                    aquafortis; but it calcines very freely and readily into a fine plaster, the use
                    of which in building and casting statues is well known.</p>
                <p part="N">The method of representing a face truly in plaster of Paris is this. The
                    person whose figure is designed is laid on his back, with any convenient thing
                    to keep off the hair. Into each nostril is conveyed a conical piece of stiff
                    paper, open at both ends, to allow of respiration. These tubes being anointed
                    with oil, are supported by the hand of an assistant; then the face is lightly
                    oiled over, and the eyes being kept shut, alabaster fresh calcined, and tempered
                    to a thinnisħ consistence with water, is by spoonfuls nimbly thrown all over the
                    face, till it lies near the thickness of an inch. This matter grows sensibly
                    hot, and in about a quarter of an hour hardens into a kind of stony concretion;
                    which being gently taken off, represents, on its concave surface, the minutest
                    part of the original face. In this a head of good clay may be moulded; and
                    therein the eyes are to be opened, and other necessary amendments made. This
                    second face being anointed with oil, a second mould of calcined alabaster is
                    made, consisting of two parts joined lengthwise along the ridge of the nose; and
                    herein may be cast, with the same matter, a face extremely like the
                    original.</p>
                <p part="N">If finely powdered alabaster, or plaster of Paris, be put into a basin
                    over a fire, it will, when heated, assume the appearance of a fluid, by rolling
                    in waves, yielding to the touch, and steaming, all which properties it again
                    loses on the departure of the heat; and being thrown upon paper, it will not at
                    all wet it, but immediately discover itself to be as motionless as before it was
                    set over the fire; wherefore it appears, that a heap of such little bodies as
                    are neither spherical nor otherwise regularly shaped, nor small enough to be
                    below the discernment of the eye, may, without fusion, be made fluid by a
                    sufficiently strong and various agitation of the particles which compose it, and
                    may lose its fluidity when the agitation is discontinued.</p>
                <p part="N">Two or three spoonfuls of burned alabaster, mixed up thin with water, in
                    a short time coagulate into a hard lump at the bottom of a vessel full of water.
                    Artificers observe, that the coagulating property of burned alabaster will be
                    very much impaired or lost if the powder be kept too long, especially in the
                    open air, before it is made use of; and when it has been once tempered with
                    water, and suffered to grow hard, they cannot, by any new burning or powdering
                    of it, make it serviceable for their purpose as before.</p>
                <p part="N">This matter, when wrought into vessels, or other forms, is still of so
                    loose and spongy a texture, that the air finds an easy passage through it. Mr
                    Boyle, in relating his experiments<pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193501448?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0717-1448-0797"/> with the
                    air-pump, gives an account of his preparing a tube of this plaster, closed at
                    one end and open at the other; and on applying the open end to the cement, as is
                    usually done with the receivers, it was found utterly impossible to exhaust all
                    the air out of it; for fresh air from without pressed in as fast as the internal
                    air was exhausted, although the sides of the tube were of considerable
                    thickness. A tube of iron was then put on the engine, so that being filled with
                    water, the tube of plaster of Paris was covered with it; and on using the pump,
                    it was immediately seen that the water passed through into it as easily as the
                    air had done when that was the ambient fluid. After this, trying it with Venice
                    turpentine instead of water, the thing succeeded very well; the tube might be
                    perfectly exhausted, and would remain in that state for several hours. But on
                    pouring some hot oil upon the turpentine, the case was much altered; for the
                    turpentine melting, became a thinner fluid, and in this state was capable of
                    passing like water into the pores of the plaster. On taking away the tube,
                    however, it was remarked that the turpentine, which had pervaded and filled its
                    pores, rendered it transparent, in the manner that water gives transparency to
                    that singular stone called <hi rend="italic">oculus mundi.</hi> In this manner,
                    the weight of air, under proper management, becomes capable of making several
                    sorts of glues penetrate plaster of Paris; and not only so, but also baked
                    earth, wood, and all other bodies porous enough to admit water.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
