<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-0785-0746-15" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PINUS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1064206">Pine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925164">Fir</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130982">Spruce</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw0c">Pine</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gp0v">Spruce</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206063">Lebanon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193500785?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">PINUS</label>, the <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Pine-tree,</hi> was one well known to the ancients, and has been described
                    and celebrated both by their philosophers and their poets. Pliny enumerates no
                    less than six species of trees of this genus; and it is mentioned by Virgil in
                    his Eclogues, his Georgics, and his AEneid; by Horace in his Odes, by Ovid in
                    his Metamorphoses, by Statius, and by Catullus.</p>
                <p part="N">There are generally reckoned fourteen species of this genus, of which
                    the most remarkable are the following :—</p>
                <p part="N">1. The <hi rend="italic">pineα, pineaster,</hi> or wild pine, which
                    grows naturally on the mountains in Italy and the south of France. It grows to
                    the size of a large tree; the branches extend to a considerable distance; and
                    whilst the trees are young, they are fully garnished with leaves, especially
                    where they are not so close as to exclude the air from those within; but as they
                    advance in age, the branches appear naked, and <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193500798?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0717-0798-0747"/>all those
                    which are situated below become unsightly in a few years; for which reason they
                    are now much less esteemed than formerly.</p>
                <p part="N">2. The <hi rend="italic">pinus pinea,</hi> or stone pine, is a tall
                    evergreen tree, a native of Italy and Spain. It delights in a sandy loam,
                    although, like most others, it will grow well in almost any land. Respecting the
                    uses of this species, Hanbury tells us that the kernels are eatable, and by many
                    preferred to almonds.</p>
                <p part="N">• 3. The <hi rend="italic">rubra,</hi> commonly called the <hi
                        rend="italic">Scotch fir</hi> or <hi rend="italic">pine,</hi> is common
                    throughout Scotland, whence its name; though it is also found in most of the
                    other countries of Europe. Μ. Duhamel mentions his having received some seeds of
                    it from St Domingo in the West Indies; and thence concludes, that it grows
                    indifferently in the temperate, frigid, and torrid zones. The wood of this tree
                    is the red or yellow deal, which is the most durable of any of the kinds yet
                    known</p>
                <p part="N">4. The <hi rend="italic">pinus picea,</hi> or yew-leaved fir, is a tall
                    evergreen, and a native of Scotland, Sweden, and Germany. This species includes
                    the silver fir and the balm of Gilead fir. The first of these is a noble upright
                    tree. The balm of*Gilead fir has of all the sorts been most coveted, on account
                    of the great fragrance of its leaves; though this’ is not its only good
                    property; for it is a very beautiful tree, naturally of an upright growth, and
                    the branches are so ornamented with their baΓmy leaves, as to exceed any of the
                    other sorts in beauty. The silver fir is very hardy, and will grow in any soil
                    or situation; but it always makes the greatest progress in rich loamy earth. The
                    balm of Gilead fir must be planted in deep, rich, good earth; nor will it live
                    long in any other. The soil may be a black mould, or of a sandy nature, if it be
                    deep enough, and if the roots have room enough to strike freely.</p>
                <p part="N">5. The <hi rend="italic">pinus abies,</hi> or European spruce fir, a
                    native of the northern parts of Europe and of Asia, includes the Norway spruce
                    and long-coned Cornish fir. The former of these is a tree of as much beauty
                    whilst growing, as its timber is valuable when propagated on that account.</p>
                <p part="N">6. The <hi rend="italic">pinus</hi><hi rend="italic">Canadensis,</hi> or
                    American and Newfoundland spruce fir, a native of Canada, Pennsylvania, and
                    other parts of North America, includes three varieties; the white Newfoundland
                    spruce, the red Newfoundland spruce, and the black Newfoundland spruce. These,
                    however, dif-er so little, that one description may serve for them all. They are
                    of an upright growth, though they do not shoot so freely or grow so fast with us
                    as the Norway spruce. The leaves are of the same green, and garnish the branches
                    in the same beautiful manner, as those of that species; only they are narrower,
                    shorter, and stand closer. The greatest difference is observable in the cones;
                    for these are no more than about an inch in length, and the scales are closely
                    placed. In the cones, indeed, consists the difference of these three sorts;
                    those of the white species are of a very light brown colour, those of the red
                    species more of a nut-brown or reddish colour, and those of the black species of
                    a dark or blackish colour.</p>
                <p part="N">7. The <hi rend="italic">pinus</hi><hi rend="italic">balsamea,</hi> or
                    hemlock fir, a native of Virginia and Canada, possesses as little beauty as any
                    of the fir tribe; though, being rather scarce in proportion, it is deemed
                    valuable. It is called by some the <hi rend="italic">yew-leaved fir,</hi> from
                    the resemblance of the leaves to those of the yew-tree. It is a tree of low
                    growth, with but few branches; and these are long and slender, spreading abroad
                    without order.</p>
                <p part="N">8. The <hi rend="italic">pinus orientalis,</hi> or oriental fir, a
                    native of the East, is a low but elegant tree. The leaves are very short, and
                    nearly square. The fruit is exceedingly small, and hangs downward; and the whole
                    tree makes an agreeable variety with the other kinds.</p>
                <p part="N">9. The <hi rend="italic">strobus,</hi> or North American white pine.
                    This grows sometimes to the height of a hundred feet and up wards, and is highly
                    valued on account of its beauty. The bark of the tree is very smooth and
                    delicate, especially when young; the leaves are long and slender, five growing
                    out of one sheath; and the branches are pretty closely garnished with them, thus
                    making a fine appearance.</p>
                <p part="N">10. The <hi rend="italic">pinus</hi><hi rend="italic">taeda,</hi> or
                    swamp-pine, is a tall evergreen tree, being a native of the swamps of Virginia
                    and Canada. 1here are several varieties of this genus.</p>
                <p part="N">11. The <hi rend="italic">pinus cedrus,</hi> ranked by Tournefort and
                    others under <hi rend="italic">lαrix,</hi> and famous for its duration, is that
                    popularly called by us the <hi rend="italic">cedar of Lebanon,</hi> by the
                    ancients <hi rend="italic">cedrus magna</hi> or the <hi rend="italic">great
                        cedar</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> also <hi rend="italic">cedrelate,
                        κεδfKατη</hi>; and sometimes the Phoenician or Syrian cedar, from the
                    country where it grows in its greatest perfection. It is a coniferous evergreen,
                    of the larger sort, bearing roundish cones of smooth scales, standing erect, the
                    leaves being small, narrow, and thickly set. They sometimes counterfeit cedar by
                    dyeing wood of a reddish hue; but the smell discovers the cheat, that of true
                    cedar being very aromatic. In some places the wood of the cajou tree passes
                    under the name of cedar, on account of its reddish colour and its aromatic
                    smell, which somewhat resemble those of sandal. Cedar-wood is reputed almost
                    immortal and incorruptible; a prerogative which it owes chiefly to its bitter
                    taste, which the worms cannot endure. For this reason it was that the ancients
                    used cedar tablets to write upon, especially for things of importance, as
                    appears from the expression of Persius, <hi rend="italic">Et</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">cedra</hi><hi rend="italic">digna locutus.</hi> A juice
                    alluded to by Horace was also drawn from cedar, with which the ancients smeared
                    their books and writings, or other matters, to preserve them from rotting; and
                    by means of which it was that Numa’s books, written on papyrus, were preserved
                    entire to the year 535, as we are informed by Pliny.</p>
                <p part="N">Solomon’s temple, as well as his palace, were both constructed with this
                    wood. That prince gave Hiram, king of Tyre, several cities for the cedars he had
                    furnished on these occasions. Cortes is said to have erected a palace at Mexico,
                    in which were 7000 beams of cedar, most of them 120 feet in length and twelve
                    feet in circumference, as we are informed by Herrera. Some tell us of a cedar
                    felled in Cyprus 130 feet in length and eighteen in diameter. It was used for
                    the mainmast in the galley of King Demetrius. Le Bruyn assures us, that the two
                    largest he saw upon Mount Lebanon measured, one of them fifty-seven palms, and
                    the other forty-seven, in circumference. In the temple of Apollo at Utica there
                    were cedar-trees near two thousand years old; which yet were nothing to the beam
                    in an oratory of Diana at Saguntum in Spain, said to have been brought thither
                    two hundred years before the destruction of Troy. Cedar is of so dry a nature
                    that it will not endure to be fastened with iron nails, from which it usually
                    shrinks; so that they commonly fasten it with pins of the same wood.</p>
                <p part="N">It is remarkable that, as far as has yet been discovered, this tree is
                    not to be found as a native in any other part of the world than Mount Libanus.
                    What we find mentioned in Scripture of the lofty cedars can be nowise applicable
                    to the common growth of this tree; since, from the experience we have of those
                    now growing in England, as also from the testimony of several travellers who
                    have visited the few trees remaining on Mount Libanus, they are not inclined to
                    grow very lofty, but, on the contrary, extend their branches very far; a
                    circumstance with which the allusion made by the Psalmist agrees very well,
                    when, describing the flourishing state of the people, he says, “They shall
                    spread their branches like the cedar-tree.”</p>
                <p part="N">12. There is another species, namely, the <hi rend="italic"
                        >larch-tree,</hi> which the old botanists ranked under <hi rend="italic"
                        >larix,</hi> with deciduous leaves and oval obtuse cones. It grows naturally
                    upon the Alps and Apennines, and of late has been very much propagated in
                    Britain. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Plantation.</hi></p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193500811?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0717-0811-0748"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
