<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-4870-0291-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PERTINAX</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120522">Slaves</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193494870?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">PERTINAX</label>, an illustrious Roman emperor, who
                    succeeded the detested Commodus. He was descended of a mean family, and, like
                    his father, who was either a slave or the son of a manumitted slave, he for some
                    time followed the humble employment of drying wood and making charcoal. His
                    poverty did not, however, prevent him from receiving a liberal education. For
                    some time he was employed in teaching a number of pupils the Greek and the Roman
                    languages in Etruria. But having left this laborious profession, he became <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193494883?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0717-4883-0292"
                    />a soldier, and by his valour and intrepidity gradually rose to offices of the
                    highest trust in the army, and for his services was made consul by Μ. Aurelius.
                    He was afterwards entrusted with the government of Moesia, and at length
                    presided over the city of Rome as governor. When Commodus was murdered, Pertinax
                    was universally chosen to succeed him in the imperial dignity; and his refusal,
                    on the plea of old age and increasing infirmities, did not prevent his being
                    saluted emperor and Augustus. He complied with reluctance; but his mildness, his
                    economy, and his popularity, convinced the senate and the people of the prudence
                    and the justice of their choice. He forbade his name to be inscribed on such
                    places or estates as formed part of the imperial domains, and asserted that they
                    belonged not to him but to the public. He melted all the silver statues which
                    had been raised to his predecessor, and exposed to sale his concubines, horses,
                    arms, and all the instruments of his pleasure and extravagance. With the money
                    raised from these sources he enriched the empire, and was enabled to abolish all
                    the taxes which Commodus had laid on the rivers, ports, and highways, throughout
                    the empire. These patriotic actions gained him the affection of the worthiest
                    and most discerning of his subjects; but the extravagant, luxurious, and
                    vicious, raised a loud clamour against him; and when the emperor attempted to
                    introduce amongst the praetorian guards such discipline as was absolutely
                    necessary to preserve the peace and tranquillity of Rome, the flames of
                    rebellion were kindled, and the minds of the soldiers completely alienated.
                    Pertinax was apprized of their mutiny, but refused to fly at the hour of danger.
                    Disregarding the advice of such of his friends as wished him to withdraw from
                    the impending storm, he unexpectedly appeared before the seditious troops, and,
                    without fear or concern, boldly asked them whether they who were bound by duty
                    to defend the person of their prince and emperor, were come to betray him and to
                    shed his blood? His undaunted courage and intrepidity would have had the desired
                    effect, and the soldiers had begun to retire, when one of the most seditious of
                    them advanced, and darted his javelin at the emperor’s breast, exclaiming, “The
                    soldiers send you this.” The rest instantly followed the example; and Pertinax,
                    muffling up his head, and calling upon Jupiter to avenge his death, remained
                    unmoved, and was immediately despatched. His head was cut off and carried in
                    triumph to the camp upon the point of a spear. This abominable murder happened
                    in the 103d year of the Christian era.</p>
                <p part="N">It was no sooner known that Pertinax had been murdered, than the enraged
                    populace flocked from all quarters of the city, and, uttering dreadful menaces
                    against the authors of his death, ran up and down the streets in quest of them.
                    The senators were no less concerned for his death than the people, probably
                    because they were now convinced that the soldiers would suffer none but tyrants
                    to reign. However, as they had' more to lose than the common people, they did
                    not offer to revenge his death, but either shut themselves up in their own
                    houses, or in those of the soldiers of their acquaintance. Such was the
                    unfortunate and lamented end of Publius Helvius Pertinax, after he had lived
                    sixty-six years, seven months, and twenty-six or twenty-eight clays; and
                    reigned, according to Dio Cassius, eightyseven days, that is, from the 1st of
                    January to the 28th of March. His body, together with his head, was interred
                    with great pomp by Didius Julianus, his successor, in the burying-place of his
                    wife’s family. Septimius Severus, with the title of emperor, assumed the name of
                    Pertinax, which he knew would, above any thing else, recommend him to the army
                    in Illyricum, and to the Roman people. He punished with great severity all those
                    who had been accessory to his death; disbanded the praetorian guards; honoured
                    his memory with a most magnificent funeral, at which was carried the effigies of
                    the deceased prince; pronounced his panegyric, and caused him to be ranked in
                    the number of the gods, appointing the son chief priest to his father. The day
                    of his accession to the empire was yearly celebrated with the Circensian games,
                    and his birth-day, for many years afterwards, with other sports. He performed
                    great things, says Herodian, during his short administration, and would have
                    restored the empire to its former lustre, had he been indulged with a longer
                    reign.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
