<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-2166-0083-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PARK</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205480">Niger</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1202705">Gambia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x921m3r">Parks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q814s63">Beasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7759r">Moors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1053705">Parks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1201065">Publications</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1083449">Publicity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:799932">Africanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193492166?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">PARK</label> (French <hi rend="italic">parque,</hi>
                    that is, <hi rend="italic">locus</hi><hi rend="italic">inclusus)</hi> is a large
                    extent of ground enclosed and privileged for wild beasts of chase, by the king’s
                    grant or prescription.</p>
                <p part="N">Manwood defines a chase a privileged place for beasts of venery, and
                    other wild beasts of the forest and chase, <hi rend="italic">tarn</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">sylvestres</hi><hi rend="italic">quam campestres.</hi> A park,
                    therefore, differs from a chase or warren in this, 'that it must be enclosed;
                    for if it lie open, this is a good cause of seizure by the king, as a thing
                    forfeited.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Park,</hi><hi rend="italic">Mungo,</hi> a
                    celebrated traveller, was born at Fowlshiels, near Selkirk, on the 10th of
                    September 1771. His father occupied the farm of Fowlshiels, under the Duke of
                    Bucclcuch. He appears to have bestowed uncommon attention on the education of
                    his children; and he even employed a tutor to reside in his house, an expense
                    which was then supposed to exceed the resources of an ordinary farmer. Young
                    Park made a good figure at school. His general demeanour was reserved and
                    thoughtful; yet occasional sparks of ambition broke forth, indicative of that
                    adventurous spirit which lay concealed under a somewhat cold exterior. This
                    thoughtful disposition led his friends to consider the church as the profession
                    best suited to his character; but as he himself preferred physic to theology,
                    his wishes were acquiesced in; and he spent three years at the University of
                    Edinburgh, in the studies necessary to qualify him for that profession.</p>
                <p part="N">At Edinburgh Park studied with ardour and success; and in particular he
                    imbibed a fondness for botany, which served to give a strong colour to his
                    future life. It strengthened his natural connection with his brother-in-law, Mr
                        <pb break="no" facs="nls:193492179?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0717-2179-0084"/>James Dickson, who, notwithstanding many
                    disadvantages, attained such skill in that science, that, on going as a gardener
                    to Hammersmith, he obtained a large share of the patronage and favour of Sir
                    Joseph Banks. This connection induced Mr Park to repair to London. He was
                    introduced to Sir Joseph, who was so much pleased with him that he obtained for
                    him the appointment of assistant-surgeon to the Worcester East Indiaman. In this
                    capacity Mr Park performed a voyage to Bencoolen, where he made some collections
                    and observations in botany and natural history, which were submitted to the
                    Linnaean Society, and an account of them printed in the third volume of their
                    Transactions.</p>
                <p part="N">The African Association were now anxiously looking out for a successor
                    to Major Houghton, their unfortunate missionary, who had perished in the attempt
                    to penetrate to the Niger and Timbuctoo. This opening, although foreign to any
                    of Mr Park’s former pursuits except that of natural history, was immediately
                    embraced by him with an ardour which showed how congenial it was to the
                    character of his mind. Without hesitation, he offered himself for this arduous
                    and perilous service, and, being supported by the recommendation of Sir Joseph
                    Banks, he was at once accepted.</p>
                <p part="N">Park spent about two years in and near London, acquiring the
                    qualifications necessary for his mission. In May 1795 he set sail, and on the
                    21st of June following arrived at Jillifree, near the mouth of the Gambia. After
                    spending some months with Dr Laidley at Pisania, in acquiring the Mandingo
                    language, he, on the 2d of December 1795, departed on his grand expedition. It
                    would be superfluous to enter here into a detail of events which are so
                    generally known, and which excited so deep an interest, as his captivity amongst
                    the Moors, his almost miraculous escape, his discovery of the course of the
                    Niger, and of the African capital of Sego, his journey through Bambarra, and the
                    train of peril and difficulty through which he effected his return. He arrived,
                    after the length of his absence, and the want of intelligence respecting him,
                    had nearly extinguished all hopes of his safety. Reaching London early in the
                    morning of Christmas 1797, he went to pass the time before breakfast in the
                    gardens of the British Museum, where, by a singular chance, he met Mr Dickson,
                    who embraced his friend as one returned from the grave. An extraordinary
                    interest in his adventures was immediately excited amongst the African
                    Institution, its friends, and the public in general. Major Rennell drew up an
                    important memoir, showing the new light thrown by his journey upon African
                    geography, which, with an abstract of his narrative by Mr Bryan Edwards, was
                    speedily offered, to satisfy the curiosity of the public. In the spring of 1799,
                    Mr Park presented the public with a full narrative from his own pen. Major
                    Rennell’s memoir was appended, and a considerable part of Mr Edwards’ abstract
                    was incorporated verbatim; upon which circumstance alone seems to have been
                    built the rumour of that gentleman having been the actual writer of the volume.
                    The work was read with an avidity proportioned to the novelty and importance of
                    the information contained in it, and to the interesting and agreeable manner in
                    which the events were narrated.</p>
                <p part="N">Having finished this task, Mr Park seems to have resolved to retire into
                    domestic and professional life. In 1799, he married Miss Anderson of Selkirk,
                    daughter of the gentleman with whom he had served his apprenticeship as a
                    surgeon. In October 1801, he embraced an opportunity which offered, of
                    commencing a professional career at Peebles, and soon found himself in
                    respectable practice. His situation now seemed sufficiently comfortable, being
                    happy in domestic life, possessed of a competence, and surrounded by respectable
                    society; but his active mind was not to be so satisfied, and was secretly
                    panting after a higher sphere of exertion.</p>
                <p part="N">Important as were his discoveries, their effect had been, not to
                    satisfy, but to excite still farther, the public curiosity. The course of the
                    Niger through the unknown and central parts of the continent could not fail to
                    excite peculiar interest. This was strongly felt, not only by the scientific
                    world, but by some intelligent members of administration, who, on the conclusion
                    of the peace in 1801, determined to fit out an expedition on a great scale, to
                    effect the discovery of the termination of this great river. In autumn 1803,
                    Lord Hobart, afterwards Earl of Buckinghamshire, who was then colonial
                    secretary, offered the command of it to Mr Park, who, though he asked a short
                    interval to consult his friends, seems never in his own mind to have hesitated
                    as to its acceptance. To those who represented to him the dangers that were to
                    be incurred, he urged, that the hardships attendant on the obscure exercise of
                    his profession, his journeys to distant patients, his long and solitary rides
                    over “cold and lonely heaths,” and over “gloomy hills, assailed by the wintry
                    tempest,” would tend as effectually to shorten life as the journey now in
                    contemplation.</p>
                <p part="N">In this new undertaking, Mr Park was amply supplied with every thing
                    which could insure success. Thirty soldiers, and nearly the same number of
                    carpenters and artificers, were placed under his command; arms, beasts of
                    burden, and commodities to trade with, were amply supplied; and he was empowered
                    to draw upon the treasury to the extent of L.5000. Everything, therefore, seemed
                    to augur a still more brilliant issue to his present than to his former journey.
                    But a dark destiny impended over it, and rendered abortive all human means and
                    efforts.</p>
                <p part="N">It would be superfluous to enter into a detail of that afflicting train
                    of events, with which the public are already but too well acquainted.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">The Narrative of
                            this journey was published in 1815, in 4to, with a very interesting
                            biographical memoir and preface, by Mr Wishaw. It may not be amiss to
                            notice here a singular oversight in Park’s Journal, lately observed by
                            Μ. Walckenaer. A 31st day is counted in April (p. 7); and as all the
                            days before and after are accounted for, there can be no doubt that all
                            the following dates are one day behind. This, as Mr Bowdich has shown,
                            is not so trifling an error as at first sight it appears; for a false
                            declination being thus taken, an error, greater or less, and sometimes
                            not inconsiderable, is committed in the calculation of all the
                            subsequent latitudes.</p></note> That Park perished in his voyage down
                    the Niger, may be considered as long since fully established; and we need not
                    swell our pages with the rumours which have been circulated respecting an event
                    which has for many years ceased to be doubtful.</p>
                <p part="N">Park has been pronounced by some the first of modern travellers. Without
                    altogether adopting this opinion, we may observe, that the problem of the course
                    of the Niger, which he had the fortune partially to solve, was one which had
                    involved in error almost all former geographical systems on Africa. D’Anville,
                    indeed, had stated it correctly; but as he had not communicated the grounds upon
                    which his conclusion rested, the opposite opinion, which represented the Niger
                    as flowing westward, and joining the ocean by the channel of the Senegal,
                    continued still prevalent. This point, finally decided, fixed the geographical
                    character of the continent. In Bambarra, also, a name as yet scarcely heard of
                    by Europeans, Park found a kingdom much farther advanced in populousness and
                    civilization than had yet been supposed to exist in the heart of Africa.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Park’s literary, though not equal to his active qualifications, were
                    nevertheless respectable. But notwithstanding his knowledge of botany, he cannot
                    be considered as a scientific traveller. We see not in him that varied and
                    splendid science which, in Humboldt, illustrates and adorns, though it sometimes
                    overlays the main subject. But with <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193492192?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0717-2192-0085"/>regard to
                    the general aspect of nature, and the forms~of human society, his observations
                    are careful, accurate, and judicious. Nothing can be more lively than the idea
                    which we receive from him of the African forests and deserts, the cities of
                    Bambarra, the stream of the Niger or Joliba, and the regions watered by that
                    river. The spirit, joined to the unpretending simplicity, of his narrative, has
                    rendered his work one of the most popular of its kind in the English
                    language.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Park’s bodily frame was well fitted for the arduous enterprises in
                    which he engaged. He was six feet in height, his limbs were well proportioned,
                    and his whole frame was active and robust. His countenance was prepossessing,
                    and his manners always retained their native plainness and simplicity. But this
                    was combined with a natural coldness and reserve, which rendered his
                    conversation less interesting than was expected by those who considered his
                    general talents and extensive opportunities of observation. His conduct in all
                    the relations of private life was highly exemplary. He left a widow, three sons,
                    and a daughter, <hi rend="smallcaps">(e.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
