<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-3239-0310-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MOCHA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 15, page 310</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205362">Chile</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:838614">Bricks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1175789">Windows</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193823239" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MOCHA</label>, one of the principal ports of the Red Sea, and
                    the chief city of the province of Yemen, in Arabia. It has a handsome appearance
                    from the sea, all its buildings being white-washed, and several of its minarets
                    overtopping the other buildings, whilst some of the tombs, which, as in many
                    eastern cities, are handsome structures, break the monotonous view of the flat
                    roofs which are common in Mahommedan cities. But if the eye is pleased by the
                    external aspect of the place, these ideas are quickly dispelled by a nearer
                    view, owing to the filth which covers the streets and all the open places, and
                    the mean and ruined state of many of the houses, which, being generally built of
                    unburnt bricks, with little lime, are destroyed by the introduction of moisture,
                    which decomposes the fragile materials of which these buildings are composed,
                    and the bricks in consequence return to their original state of mud. The
                    principal edifice is the residence of the Dola, which is large and lofty, having
                    one front to the sea, and another to a square, which forms the only regular
                    portion of the town. The other sides of this square are occupied by the
                    residences of the other public functionaries, and by one extensive serai built
                    by the Turks whilst they were in possession of the place. Those houses which
                    front the sea, with their turreted tops and fantastic ornaments of white stucco,
                    make a respectable appearance. They have mostly small and irregularly-placed
                    windows, and in the upper apartments they substitute for glass a thin strata of
                    a transparent stone found in a mountain near to Sana. These windows are mostly
                    of a circular form. The houses are but rudely finished in the interior, the
                    floors and roofs being made of chunam, and very uneven; the passages in them are
                    long and narrow, and their staircases very steep. Those of the lower classes are
                    still more rude, being mere huts of brick covered in the inside with mats, and
                    sometimes in the outside with a little clay, with which the roof is thatched.
                    The town is fortified by a wall sixteen feet towards the sea,'but thirty feet
                    towards the land; and it extends for about a mile in nearly a straight line
                    facing the sea, and afterwards takes a circular direction. It is of no strength,
                    and would be shattered to pieces by the first shock of artillery; in some
                    places, indeed, it would scarcely bear the firing of its own cannon. Nor are the
                    forts which defend it in any better condition. They might all be levelled to the
                    ground by a single broadside from an English man-of-war. Its only use was to
                    repel an irregular attack of the Wahabee cavalry. The garrison consists of about
                    200 musqueteers and eighty cavalry, who receive two dollars of pay per month,
                    and provide their own arms and ammunition. Mocha possesses a considerable trade,
                    and is the channel through which the intercourse of Europe with this part of the
                    world is carried on. Coffee is the main staple, and is indigenous to the
                    country, which produces it in great abundance, and of unrivalled excellence. It
                    was introduced from Arabia into Aleppo and Damascus, and other great cities. It
                    became known in France and England in the middle of the seventeenth century; the
                    demand for it increased, and it became a source of wealth; but the shrub having
                    been transplanted to the West Indies, the cheaper coffee of these countries,
                    though of inferior quality, rivalled the produce of Mocha in the European
                    markets. The whole quantity of coffee produced at Mocha, amounting, according to
                    the estimate of Lord Valentia, to 4,880,000 lbs. was formerly conveyed to Jidda,
                    where it was purchased by merchants from Europe or from India, and partly also
                    from America. Mocha also carries on a considerable trade in myrrh, frankincense,
                    and gum-arabic, which commodities are brought from the opposite coast of
                    Berbera, in Africa; in balm of Gilead or of Mekka, a resinous juice much used in
                    the East as a cosmetic; in senna, of which about 30,000 cwt. are exported; in
                    sharks' fins, rhinoceros’ horns and hides, acacia and civet from the interior of
                    Africa. Grain and piece-goods are imported to a considerable amount from Bombay.
                    The trade is carried on by about 250 Banians or Gentoo merchants, who are
                    subject to great oppression, and who are only induced to remain from the great
                    profits which they realize. Three per cent, of custom duty is imposed on English
                    goods, and on those of other foreigners five per cent. A three-masted vessel
                    pays 384 dollars on its arrival, and vessels with two masts only <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193823252" xml:id="kp-eb0715-3252-0311"/>one half each. Mocha is not a
                    city of any antiquity. It does not appear to have been known so far back as four
                    centuries. When it was visited by Alphonso Albuquerque in 1513, it seems to have
                    been an inconsiderable place. The first attempt to open a trade with it was in
                    1610, by the British expeditions under Sharpey. and Sir H. Middleton. It was
                    here that the latter was treacherously surprised and made prisoner with a number
                    of his men, though he afterwards obtained his release, and exacted satisfaction
                    for the injuries which he had received. The Dutch took the lead amongst the
                    Europeans in establishing a factory here; and they were followed in 1708 by the
                    French, and afterwards by the English, who at length engrossed almost the whole
                    trade, till they found formidable rivals in the Americans. The surrounding
                    country is a dreary plain of arid sand, environed by mountains, and covered with
                    a saline efflorescence, scarcely relieved in some parts by embrowned leaves and
                    stunted vegetables, whose burnt appearance does not diminish,the dreariness of
                    the scenery. Dates grow in abundance around the town, but, like every thing
                    else, are affected by the poverty of the soil from which they spring. The
                    south-east wind, which blows for eight months of the year, and passes over the
                    burning sands of Africa, renders the climate intensely hot. The northwest wind,
                    which blows for the other four months, is also hot, as it passes over the
                    burning sands of Arabia. It is supposed by travellers that the town does not
                    contain above 5000 inhabitants. Long. 43. 20. E. Lat. 13. 20. N.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Mocha,</hi> an island off the coast of Chile, above sixty
                    miles in circumference. It is fertile, and was formerly settled by Spaniards,
                    but it is now uninhabited. It is, however, frequented by whale ships belonging
                    to England and the United States.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
