<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-6931-0594-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MURAT, Joachim</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 15, page 594</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:981035">Jacobins</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f1p">Jacobins</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gg1n">Clouds</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193826931" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MURAT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joachim</hi></label>, one of the
                    lieutenants of Napoleon, was born on the 25th of March 1771, at La Bastide, near
                    Cahors, where his father was an innkeeper. Being sent to school at Toulouse, he
                    there acquired some slight degree of elementary instruction; but his taste for
                    dissipation and adventure soon drew him away from his studies, which he appears
                    to have entirely neglected. Having returned to the hostelry of his father, he
                    engaged in the service of the house along with the domestics, and then enlisted
                    in the chasseurs of the Ardennes. But, in consequence of some misconduct, he
                    soon afterwards deserted, and having gone to Paris, fell into such distress that
                    he was obliged to serve at the table of a restaurateur. Being remarked for his
                    activity and bearing, and his father having resolved to send him some
                    assistance, he was admitted into the constitutional guard of Louis XVI.; and, on
                    the disbanding of that body, which followed soon after its formation, he
                    obtained a sub-lieutenancy in the eleventh regiment of <hi rend="italic"
                    >chasseurs à cheval.</hi> Here he showed himself a furious revolutionist, and in
                    consequence obtained rapid promotion. He was already lieutenant-colonel, and one
                    of the most fervent adherents of Marat, when, upon the death of that ferocious
                    tribune of the people, he wrote from Abbeville, where he was then in garrison,
                    requesting the society of the Jacobins at Paris to grant him permission to
                    change his name into that of Marat. It is not known whether his request was
                    positively complied with; but it is certain that, after the fall of Robespierre,
                    he was, like Bonaparte, dismissed as a terrorist, and, like him also, found
                    himself at Paris, nearly without resources, in expectation of some change which
                    might prove favourable to his prospects. Nor were his hopes in this respect
                    disappointed. Being restored to his rank at the epoch of the 13th Vendémiaire
                    (5th October 1795), he served under the orders of Bonaparte, when the latter was
                    employed to disperse the Parisians who had armed against the Convention.
                    Attaching himself more and more to this young general, Murat showed much
                    intelligence and bravery at the opening of the campaign of Italy in 1796, and
                    became the confidential aide-de-camp of Bonaparte. In consequence of a mission
                    to the court of Turin, which had made overtures of peace, he set out for Paris
                    with despatches relative to the negociations; and, in the month of June, he
                    accompanied Faypoult to Genoa, with instructions to demand of the doge the
                    expulsion of the imperial minister. On his return to the army, Murat directed
                    several attacks with success; and during all that campaign, and the subsequent
                    one of 1797, he signalised himself by his bravery. In March 1798, he proceeded
                    at the head of a column to the confines of the Valteline, and united that
                    province to the new Cisalpine republic. He likewise preceded Bonaparte when,
                    after the peace of Campo Formio, that general traversed Switzerland and Alsace
                    on his way to Rastadt. Being sent to Rome with Berthier, he marched against the
                    insurgents of Marino, Albano, and Castello, killed a great many of them, and
                    caused to be arrested a considerable number of monks and prelates, reputed
                    eneínies of France. When the expedition to Egypt had been resolved on, he
                    declared, that being attached by gratitude to Bonaparte, he would follow him
                    through the world; in fact, he never quitted his chief, and throughout the whole
                    course of that expedition distinguished himself, particularly at Mount Tabor,
                    where, by a series of brilliant charges, he completed the dispersion of the
                    Turkish army, and was rewarded with the rank of general of division. On his
                    return to France with Napoleon, Murat rendered him effectual service at
                    Saint-Cloud, when he changed the form of the government, and took possession of
                    power. It was Murat who, at the head of sixty grenadiers, dispersed the Council
                    of Five Hundred. He was immediately named commandant of the consular guard, and
                    henceforth enjoyed unlimited favour. To draw still closer the ties which united
                    them, Napoleon<pb break="no" facs="nls:193826944" xml:id="kp-eb0715-6944-0595"/>
                    gave Murat his sister Caroline in marriage. He also employed him as one of his
                    lieutenants in the army of reserve, and in this capacity Murat entered Milan,
                    occupied Piacenza, and commanded the cavalry at the battle of Marengo. In the
                    following year he commanded the army of observation, and, along with Micheroux,
                    signed at Foligno an armistice between the French government and the king of the
                    Two Sicilies. He then governed, with the title of general, the Cisalpine
                    republic, and repaired to the <hi rend="italic">Consulta</hi> at Lyons, in
                    virtue of which he installed the new authorities in 1802. On the 1st of January
                    1804, he was appointed governor of Paris, with the rank of general-in-chief, and
                    directed the military force when Napoleon was proclaimed emperor. A&gt; few days
                    after this event, he was elevated to the rank of marshal of the empire, and in
                    the following year he was raised to the dignity of prince and of high
                    admiral.</p>
                <p>On the breaking out of hostilities with Austria in 1806, he passed the Rhine at
                    Kehl with the reserve of cavalry, advanced into Suabia, and, at the moment of
                    the capture of Ulm and the capitulation of Mack, pursued vigorously the Austrian
                    corps under the orders of the Archduke Ferdinand, in their retreat through
                    Franconia towards Bohemia. Having overtaken the corps of Werneck, he forced it
                    to lay down its arms, and, taking the road to Vienna, entered that capital on
                    the 11th of November. He then marched against the Russians in Moravia, and by
                    different charges of cavalry contributed to the victory of Austerlitz. Being
                    invested with the grand duchy of Berg, he assumed the style of a sovereign;
                    figured in the two subsequent campaigns, particularly at the battle of lena;
                    made his public entry into Warsaw on the 28th of November 1807; and commanded
                    the cavalry at the battle of Eylau, and also at that of Friedland.</p>
                <p>In April 1808, he entered Spain at the head of a numerous army, and employed all
                    sorts of artifices to exasperate the differences which already existed in the
                    royal family. Having, by a mixture of intimidation and cajolery, induced them to
                    set out for Bayonne, where Napoleon waited to receive them, he provoked an
                    insurrection in the capital, which, though speedily extinguished, spread the
                    flame of discontent throughout the whole of Spain, and gave the first impulse to
                    that spirit of resistance which, encouraged and supported by Britain, ultimately
                    effected the deliverance of the Peninsula. Being recalled from Spain, where his
                    imprudence had proved so detrimental to the interests of his master, he was, on
                    the 1st of August 1808, proclaimed king of the Two Sicilies, under the name of
                    Joachim-Napoleon. As he succeeded Joseph Bonaparte, whom the Neapolitans
                    despised, the comparison was to his advantage; whilst, by the pomp he displayed,
                    and his martial air and bearing, he won the favour of the people, who are always
                    ready to be caught by appearances. The invasion of Russia in 1812 recalled him
                    under the banners of his former master. Being placed at the head of the cavalry,
                    he took part in all the operations which preceded the capture of Moscow; he also
                    commanded a separate corps at Kaluga, where at first he obtained some
                    advantages, but subsequently experienced great reverses; and after the departure
                    of Napoleon from the army, he ’ was intrusted with the command of it in its
                    disastrous retreat from Smorgoni. Fatigued and discontented, however, he also
                    abandoned the army, and took the road to Naples, in the hope of yet supporting a
                    throne which seemed destined to crumble into pieces along with the colossal
                    fabric of the French empire. His whole subsequent conduct betrays the inherent
                    weakness and instability of his character. On his return to his capital, he made
                    overtures to the court of Vienna, with a view to the formation of an alliance
                    with Austria; but the campaign of 1813 soon afterwards opened; and as the first
                    events proved favourable to Napoleon, Murat quitted Naples, and once more
                    repaired to the headquarters of the French army,'though with less zeal and
                    parade than formerly, and as if constrained to appear there. After the loss of
                    the battle of Léipzig, he withdrew to his states, and, considering the star of
                    Napoleon as for ever eclipsed, he opened his ports to the English, and renewed
                    the negociations for the accession of Naples to the European alliance against
                    France. As the price of this defection, he obtained the recognition of his
                    political existence and of his right of conquest to the city of Ancona and the
                    pontifical marches; but his sincerity was justly doubted by the allies, whom he
                    had joined from necessity, whilst Napoleon naturally reproached him with conduct
                    at variance with every principle of loyalty and gratitude.</p>
                <p>It is unnecessary to give details of bis subsequent proceedings, the account of
                    which belongs properly to the history of the country at the head of which the
                    fortune of war and of conquest had placed him. Though brave as a lion in the
                    field of battle, he showed himself one of the weakest of men when not in
                    presence of the enemy. He had no moral courage. His title of king had turned his
                    head, and he incurred the double reproach of treachery and ingratitude, without
                    deriving the slightest advantage from his dereliction of principle. His invasion
                    of Italy after the return of Napoleon from Elba was in every view a most
                    headlong and irrational proceeding, inasmuch as all the chances were against
                    him, and defeat was certain to be followed by destruction. After the failure of
                    this absurd attempt, he lived for some time in retirement at Plaisance, a
                    country-house near Toulon, where he first learned the tidings of the battle of
                    Waterloo. The news of this disaster sounded as the deathknell of all his hopes.
                    In the space of two months, he had lost his army, his fleet, part of his
                    treasures, bis crown, and even his field equipage; and now, after the second
                    abdication of the man in whose fortune alone he could repose any hope for the
                    future, all seemed irrecoverably lost. He escaped to the island of Corsica,
                    where he had many partizans, and began to form new projects. An asylum was
                    offered him in Bohemia, Moravia, or Austria, on condition of his renouncing the
                    title of king, submitting to the laws of the country, and consenting not to quit
                    his residence without the permission of the emperor. But having resolved to make
                    an attempt to recover his power by effecting a landing in Italy, he sailed from
                    Corsica on the 28th of September 1815, with seven transports, containing 250
                    men, and, on the 8th of October, reached the Gulf of St Euphemia, where one only
                    of his barks had rejoined him, the rest being separated in a gale of wind. When
                    he landed at Pizzo, he was accompanied by only thirty men, and knew not what
                    course to follow. To wait for the other barks, or to make an attempt to raise
                    the country, seemed equally dangerous. He at length decided in favour of the
                    latter course; but all his efforts were vain. The inhabitants flew to arms, and
                    attacked his troop, upon which the two small vessels immediately stood out to
                    sea. Murat attempted to launch a fishing-boat which he found upon the beach; but
                    the task exceeded his strength, and escape was impossible. Having been made
                    prisoner, he was lodged in the castle of Pizzo, tried by a military commission,
                    condemned, and sentenced to be shot. The judgment of the court was carried into
                    execution on the 13th of October, when this singular man, whom death had spared
                    in a hundred battles, fell ingloriously in an obscure town of Calabria, the
                    victim of his own folly and ambition. He appears to have died in a manner worthy
                    of his reputation for courage. He refused to allow his eyes to be bandaged, saw
                    the arms charged, placed himself so as to receive the concentrated fire of the
                    soldiers, and, exclaiming “Sauvez le visage, visez au coeur,” instantly fell
                    dead under the discharge. Murat perished in the forty-eighth year of his age,
                    after <pb break="no" facs="nls:193826957" xml:id="kp-eb0715-6957-0596"/>having
                    experienced every variety of fortune; indeed he was a man whose destiny mây, in
                    some respects, be considered as the most extraordinary in modern times. Sprung
                    from the lowest class of society, and raised to supreme rank, his elevation was
                    the more surprising that he had neither the great qualities nor the great vices
                    which seem to command events. Fortune had so blinded him, that he neither
                    perceived the inevitable dangers with which the fall of Bonaparte and the
                    restoration of the Bourbons had surrounded him, nor could he turn to account the
                    resources which circumstances still placed in his power. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(a.)</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Murat,</hi> an arrondissement of the department
                    of Cantal, in France, 343 square miles in extent. It is divided into three
                    cantons, and subdivided into thirty-one communes, containing 34,250 inhabitants.
                    The capital, a city of the same name, stands at the foot of the mountain Cantal,
                    on the river Alagnon. It contains 530 houses, and 2640 inhabitants, who are
                    chiefly employed as coppersmiths, but also make some thread lace.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
