<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-9339-0010-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MICROMETER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 15, page 10</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="69" ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dk97">Lenses</term>
                    <term n="73" ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68d53">Tubes</term>
                    <term n="17" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="69" ref="fasttopic:996178">Lenses</term>
                    <term n="73" ref="fasttopic:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1158581">Tubes</term>
                    <term n="76" ref="fasttopic:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193819339" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MICROMETER</label>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Micrometer,</hi> from <hi rend="italic">μικοος, small,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">μετξον, a measure,</hi> is the name of an instrument
                    generally applied to telescopes and microscopes, for measuring small angular
                    distances within the field of the former, or the size of small objects within
                    that of the latter.</p>
                <p>Previously to the invention of the telescope, astronomers experienced great
                    difficulty in measuring small angles in the heavens; but we may safely infer
                    from the observations of Hipparchus, that he had succeeded, either by the actual
                    division of his instruments, or by estimation, in determining celestial arcs to
                    <hi rend="italic">one third</hi> of a degree.</p>
                <p>When the telescope was applied by Galileo, and our countryman Harriot, to the
                    examination of the solar spots, it does not appear that they executed their
                    drawings from any other than estimated measures. This indeed seems quite certain
                    in the case of Harriot, whose original sketches we have had an opportunity of
                    inspecting. The elaborate solar observations of Scheiner made in 1611, with a
                    telescope on a polar axis, and published in 1630 in his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Posa</hi><hi rend="italic">Ursina,</hi> though minutely laid down, and
                    performed with great care, were certainly made without any instrument for
                    subdividing the field of view.</p>
                <p>As telescopic observations, however, multiplied, astronomers felt the necessity
                    of having something more accurate than their eye for ascertaining minute
                    distances in the heavens; and there can be no doubt that a micrometer was
                    invented by our countryman Mr Gascoigne, previous to 1640, not long after the
                    publication of the <hi rend="italic">Posa</hi><hi rend="italic">Ursina.</hi>
                    According to the description of it which he addressed in a letter to Mr
                    Oughtred, and to the account of one of Gascoigne’s own instruments which Dr
                    Hooke examined, its construction is as follows :—A small cylinder, stretching
                    across the eye-tube of the telescope, is cut into a fine screw throughout one
                    third of its length, the other two thirds being formed into a coarser screw,
                    with threads at twice the distance. This compound screw is confined at both ends
                    to its place, the fine part of it passing through a female screw in one bar, and
                    the coarse part through a female screw in another bar, these two bars being
                    grooved into each other, as in a sliding rule. Hence, if a nicely ground edge is
                    fixed to one bar, and another to the other bar, so that these edges are
                    accurately parallel, a motion of the screw round its axis will separate these
                    two edges, andeach edge will move with a different velocity. The parts of a
                    revolution are measured by an index and divided face, at the coarse end of the
                    screw, while the number of whole revolutions is measured by a graduated bar
                    moved by the coarse screw. The fine screw serves the purpose of keeping the
                    middle part of this variable field (or the opening between the edges) in the
                    axis or line of collimation of the telescope; for while the coarse screw moves
                    the edge which it carries from the other edge considered as fixed, the fine
                    screw moves both the edges, and indeed the whole frame, in an opposite
                    direction, with one half of the velocity, an effect which is produced by fixing
                    its bar to the tube of the telescope.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See Phil. Trans. No. 29, p. 540, Nov. 1667 » Lowthorp’s
                    Abridgment, vol. i. p. 22G; and Costard’s History of Astronomy.</p></note> As Mr
                    Gascoigne fell in the civil wars, near York, in 1644, before he had given any
                    full account of his invention, and its application to astronomy, <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193819352" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9352-0011"/>we are indebted to Mr Richard
                    Townley, into whose hands one of the instruments fell, for the preservation of
                    so valuable a relic. Mr Townley informs us that Mr Gascoigne had made use of his
                    micrometer for some years before the civil wars, and had measured distances on
                    the earth, determined the diameters of the planets, and endeavoured to find the
                    moon’s distance from two observations of her horizontal and meridional
                    diameters. Mr Townley’s instrument was of the size and weight of “an ordinary
                    pocket watch.” It marked 40,000 divisions in a foot, 2½ divisions corresponding
                    to a second of space. Mr Townley had it improved by a common watchmaker.
                    Flamsteed was presented with one of the instruments in 1670, by Sir Jonas Moore;
                    but though he left three guineas with Mr Collins to get proper glasses made for
                    it, he could not procure them till autumn 1671, when he began his observations
                    with it at Derby, and continued them with it in 1671, 1672, 16/3, and 1674.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Mr Baily’s Account of the
                    Reverend John Flamsteed, 1835, p. <hi rend="italic">24,</hi> 29,
                    &amp;c.</p></note> He informs us that Townley’s improvement consisted in
                    substituting one screw for two. He mentions also that Gascoigne had, in August
                    1640, measured with his micrometer the diameters of the sun and moon, and the
                    relative distances of the stars in the Pleiades.</p>
                <p>Dr Hooke made an important improvement in this micrometer, by substituting
                    parallel <hi rend="italic">hairs</hi> for the parallel edges of the brass
                    plates;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Hooke’s
                    Posthumous Works, p. 497-8.</p></note> and Dr Pearson conjectures that he had
                    adopted this construction in his zenith sector, by which he proposed, in his
                    dispute with Hevclius, to measure <hi rend="italic">single seconds.</hi></p>
                <p>It would appear, from the Ephemerides of the Marquis of Malvasia, published in
                    the year 1662, that he had measured the distances of stars, and the diameters of
                    the planets, and projected the lunar spots, by means of a <hi rend="italic"
                    >reticle</hi> of silver wire fixed in the focus of the eye-glass of his
                    telescope. In order to determine the distances of the wires which composed this
                    network, he turned it round till a star moved along one of the wires, and having
                    counted the number of seconds which the star took to pass over the different
                    distances between the wires, he obtained a very accurate scale for all
                    micrometrical purposes.</p>
                <p>About the year 1666, MM. Auzout and Picard, unacquainted with what had been done
                    by Gascoigne, published an account of a micrometer.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Phil. Trans. No. 21, p. 373, January
                    1G6G.</p></note> Auzout’s micrometer is said to have divided a foot into 24,000
                    or 30,000 parts. It resembled the Marquis of Malvasia’s, with this difference,
                    that the divisions were measured by a screw, and he sometimes employed fibres of
                    silk in place of silver wires.</p>
                <p>The celebrated Christian Huygens was also an early inventor of micrometrical
                    methods; and the subject was prosecuted with great diligence and success by
                    Cassini, Roemer, Bradley, Savary, Bouguer, Dollond, Maskelyne, Ramsden, Sir W.
                    Herschel, Troughton, Wollaston, Arago, Fraunhofer, and Amici.</p>
                <p>In giving an account of the inventions and methods of these various authors, we
                    shall adopt the following arrangement:—</p>
                <p>1. Description of wire-micrometers in which the wires are moved by one or more
                    screws.</p>
                <p>2. Description of wire-micrometers in which the angular distance of the wires is
                    varied optically, by changing the magnifying power of the telescope.</p>
                <p>3. Description of double-image micrometers in which two singly refracting lenses,
                    semi-lenses, or prisms, are separated by screws.</p>
                <p>4. Description of double-image micrometers in which the two images formed by two
                    singly refracting lenses, semi-lenses, or prisms, are separated optically.</p>
                <p>5. Description of double-image micrometers in which the two images are formed by
                    double refraction.</p>
                <p>6. Description of position-micrometers.</p>
                <p>7. Description of the lamp-micrometer, and the lucid disc micrometer.</p>
                <p>8. Description of fixed micrometers with an invariable scale.</p>
                <p>9. Description of micrometers for microscopes.</p>
                <p>CHAP. I DESCRIPTION OF WIRE-MICROMETERS IN WHICH</p>
                <p>THE WIRES ARE MOVED BY MEANS OF ONE OR MORE SCREWS.</p>
                <p>The micrometer of Gascoigne, when furnished with hairs, as suggested by Dr Hooke,
                    embodies the principle of the best and most recent micrometers. Instruments on
                    this construction have been made by all our eminent opticians; but we have no
                    hesitation in saying, that the micrometer constructed by the late celebrated
                    artist Mr Troughton combines all the ingenuity which has been displayed in this
                    delicate and useful apparatus. This eye-piece, and micrometer attached to it,are
                    shown inPlate CCCLVII. fig. 1, 2, and 3, where fig. 1 is a horizontal section in
                    the direction of the axis of the telescope. The eye-piece AB consists of two
                    plano-convex lenses A, B, of nearly the same focal length, and the two convex
                    sides facing each other. They are placed at a distance less than the focal
                    length of A, so that the wires of the micrometer, which must be distinctly seen,
                    are beyond B. This arrangement gives a <hi rend="italic">flat field,</hi> and
                    prevents any distortion of the object. This eye-piece slides into the tube CD,
                    which screws into the brass ring EF, through two openings, in which the oblong
                    frame MW passes. A brass circle GIT, fixed to the telescope by the screw I, has
                    rack-teeth on its circumference, that receive the teeth of an endless screw W,
                    which, being fixed by the arms XX to the oblong box MN, gives the latter and the
                    eye-piece a motion of rotation round the axis of the telescope; and an index
                    upon this box points out on the graduated circle upon GH, fig. 3, the angular
                    motion of the eye-piece. The micrometer properly so called is shown in fig. 2,
                    where K, L arc two forks, each connected with a screw 0 and P, turned by the
                    milled heads Μ and N. These forks are so fitted as to have no lateral shake. Two
                    pins Q, R, with spiral springs coiled round them, pass loosely through holes in
                    the forks K, L, so that when the forks are pressed by their screws towards Q,and
                    R, the spiral springs resist them, and consequently push them back when the
                    screws are turned in the opposite direction.</p>
                <p>Two fine hairs, or wires, or spiders’ lines, S, T, are stretched across the
                    forks, the one being fixed to the inner fork K, and the other to the outer fork
                    L, so as to be perfectly parallel, and not to come in contact when they pass or
                    eclipse one another, in which case they will appear as one line. A wire ST is
                    stretched across the centre of the field, perpendicular to the parallel
                    wires.</p>
                <p>The most difficult part of this instrument in the execution, as well as the most
                    important, is the screw or screws which move the forks. The threads must not
                    only be at the same distance, but have their inclination equal all round. In the
                    screw used tíy Troughton, there are about 103∙6 threads in an inch. On the right
                    hand of the line ST, fig. 2, is seen a scale, which indicates a complete
                    revolution of either screw, the small round hole being the zero. This hole is
                    bisected when the two lines appear as one.</p>
                <p>In using this instrument, we separate the wires by their respective screws, till
                    the object to be measured is exactly <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819365"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0715-9365-0012"/>included between them. The number of revolutions
                    and parts of a revolution necessary to bring the two wires into the position of
                    zero, will then be a measure of the angle required, provided the value of a
                    revolution has been previously ascertained with accuracy.</p>
                <p>The easiest method of ascertaining the value of a revolution of-the screw,
                    according to the late Dr Pearson, who devoted much attention to this subject, is
                    to ascertain how many revolutions and parts of one measure exactly the sun’s
                    vertical diameter in summer, when his altitude is such that the refraction of
                    both limbs is almost the same. The sun’s diameter in seconds being divided by
                    that number, the quotient will be the value of a single revolution, the sun’s
                    diameter having been corrected by the difference between the refraction of his
                    two limbs. The ordinary method of ascertaining the value of a revolution is, to
                    observe accurately the time taken by an equatorial star, or a star of known
                    declination reduced to the equator, to pass over the space between the wires
                    when at a distance, and to convert this time into degrees, at the rate of 15°
                    per hour. The number of degrees, minutes, and seconds, divided by the
                    revolutions and parts of a revolution which are necessary to bring both wires
                    into zero, will give the value of one revolution of the screw. The same thing
                    may be done by measuring a base with great accuracy, and observing the space
                    comprehended between the wires at that distance. The angular magnitude of this
                    space, divided by the number of revolutions of the screws which bring the wires
                    to zero, will be the value of each.</p>
                <p>A most elegant and accurate method has been recently employed, we believe by
                    Professor Gauss of Göttingen, for measuring the value of the revolutions of
                    micrometer screws. He employs for this purpose a standard telescope, with a
                    micrometer the value of whose scale has been accurately determined. Since the
                    wires of a telescope-micrometer adjusted to distinct vision of the stars or
                    planets are accurately in the focus of parallel rays falling on the.
                    object-glass, it follows, that rays issuing from the wires and falling on the
                    inside of the object-glass, will emerge from it perfectly parallel. Now, if we
                    place the object-glass of the standard telescope close or near to that of the
                    first telescope, the parallel rays formed by those issuing from its wires will
                    be refracted to the focus of the standard telescope, and a distinct image of the
                    wires will be there formed. The observer, therefore, when he looks into the
                    standard telescope, will see distinctly the wires of the first telescope, and,
                    by means of his micrometer, he will be able to measure exactly the angular
                    distance of these wires, at whatever distance they happen to be placed. This
                    angular distance divided by the revolutions and parts of a revolution which are
                    necessary to bring the wires of the first telescope to the zero of their scale,
                    will give the value of one revolution of the screw, or of one unit of the scale
                    on the right hand of the long wire ST, fig. 2.</p>
                <p>The most essential parts of a micrometer are the parallel fibres, which require
                    not only to be extremely fine, but of an uniform diameter throughout. Gascoigne,
                    as we have seen, employed the edges of brass plates, Dr Hooke hairs, and
                    subsequent astronomers wires and fibres of silk. Fontana, in 1775, recommended
                    the spider’s line as a substitute for wires, and he is said (we think
                    erroneously) to have obtained them so fine as the 8000th part of a line. Mr
                    Troughton had the merit of introducing the spider’s line, which he found to be
                    so fine, opaque, and elastic, as to answer all the purposes of practical
                    astronomy. This distinguished artist, however, informed the writer of this
                    article, that it was only the stretcher, or the long line which sustains the
                    web, which possesses these useful properties. Sir David Brewster has employed
                    the fibres of spun glass, which are bisected longitudinally with a fine
                    transparent line about the 5∙^ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 00th of an inch in
                    diameter. This central line increases with the diameter of the fibre, and
                    diminishes with the refractive power of the glass. In cases of emergency, the
                    fibres of melted sealing-wax may be advantageously employed, or, as recommended
                    by Professor Wallace, the fibres of asbestos. We have found crystals of <hi
                    rend="italic">mesolite</hi> so minute and regular as to be well adapted for the
                    same purpose.</p>
                <p>The art of forming silver wire of extreme minuteness has been perfected by Dr
                    Wollaston. Having placed a small platinum wire in the axis of a cylindrical
                    mould, he poured melted silver into the mould, so that the platinum wire formed
                    the axis of the silver cylinder. The silver was now drawn out in the usual way,
                    till its diameter was about the 300th of an inch, so that if the platinum wire
                    was at first <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> θth of
                    the diameter of the silver cylinder, it will now be reduced to the 3000th part
                    of an inch. The silver wire is now bent into the form of the letter U, and a
                    hook being made at each of its ends, it is suspended by a gold wire in hot
                    nitric acid. The silver is speedily dissolved by the acid, excepting at its
                    ends, and the fine platinum wire which formed its axis remains untouched. In
                    this way Dr Wollaston succeeded in forming wire ∙¾(⅛yth, i⅛⅛0. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> t</hi> ^&gt; <hi rend="superscript"> an</hi> d even τ7 <hi
                    rend="strikethrough">⅛Λ-</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough"> 0</hi> th of an
                    inch in diameter. When the fibres are prepared, their ends are placed in
                    parallel scratches or grooves drawn on the forks, or, in other cases, on the
                    diaphragm or field bar, and fixed by a layer of bees’ wax or varnish, or, what
                    is more secure, by pinching them with a small screw-nail near their extremities.
                    For a great deal of valuable practical information respecting the construction
                    and use of the wire-micrometer, the reader is referred to the late Dr Pearson’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Introduction to Practical Astronomy</hi> (vol. ii. p. 99, 110,
                    115, &amp;c.), where valuable tables will be found for facilitating the
                    application of the micrometer, both to celestial and terrestrial purposes. See
                    also Sir John Herschel and Sir James South’s <hi rend="italic">Observations
                    of</hi> 380 <hi rend="italic">Double and Triple Stars(p.</hi> 22, 23),
                    containing tables of the values of Troughton’s screws.</p>
                <p>CHAP. II. DESCRIPTION OF WIRE-MICROMETERS IN WHICH THE ANGULAR DISTANCE OF THE
                    WIRES IS VARIED OPTICALLY BY CHANGING THE MAGNIFYING POWER OF THE TELESCOPE.</p>
                <p> MM. Roemer and De la Hire first conceived the idea of varying the angular
                    magnitude of the meshes of a net of silver wire fixed in the focus of the
                    eye-glass of a telescope, for the purpose of measuring the digits of eclipses.
                    This was done by a second lens moving between the wires and the object-glass.
                    The late Mr Watt informed the writer of this article that he had used a similar
                    principle, but bad never published any account of it.</p>
                <p>The plan of opening and shutting a <hi rend="italic">pair of parallel wires</hi>
                    optically instead of mechanically, and of using it as a general principle in
                    micrometers, was first adopted by Sir David Brewster, and has been applied to a
                    variety of methods of varying the magnifying power of the telescope.</p>
                <p>The general principle will be readily understood from the annexed diagram, where
                    AB, CD are two wires or lines of any kind permanently fixed in the focus of the
                    eye-glass of a telescope. If the sun S'√ is in contact with the lower wire CD,
                    it is obvious, that if we increase the magnifying power of the telescope by any
                    optical means anterior to the wires, we may magnify or expand the sun’s disc S⅛
                    ’, till it becomes Ss, when its north or upper limb will exactly touch the upper
                    wire AB. Now if the sun’s diameter happens to be 31'</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819378" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9378-0013"/>
                <p>when its disc Ss just fills the space between the wires -AB, CD, the distance of
                    the wires must have been 62' when, as at S's', it fills only half that space.
                    Hence the wires have been moved optically, so to speak, and have subtended all
                    angles between 31' and 62'.</p>
                <p>The methods of varying the magnifying power of the telescope used by Sir David
                    Brewster, consist, 1, in varying the distance of the two parts of the achromatic
                    eyepiece; and, 2, by varying the focal length of the principal object-glass by
                    means of another object-glass, either convex or concave, moving between it and
                    its principal focus.</p>
                <p>The first of these methods is shown in fig. 2, where AB is the eye-piece with its
                    four lenses, A, C, D, B, in their natural position. The part AFG, with the two
                    lenses A, C, is fixed to the telescope, and a space is left between the tube AC
                    and the outer tube AFG, to allow the moveable part DB of the eye-piece to get
                    sufficiently near the lens C. The tube DB is moved out and in by a rack and
                    pinion E. A scale is formed on the upper surface <hi rend="italic">mn,</hi> and
                    subdivided in the usual manner with a lens and vernier, which it is unnecessary
                    to represent in the figure. The value of the divisions of the scale are
                    determined by.direct experiment. A motion of DB through a space of four inches
                    will, generally speaking, double the magnifying, power of the telescope.</p>
                <p>The best method, however, of varying the magnifying power of the telescope is the
                    second, η+ich is shown in fig. 3, where 0 is the object-glass,∕*its principal
                    focus, and</p>
                <p>L the second lens, which is moveable between 0 and <hi rend="italic">f</hi>
                    Parallel rays RR, after being refracted by 0, so that they would converge to <hi
                    rend="italic">f,</hi> are intercepted by L, which converges them to F, the focus
                    of the combined lenses. The effect of the lens L is therefore to diminish the
                    focal length of the object-glass, and consequently the magnifying power of the
                    telescope, which will obviously be a <hi rend="italic">minimum</hi> when the
                    lens L is at <hi rend="italic">l,</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">maximum</hi> when
                    it is at <hi rend="italic">l'.</hi> The angle subtended by a pair of fixed wires
                    will suffer an opposite change to the magnifying power, being a maximum when the
                    lens L is at Z, and a minimum when it is at- <hi rend="italic">l'.</hi> Hence
                    the scale for measuring the variable angle of these wires may always be equal to
                    the <hi rend="italic">focal length</hi> of the object-glass 0; and the inventor
                    of the instrument has shown, both by theory and by experiment, that the scale is
                    one of equal parts, the variations in the angle of the fixed wires being
                    proportional to the variations in the position of the moveable lens.</p>
                <p>When we wish to measure angles that do not suffer a great change, such as the
                    diameters of the sun and moon, a scale less than the focal length of the
                    object-glass will be sufficient. For example, if we take a lens L, which by a
                    motion of ten inches varies the magnifying power from 40 to 35, then, if the
                    angle of the wires is 29' when the lens L is at <hi rend="italic">l',</hi> it
                    will be 33' 9" when the lens is ten inches from <hi rend="italic">l',</hi> or
                    the magnifying power 35. We have, therefore, a scale of <hi rend="italic"
                    >ten</hi> inches to measure a change of angle of <hi rend="italic">4l</hi> 9*,
                    so that every tenth of an inch will correspond to 3"∙3, and every 100th of an
                    inch to ⅜d of a second. Such a micrometer will serve to measure the diameters of
                    the sun and moon at their various distances from the earth.</p>
                <p>If we wish to measure the distances of some double stars, or the diameters of
                    some of the smaller planets, with a telescope whose magnifying power varies from
                    300 to 240, by the motion of a lens over <hi rend="italic">ten inches,</hi>
                    place the parallel wires at a distance of 40", which will be increased to 50" by
                    the motion of the lens. Hence we have a scale of <hi rend="italic">ten
                    inches</hi> to measure <hi rend="italic">ten seconds,</hi> or the <hi
                    rend="italic">tenth</hi> of an inch to measure <hi rend="italic">one</hi>
                    second, or the 100th of*hn inch to measure ∙⅛th of a second.</p>
                <p>Several pairs of wires placed at different distances might be fixed upon the same
                    diaphragm, or upon separate diaphragms, which could be brought into the focus
                    when wanted; and the second pair of wires might be placed at such a distance
                    that their least angle was equal to the largest angle of the first pair, and so
                    on with the rest.</p>
                <p>A wire-micrometer thus constructed is certainly free from almost all the sources
                    of error which affect the common moveable wire-micrometer. The errors arising
                    from the imperfection of the screw, the uncertainty of zero, and other causes,
                    are avoided; and the wires are always equidistant from the centre of the field,
                    so as to be equally affected by any optical imperfection in the telescope. The
                    scale indeed may be formed by direct experiment, and the results will be as free
                    from error as the experiments by which the scale was made.</p>
                <p>When this micrometer is applied to a portable telescope, it becomes of great use
                    in naval, military, or geodetical operations, and is employed in measuring
                    distances, either by taking the angle subtended by a body of known dimensions,
                    or by measuring the two angles subtended by a body of unknown dimensions from
                    the two extremities of a known or measured base. For these purposes the
                    telescope is fitted up without a stand, as shown in Plate CCCLVII. fig. 4.</p>
                <p>The principle of separating a pair of wires optically is singularly applicable to
                    the Gregorian and Cassegrainian telescopes, where no additional lens or mirror
                    is required. As the magnifying power of both these telescopes maybe increased
                    merely by increasing the distance of the eyepiece from the great speculum, and
                    then re-adjusting the small speculum to distinct vision, we can thus vary the
                    angle of a pair of fixed wires by making the eye-piece moveable. This will be
                    easily comprehended from the annexed figure, where SS is the great speculum of a
                    Gregorian reflector, AA the tube, Μ the small speculum, whose focus is G, and
                    centre of curvature H. It is fixed to an arm MQ, moveable to and from SS in the
                    usual way. The image R'r' is that formed by the speculum SS, and r"R* that
                    formed by the small speculum. This last image being in the focus of the
                    eye-glass E, will be seen distinct and magnified. If the eye-glass E is pulled
                    out to E', then, in order that the object may be seen distinctly, the image r*BΛ
                    must be brought into the position r* ’ R'", FF' being equal to EE'; but this can
                    be done only by advancing the small speculum Μ to M',∕and F' being now the
                    conjugate <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819391" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9391-0014"/>foci
                    of Μ. But by this process the magnifying power has been considerably increased,
                    because the part of the whole MF magnifying power produced by Μ was equal to
                    where-M‘F' . <hi rend="superscript"> ιv</hi> V</p>
                <p>as it is now a much larger quantity. The angle subtended by the wires has
                    therefore been diminished in the same proportion as the magnifying power has
                    been increased. The scale, in this case, is not one of equal parts, but after
                    the extreme points of it have been determined experimentally, the rest may be
                    filled up either by calculation or direct experiment.</p>
                <p>Dr Pearson<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Introduction
                    to Practical Astronomy, vol. ii.</p></note> has, with singular inaccuracy,
                    stated that Sir David Brewster’s “patent micrometer is not competent to measure
                    very small angles, even if it had sufficient magnifying power.” If he means the
                    patent micrometer as made by Mr Harris, as a naval and military telescope for
                    measuring distances, or as a coming-up glass, he is quite right, because the
                    power of measuring small angles is not required for these practical purposes.
                    But it is quite evident that the <hi rend="italic">smallest</hi> angles can be
                    measured by the micrometer when fitted up for astronomical purposes. We have
                    only to use a pair of wires placed at a very small distance, or a pair of
                    semi-lenses whose centres are placed at a very small distance, and then vary
                    their angles till it becomes equal to the very small angle which we wish to
                    measure.</p>
                <p>CHAP. III. DESCRIPTION OF DOUBLE-IMAGE MICROMETERS IN WHICH TWO SINGLY REFRACTING
                    LENSES, SEMI-LENSES, OR PRISMS, ARE SEPARATED BY SCREWS.</p>
                <p>Μ. Roemer, the celebrated Danish astronomer, is said to have been the first who
                    suggested the use of a doubleimage micrometer. He did this about 1678, but the
                    idea does not seem to have been carried into effect, or known to bis successors.
                    Nearly seventy years afterwards, viz. in 1743, Mr Servington Savary, of Exeter,
                    communicated to the Royal Society an account of a double-image micrometer; and
                    five years afterwards, in 1748, the celebrated Bouguer proposed the very same
                    construction, which he called a heliometer. This instrument consisted of two’
                    lenses, which could be separated and made to approach each other by a screw or
                    other mechanical means. These lenses gave double images of every object; and
                    when the two images of any object, such as the sun or moon, were separated till
                    they exactly touched one another, the distance of the object-glasses afforded a
                    measure of the solar or lunar diameter, after an experimental value of the
                    divisions of the scale had been obtained.</p>
                <p>As two complete lenses, however, must always have their least distance equal to
                    the diameter of either, this instrument was incapable of measuring the diameters
                    of small bodies. This obvious defect no doubt led John Dollond, in 1753, to the
                    happy idea of the divided object-glass micrometer, in which the two halves of an
                    object-glass are made to recede from the position in which they form a complete
                    object-glass. When the centres of the two halves coincide, they obviously form
                    one lens, and give only one image. When the centres arc slightly separated the
                    images will be slightly separated; and small objects may be brought into
                    contact, and have the angles which they subtend accurately measured. The scale
                    will, therefore, have a zero corresponding to the coincidence of the centres of
                    the semi-lenses. The principle of this instrument will be understood from fig.
                    5, where H, E are two semi-lenses, whose centres are at H, E, and F their focus.
                    If PQ be a circular object whose diameter is to be measured, or P, Q two points
                    whose angular distance is to be determined, the lenses arc to be separated till
                    the two images <hi rend="italic">x, z</hi> are in contact at F.</p>
                <p>As the rays QHF, PEF pass unrefracted through the centres H, E of the
                    semi-lenses, the angle subtended by QP will be equal to the angle HFE, or that
                    which the distance of the centres of the semi-lenses subtends at F. As the
                    angles, therefore, are very small, they"will vary as HE; and when the angles
                    corresponding to any one distance of the centres is determined, those for any
                    other distance will be ascertained by simple proportion.</p>
                <p>Mr Dollond, who had not at this time invented the achromatic telescope, applied
                    his micrometer to the object end of a reflecting telescope, as shown in Plate
                    CCCLVII. fig. 5, which represents the micrometer as seen from beyond the object
                    end of the reflector. A piece of tube B, carrying the micrometer, slides into or
                    over the tube A of the telescope, and is fastened to it by a screw. The tube B
                    carries a wheel (not seen in the figure) formed of a ring racked at the outer
                    edge, and fixed*, td the brass plate CC, so that a pinion moved by the handle D
                    may turn it into any position. Two plates F, G are kept close to the plate CC by
                    the rabbeted bars H, H, but with so much play that they can move in contrary
                    directions by turning the handle E, which drives a concealed pinion that works
                    in the two racks seen in the highest part of the figure. As the two semi-lenses
                    are fixed to the plates F, G, their centres will be separated by the action of
                    the handle E, and their degree of separation is measured by a scale of five
                    inches subdivided into 20ths of an inch, and read off by a vernier on the plate
                    F, divided into 25 parts, corresponding to 24 of the scale, so that we can
                    measure the separation of the semi-lenses to the <hi rend="superscript"
                    >1</hi>/<hi rend="subscript">500</hi> th of an inch. The vernier is seen to the
                    right of H, and may be adjusted to the zero of the scale, or the position of the
                    lenses when they give only one image, by means of the thumb-screw I, a motion of
                    the vernier being permitted by the screws which fix it to the plate F passing
                    through oblong holes.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Phil. Trans. vol. xlviii.</p></note></p>
                <p>In this construction, the micrometer is too far from the observer, and destroys
                    the equilibrium of the telescope. The instrument itself, however, has more
                    serious defects, as it has been found that the measures of the sun’s diameter,
                    taken by different observers, with the same instrument, and at the same time,
                    differ so much as 12 or 15 seconds. This defect has been ascribed to the
                    different states of the observers’ eyes, according as they have a tendency to
                    give distinct vision within or beyond the focal point, where the image is most
                    perfect; in the former case the limbs being somewhat separated, and in the
                    latter overlapping. Μ. Mosotti, in the <hi rend="italic">Effemeride</hi> of
                    Milan for 1821, has discovered the true cause of this defect, by a series of
                    accurate experiments which he made with this micrometer attached to a Gregorian
                    reflector of two feet in focal length. The focal length of the divided
                    object-glass was 511∙3357 inches, or 42 feet 7½ inches. Μ. Mosotti has shown
                    that a diversity of measures will be obtained by the same observer, if, for the
                    purpose of obtaining distinct vision, he gives a slight displacement to the
                    small speculum by the adjusting screw. If the position of this speculum which
                    gives distinct vision were a point, it would be easy to find that point; but as
                    distinct vision may be obtained within a <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819404"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0715-9404-0015"/>space of 10 or 12 thousandths of an inch, owing to
                    aberration, every different observer will place the mirror at a different point
                    within that range, and consequently obtain a measure corresponding to the image
                    which he views. Μ. Mosotti recommends that the axis of the adjusting screw,
                    which carries the small speculum, should carry a vernier connected with a scale
                    on the outer surface of the tube A. By means of this vernier the observer is
                    able to give a fixed position to the small speculum, so that he always views the
                    same image, and is thus sure of obtaining the same measure of the same object,
                    so far as the observation is concerned. Μ. Mosotti found also that the measures
                    were affected by a change of temperature, which, by changing the length of the
                    tube, displaced the small speculum. In his instrument this displacement amounted
                    to 0∙0075 of an inch, which, he has shown, corresponds to a change of focal
                    length from 5] 1∙3357 to 514∙84 inches; and that the error from this cause, upon
                    a length of 30', will be 13" in excess.</p>
                <p>The following is Dr Pearson’s enumeration of the different sources of error in
                    the divided object-glass micrometer when applied to reflectors.</p>
                <p>1. A variation in the position of the small mirror when the eye estimates the
                    point of distinct vision.</p>
                <p>2. A displacement of the small mirror by change of temperature.</p>
                <p>3. A change of focal distance when central and extreme rays are indiscriminately
                    used. The amount of this error depends on the aberration of the semi-lenses.</p>
                <p>4. A defect of adjustment, or of perfect figure, in the two specula, as they
                    regard each other, the measures varying when taken in different directions.</p>
                <p>In order to enable Dollond’s micrometer to measure differences of declination and
                    right ascension, Dr Maskelyne introduced the aid of cross wires, which he fixed
                    in a moveable ring at the place where the double image is formed. One or both of
                    the two planets or stars are referred to one or other of these lines, as will be
                    seen in the annexed figure, which we take as an example, out of four cases. Let
                    ENWS be the field of view, NS the meridian, and EW the line of east and west;
                    then, in order to obtain the difference of right ascension and declination of
                    two stars, he opened the semi-lenses till he obtained double images of each
                    star. He then turned round the micrometer till the two images of the first star
                    passed over the vertical wire NS at the same instant, and having counted the
                    time that elapsed till the two images of the other star passed over the same
                    line, he had the difference of right ascension in time. By means of the screw
                    which elevated his telescope, and partly by opening the semi-lenses, he made the
                    north image of one star, and the south image of the other, as at A, B, describe
                    in their motion the horizontal wire EW, and at that position of the semi-lenses
                    the scale indicated the difference of declination.</p>
                <p>A very important improvement upon the divided object-glass micrometer was made by
                    Mr Dollond’s son, who adapted it to a refracting telescope, and removed the
                    different sources of error to which it had been found liable. This improvement
                    consists both in the <hi rend="italic">nature, form,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >position</hi> of the semi-lenses. The semi-lenses are made concave, and consist
                    of crown and flint glass, so as to give an achromatic image along with the
                    object-glass of the telescope to which they are applied. These concave
                    semi-lenses, of course, lengthen the focal distance of that object-glass. When a
                    <hi rend="italic">circular</hi> lens was bisected, as in the old construction,
                    the metallic parts which held the semi-lenses obstructed the light in proportion
                    to their separation; a defect of a serious nature in an instrument. In order to
                    correct this evil, Mr J. Dollond substituted two long slices of glass cut from
                    the diametral portion of a lens nearly six inches in diameter. Hence, in every
                    position of these oblong semi-lenses, none of the metallic setting comes before
                    the object-glass, and consequently the light is never obstructed, and is always
                    of the same amount, whatever be the separation of the lenses. In the old
                    construction, where the diameters of each lens slid along each other in contact,
                    a part of the central portions having been removed by grinding the diameters
                    smooth, the two images of an object never could coincide so as to give an
                    accurate <hi rend="italic">zero</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but in the new
                    construction, the space equal to what was removed by grinding is filled up with
                    a brass scale and vernier, and the only evil of this is the loss of light
                    corresponding to the thickness of this scale; but this trifling defect is amply
                    compensated by the perfect coincidence of the images at <hi rend="italic"
                    >zero.</hi></p>
                <p>This important instrument is shown in Plate CCCLVII. fig. 6, where the same
                    letters are used as in fig. 5 to denote the analogous parts of the two
                    instruments. The end of the telescope is shown at A, and B is the rim of brass,
                    which, by sliding upon A, fixes the micrometer to the telescope. The frame CC',
                    moved by teeth on its outer edge, carries one of the halves G of the lens, and a
                    similar frame with teeth carries the other half F. The scale S, six inches long,
                    is fastened like an edge-bar to CC', and each inch is subdivided into 20 parts,
                    which are read off with a vernier of 25 parts, which is fastened as an edge-bar
                    to the moveable frame that carries F. The two moveable frames are imbedded in a
                    fixed plate HH', screwed to the tube B of the-micrometer, and having a circular
                    hole in its middle equal to the diameter of the object-glass. The two
                    semi-lenses are separated by turning the milled head to the right of A, which
                    moves the frame CC', and then the other frame F through the medium of a
                    concealed wheel and a concealed pinion. The mechanism for giving the rotatory
                    motion is also concealed. The adjustment of the vernier to zero is effected by
                    the screw I.</p>
                <p>The property which the double-image micrometer possesses, of measuring angles in
                    all directions, directed to it the attention of Ramsden and other eminent
                    opticians. Ramsden accordingly communicated to the Royal Society of London, in
                    1777,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Phil. Trans,
                    vol. Ixix. 1779, p. 419.</p></note> an account of two instruments of this kind,
                    under the name of the <hi rend="italic">Dioptric</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catoptric</hi> Micrometers. In order to avoid the effects of aberration,
                    Ramsden proposed, in his dioptric micrometer, to place two semi-lenses in the
                    conjugate focus of the innermost lens of the erect eye-tube of a refracting
                    telescope. In place of the imperfections of the lenses being magnified by the
                    whole power of the telescope, they are magnified only about five or six times,
                    and the size of the micrometer glass does not require to be T⅜o th part of the
                    area which is necessary in Dollond’s instrument. This instrument is shown in
                    Plate CCCLVII. fig. 7, where A is a convex or concave lens, bisected in the
                    usual way. One of the semi-lenses is fixed in a frame B and the other in a
                    similar frame E, both of which slide upon a plate H, against which they are
                    pressed by thin plates α, <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> The milled button D, by
                    means of a pinion and rack, moves these frames in opposite directions; and the
                    separation of the semi-lenses thus effected is measured by a scale of equal
                    parts L on the frame B, the zero being in the middle, and the divisions read off
                    by two verniers at Μ and N, carried by the frame E; the <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193819417" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9417-0016"/>vernier Μ showing the
                    relative motion of the two frames when the frame B moves to the right, and N
                    when the frame B is moved to the left. An endless screw F gives the whole
                    micrometer a motion round the axis of vision. This instrument being only the
                    divided object-glass micrometer in miniature, and differently placed, the reader
                    will have no difficulty in understanding its construction and use, from the
                    details already given in the preceding pages.</p>
                <p>Dr Pearson informs us, on the authority of Mr Troughton, that a Captain Countess,
                    R. N. having accidentally broken the third lens of a terrestrial eye-piece of
                    his telescope, observed the double images which it produced; and that this
                    observation led to the contrivance of the coming-up glass that was first made by
                    Nairne, with a double screw for separating the halves of the amplifying lens.
                    Hence it is <hi rend="italic">conjectured</hi> that Ramsden derived his idea of
                    using a bisected lens for his dioptric micrometer and dynameter. The above facts
                    may be quite true, but Ramsden certainly did not require any such hint, as it
                    was a very natural transition from a bisected object-glass to a bisected
                    eye-glass.</p>
                <p>Dr Pearson also states that Mr George Dollond had constructed a dioptric
                    micrometer almost the same as Ramsden’s, without knowing any thing of what
                    Ramsden had proposed. We have no doubt that both these ingenious opticians were
                    quite original in their ideas, for it will not be supposed that Captain
                    Countess’s broken lens furnished Mr Dollond with the idea of his contrivance. Dr
                    Pearson has given a drawing and description of Mr Dollond’s construction of the
                    micrometer as made for Mr Davies Gilbert and himself.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Introduction to Practical Astronomy, vol. ii.
                    p. 182.</p></note> It does not appear that Mr Ramsden ever constructed it. The
                    weight of this micrometer was found by Dr Pearson too great for an ordinary
                    achromatic telescope.</p>
                <p>Mr Ramsden likewise proposed a catoptric double-image micrometer,‘which, from
                    being founded on the principle of reflection, is not disturbed by the
                    heterogeneity of light, while he considered it as “avoiding every defect of
                    other micrometers,” having “no aberration, nor any defect which arises from the
                    imperfection of materials or of ^execution, as the extreme simplicity of its
                    construction requires no additional mirrors or glasses to those required for the
                    telescope.” “It has also, peculiar to itself, the advantages of an adjustment to
                    make the images coincide in a direction perpendicular to that of their motion.
                    In order to effect these objects, Mr Ramsden divided the small speculum of a
                    Cassegrainian reflector into two equal halves, and by inclining each half on an
                    axis at right angles to the plane that separated them, he obtained two distinct
                    images; but as their angular separation was only half the inclination of the
                    specula, which would give only a small scale, he rejected this first idea, and
                    separated the semi-specula by making them turn on their centre of curvature, any
                    extent of scale being obtained by fixing the centre of motion at a proportional
                    distance from the common centre of curvature. The mechanism necessary to effect
                    this is shown in Plate CCCLVII. fig. 8, where A is the bisected speculum, one of
                    the semi-specula being fixed on the inner end of the arm B, its outer end being
                    fixed on a steel axis X extending across the mouth of the tube C. The other
                    semi-speculum is fixed on the inner end of the arm D, its outer end terminating
                    in a socket <hi rend="italic">y,</hi> which turns upon the steel axis <hi
                    rend="italic">x.</hi> These arms are braced by the bars <hi rend="italic">a,
                    a.</hi>. A compound screw G, having its upper part cut into double the number of
                    threads in an inch, viz. 100, to the lower part <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> which
                    has only 50, works with the handle in a nut F in the side of the tube, while the
                    part <hi rend="italic">g</hi> turns in a nut H fixed to the arm B. The point of
                    the compound screw separates the ends of the arms B and D, and, pressing against
                    the stud <hi rend="italic">h</hi> fixed to the arm D, turns in the nut H on the
                    arm B. A spiral spring within the part <hi rend="italic">η</hi> presses the two
                    arms B, D against the direction of the double screw <hi rend="italic">e
                    g</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> so as to prevent all shake or play in
                    the nut H. The progressive motion of the screw through the nut will be half the
                    distance of the semi-specula, so that these specula will be moved equally in
                    opposite directions from the axis of the telescope.</p>
                <p>A graduated circle V, divided into 100 parts on its cylindrical surface, is fixed
                    on the upper end of the screw G, so as to cause it to separate the semi-specula.
                    The fixed index I shows the parts of a revolution performed by the screw, while
                    the number of whole revolutions of the screw is shown by the divisions of the
                    same index. A steel screw R, moveable by a key, inclines the small speculum at
                    right angles to the direction of its motion. Distinct vision is procured in the
                    usual manner, and the telescope has a motion about its axis, in order to measure
                    the diameter of a planet in any direction; and the angle of rotation in
                    reference to the horizon is shown by a level, graduated circle, and vernier, at
                    the eye end of the large tube.</p>
                <p>A catoptric double-image micrometer has been suggested by Sir David Brewster as
                    applicable to the Newtonian telescope. The plane mirror is bisected, and is made
                    to form two images, either by giving each semi-speculum a motion round .their
                    common line of junction, or round a line perpendicular to that common line. The
                    mechanism by which this may be effected does not require any description. If the
                    micrometer is required for the sun or any luminous body, the small mirror may be
                    made of parallel glass, which would have the advantage of not obstructing any of
                    the light which enters the telescope, while it reflects enough for the purposes
                    of distinct vision. We shall again have occasion to refer more particularly to
                    this idea in the next section.</p>
                <p>Professor Amici of Modena has described, in the Memoirs of the Italian Society, a
                    new micrometer, which gives double images by means of semi-lenses separated by
                    mechanical means; but as we have not access to this work, we shall draw our
                    description of the instrument from one given by Dr Pearson, which is very far
                    from being distinct, in so far at least as the construction of the semi-lenses,
                    or <hi rend="italic">bars of glass</hi> as they are called, are concerned. The
                    semi-lenses seem to be portions of a large concave lens, separated in the usual
                    manner, so as to give two distinct images of objects; but the peculiarity of the
                    invention seems to consist in the lenses being placed between the object-glass
                    of a telescope and its principal focus, the cone of rays being divided at a
                    point about six inches before the place where the focal image is formed. Dr
                    Pearson, who made experiments with one of these instruments, has hinted at the
                    inconveniences which he experienced in using it.</p>
                <p>CHAP. IV. DESCRIPTION OF DOUBLE-IMAGE MICROMETERS IN WHICH THE TWO IMAGES FORMED
                    BY TW0 SIMPLY REFRACTING LENSES, SEMI-LENSES, OR PRISMS, ARE SEPARATED
                    OPTICALLY.</p>
                <p>In the year 1776 Dr Maskelyne constructed and used his prismatic micrometer,
                    which he had contrived with the view of getting rid of the sources of error to
                    which he found the divided object-glass micrometer liable. Having cut a prism or
                    wedge of glass into two parts, so as to form two prisms of exactly the same
                    refracting angle, he conceived the idea of fixing them together, so as to
                    produce two images, and to vary the angle which these two images formed, by
                    making the prisms move between the object<pb break="no" facs="nls:193819430"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0715-9430-0017"/>-glass and its principal focus; so that the scale
                    is equal to the whole focal length of the telescope. The two prisms may be
                    placed in three, ways, with their thin edges joined, with their square thick
                    edges or backs joined, or with their sides or triangular edgés joined. In the
                    first position the double images will have only one half of the light which is
                    incident on the object-lens when the prisms are close to it, and their degree of
                    illumination will diminish as they approach the focus. In the second position
                    they will, as before, have only one half of the incident light when close to the
                    object-glass, but the illumination will gradually increase as the prisms advance
                    to the focus. In the third case, the prisms being in a reverse position, the
                    light will be the same in every part of the scale, each of them receiving half
                    the rays which fall upon the objectglass. On this account Dr Maskelyne preferred
                    this last arrangement.</p>
                <p>In the instrument which Dr Maskelyne constructed, and which seemed to have had
                    only a thirty-inch objectglass, the prisms were not achromatic, and consequently
                    the touching limbs of a luminous body were affected with the prismatic colours.
                    In the case of the sun, where all the rays might have been absorbed but the red,
                    this was of little consequence; but in other cases it was a serious defect,
                    which could be removed only by making the prisms achromatic; or it might have
                    been diminished by making the prisms of fluor spar, in which the dispersion is
                    very small. One of the Dollonds, accordingly, executed for Dr Maskelyne an
                    achromatic prism, which performed well. It does not appear that Dr Maskelyne
                    made any observations of value with this instrument.</p>
                <p>A new divided object-glass micrometer has been constructed by Sir David Brewster,
                    and described in his Treatise on New Philosophical Instruments. It consists of
                    an achromatic object-glass LL, fig. 7, between which and its principal focus/
                    two achromatic semi-lenses, fixed at a given distance, are made to move. These
                    lenses are shown in fig. 8, and are fixed on a piece of tube, which screws into
                    a tube; by pulling out and pushing in which, they are made to recede from or
                    approach to the object-glass LL. By this motion the angle subtended by the two
                    images varies in the same manner as the angle subtended by a pair of fixed wires
                    was made to vary by the motion of a second object-glass. When the semilenses are
                    close to LL, as shown at A, B, fig. 7, the two images which they form are much
                    separated, and their centres subtend a large angle; but as the lenses approach
                    to/ the centres of the images gradually approach each other, and consequently
                    the angle which they subtend continually increases. Hence, if we determine by
                    experiment the angular distance of their centres when the lenses are close to
                    LL, and likewise the angle when they are at <hi rend="italic">f</hi> the other
                    end of the scale, and if we fill up the intermediate points of the scale either
                    from theory or direct experiment, we shall have an instrument which will measure
                    with the greatest accuracy all angles between the two extreme ones. Another or
                    more pair of semi-lenses may be used in the same telescope, and placed at
                    smaller or greater distances, so that, by means of other scales adapted to them,
                    we may obtain all angles that may be required. The lenses A, B may be concave or
                    convex; and when a large scale is required, with a tenth of an inch to a second,
                    or even greater, we have only to use semi-lenses of long foci, and the scale may
                    be confined to the part of the tube nearest the focal point.</p>
                <p>Sir David Brewster has proved, both from theory and experiment, that the scale is
                    one of equal parts; so that, after having ascertained by experiment the two
                    extreme angles, the whole scales may be completed by dividing the interval into
                    any number of equal parts, and these subdivided, if necessary, by a vernier
                    scale.</p>
                <p>When the semi-lenses are placed without the objectglass LL, and this object-glass
                    moved towards <hi rend="italic">f</hi> as in the annexed figure, the angular
                    distance of the images is invariable.</p>
                <p>This instrument has been constructed for measuring distances, and as a coming-up
                    glass for ascertaining whether a ship is approaching to or receding from the
                    observer. In this form it constitutes part of fig. 4, Plate CCCLVII., the
                    semi-lenses being made to screw into the same place as the second object-glass,
                    and having a separate scale for themselves. In this form many of the instruments
                    have been constructed by Tulley.</p>
                <p>Among the optical micrometers, we may describe another invented by Sir David
                    Brewster, and adapted solely to the Newtonian telescope. In order to get rid of
                    the loss of light by the reflection of the small plane speculum, he uses an
                    achromatic prism to reflect the light just as much out of the axis of the
                    telescope as will allow the bead of the observer to be applied to the eye-tube,
                    without obstructing any of the light which enters the tube. By using two prisms,
                    as in Maskelyne’s instrument, and moving them along the axis of his telescope
                    through a small distance, we shall obtain a good micrometer. The prisms may be
                    separated mechanically, or a doubly refracting prism may be fixed upon the face
                    of the single or achromatic prism used to turn aside the rays. The achromatism
                    of a single glass prism may be corrected by the doubly refracting prism, a
                    balance of refraction being left sufficient to turn aside the image to the
                    observers eye.</p>
                <p>CHAP. V. DESCRIPTION OF DOUBLE-IMAGE MICROMETERS</p>
                <p>IN WHICH THE TWO IMAGES ARE FORMED BY DOUBLE REFRACTION.</p>
                <p>The happy idea of applying the two images formed by double refraction to the
                    construction of a micrometer unquestionably belongs to the Abbé Rochon; and
                    though Dr Pearson has laboured to show that Dr Maskelyne’s prismatic telescope
                    was constructed before Rochon’s, yet this does not in the smallest degree take
                    away from the originality and priority of Rochon’s invention; for the idea of
                    varying the angle by the motion of the prisms can scarcely be viewed as an
                    essential part of the invention.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819443" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9443-0018"/>
                <p>Although the double refraction of rock-crystal is small, yet, from its limpidity
                    and hardness, the Abbé Rochon regarded it as superior to any other substance for
                    making doubly refracting prisms. When he used one prism so cut that its
                    refracting edge coincided with the axis of the prism, in which case its double
                    refraction was the greatest, he found that the separation of the two images was
                    too small to-give the angles which he required.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In his first experiments Rochon corrected the
                    dispersion of the rock-crystal prism by a similar prism placed in front of it,
                    and having its exterior face perpendicular to the axis of the crystal. This
                    prism, having no effect in doubling the image, gave him a complete correction of
                    the dispersion for the ordinary image.</p></note> He therefore fell upon a most
                    ingenious plan of doubling the amount of the double refraction of one prism, by
                    using two prisms of rock-crystal, so cut out of the solid as to give each the
                    same quantity of double refraction, and yet to double that quantity in the
                    effect produced. This construction of the compound prism was so difficult, that
                    Μ. Rochon informs us, that “he knew only one person, Μ. Narci, who was capable
                    of giving rock-crystal the prismatic form in the proper direction for obtaining
                    the double refractions necessary to the goodness of the micrometer.” The method
                    used by Narci seems to have been kept a secret, for in 1819 Dr Wollaston set
                    himsèlf to discover the method of constructing these compound prisms, and has
                    described it in the Philosophical Transactions,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Phil. Trans. 1820, p. 126.</p></note> but not
                    in such a manner as to be very intelligible to those who are not familiar with
                    such subjects. We conceive that the process may be easily understood from the
                    following rule. Cut a hexagonal prism of quartz into two halves by a plane
                    passing through or parallel to its axis. Grind and polish the two cut faces, and
                    by means of Canada balsam cement the one upon the other, so that any line or
                    edge in the one face may be perpendicular to the same line in the other. Cut and
                    polish a face on each of the united portions, so that the common section of
                    these faces with the cemented planes may be parallel to the axis of the crystal,
                    while they are equally inclined to these planes, and the prism will be
                    completed.</p>
                <p>We shall now explain, by a diagram, a more simple and economical way of cutting
                    these prisms, though the principle is exactly the same. Let AKGDBLHF be half of
                    a hexagonal prism of quartz, the height of which, DF, is equal to half of its
                    diameter AD. Bisect AD in C, and join CK, CG, and draw CE parallel to AB or DF.
                    This line CE will be the axis of the prism. Grind and polish the section ABFD,
                    and cut off the prisms AKCBLE and DGCFHE, setting aside the intermediate similar
                    prism KGCLHF. The faces ACEB, DCEF arc square and equal, so that if we cement
                    these faces together, making the line AB coincide with FE, AC will coincide with
                    FD, CE with CF, and EB with CF. If we wish each prism to have an angle of 60°,
                    we may take either GDFH or GCEH for the refracting face of it; we shall suppose
                    the former. In this case we must grind and polish a face on the other prism ABL,
                    which is accurately parallel to the face GDFH, and the compound prism will be
                    completed. If 60° is too great, we must grind down the face GDFH till it has the
                    desired inclination to DF, and grind and polish a face parallel to it on the
                    other prism. The external faces, in short, to be made upon each prism, must be
                    equally inclined to the cemented planes DCEF, ABEC, and have their common
                    section DF parallel to the axis CE of the prism.</p>
                <p>In place of cutting off the prism AKCBLE, we may cut off only the prism GCDHEF,
                    leaving the intermediate one KGCLHE attached to AKCBLE, and proceed as before.
                    The object of this is to leave enough of solid quartz at KL to give a face of
                    the same breadth as GDFH. If the prisms required are small compared with the
                    quartz crystal, we may obtain, by the first method, six prisms out of the
                    crystal, or three pair of compound ones. On the other hand, if the required
                    prism is large compared with the crystal of quartz, it may require one half of
                    the crystal to make one prism, and the other half the other. Nay, it may be
                    necessary to cut each individual prism out of separate crystals, the method of
                    doing which is very obvious from the preceding description.</p>
                <p>When the prism is completed, it is obvious that a ray of light incident
                    perpendicularly on the face GHFD wi∏ be perpendicular to the axis of the prism
                    CE, and therefore the extraordinary ray will suffer the greatest deviation, viz.
                    17'; and the same is true of the other prism. But when the ray passes through
                    both, it is found to have a deviation of 34', which is produced in the following
                    manner: Let AB be a line viewed through one of the prisms, with its refracting
                    angle turned upwards; two images of it will be seen, viz. the extraordinary
                    image at E, and the ordinary one at 0.</p>
                <p>If we now interpose the other prism with its refracting angle downwards, both
                    these images E, O will be refracted downwards. But, owing to the transverse
                    cutting of the prisms, the extraordinary image E, which was most raised, now
                    suffers ordinary refraction, and is least depressed, so that in place of being
                    refracted back to AB, it comes only to E'O'. On the other hand, the ordinary
                    image 0, which suffered the least refraction, is now extraordinarily refracted,
                    and, in place of reaching AB, is depressed to O'E'; and since the double
                    refraction of each prism, as well as the angles of the prism, are equal, the
                    angular distance of the images E'O', O'E ’ formed by the combined prisms will be
                    double of the distance EO, or 34'.</p>
                <p>The same rule may be followed in cutting the prism out of the limpid arid
                    homogeneous topazes of New Holland, the principal axis of which coincides with
                    the axis of the prism. When the crystals are amorphous, the cleavage planes will
                    be a sufficient guide, as the above axis is always perpendicular to them. Such
                    prisms are incomparably superior, as we have practically experienced, to those
                    made of rock-crystal.</p>
                <p>When a very large angle is required for any particular purposes, artificial
                    crystals, such as carbonate of potash, &amp;c. may be advantageously employed,
                    the crystals being ground with oil, or any fluid in which they are not soluble.
                    By cementing plates of parallel glass on their outer surfaces, they will be as
                    permanent as rock-crystal.</p>
                <p>Dr Pearson fitted up with one of Rochon’s micrometers an achromatic telescope 33
                    inches in focal length, and having a magnifying power of 35½. He applied to it
                    two separate compound prisms, one of which had a constant angle of 32', and the
                    other an angle only of 5', the vernier in the former case indicating seconds,
                    and in the latter tenths of seconds. A drawing is given of the tube, with the
                    prisms and scales, in Plate CCCLVII. fig. 9 and 10, as given by Dr Pearson. The
                    tube is graduated from the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819456"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0715-9456-0019"/>solar focus into two scales, one being placed on
                    each side of the slit or opening cut along the middle of the tubes, to allow the
                    sliding piece, shown separately in fig. 10, to move from the object-glass to the
                    solar focus. This sliding piece holds the prism, the larger prism of 32' being
                    shown as placed with its sliding piece in the tube, and the smaller prism of 5'
                    being shown in the separate sliding piece, fig. 9. The two verniers of the
                    scales are seen on each side of the two screws with milled beads, which pass
                    through the slit, and serve to move the sliding piece to or from the
                    object-glass when they are not too much tightened.</p>
                <p>In his original memoir on the subject, published in the <hi rend="italic">Journal
                    de Physique</hi> for 1801,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Translated in Nicholson’s Journal, 8vo, vol. iv. p. 110-120.</p></note>
                    M.Rochon makes the following observations. “I ought not to omit, that in this
                    new construction there are difficulties of execution not easy to surmount, which
                    may have been one reason why these instruments, so useful to navigators, and in
                    certain very nice astronomical observations, have not been adopted. This induced
                    me at length to adopt Euler’s method. In the construction of achromatic
                    object-glasses I found I could increase or diminish the absolute effect of the
                    double refraction within certain limits, by means <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the
                    interval between the glasses of different refracting powers; the separation of
                    the images at the focus being so much the greater, as the interval is larger,
                    when the flint-glass is the first of the object-glasses, and less when it is the
                    second. Conformably to these new principles, I have had two telescopes with a
                    doubly refracting medium constructed under my own inspection, which General
                    Gantheaumc will employ for determining the position of his ships, and to find
                    whether he be approaching any he may meet with at sea.”<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">It&gt;id∙</hi> p∙
                    117∙</p></note></p>
                <p>In 1812 Μ. Rochon constructed his doubly refracting micrometer in another form,
                    from which he anticipated great advantages. He made a parallelopiped of
                    rock-crystal, consisting of two prisms whose refracting angles were each about
                    30°, so that the angle which they gave was less than 30', and the two images of
                    the sun of course overlapped each other. The prisms being firmly united by
                    mastic, he ground the parallelopiped into a convex lens, so that when combined
                    with a concave one of flint-glass, it formed an achromatic object-glass with a
                    focal length of about 3 decimetres, or nearly 12 inches. This object-glass
                    separated the centres of the images of the sun about 28 minutes. “He then
                    adapted to this objectglass a common micrometer, which measured angles of 10
                    minutes, and he had thus 3 decimetres and 10 minutes to complete the measure of
                    the diameters of the sun or moon.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>“This description is not very intelligible, but we cannot at
                    present refer to the original memoir.</p></note></p>
                <p>Μ. Arago appears to have been the first person to apply doubly refracting prisms
                    to the eye-pieces of telescopes for the purpose of measuring very small angles.
                    He explained his general method to the writer of this article in July 1814, and
                    mentioned the results which he had obtained with it in measuring the diameters
                    of the planets. We do not recollect distinctly how he varied the constant angle
                    of the doubly refracting prism; but Dr Pearson and ,Μ. Biot state,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Introduction to Practical
                    Astronomy, vol. ii. p. 20G-212.</p></note> that the constant angle was increased
                    by placing the prism in an oblique direction as regards the line of vision; and
                    “that he determined the respective values of the angles thus increased by means
                    of concentric circles placed vertically at a measured distance from the eye
                    wheii looking through the prism; for as he knew the diameters of each circle, he
                    could generally find one out of the number which would come into exact contact
                    with its image, and thus give the value of the constant angle.”<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>We regret that Μ. Arago has,
                    in so far as we know, not published an account of his methods. What Dr Pearson
                    says is not very intelligible. We presume his meaning to be, that Μ. Arago made
                    his scale for measuring the varying angle of the images by direct
                    experiment.</p></note></p>
                <p>Dr Pearson has proposed an <hi rend="italic">ocular crystal micrometer,</hi> and
                    has given a drawing and description of the instrument.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Introd. Pract. Astron, vol. ii. p.
                    219.</p></note> It is nothing more than Μ. Arago’s ocular crystal prism, in
                    which the constant angle is varied by Sir David Brewster’s variable eye-piece
                    already described. On the same principle, the angle of the prism may be varied
                    by a convex or concave lens moving between the object-glass and its principal
                    focus; but what would be still better, by pulling out or pushing in the
                    eye-piece of a Gregorian or Cassegrainian telescope.</p>
                <p>In 1821 Mr George Dollond communicated to the Royal Society an account of his
                    spherical crystal micrometer, a very ingenious instrument, though, we should
                    think, one difficult to execute; and, at the same time, even when well executed,
                    liable to error. Mr Dollond’s improvement consists in making a sphere or lens
                    from a piece of rock-crystal, and adapting it to a telescope in place of the
                    usual eye-glass, as shown in Plate CCCLVII. fig. 11, where <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi> is the sphere or lens, formed of rock-crystal, and placed in <hi
                    rend="italic">half holes,</hi> from which is extended the axis <hi rend="italic"
                    >bb,</hi> with an attached index, the face of which is shown in fig. 12. This
                    index registers the motion of the sphere on the graduated circle. The sphere <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> is so placed in the half holes, that when its natural axis
                    (axis of double refraction, we presume) is parallel to the axis of the
                    telescope, it gives only one image of the object. In a direction perpendicular
                    to that axis, it must be so placed that when it is moved the separation of the
                    images may be parallel to that motion. The method of acquiring this adjustment
                    is by turning the sphere <hi rend="italic">a</hi> in the half holes parallel to
                    its own axis. A second lens <hi rend="italic">d</hi> is introduced between the
                    sphere and the primary image given by the object-glass, and its distance from
                    the sphere should be in proportion to the magnifying power required. The
                    magnifying powers engraven in fig. 12 are suited to an object-glass of 44 inches
                    focal length. The following are the advantages of this construction, as stated
                    by its inventor. 1. It is only necessary to select a piece of perfect crystal,
                    and, without any knowledge of the angle that will give the greatest double
                    refraction, to form the sphere of a proper diameter for the focal length
                    required. 2. The angle may be taken on each side of <hi rend="italic">zero,</hi>
                    without reversing the eye-tube; and intermediate angles may be taken between
                    zero and the greatest separation of the images, without exchanging any part of
                    the eye-tube, it being only required to move the axis in which the sphere is
                    placed. 3. It possesses the property of a common eye-tube and lens; for when the
                    axis of the crystal is parallel to that of the objpet-glass, only one image will
                    be formed, and that as distinctly as with any lens that does not refract
                    doubly.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Phil. Trans.
                    1821, p. 101-104.</p></note></p>
                <p>Dr Pearson had one of these instruments constructed by Mr Dollond, and applied to
                    an achromatic object-glass 43∙6 inches in focal length. He has shown that the
                    scale is not one of equal parts, and has pointed out a method of determining the
                    constant angle of the crystal.</p>
                <p>Knowing from experience the imperfect structure of rock-crystal, especially in
                    directions approaching to the axis, we dreaded that a spherical eye-glass of
                    this material would not give perfect vision. Dr Pearson confirms this opinion by
                    actual observation. He attempted to measure the diameter of Mars when about 9",
                    “but its limits were <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819469"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0715-9469-0020"/>so imperfectly defined that no satisfactory
                    observation could be made.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Introd. Pract. Astron, vol. ii. p. 233.</p></note> We would therefore
                    strongly recommend to Mr Dollond the substitution of limpid topaz from New
                    Holland, in place of the rock-crystal.</p>
                <p>CHAP. VI. DESCRIPTION OF POSITION MICROMETERS.</p>
                <p>A position micrometer is an instrument for measuring angles when a plane passing
                    through the two lines which contain these angles is perpendicular to the axis of
                    vision. Sir W. Herschel first proposed such an instrument for the purpose of
                    verifying a conjecture, that the smaller of the two stars which compose a double
                    star revolves round the larger one. Hence it became necessary to observe if a
                    line joining the centres of any two stars always formed the same angle with the
                    direction of its daily motion. After constructing the instrument which we are
                    about to describe, and making a long series of observations, he verified his
                    conjecture by the important discovery, that the double stars formed binary
                    systems, in which the one revolved round the other.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In the case of the double star <hi
                    rend="italic">Castor,</hi> this revolution is performed in 342 years.</p></note>
                    The position micrometer used by Sir William Herschel in his earliest
                    observations, viz. those made in 1779-1783, was made by Nairne, and was
                    constructed as shown in Plate CCCLVII. fig. 13, which represents it when
                    enclosed in. a turned case of wood, and ready to be screwed into the eye-piece
                    of the telescope. “A is a little box which holds the eye-glass. B is the piece
                    which covers the inside work, and the box A screwed into it. C is the body of
                    the micrometer, containing the brass work, showing the index-plate <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> projecting at one side, where the case is cut away to
                    receive it. D is a piece having a screw <hi rend="italic">b</hi> at the bottom,
                    by means of which the micrometer is fastened to the telescope. To the piece C is
                    given a circular motion, in the manner the horizontal motion is generally given
                    to Gregorian reflectors, by the lower part going through the piece D, where it
                    is held by the screw E, which keeps the two pieces C and D together, but leaves
                    them at liberty to turn on each other. Fig. 14 is a section of the case
                    containing the brass work, where may be observed the piece B hollowed out to
                    receive the box A, which consists of two parts enclosing the eye-lens. This
                    figure shows how the piece C passes through D, and is held by the ring E. The
                    brass work, consisting of a hollow cylinder, a wheel and pinion, and
                    index-plate, is there represented in its place. F is the body of the brass work,
                    being a hollow cylinder with a broad rim C at its upper end; this rim is partly
                    turned away to make a bed for the wheel <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> The pinion <hi
                    rend="italic">e</hi> turns the wheel <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> and carries the
                    index-plate <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> One of its pivots moves in the arm <hi
                    rend="italic">f</hi> screwed on “the upper part of <hi rend="italic">c,</hi>
                    which arm serves also to confine the wheel <hi rend="italic">d</hi> to its place
                    on c. The other pivot is held by the arm <hi rend="italic">g</hi> fastened to
                    F.</p>
                <p>A section of the brass work is shown in fig. 15, where the wheel <hi
                    rend="italic">d,</hi> which is in the form of a ring, is laid on the upper part
                    of F or C, and held by two small arms / <hi rend="italic">h,</hi> screwed down
                    to <hi rend="italic">e</hi> with the screws <hi rend="italic">i, i.</hi></p>
                <p>A plan of the brass work is shown in fig. 16, where <hi rend="italic">d d</hi> is
                    the wheel placed on the bed or socket of the rim of the cylinder <hi
                    rend="italic">cc,</hi> and is held down by the two pieces ∕ A, which are screwed
                    on <hi rend="italic">cc.</hi> The piece ∕projects over the centre of the
                    index-plate to receive the upper pivot of the pinion <hi rend="italic">mn,</hi>
                    the fixed wire being fastened to <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> cc,</hi> and the
                    moveable wire <hi rend="italic">op,</hi> fastened to the annular wheel <hi
                    rend="italic">dd.</hi> The index-plate <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> milled on the
                    edge, is divided into sixty parts, each subdivided into two. V√hen the finger is
                    drawn over the milled edge of the index-plate from <hi rend="italic">q</hi> to
                    <hi rend="italic">r,</hi> the angle <hi rend="italic">rnso</hi> will open, and
                    if drawn from <hi rend="italic">r</hi> towards <hi rend="italic">q,</hi> it will
                    shut again. The case <hi rend="italic">cc</hi> must have a sharp corner <hi
                    rend="italic">t,</hi> which serves as an index to point out the divisions on the
                    index-plate.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Phil.
                    Trans. 1781, p. 503.</p></note></p>
                <p>We do not know the value of the divisions in the instrument used by Sir William
                    Herschel; but in the position micrometer of the five-feet equatorial used by Sir
                    John Herschel and Sir James South, in their observations on double stars, the
                    position circle was large enough to show distinctly minutes of a degree by means
                    of its vernier.</p>
                <p>The position micrometer which we have now described has been greatly improved by
                    Sir David Brewster; and the following account of these improvements, which is
                    not susceptible of abridgment, is given in his own words.</p>
                <p>In the position micrometer invented by Sir William Herschel, “the two wires
                    always cross each other at the centre of the field, and consequently their
                    angular separation is produced uniformly by the motion of the pinion. This very
                    circumstance, however, though it renders it easy for the observer to read off
                    the angle from the scale, is one of the greatest imperfections of the
                    instrument. The observations must obviously be all made on one side of the
                    centre of the field, as appears from fig. 16; and the use of the instrument is
                    limited to those cases in which Ss is less than the radius SC. The greatest
                    disadvantage of the instrument, however, is the shortness of the radius SC; for
                    the error of observation must always diminish as the length of this raditfs
                    increases. This disadvantage does not exist in measuring the angle of position
                    of two stars S, <hi rend="italic">s, for</hi> the distance Ss remains the same
                    whatever be the length of SC; but in determining the angle which a line joining
                    two stars forms with a line joining other two stars, or those which compose a
                    double star (an observation which it may often be of great importance to make),
                    and all other angles contained by lines whose apparent length is greater than
                    SC, this imperfection is inseparable from the instrument. Nay, there are some
                    cases in which the instrument completely fails; as, for instance, when we wish
                    to measure the angles formed by two lines which do not meet in a focus, but only
                    tend to a remote vertex. If the distance of the nearest extremities of these
                    lines is greater than the chord of the angle which they form measured upon the
                    radius SC, then it is impossible to measure that angle, for the wires cannot be
                    brought to coincide with the lines by which it is contained. Nay, when the chord
                    of the angle does exceed the distance between the nearest extremities, the
                    position of the wires which can be brought into coincidence with the lines is so
                    small as to lead to very serious errors in the result.</p>
                <p>The new position micrometer which we propose to substitute for this instrument is
                    free from the defects just noticed, and is founded on a beautiful property of
                    the circle. If any two chords, AB, CD, fig. 12, intersect each other in the
                    point O within the circle, the angle which they form at 0 will be equal to half
                    the sum of the arches AC, BD; but if these chords do not intersect each other
                    within the circle, but tend to any point 0 without the circle, when they would
                    intersect each other if continued, as in fig. 13, then the angle which they form
                    is equal to half the difference of the arches AC, BD; that is, calling <hi
                    rend="italic">&lt;ρ</hi> the angle required, we have, in the first case, as
                    shown in fig. 12,</p>
                <p>AC + BD , . <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic">&lt;f&gt;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> ·_·; and in the second case, as shown in fig.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819482" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9482-0021"/>
                <p>13, <hi rend="italic">&lt;p</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="strikethrough"
                    >g BD</hi>. Hence, if the two wires AB, CD be placed in the focus of the first
                    eye-glass of a telescope, the moveable one AB may be made to form every possible
                    angle with the fixed one CD, and that angle may be readily found from the arches
                    AB, CD.</p>
                <p>The mechanism for measuring these arches is shown in Plate CCCLVIII. fig. 17,
                    where the graduated circular head CD may be divided only into 180°, in order to
                    save the trouble of halving the sum or the difference of the arches AC, BD; but
                    as it would still be necessary to measure <hi rend="italic">two</hi> arches
                    before the angle could be ascertained, we have adopted another method,
                    remarkable for its simplicity, and giving no more trouble than if the wires
                    always intersected each other in the centre of the field.</p>
                <p>Let AB, for example, fig. 13, be the fixed wire, and CD the moveable one, and let
                    it be required to find at one observation the angle AOC or ç&gt;. Set the index
                    of the vernier to <hi rend="italic">zero</hi> when D coincides with B; and as C
                    will be at <hi rend="italic">c</hi> when D is at B, the arch cAwill
                    beaconstantquantity, which we shall call <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Making AC =
                    <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> and BD = <hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> i</hi> we have <hi rend="italic">&lt;p ~</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> m</hi><hi rend="superscript"> n</hi>. But since the extremity C
                    will move over the space Cc while D describes the space DB, these arches must be
                    equal, consequently <hi rend="italic">b = rn</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">η</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> hence, adding 2n to each side of
                    the equation, we obtain <hi rend="italic">b + 2n</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> 1 1</hi><hi rend="italic">m + n .</hi><hi rend="italic">= m +
                    n</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> or ½ <hi rend="italic">o + n</hi> =
                    —~—, consequently <hi rend="italic">φ = ½ b + η.</hi> Hence the angle AOC is
                    equal to half the arch Ac added to the arch DB; or, since Ac is invariable, the
                    half of it is a constant quantity, and the angle required is equal to the sum of
                    this constant quantity and the arch DB.</p>
                <p>When the wires do not intersect each other, as in fig. 13, we have <hi
                    rend="italic">φ</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    m</hi><hi rend="superscript"> ¾</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">b = m + n;</hi>
                    hence, sub-trading <hi rend="italic">2n</hi> from each side of the equation, we
                    have <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">2n =
                    nι</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">n</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> i</hi> and, dividing by 2, we have ½ <hi rend="italic">b</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">n</hi> = ———, consequently <hi
                    rend="italic">&lt;f&gt; = ½ b</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >n.</hi> That is, the angle AOC is equal to the difference between half the arch
                    Ac and the arch DB, or to a constant quantity diminished by the arch DB.</p>
                <p>In finding the angle AOC, therefore, we have merely to observe the place of the
                    index when the wires are in their proper position; and as the scale commences at
                    B, or where D and B coincide, and is numbered both ways from B, the degree
                    pointed out on the circular head CD, when increased or diminished by the
                    constant quantity, will give the angle of the wires which is sought. The
                    semicircle on each side of a diameter drawn through B is divided into 180°, the
                    180th degree being at the opposite end of that diameter.</p>
                <p>We may simplify still further the method of reading off the angle AOC, so as to
                    save the trouble even of recollecting the constant quantity, and of adding it
                    to, or subtracting it from, the arch pointed out by the index of the vernier.
                    This advantage is obtained by making the index of the vernier point to the
                    constant quantity upon the part of the scale below B, fig. 12, when the points
                    D, B coincide, or when the wire CD is in the dotted position cB; for it is
                    obvious that if <hi rend="italic">z</hi> marks the zero of the scale, and Bz is
                    equal to the constant quantity, the arch <hi rend="italic">Oz,</hi> which is
                    pointed out by the index of the vernier, will be equal to <hi rend="italic">½ b
                    + n</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> y</hi> or the angle AOC. In like manner, in
                    fig. 13, where the wires do not cross each other within the field, and where Bz
                    is the constant quantity, the arch Dz marked out by the index of the vernier is
                    obviously equal to ½ó—n, or the angle AOC, which the wires tend to form at 0. By
                    means of this adjustment, therefore, we are able to read off the angle AOC with
                    the same facility as if the wires intersected each other in the centre of the
                    field, when the arches are accurate measures of the angles at the centre.</p>
                <p>The end of the eye-tube is represented in Plate CCCLVIII. fig. 17, where the
                    circular head CD is divided into 360°, and subdivided by the vernier V. L is the
                    level, and AB the part of the eye-piece which contains the diaphragm, with the
                    fixed and moveable wires. The head CD, and the level L, are firmly fixed to the
                    eye-tube T; and from the head CD there rises an annular shoulder, concentric
                    with the tube, and containing the diaphragm, across which the fixed wire is
                    stretched. This diaphragm, which is rcpre≠ sented in fig 18, with the wire
                    extended across, projects through the circle of brass EF. All these parts remain
                    immoveable, while the outer tube AB, and the other half EF, of the circular head
                    which contains the vernier V, have a rotatory motion upon the shoulder, which
                    rises from CD. The tube AB is merely an outer case, to protect a little tube
                    within it, which contains the eye-glass, and the moveable diaphragm, with its
                    wire extended across it. The enclosed tube is screwed into the ring EF, and the
                    outer tube is also screwed upon the same ring, so that by moving AB, a motion of
                    rotation is communicated to the vernier V, and to the diaphragm and wire
                    belonging to the inner tube, while the rest of the eye-piece, containing the
                    other diaphragm with its wire, remains stationary. By these means the moveable
                    wire is made to form every possible angle with the fixed wire, and the angle is
                    determined by the method which we have already explained. The fixed wire is
                    placed a good deal ont of the centre of the diaphragm to which it belongs; and
                    the diaphragm itself is placed in a cell, in which it can be turned round so as
                    to adjust the wire to a horizontal line when the level is set. The moveable wire
                    is likewise placed at a distance from the&gt;centre of its diaphragm, as shown
                    in Plate CCCLVIII. fig. 19; but, by means of screws which pass through the inner
                    tube into the edge of this diaphragm, it can be moved in a plane at right angles
                    to the axis of the eye-piece, so that the moveable wire may be placed either in
                    the centre of the field or at different distances from it.</p>
                <p>The double-image micrometer affords a convenient method of measuring angles of
                    position; and we believe this application of it was first made by Sir David
                    Brewster.</p>
                <p>In every instrument in which a double image of an object is formed by means of
                    two semi-lenses with their centres at a distance, the one image appears to have
                    a rotatory motion round the other when the telescope is turned about its axis.
                    Thus, in Plate CCCLVIII. fig. 20, if A, B be images of two objects formed by the
                    upper semi-lens when the common diameter of the semi-lenses is perpendicular to
                    the horizon, and C, D the images of the same objects formed by the lower
                    semi-lens; then, by turning the telescope about its axis, or the semi-lenses
                    round in their tube, the image A will appear to move round C in the circle A«E,
                    and the image B round D in the circle B6F, or in the opposite direction if the
                    telescope, or the semi-lenses, arc turned the other way. When the distance AC is
                    equal to CD, as in fig. 21, the image A will pass over the image D; or if the
                    telescope is turned in the opposite direction, the image B will pass over the
                    image C. In like manner, when AC is greater or less than CD, the images will
                    move as we have represented them in fig. 20 and 22. In all these cases the four
                    images may be brought into one straight line; and when this takes place, <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193819495" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9495-0022"/> the line which
                    passes through all the images will uniformly form the same angle with the
                    horizon, as the common diameter of the semi-lenses. It is very easy to ascertain
                    with the utmost accuracy when the images form one straight line; but
                    particularly in the case where AC, fig. 21, is equal to CD, for the image of A
                    will then pass over D; and the coincidence of the images will mark the instant
                    when the line which joins them is parallel to the common diameter of the lenses.
                    Hence, as we obtain by this means the relation of the line joining the images to
                    a fixed line in the instrument, the relation of this line to the horizon may be
                    easily found by means of a level, and a divided circular head. If the image is a
                    straight line (fig. 22), then the coincidence of the two images, so as to form
                    one straight line, will indicate the parallelism of that line to the diameter of
                    the semi-lenses.</p>
                <p>In constructing a micrometer <hi rend="italic">of</hi> this kind solely for the
                    purpose of measuring angles when the eye is not at their vertex, either the
                    object-glass or the third eye-glass might be made the divided lens. If the
                    object-glass is divided, it should be so constructed that it may have a rotatory
                    motion in its cell, by applying the hand to a milled circumference AB, Plate
                    CCCLVIII. fig. 23. Connected with the tube TT of the telescope is a circular
                    ring of brass CD divided into 360°; and the divisions upon this scale are
                    pointed out by the index of a vernier <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> which moves
                    along with the semi-lenses. A level L is fixed to the plate AB, having its axis
                    parallel to the common diameter of the lenses, and being adjusted to a
                    horizontal line when the index points to the zero of the scale. In using the
                    instrument, therefore, the observer turns round the semi-lenses by means of the
                    projecting milled circumference AB, till the coincidence of the two images is
                    distinctly perceived. The index of the vernier will then point out upon the
                    graduated head the inclination of the line which is required.</p>
                <p>When the telescope is long, this form of the instrument, though extremely simple,
                    is not very convenient. The construction represented in Plate CCCLVIII. fig. 24,
                    is in general to be preferred. This instrument consists of three tubes BL, LC,
                    CA. At the extremity B of the first tube is placed the divided object-glass, and
                    at the other extremity L is fixed the divided circular head EF. The tube CL,
                    which remains always at rest, is fixed to the stand HI by means of the clasp and
                    screw at H. The tube AC, which contains an eye-piece, moves within both the
                    tubes CL and LB. The tube BL extends towards C within the tube CL, and round its
                    circumference are cut a number of teeth, in which the endless 'screw G works,
                    and thus gives a rotatory motion to the tube LB and the divided head EF. By this
                    means the common diameter of the semi-lenses at B is made to form every possible
                    angle with a horizontal line, which is indicated-by a level above L, having its
                    axis parallel to the common diameter of the semi-lenses. The index of the
                    vernier <hi rend="italic">v,</hi> fixed to the stationary tube CL, points out on
                    the graduated head the angle required. When the instrument is constructed so
                    that the semi-lenses are in the eye-piece, the graduated head must be placed in
                    the eye-tube.</p>
                <p>If the principle of this micrometer is applied to the double-image micrometer
                    described in Chap. IV. in which a pair of fixed semi-lenses moves between the
                    object-glass and its principal focus, we obtain an instrument which will measure
                    at the same observation the angle subtended at the eye of the observer by a line
                    joining two points, and likewise the angle which that line forms with the
                    horizon or any other line. When the two images of the line which joins the two
                    points are brought into contact by the motion of the semi-lenses along the axis
                    of the tube, these images must necessarily be in the same straight line, so that
                    the relation of that line to the horizon, or to any other given line, and the
                    contact of the two images of it which determines its angular magnitude, are
                    obtained simultaneously, without any additional observation or adjustment.</p>
                <p>Dr Pearson has given some very useful details respecting the use of double-image
                    micrometers in measuring angles of position.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Introd, to Practical Astron, vol. ii. p. 25ð.</p></note></p>
                <p>When the brightness of the two stars which compose a double star is considerable,
                    their discs may be drawn out into lines of light either by cylindrical
                    refraction or reflection, and the coincidence of these lines will furnish the
                    means of determining the angle of position.</p>
                <p>A position micrometer upon a new principle has been proposed by Sir David
                    Brewster. He expands the images of the two stars into luminous discs till they
                    overlap each other. The southern limb of the lower disc is then made to move
                    along the fixed wire of the position micrometer. A line joining the two points
                    where the circumferences of the discs intersect each other, is obviously
                    perpendicular to a line joining the centres of the stars, and will therefore
                    form an angle with the fixed wire-equal to the complement of the angle of
                    position required. If we therefore make the moveable wire pass through the two
                    points where the luminous discs intersect each other, the micrometer scale will
                    give the complement of the angle of position.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Treatise on New Philosophical Instruments, p.
                    45.</p></note></p>
                <p>CHAP. VII. DESCRIPTION OF THE LAMP MICROMETER</p>
                <p>AND THE LUCID-DISC MICROMETER.</p>
                <p>In measuring the distances and angle of position of double stars, Sir William
                    Herschel encountered many practical difficulties which interfered with the
                    accuracy of his results. The uncertainty of the real zero of his scale, the
                    inflexion of light, the imperfections of the screws and divided bars and
                    pinions, and the difficulty of obtaining fibres sufficiently minute for his
                    purpose, but, above all, the disappearance of small stars by the illumination of
                    the wire, led this eminent astronomer to the contrivance of his <hi
                    rend="italic">lamp micrometer,</hi> which, while it is exempt from these sources
                    of error, has also the advantage of a large scale.</p>
                <p>The lamp micrometer is represented in Plate CCCLVIII. fig. 25, where AB is the
                    upright part of the stand, 9 feet high, upon which a wooden semicircle <hi
                    rend="italic">qhogp,</hi> 14 inches radius, may be fixed at different heights,
                    by a peg <hi rend="italic">p</hi> put into holes in the stand. An arm L, 30
                    inches long, moves round a pivot in the centre of the board by means of the
                    handle P, which works by a string <hi rend="italic">eqho</hi> fastened to a hook
                    at the back of L. The arm L is kept at any inclination to the horizon by the
                    weight of the handle P, which is 10 feet long. A small slider <hi rend="italic"
                    >b,</hi> about 3 inches long, moves along the front of L towards and from the
                    centre at <hi rend="italic">n,</hi> by means of the handle rD, which operates by
                    a string passing over the pulley <hi rend="italic">m,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> returning by <hi rend="italic">η</hi> to a barrel at
                    <hi rend="italic">τ,</hi> while a second string <hi rend="italic">bnw,</hi> with
                    a weight <hi rend="italic">w,</hi> causes the slider <hi rend="italic">b</hi> to
                    return to the centre. The end of the arm L is shown on a large scale in fig.
                    26.</p>
                <p>Two lamps <hi rend="italic">a, b,</hi> figs. 27 and 28, 1½ inch high and 1∣ inch
                    deep, having sliding doors with small apertures made with a fine needle opposite
                    the flame of a single cotton-thread wick, so that when the sliders are shut
                    down, nothing is seen but two fine lucid points like stars of the third or
                    fourth magnitude. The lamp <hi rend="italic">α</hi> is placed at the centre <hi
                    rend="italic">τι,</hi> so that its lucid point may occupy that centre, while <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> is hung on the slider S, so that its lucid point may be in
                    a line with the lucid point of <hi rend="italic">a</hi> when the arm L has a
                    horizontal position.</p>
                <p>A person, therefore, at a distance of ten feet <hi rend="subscript"> r</hi> may
                    govern <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819508" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9508-0023"/>the two
                    lucid points so as to bring them into any required position by the handle P; and
                    by the handle D he may place them at any distance, from six tenths of an inch to
                    twenty-five inches.</p>
                <p>In using this micrometer, SirW. Herschel placed it ten feet from his left eye,
                    while with his right he viewed a double star through his Newtonian reflector. By
                    means of his left eye the double star is seen projected upon the micrometer, and
                    he then placed his two lucid points at such a distance that they were exactly
                    covered by the stars. The distance of the lucid points was the tangent of the
                    magnified angles subtended by the stars to a radius of ten feet. This angle,
                    therefore, being divided by the magnifying power of the telescope, gives the
                    real angular distance of the centres of a double star. With a power of 460 the
                    scale was a quarter of an inch for every second. Sir W. Herschel, in measuring
                    the apparent diameter of α <hi rend="italic">Lyrae</hi> with this instrument,
                    used a magnifying power of 6450. The magnified angle was 38' 10", so that the
                    real 38 ’ 10"</p>
                <p>angle was - <hi rend="strikethrough smallcaps"> √v</hi><hi rend="subscript
                    strikethrough smallcaps"> l</hi><hi rend="strikethrough smallcaps"> &gt;∩</hi> =
                    0"∙355, giving on this occasion a scale Oτt <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> O
                    U</p>
                <p>of no less than 8½ inches to a second.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Phil. Trans, vol. Ixxiì. p. 102.</p></note></p>
                <p>In using high magnifying powers, Sir W. Herschel employed another apparatus
                    called the lucid-disc micrometer. A lucid disc made of oiled paper, or any other
                    semi-transparent substance, was placed in the front slider of a lantern, and
                    illuminated by a flame behind it. The lantern was then removed to a distance
                    till the diameter of the disc appeared equal to that of a planet seen in the
                    telescope, so that the angular diameter of the planet became known by dividing
                    the angle subtended by the disc by the magnifying power of the telescope. The
                    result was affected by the colour of the disc and the degree of illumination.
                    The measure was always too small when the illumination was strong, and too great
                    when a black disc was placed on an illuminated ground. Hence Sir William
                    Herschel took a mean of the two as the true measure.</p>
                <p>Μ. Schroeter of Lilienthal, in measuring the diameters of the four new planets,
                    used a lucid-disc micrometer, which we presume was not much different from Sir
                    W. Herschel’s.</p>
                <p>Dr Pearson constructed and used an analogous instrument, in which the left eye
                    looked into a tube containing a system of lines upon a disc of glass, or a
                    spider’s line micrometer, so that the object seen with the right eye was
                    projected against these divisions, and its angular diameter ascertained.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Introd. Tract. Astron, vol.
                    ii. p. 245.</p></note></p>
                <p>CHAP. VIII DESCRIPTION OF FIXED MICROMETERS WITH</p>
                <p>AN INVARIABLE SCALE.</p>
                <p>The earliest fixed micrometer of which we have a distinct account is that of
                    Huygens, who placed a circular diaphragm in the focus of the eye-glass of his
                    telescope, and found its angular value to be seventeen and a quarter minutes by
                    the time which a star took to pass across it. He then formed two or three long
                    brass plates of different breadths so as to form wedges of different angles. In
                    measuring the diameter of a planet with one of these, he made one of them slide
                    through two slits in the opposite sides of the tube, so that the plane of the
                    brass wedges touched the plane of the circular diaphragm; and having observed in
                    what part of the wedge its breadth just covered the whole planet, he took this
                    breadth in a pair of compasses, and having found what part it was of the whole
                    aperture, he divided seventeen and a quarter minutes by this part, and obtained
                    the diameter required. Sir Isaac</p>
                <p>Newton has stated, that the measures thus taken are always in excess. Had Huygens
                    used long wedge-shaped slits or openings, he would by the same process have
                    obtained measures which erred in defect, and the mean between these two measures
                    would have given the true diameter of the planet.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">reticulum</hi> or fixed micrometer, composed of wires, was
                    invented and used by Cassini. It is shown in the annexed figure, where <hi
                    rend="italic">ab,</hi><hi rend="italic">cd, er, gh,</hi> are four hairs or wires
                    intersecting each other at right angles at <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> in the
                    focus of the eye-glass, <hi rend="italic">ab,</hi><hi rend="italic">cd</hi>
                    being inclined 45° to <hi rend="italic">er</hi> and <hi rend="italic">gk.</hi>
                    In order to find with this apparatus the differences of the right ascension and
                    declination of two stars, direct the telescope so that the first or <hi
                    rend="italic">preceding</hi> star may appear upon the wire <hi rend="italic"
                    >ab,</hi> and turn round the tube till that star moves along <hi rend="italic"
                    >ab.</hi> The time when this star reaches <hi rend="italic">i</hi> is carefully
                    noted, and also the time when the <hi rend="italic">following</hi> star reaches
                    the wire <hi rend="italic">ed.</hi> The interval between these times, converted
                    into degrees, is the difference of right ascension required. To find the
                    difference of their declinations, mark the time of the second or <hi
                    rend="italic">following</hi> star’s arrival at the points <hi rend="italic"
                    >k</hi> and <hi rend="italic">l</hi> of the oblique wires <hi rend="italic">er,
                    gh.</hi> The half of the interval between these times is the time in which the
                    star describes the space <hi rend="italic">lm</hi> or <hi rend="italic">mk,</hi>
                    which, converted into degrees <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> is the angular distance
                    <hi rend="italic">lm,</hi> which, multiplied by the cosine of the declination of
                    the known or preceding star, gives an approximate difference, which, when
                    applied to the declination of the known star, gives the approximate declination
                    of the unknown or following star. If we now multiply the angular value of <hi
                    rend="italic">lm</hi> by the cosine of this approximate declination, we shall
                    have the correct difference of declination, which, applied to the declination of
                    the known star, will give the true declination of the unknown star.</p>
                <p>In using the above reticulum, Dr Bradley found his observations embarrassed by
                    the crossing of all the wires at <hi rend="italic">i,</hi> which hid the
                    preceding star at the very point where it was required to be most distinctly
                    seen. He therefore proposed the construction shown in the annexed figure, where
                    the wires <hi rend="italic">hg, hi,</hi> intersect one another perpendicularly
                    at <hi rend="italic">f,</hi> the centre of the rings. Two slender bars of brass
                    <hi rend="italic">pg, og</hi> are fixed to the ring <hi rend="italic">abc,</hi>
                    and inclined each to the diameter <hi rend="italic">hg</hi> 26° 34', half the
                    angle of a rhomb whose greater diagonal is double of the lesser. Hence <hi
                    rend="italic">fk</hi> and <hi rend="italic">f i</hi> will be each one half of
                    <hi rend="italic">fg, hi = fg,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">fm = nl</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">ik.</hi> To avoid the inconvenience of
                    turning the telescope about its axis, Dr Bradley placed the ring <hi
                    rend="italic">abc,</hi> which carries the wires or brass bars in a groove in the
                    fixed ring ABC, and, confining it laterally by three pieces of brass at A, B,
                    and C, he employed an endless screw DEF to work in a toothed rack <hi
                    rend="italic">de,</hi> fixed to the inner ring <hi rend="italic">abc.</hi> Let
                    us now suppose the telescope so directed that a star is at <hi rend="italic"
                    >f,</hi> and moving in any line <hi rend="italic">fg</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> then, by turning the milled head D, the wire/Ãwill move round/till it
                    touches the star at <hi rend="italic">g,</hi> and will then lie in the direction
                    of the star’s motion, while all other stars will move parallel to it. The mode
                    of obtaining accurate results from this apparatus will be understood<pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193819521" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9521-0024"/> from the
                    following description of an analogous contrivance described by Lacaille.</p>
                <p>This eminent astronomer used a rhomb FMIL, the diagonals of which, FI, ML, must
                    be exactly perpendicular to one another, and as two to one. The length F was 15
                    ’ 4 lines, the angle subtended by ML 1° 25'∙5, and consequently FI 2° 50' 10",
                    as determined by the passage of several of the equatorial stars. Now, as the
                    vertical height of each triangle in the rhomb is equal to the short diagonal,
                    the path of any star passing through the field in a line parallel to that
                    diagonal will always cut off a similar triangle, and the distance of this path
                    from the common apex will have the same ratio to the vertical height of the
                    large triangle, one half FI, or ML, that the value of the diagonal in time has
                    to the observed time of the passage. Hence the time which any star takes to pass
                    from <hi rend="italic">m</hi> to Z, reduced to degrees, and multiplied by the
                    cosine of the declination, is the difference of declination required. The
                    difference of right ascension is obtained as before. With this simple apparatus,
                    Lacaille observed the comparative right ascensions and declinations of the 1942
                    stars which are given in his <hi rend="italic">Coelum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Australe</hi><hi rend="italic">Stelliferum.</hi> Lacaille constructed another
                    reticulum, in which ML was one fourth of FI.</p>
                <p>Mr Wollaston employed a reticulum similar to that shown in the annexed figure, AB
                    being the horary line, and CD the equatorial line. The four squares being within
                    the field, any of them may be used separately, so that observations made
                    successively in a pair of them will check each other as well as the principal
                    observation made in the large right-angled triangle. As the diagonals are equal
                    to one another, they afford a larger passage of a star, and thus increase the
                    accuracy of the observation.</p>
                <p>Μ. Valz<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Zach’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Correspondance Astronomique,</hi> tom. i. p∙ 353.</p></note> of
                    Nismes has proposed the reticulum shown in fig. 18, as possessing several
                    advantages over others. It consists of three wires AB, CD, AD, and the
                    equatorial one MN perpendicular to AB, CD. The arches AC, CM, MD, DB, &amp;c.
                    are all 60°. When the stars pass parallel to the equator, the angle formed at
                    the vertex A or B will be 30°, and its cotangent = √3 = 1·732; therefore,
                    calling <hi rend="italic">t</hi> the line of passage of one star from the first
                    to the second wire, and <hi rend="italic">tl</hi> that of the other star, the
                    difference of declination will be 1∙732 (∑±z <hi rend="italic">t</hi> zψz f),
                    and the difference of right ascension will be had from the times of the stars
                    passing the middle of the space between CD and AB, or the means of the times of
                    passing CD and AB. Baron Zach observes, that this reticulum requires no
                    illumination, that the values of its lines do not require to be known, and that
                    it maybe used out of exact adjustment to the parallel of declination, as the
                    corrections for such want of adjustment are easily computed.</p>
                <p>The fixed net-micrometer of Fraunhofer is shown in Plate CCCLVIII. fig. 29. The
                    vertical and oblique lines shown in the figure are cut upon glass with fluoric
                    acid or dia mond, and the plate has a circular motion in its cell. These lines
                    are illuminated by light passing through the eye-tube and falling on their cut
                    edges, so that no light passes down the tube. The lines parallel to <hi
                    rend="italic">er</hi> are adjusted perpendicular to a circle of declination, and
                    in that position the oblique light of the lamp illuminates both the vertical and
                    inclined lines. The mutual distances both of the vertical and inclined lines are
                    known from the machine by which they were drawn, and hence the ratio of the
                    times of transit of a star from the vertical to the inclined lines will enable
                    us to determine the position of these in reference to a circle of declination.
                    “The great number of lines,” says Dr Pearson, “afford the means of making
                    several observations, which, on an average, will give right ascensions and
                    declinations equally exact, whether the differences of declination be great or
                    small. When the difference of right ascension is small, as in the case of double
                    stars, the transit of both stars cannot well be observed over the same
                    individual line, but one of them may be observed at the first, and the other at
                    the second line, alternately, till the observer is satisfied with his
                    observation; and should the network experience an alteration of position from
                    any cause, it will in all probability be detected before the computation is
                    commenced. The ingenious artist contrived an engine by which he could cut
                    straight parallel lines at distances so small as <hi rend="subscript"> τσ</hi> ½
                    <hi rend="subscript"> σπ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> un</hi> R <hi
                    rend="superscript"> s</hi> from each other, and to be crossed by other parallel
                    lines at any given angle of declination; and in the net-micrometer he formed the
                    parallel lines at such a distance from each other that the inclined intervals
                    bear the same proportion to the vertical intervals that the cosine of the angle
                    of inclination bears to radius, so that about as tnany transits will take place
                    over the inclined <hi rend="subscript"> tu</hi> as over the vertical lines. Five
                    lines only are drawn at equal distances from each other, and the sixth line,
                    including the fifth interval, is cut at the distance of one interstice and a
                    half; yet the whole value of any number of intervals may always be known,
                    provided it be noticed how many of the larger kind are included in the whole
                    number. When the cell containing the disc is attached to a revolving graduated
                    circle, the position of a line uniting two stars may also be measured, by first
                    adjusting <hi rend="italic">zero</hi> to the equatorial position of the line <hi
                    rend="italic">fg,</hi> and then turning the divided disc round till all its
                    parallels successively receive both the stars at the same instant as they pass
                    through the field, which contemporary ingresses may be effected by repeated
                    adjustments and subsequent trials, when the telescope is mounted on an
                    equatorial stand properly rectified.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript">!</hi> Introd. Pract. Astron, vol.
                    ii. p. 143.</p></note></p>
                <p>Another micrometer of Fraunhofer’s is shown in Plate CCCLVI1I. fig. 30, and
                    consists of concentric circles cut upon glass, and illuminated like the
                    preceding one. The inner and smallest circle is like a dot. Other five circles
                    are seen in a telescope of fi,ve feet focal length, magnifying 110 times. With a
                    power of 63, eight circles are visible; and with the lowest power of 45, eleven
                    circular lines are visible. The observer may choose any circle he likes for
                    observing the passage of the star, avoiding those in which it would pass near
                    the centre or near the circumference. The observation, too, may be made with
                    more rings than one. The following are the dimensions of the circles in one of
                    these instruments.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Diameter in</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Diameter in</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Paris Inches.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Paris Inches.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Circle 1.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•0038</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Circle 7.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•4426</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•0243</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•5264</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•0840</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•6338</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•1678</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•7178</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•2513</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•8012</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>•3590</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819534" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9534-0025"/>
                <p>By subtracting these numbers from one another, we obtain the breadths of the
                    spaces between the rings.</p>
                <p>Fraunhofer’s suspended annular micrometer, which is a more perfect instrument
                    than the preceding, is shown in Plate CCCLVIII. fig. 31, which represents a disc
                    of glass, having a hole in its centre a little larger than the inner diameter of
                    a metallic ring oo, turned truly in a lathe. This ring is cemented on the glass
                    disc, and when placed in the field of view of a telescope, the observer notes
                    the instants when, a star on the limb of a planet enters and emerges from each
                    side of the ring. The only data required for computing the difference of right
                    ascension and declination, are the times that an equatorial star takes to pass
                    along the internal and external diameters of the ring. The passage of stars
                    whose relative position is required, must be observed at a distance from the
                    centre, as well as from the upper edge of the ring. The formulae of Bessel for
                    using this and other circular micrometers will be found in Zach’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Monailiche Correspondenz,</hi> vol. xvii. xxiv. and xxvi.</p>
                <p>A simple and useful fixed micrometer, proposed by Mr Cavallo, is a divided slip
                    of thin mother-of-pearl stretching across the diaphragm of the telescope, and
                    finely divided into 200ths of an inch. It is shown in Plate CCCLVIII. fig. 32,
                    crossing the diaphragm of the telescope. The value of the division maybe
                    ascertained either by measuring a bar, or by the passage of an equatorial star
                    across the field of view.</p>
                <p>In a portable telescope this micrometer is very convenient, though it has the
                    great disadvantage of shutting out the field of view. In telescopes upon stands
                    it will measure only angles in one direction, unless there is a contrivance to
                    turn it round. This micrometer has also the additional imperfection, that its
                    divisions, from being unequally distant from the eye-glass, are not all seen
                    with the same distinctness.</p>
                <p>To remove these imperfections, Sir David Brewster proposed, in 1805, the circular
                    mother-of-pearl micrometer, which is shown in Plate CCCLVIII.fig.33, where the
                    black ring which forms part of the figure is the diaphragm of the telescope, and
                    the more luminous part is an annular portion of mother-of-pearl divided on its
                    inner circumference into 360°. This divided circumference can be placed exactly
                    in the focus of the eye-glass, and all its parts seen with perfect distinctness.
                    In order to understand the use of the instrument, let Ay&gt;B be the inner edge
                    of the mother-of-pearl ring, and <hi rend="italic">mn</hi> the object to be
                    measured. Bisect the arch <hi rend="italic">rnn</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
                    >p,</hi> and draw <hi rend="italic">Cm, Cp, Cη,</hi> and we shall have AB: <hi
                    rend="italic">rnn</hi> = rad.: sin. and <hi rend="italic subscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∏ρn</hi> — <hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> ; <hi rend="subscript">
                    rb</hi><hi rend="italic                     strikethrough"> ∙%mpn</hi> χAB, a
                    formula by which rad. <hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> the angle subtended by the
                    chord of any number of degrees may be readily found. The first part of the
                    formula is constant, while AB varies with the magnifying power employed.</p>
                <p>CHAP. IX.—DESCRIPTION OF MICROMETERS FOR MICROSCOPES.</p>
                <p>All the micrometers above described may be adapted to compound microscopes, where
                    the eye-glass has a considerable focal length. A good micrometer, however, for
                    single microscopes, which can be used with facility, and at the same time give
                    accurate results, is still a desideratum. When the single lens is so minute, or
                    when the first lens of a microscopic doublet or triplet almost touches the
                    surface of the object, it is an extremely difficult matter to introduce any
                    scale, or any minute body of known dimensions, with which the object may be
                    compared. In some cases, when the object to be measured is minute, the seed of
                    the <hi rend="italic">lycoperdon bovista</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >puff-ball</hi> might be introduced, its diameter being about the <hi
                    rend="subscript"> τr</hi> ⅛ <hi rend="subscript"> σ</hi> th part of an inch; and
                    when the object is less minute, the seed of <hi rend="italic">lycopodium</hi>
                    may be used, its diameter being <hi rend="subscript"> 9</hi> ½ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> π</hi> th of an inch. We may advantageously adopt, in some
                    cases, the method of Dr Jurin,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>PhysicoMathematical Dissertations, p. 45.</p></note> who
                    introduced into the field small pieces of silver or brass wire, whose diameter
                    he had previously ascertained by coiling the wire round a cylinder, and
                    observing how many breadths of the wire were contained in a given number of
                    inches.</p>
                <p>This method of introducing a substance of known dimensions may be carried much
                    farther. We may use all the variety of hairs and wool which have a known
                    diameter; and for this purpose Dr Young’s .tables of substances measured by the
                    eriometer will be of great use. The following are a few of them:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>«</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Diameter in Parts of an
                            Inch.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Lycoperdon bovista, seed
                            of.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>...8500th of an inch.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Smut of barley</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>... 4600th</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ditto.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Silk, fibre of (average)</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>....2500th</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ditto.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Human blood, particles of <hi
                            rend="italic">(Eauer)...</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>....2500th<note anchored="true"
                            place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>We consider this the best
                            measure.</p></note></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ditto.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mole’s fur</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>... 1875th</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ditto.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Goat’s wool</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>....1575th</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ditto, ditto.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Saxon wool .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>.... 1320th</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Farina of Laurestinus</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>....1100ch</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ditto.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Seed of lycopodium</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>940th</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>ditto.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The distance of the fibres of the crystalline lens of fishes may also be
                    advantageously used, and also the distance of the teeth which unite the fibres.
                    For this purpose, the lens must be well dried, and perfectly hard, so that with
                    a sharp knife we can detach minute portions of any of the laminae. The thinnest
                    should be used; and as the fibres always taper to the pole, and the teeth become
                    smaller in proportion as the fibres diminish, we must determine the distance of
                    the fibres, and also those of the teeth, at both ends of the laminae, by the
                    method described by Sir David Brewster in the Philosophical Transactions for
                    1833, p. 324. The larger lined scales of moths and butterflies may also be used,
                    especially as we can measure the distance of the lines by the coloured spectra
                    which these lines produce.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>The late Mr Pond has observed, that the pale, slender, double-headed scales
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Pontia</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Pieris brassica,</hi>
                    which taper to a point, and terminate in a brush-like appendage, are of an
                    invariable length, about⅛th of an inch.</p></note> These operations will require
                    much dexterity on the part of the observer, and they are recommended only to
                    those who cannot succeed in their measurements by other methods.</p>
                <p>An excellent method of measuring microscopic objects is to project the image of
                    the object against a divided scale, at a given distance from the eye. The scale
                    must be seen either by the same eye which is looking into the microscope, or by
                    the other eye. In the first case, the rays from the microscope will enter one
                    side of the pupil, and the rays from the divided scale the other side; the
                    aperture through which we look at the scale, and the aperture of the microscope,
                    being at a distance less than the diameter of the pupil. When the right eye
                    looks at the divided scale, the left, which looks into the microscope, will see
                    the object projected against the scale, although it has no vision of the scale
                    itself. This second method may be carried into effect in two ways. The scale may
                    form no part <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819547" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9547-0026"
                    />of the instrument, and may be viewed by the naked eye; or it may form part of
                    the instrument, like a binocular telescope, the left eye looking into one tube,
                    viz. the microscope, while the right eye looks into another tube, in which a
                    divided scale is magnified by an eye-lens.</p>
                <p>Dr Wollaston has constructed and used a very ingenious micrometer on the first of
                    the principles above mentioned, viz. when the object and the scale are viewed by
                    the same eye; but its use is limited to microscopes with small lenses. When the
                    lenses are larger, we have adopted another method, namely, to perforate the lens
                    with a small hole in or near the centre, or, if it is thought better, near the
                    margin of the lens. A slit extending from the margin of the lens may often be
                    executed more easily.</p>
                <p>The following is Dr Wollaston’S own description of this instrument:</p>
                <p>“This instrument,” says Dr Wollaston, “is furnished with a single lens of about
                    ⅛th of an inch focal length. The aperture of each lens is necessarily small, so
                    that when it is mounted on a plate of brass, a small perforation can be made by
                    the side of it in the brass, as near to its centre as ⅛th of an inch.</p>
                <p>“When a lens thus mounted is placed before the eye for the purpose of examining
                    any small object, the pupil is of sufficient magnitude for seeing distant
                    objects at the same time through the adjacent perforation, so that the apparent
                    dimensions of the magnified image might be compared with a scale of inches,
                    feet, and yards, according to the distance at which it might be convenient to
                    place it.</p>
                <p>“A scale of smaller dimensions, attached to the instrument, will, however, be
                    found preferable, on account of the steadiness with which the comparison may be
                    made; and it may be seen with sufficient distinctness by the naked eye, without
                    any effort of nice adaptation, by reason of the smallness of the hole through
                    which it is viewed.</p>
                <p>“The construction that I have chosen for the scale is represented in Plate
                    CCCLVIII. fig. 33. It is composed of small wires about <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> ⅛th of an inch in diameter, placed side by side so as to form a scale of
                    equal parts, which may be with ease counted by means of a certain regular
                    variation of the lengths of the wires.</p>
                <p>“The external appearance of the whole instrument is that of a common telescope
                    consisting of three tubes. The scale occupies the place of the object-glass, and
                    the little lens is situated at the smaller end, with a pair of plain glasses
                    sliding before it, between which the subject of examination is to be included.
                    This part of the apparatus is shown separately in fig. 35. It has a projection,
                    with a perforation, through which a pin is inserted to connect it with a screw,
                    represented at <hi rend="italic">b,</hi> fig. 34. This screw gives lateral
                    motion to the object, so as to make it correspond with any particular part of
                    the scale. The lens has also a small motion of adjustment, by means of the cape,
                    fig. 36, which renders the view of the magnified object distinct.</p>
                <p>“Before the instrument is completed, it is necessary to determine with precision
                    the indications of the scale, which must be different, according to the distance
                    to which the tube is drawn out. In my instrument, one division of the scale
                    corresponds to <hi rend="subscript"> τσ</hi> ⅛ <hi rend="subscript"> ππ</hi> th
                    of an inch when it is at the distance of 16∙6 inches from the lens; and since
                    the apparent magnitude in small angles varies in the simple inverse ratio of
                    this distance, each division of the same scale will correspond to <hi
                    rend="subscript"> y</hi> ⅛ <hi rend="subscript"> π</hi> th at the distance of 8
                    <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ¾ inches; and the intermediate fractions ∙ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> δ7</hi> ⅛ <hi rend="subscript"> π</hi>, <hi rend="subscript">
                    7</hi>- <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi>,</p>
                <p>&amp;c. are found by intervals of 1∙66 inch, marked°on °th°e outside of the tube.
                    The basis on which these indications were founded in this instrument was a wire,
                    carefully ascertained to be g⅜(yth of an inch in diameter, the magnified image
                    of which occupied fifty divisions of the scale when it was at the distance of
                    16∙6 inches; and hence one division = so X ¾oo = īōöōō' since any error in the
                    original estimate of this wire must pervade all subsequent measures derived from
                    it, the substance employed was pure gold drawn till fifty-two inches in length
                    weighed exactly five grains. If we assume the specific gravity of gold to be
                    19-36, a cylindrical inch will weigh 3837 grains; and we may hence infer the
                    diameter of such a wire to be ^⅛(&gt;th of an inch, more nearly than can be
                    ascertained by any other method.</p>
                <p>“For the sake of rendering the scale more accurate, a similar method was, in
                    fact, pursued with several gold wires of different sizes, weighed with equal’
                    care; and the subdivisions of the exterior scale were made to correspond with
                    the average of their indications.</p>
                <p>“In making use of this micrometer for taking the measure of any object, it would
                    be sufficient, at any one accidental position of the tube, to note the number on
                    the outside as denominator, and to observe the number of divisions and decimal
                    parts which the subject of examination occupies on the interior scale as
                    numerator of a fraction, expressing its dimensions in proportional parts of an
                    inch; but it is preferable to obtain an integer as numerator, by sliding the
                    tube inward or outward, till the image of the wire is seen to correspond with
                    some exact number of divisions, not only for the sake of greater simplicity in
                    the arithmetical computations, but because we can by the eye judge more
                    correctly of actual coincidence than of the comparative magnitudes of adjacent
                    intervals. The smallest quantity which the graduations of this instrument
                    profess to measure, is less than the eye can really appreciate ∙ in sliding the
                    tube inward or outward. If, for instance, the object measured be really ^ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> πy</hi>, it may appear <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi> θ⅛ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> π77</hi>, or -g⅛θ, in which case the doubt amounts to <hi
                    rend="subscript"> y</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> θth part of the whole
                    quantity. But the difference is here exceedingly small in comparison to the
                    extreme division of other instruments, where the nominal effect of its power is.
                    the same.</p>
                <p>“A micrometer with a divided eye-glass may profèss to measure as far as <hi
                    rend="subscript"> τσ</hi> ⅛ <hi rend="subscript"> ππ</hi> of an inch; but the
                    next division is Tōoōō <hi rend="superscript"> or</hi> 3^⅛σ ’ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> a11d</hi> though the eye may be able ’ to distinguish that
                    the truth lies between the two, it receives no assistance within one-half part
                    of the larger measure.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Phil. Trans. 1813, p. 119.</p></note></p>
                <p>The micrometer microscopes used for reading off the divisions on the graduated
                    limb of astronomical instruments differ in no respect from the eye-pieces of
                    telescopes fitted up with micrometers.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the value of the methods described above, the want of a simple
                    micrometer for microscopes of high power is felt by every person who has been
                    practically occupied with this class of researches; and we cannot give a better
                    proof of this than by adducing in support of our opinion the different measures
                    that have been given by able and ingenious observers of the size of the
                    particles of the human blood.</p>
                <p>Dr Thomas Young 1-6060th part of an inch.</p>
                <p>Dr Wollaston 1-5000th ditto.</p>
                <p> MM. Prevost and Dumas 1-4076th ditto.</p>
                <p>Captain Kater 1-4000th ditto.</p>
                <p>Μ. Ehrenberg<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In measuring
                    the size of the fossilinfusorias recently discovered by himself, Μ. Ehrenberg
                    assumes a globule of human blood to be ,J,⅛ of a line in diameter, or „'„th of
                    an inch, but of what inch is not mentioned. He does not state whether this mea
                    <pb break="no" n="027"/>sure is taken by himself or not. He reckons the
                    thickness of a human hair at <hi rend="subscript"> î5</hi> th of a line at its
                    mean thickness, or⅞th of an inch.</p></note> 1-3600th ditto.</p>
                <p>Messrs Hodgkin and Lister 1-3000th ditto.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193819560" xml:id="kp-eb0715-9560-0027"/>
                <p>Sir David Brewster 1-2556th part of an inch.</p>
                <p>Dr Jurin<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This result was
                    confirmed by Leewenhoeck, who used the same wire, which was sent to him by Dr
                    Jurin. Phil. Trans. No. 377.</p></note> 1-1940th ditto.</p>
                <p>Mr Bauer’s best observation 1-2500th ditto, next best 1-2000th ditto, worst
                    observation....l-1000th ditto.</p>
                <p>The three measures of 1000, 2000, and 2500, have been recently given by Mr Bauer
                    himself, as the different steps which he made towards what he conceives the best
                    measure, viz. 1-2500th, which he obtained repeatedly with an improved achromatic
                    microscope. As Dr Young obtained his measure <hi rend="italic"
                    >criometrically,</hi> namely, by measuring the diameter of the first red ring
                    produced by looking through the blood at a luminous object, we cannot conceive
                    it possible that he could have committed such a mistake as to make the diameter
                    of that ring nearly <hi rend="italic">thrice as great</hi> as it should be,
                    according to Mr Bauer’s results, or more than thrice as great as the concurring
                    measures obtained by Jurin and Leewenhoeck. The only explanation we can give is,
                    that the particles of the blood must have an organized structure, or consist of
                    portions separated by lines which have the magnitude assigned by Dr Young. In
                    order to submit this explanation to the test of experiment, Sir David Brewster
                    examined the particles of blood a few minutes after it was drawn, when dried by
                    natural evaporation on a plate of glass. Each particle he found to consist of a
                    dark rim, within which is a bright circle, then a darkish central spot, which
                    spot in some globules may be resolved into a dark ring, a bright ring within
                    this, and then a small central black spot. Here, then, is the cause of Dr
                    Young’s mistake. The red ring of light which he measured in the eriometer was
                    not that which was due to the globule as a whole, but to the parts of the
                    globule. Being anxious to obtain more complete evidence of this fact, we placed
                    lycopodium powder beside the globule of blood, and found that the diameter of
                    the globules was to that of the lycopodium seed as 5 to 18. We then compared the
                    diameter of the red ring produced by the seed with the diameter of the red ring
                    produced by division on steel, in which there were 1250 to the inch, as executed
                    for us by the late Sir John Barton, and found the diameter of the seed to be the
                    697th of an inch. We compared it also with the ring produced by divisions of
                    which there were 625 to the inch, and found its diameter the 717th part of an
                    inch. The mean of these two is the 710th<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Dr Young makes this the 940th of an inch, but he has
                    certainly committed a mistake in his observation.</p></note> part of an inch,
                    which, increased in the ratio of 5 to 18, gives the 2556th part of an inch as
                    the measure of the diameter of the globules of blood, agreeing almost exactly
                    with the recent measure of Mr Bauer.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
