<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0715-4916-0439-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MONTSERRAT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 15, page 439</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k440">Indigo</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1211569">Montserrat</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193824916" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MONTSERRAT</label>, a celebrated monastery of the
                    Benedictines, in Spain. It is about nine leagues to the northwest of Barcelona,
                    being situated on the right bank of the river Llobregat, on an insulated
                    mountain nearly eight leagues in circumference, and raising its head above the
                    surrounding bills till it reaches the height of 3300 feet. It appears, from the
                    road to it, like ahuge pile of most enormous bowls,The bitumen which joined the
                    stones having been decomposed. As the traveller ascends, he observes vegetation
                    gradually decreasing, till towards the top, when it entirely ceases, and nothing
                    is presented to the view but naked rocks, separated like pillars, forming
                    various pyramids, varying in height from 20 to 150 feet. The ascent, though
                    steep and fatiguing, is not dangerous, as far as the church, which is large and
                    richly ornamented; but the constant smoke of upwards of eighty lamps lighted
                    with oil has sullied the statues and pictures, and dimmed the brilliancy of the
                    silver. The number of monks and lay-brothers residing here amounts to upwards of
                    one hundred; besides which, there are twenty-five boys who officiate in.the
                    choir, with a physician, surgeon, and servants. Besides those who reside in the
                    convent, there are several of the monks who live in a kind of hermitage or
                    oratory on the pinnacle of several of the insulated rocks. These hermits are
                    supplied with food twice in the week, and their gardens yield some <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193824929" xml:id="kp-eb0715-4929-0440"/> fruits. They are
                    not permitted to eat meat, or to converse with each other, but live a life of
                    perfect solitude, possibly of devotion, during the whole day, excepting when
                    they descend to the general service, which is performed in the church of the
                    convent. The term of the noviciate for the ordinary monks is six months; but
                    those who wish to live in one of the hermitages must pass six years of very
                    severe probation before they can be allowed to reside in them. Although the
                    romantic situation, the extensive and varied prospects, and the natural
                    curiosities of the place, draw to it many travellers who are not infected with
                    any devotional feeling, yet the number of real votaries is very great. These
                    come to say prayers, to pass a few days in devotion and contemplation, to kiss
                    with reverence the hand of a miraculous image of the holy Virgin; and, what is
                    of most importance to the institution, to deposit votive offerings, which are
                    eagerly accepted by the recluse inhabitants. By the rules of the order, they are
                    bound to maintain for three days every pilgrim who comes to pay his devotions to
                    the sacred image. The devotees are allowed bread in the morning, broth at noon,
                    and bread again at night. Although this parsimonious kind of hospitality is not
                    very expensive for each individual who arrives, yet the number is so great that
                    the annual cost is considerable; and although the presents from the rich far
                    exceed the cost of their maintenance, yet these presents are preserved carefully
                    till they are quite spoiled by age. Their original endowment was only the
                    mountain; but by rigid economy they have, in the course of ages, been enabled to
                    purchase considerable estates in the vicinity. Some of these, indeed, have been
                    appropriated by the government to its own use, and probably at no distant period
                    the remainder may share the same fate.</p>
                <p>It is singular that there should be always a number of candidates, both for the
                    cells of the monks and for the hermitages of the recluses. They make a vow never
                    to quit the mountain, and they are not allowed to enter into holy orders. This
                    may perhaps account for the continuance of those who are once admitted; but it
                    is not easy for Protestants to understand that state of mind which induces men
                    in the full vigour of their bodily and mental faculties to withdraw from the
                    world, and abandon every pursuit but that of inactive devotion and the tiresome
                    repetition of prayers, with no variety to amuse and no excitement to animate
                    them.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Montserrat,</hi> one of the West Indian islands, belonging
                    to Great Britain, is situated in 16. 47. north latitude, and 92. 13. 25. west
                    longitude. It is about twelve miles in length by seven and a half in breadth,
                    and contains a superficies of 30,000 acres. Like the islands in its vicinity, it
                    runs from south-east to north-west, and presents an equally broken and
                    mountainous surface; an arrangement and physical structure which has led to the
                    conclusion that these islands owe their origin to volcanic eruption. The
                    extremity of the mountain chain terminates on the north in a bold headland
                    coast, where there is no landingplace and little anchorage. The land slopes to
                    the sea in a supcession of conglomerate eminences, which extend to the base of
                    the mountain. On the south there is no approach for vessels of any size until
                    they get to the westward, the sea for a mile or two being studded with huge
                    rocks and shelving banks of coral. The island then suddenly shoots up to the
                    height of 1500 feet, and continues to rise pile above pile, throwing out lateral
                    branches, until they attain the altitude of 2500 feet above the level of the
                    Atlantic. This chain stretches across to the northern extremity of Montserrat,
                    where it terminates, as we have mentioned. Many of the mountains are
                    inaccessible, and are separated from each other by immense perpendicular chasms
                    several hundred feet in depth. These gullies, however, as well as the mountains,
                    are covered to the very summits with lofty woods, and all the beautiful variety
                    of vegetation which a mountainous region within the tropics presents. On the
                    south-west side of the chain is a small <hi rend="italic">souffrière,</hi>
                    situated 1000 feet above the sea, in a dell formed by the approximation of three
                    conical hills, the scenery around which has been described by Mr Coleridge as
                    grand and beautiful in the highest degree. The road from Plymouth, the capital
                    of Montserrat, to this place, after stretching along the margin of the sea,
                    winds inwards by a gentle declivity towards the mountains. The path becomes
                    strewed with the snowy amaryllis <hi rend="italic">(pancratia Cα-ribbaea),</hi>
                    and the scarlet hibiscus; and on either side lime and orange trees form a
                    verdant hedge. The whole of the valley in which the souffrière lies is broken
                    into vast and irregular masses of clay and limestone, which are scattered about
                    in the utmost confusion. The surface of the ground is everywhere hot, indeed so
                    much so near the streams of water which run between the fragments, that it is
                    difficult for the foot to support it more than half a minute. The water at its
                    source boils up violently, and a cloud of vapour constantly settles over it. The
                    sides of the mounds of clay are encrusted with pure alum; but, notwithstanding
                    this, the vegetation of bushes and creepers all round is green and luxuriant,
                    whilst the rampart of mountains in which the solitary valley is embosomed is
                    clothed with woods whose feathery grass-like plumage bends devotedly to the
                    setting sun under the unceasing breath of the trade-wind. There are no marshes,
                    but there is a small lake on the top of a hill about two miles west from
                    Plymouth, which remains constantly full. Plymouth, the capital, is small, but
                    substantially built, of a fine gray stone, and has a comfortable appearance. The
                    geological features of this island are similar to those of the islands in the
                    neighbourhood. Many of the rocks have been termed only vast masses of clay of
                    divers hues; but in the conical hills carbonate of lime, iron pyrites, and
                    aluminous earth abound. The soil is in general dry, light, thin, gravelly, and
                    thickly covered with blocks of clay and sandstone, excepting in the valleys
                    where the loamy earth is deposited by rains. The climate of Montserrat is
                    remarkable for its salubrity, a characteristic which has obtained for it the
                    name of the Montpellier of the West Indies. The temperature of course varies
                    according to the locality and the elevation above the sea. It is subject to
                    hurricanes, but these are neither frequent nor severe. To enumerate the staple
                    products of Montserrat, would be merely to recapitulate what is said of them
                    under the heads of <hi rend="smallcaps">Jamaica, St Lucia,</hi> and other West
                    India islands. Indigo was formerly-raised in great quantities, but this branch
                    of agriculture is now abandoned. The sugar and rum produced are highly esteemed.
                    Of the former there were exported in 1832, 2,322,208 pounds, valued at L.16,549;
                    and of the latter, 74,064 gallons, valued at L.3307. The total amount of exports
                    for the same year was L.21,517, and of imports L.11,067. In 1830 the shipping
                    inwards was 5824 tons, and outwards 6576 tons. By the latest return it appears
                    that, between the 5th of January 1836 and the 5th of January 1837, there were
                    imported into the united kingdom from this island 12,152 cwts. of sugar, 16,256
                    gallons of rum, and 2694 cwts. of molasses.</p>
                <p>The executive of this island is embodied in the government of Antigua, but the
                    inhabitants enjoy their separate council and house <hi rend="italic">of</hi>
                    assembly, the former consisting of six members and the latter of eight, two
                    being sent from each of the four districts into which Montserrat is divided. The
                    gross annual revenue is about L.2500. There are five places of public worship,
                    capable of containing 1000 persons, and also a Wesleyan missionary station; and
                    there are six public or free schools, with 298 male and 390 female scholars.
                    Montserrat was at one time more densely peopled with Europeans than it is at
                    present. The popu <pb break="no" facs="nls:193824942"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0715-4942-0441"/>lation, including all classes, is now estimated at
                    about 7400. This island was discovered by the companions of Columbus, and called
                    by them Montserrat, a name expressive, in the Spanish language, of its broken
                    and mountainous appearance. It was first settled in 1632, by Sir Thomas Warner,
                    under the protection of the British government. It was taken by the French about
                    the year 1664, but restored to Britain at the peace of Breda, and it has ever
                    since formed a part of our empire.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
