<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0715-3278-0313-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">MODENA</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 15, page 313</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1086604">Racing</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1086436">Race</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:829302">Bears</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1150446">Thrones</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193823278" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">MODENA</label>, an independent sovereign state in the north
                    of Italy, the chief of which bears the title of his Royal Highness the Duke of
                    Modena, Reggio, Mirandola, Massa, and Carrara, and is descended from a branch of
                    the Austrian family. This sovereign is descended from the house of Este, one of
                    the most ancient families in Europe. A member of that house, then settled in
                    Lombardy, became Marquis of Modena, in 960; and his successor, in 1097, obtained
                    the sole power over Milan and Genoa, under the name of Azzo II. He was the
                    founder of that family, one branch of which having settled in Bavaria, and
                    afterwards becoming possessed of Brunswick, in Germany, gave origin to that race
                    of monarchs of which five in succession have filled the throne of Great Britain.
                    During the civil wars which ragedin Italy in the course of the thirteenth
                    century, when so many small republics were formed, the territories of Ferrara,
                    Modena, and Reggio, chose the then Marquis of Este, Obizzo III. who had attained
                    great respect as a warrior, for their supreme lord. One of his successors, Borso
                    d’Este, was, in 1452, raised to the dignity of Duke of Modena and Reggio by the
                    Emperor Frederick 111., Alfonzo II. having no legitimate male issue, obtained
                    from the Emperor Rudolph II. permission to nominate as successor a son of his
                    uncle by a doubtful or left-handed marriage, who had gained the sovereignty
                    under the name of Caesar d Este, and from whom are descended the present
                    reigning race. These have since gained from the popes some additional territory,
                    and also a portion from the emperors originally granted as feudal tenures, but
                    successively affirmed as permanent sovereignty. The last acquisition was’
                    Carrara, gained by the marriage of the duke with the heiress of the duchies of
                    Massa and Carrara in 1741. The issue of this marriage was only a daughter, who
                    married the Archduke Ferdinand of Austria, the brother of Joseph II. and of
                    Leopold II. whose son succeeded to the dominions.</p><p>In 1796, the French expelled the duke, and his territory was formed into a
                    province of the ephemeral Cisalpine republic; and, by the peace of Campo Formio,
                    the duke was to receive an indemnification in Suabia. It then became a part of
                    Bonaparte’s kingdom of Italy; but after his fall, it was, by the congress of
                    Vienna in 1814, restored to the ancient family which had before possessed
                    it.</p><p>This state extends in north latitude from 43. 56. 10. to 44. 57. 30. and in east
                    longitude from 10. 20. 25. to 11. 17. 2. It is bounded on the north by the
                    Austrian kingdom of Lombardy and by Guastalla, on the east by the papal
                    dominions, on the south-east by Tuscany, on the south by Lucca, on the
                    south-west by Tuscany, and on the west by Parma. It extends over 2140 square
                    miles, and contains at present 395,000 inhabitants, being one of the most
                    densely-peopled districts in Europe. The Apennine Mountains form a part of the
                    southern division of the territory, and the rest is generally a level plain,
                    very gradually declining towards the north, and watered by several small streams
                    which finally unite in the river Secchia, and empty themselves into the Po.
                    There are numerous canals, formed chiefly for the purpose of irrigation. The
                    soil is generally fertile. The system of cultivation so nearly resembles that
                    already fully described in this work under the head of <hi rend="smallcaps">Lombardy,</hi> that the reader is referred to that article. We have only to
                    remark here, that the olive trees are much more numerous than in Lombardy, and
                    that the oil expressed from their fruit is much esteemed, and forms an article
                    <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the export trade.</p><p>The chief product is silk, some of which is organized before being exported, but
                    most of it is sent to foreign markets in the raw state: a small portion only of
                    it is manufactured into finished goods within the territory. The other fabrics
                    are of hemp and flax, and only for domestic consumption. The country is divided
                    into six ecclesiastical dioceses, each with a bishop, and in the capital an
                    archbishop; and the whole of the inhabitants adhere to the Roman Catholic
                    church, with the exception of about 1200 Jews, who reside chiefly in and around
                    the capital. It contains ten cities, sixty-three market-towns, forty-nine
                    communes, and 463 villages. The larger cities and their population are, Modena
                    with 27,000 inhabitants, Reggio with 18,000, Massa with 7000, and Carrara with
                    4000; the others, though they were once walled, are now inconsiderable. The
                    annual revenue of the whole state amounts to about L.150,000, the chief part
                    being derived from patrimonial estates; and besides that, the duke enjoys the
                    valuable property of the ancient house of Obizzi, near to Treviso in Austrian
                    Lombardy, which is said to produce him annually L.20,000. The expenditure of the
                    state is nearly equal to the annual income; and the whole debt does not quite
                    amount to the revenue of half a year. The duke maintains an armed force, which,
                    including 100 cavalry and his guards, amounts to about 1800 men.</p><p>The capital city, of the same name, is in north latitude 44. 34. and in east
                    longitude 11. 7. 25. It is situated on the banks of a canal, by which it is
                    connected with the rivers Secchia and Panaro, and is surrounded with walls <pb break="no" facs="nls:193823291" xml:id="kp-eb0715-3291-0314"/> and
                    defended by bastions; but it is not deemed capable of much defence, more
                    especially as the citadel is very weak. It is a well-built city, with a broad
                    street, the Corso, running from one gate to the opposite one. The houses are
                    handsome, and mostly furnished with piazzas on the ground floor. The most
                    distinguished building is the ducal palace. It is surrounded with a garden,
                    which is used as a place of recreation for the inhabitants. It is built of
                    marble, contains a library of 80,000 volumes, and many antiquities; but the
                    collection of paintings, which was formerly the chief attraction, has been
                    transferred by sale to Dresden. The cathedral, the theatre, the opera-house, and
                    the barracks, are the other most remarkable edifices in the city. There are
                    within the city no less than fifty churches, of which twenty-six formerly
                    belonged to religious houses. Of late the duke has restored the Jesuits, and the
                    order is more flourishing here than in any of the other cities of Italy. There
                    is a university with seven professors, a gymnasium, a scientific society, an
                    academy for nobles, and a veterinary college. But there is little trade of any
                    kind, and the inhabitants chiefly depend on the expenditure of the court for
                    their subsistence.</p></div></body></text></TEI>