<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0790-0755-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CZERNY GEORGE (9th edition, volume 6, page 755)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1734394">Peasants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159314">Turkeys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921422">Farms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1054286">Pashas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jw08">Servians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222rc91">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892j89">Turkeys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n790/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CZERNY GEORGE</label> (1 1766-1817), or <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Kardjordje,</hi> or Black George, as he is always called, though his name
                    was properly George Petrovitch, a Servian who freed his country from the
                    domination of the Turks, born about 1766, was the son of a Servian peasant. He
                    was about twenty when, having killed a Turk in some wild adventure, he was
                    forced to flee into Austria. It said that he forced his father, or his
                    stepfather or father-in-law, to accompany him; but the old peasant could not be
                    persuaded to leave his country, and, to prevent his falling into the pitiless
                    hands of the Turks, Czerny George put him to death with a pistol-shot. In the
                    Austrian army Czerny George fought against the Turks from 1788 to 1791, and rose
                    to the rank of sergeant; but, either unwilling to submit to discipline or
                    disgusted by some slight, he left the service for the life of <hi rend="italic"
                        >ρAιeyduc,</hi> or bandit who preyed only upon the Mahometans. He
                    afterwards, however, is said to have held an appointment as inspector of forests
                    to a monastery in Austria.</p>
                <p>For a time Servia was under the mild rule of Hadji Mustapha, and Czerny George
                    lived on his farm in peace. But the Janissaries overran the country, killed the
                    Pasha, and began to murder the Servian chiefs. Many escaped, however, and,
                    headed by Czerny George, who was chosen commander-in-chief, summoned every male
                    Servian to arms. The sultan sent troops against the Janissaries, who were
                    overwhelmed, and their leaders executed. But the Servians now refused to receive
                    again the yoke of the Turks, Russia supported their claim to independence, and
                    war commenced. Czerny George commanded his countrymen' with fiery enthusiasm,
                    rough vigour, and considerable ability. Several victories over the Turks were
                    won; and, in October 1806, the independence of Servia was recognized by the
                    Porte, a tribute only being exacted, and the sign of Turkish sovereignty
                    maintained by the residence at Belgrade of a Turkish officer with a very small
                    force. The Turks refusing, however, to give up Belgrade and Schabaz, both towns
                    were taken by Czerny George by assault, and the Janissaries and Turks in both
                    were massacred in cold blood.</p>
                <p>Czerny George, as commander-in-chief, now became the ruler of Servia; and till
                    1813, despite strong opposition in the Servian senate and constant danger from
                    the Turks, he maintained his position. His elevation made no change in his
                    habits. He continued during peace to cultivate his farm at Topola with his own
                    hands, and he never laid aside his coarse peasant’s dress. He had received no
                    school education, and was never able to write. In general, he was moody and
                    taciturn, though, when excited, he was fond of joining in the village dances.
                    His passion was terrible; he killed his warmest adherent in a fit of anger. His
                    execution of justice was stern and prompt; he hanged his own brother for
                    assaulting a girl, and forbade his mother to make any signs of mourning. In war
                    he displayed marvellous energy and valour, and he had the power of inspiring his
                    followers with the fierce enthusiasm by which he was himself animated.</p>
                <p>In 1809, on the outbreak of war between Russia and Turkey, Czerny George, who had
                    formed the scheme of achieving the independence of all the Slavonic countries
                    under the rule of Turkey, took up arms against the Turks, and, after attempting
                    to excite a revolt in Bosnia, marched on Herzegovina. The Turks at this juncture
                    invaded Servia; and Czerny George, though wishing to place the country under the
                    protection of Austria, was forced to seek the aid of Russia. A vigorous attempt
                    was now made to dispossess him of the supreme power; but he forced his opponents
                    to submit or flee the country. The treaty of Bucharest (May 1812), however,
                    while depriving the Servians of the protection of Russia, failed to claim for
                    them sufficient guarantees from the Turks, in whose hands all the Servian
                    fortresses were placed. In June 1813 the Turks again entered Servia, and Czerny
                    George, in despair, with almost all the Servian chiefs, took refuge in
                    Austria.</p>
                <p>Four years after, having been persuaded that his countrymen were only awaiting
                    his signal to burst into revolt, he ventured to return in disguise into Servia
                    He discovered himself to Vuitza, an officer who had served under him, by whom he
                    was basely murdered (27th July 181 ∕), at the instigation of Milosch
                    Obrenovitch, a Servian senator, whυ had come to a compromise with Turkey and
                    obtained the chief power, and was jealous of the popularity of the old chief.
                    See <hi rend="smallcaps">Servia,</hi> and Ranke’s <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Serbische</hi><hi rend="italic">Revolution.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
