<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0051-0042-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CLUB-FOOT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 42</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4930p161">Surgeons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fs4j">Toes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:836543">Boots</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1115245">Shapes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1139336">Surgeons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n51/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CLUB-FOOT</label><hi rend="italic">(Talipes).</hi> The
                    pathology and treatment of the various deformities of the foot, which are
                    included under the above general title, come strictly under orthopaedic surgery.
                    Several forms of club-foot have been recognized by surgeons There are four
                    primary forms :— (1) <hi rend="italic">Talipes equinus,</hi> in which the heel
                    does not touch the ground, the child resting on the toes; (2) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Talipes varus,</hi> in which the foot is turned inwards and shortened, the
                    inner edge of the foot raised, the outer edge of the foot only touching the
                    ground; (3) <hi rend="italic">Talipes calcaneus,</hi> a rare form, in which the
                    heel only touches the ground, the toes being raised; (4) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Talipes valgus,</hi> in which the foot is turned outwards. The third and fourth
                    varieties are so rare that they are of no practical interest, and need not be
                    further alluded to. It is possible to confound true talipes valgus with
                    flat-foot, a deformity which is the result of undue stretching, from weakness,
                    of the fascial and ligamentous structures which maintain the arched form of the
                    foot. In flat-foot the arch is lost, the patient is splay or flat-footed, and as
                    a secondary deformity the foot is turned outwards, resembling and often
                    confounded with true talipes valgus.</p>
                <p>The two common primary forms of club-foot are <hi rend="italic">talipes
                    equinus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">talipes varus.</hi> These two varieties are
                    frequently combined; the deformity is then termed <hi rend="italic"
                    >talipes</hi><hi rend="italic">equino-varus.</hi> A shortening or contraction of
                    one group, or of allied groups, of muscles is always to be observed; as, for
                    instance, in <hi rend="italic">talipes equinus,</hi> to which the muscles of the
                    calf are con tracted, or in <hi rend="italic">talipes varus,</hi> in which the
                    group of muscles which turn the foot inwards are contracted, or in <hi
                    rend="italic">talipes equino-varus,</hi> in which both sets are at fault. This
                    contraction is due either to excessive primary irritation of the muscular group
                    implicated, or is secondary to and the result of paralysis of an opposing group
                    of muscles. In certain cases the paralysis affects more or less all the muscles
                    of the limb; the result of this is a deformity in the direction of the most
                    powerful group. The primary cause of these diseased conditions is some
                    irritation of the cerebrospinal central nervous system, either occurring before
                    birth, and termed congenital, or appearing after birth, generally during
                    theperiodof first dentition, and termed non-congenital. As a rule well-marked
                    cases are congenital. Such deformities are frequently hereditary. Both feet may
                    or may not be affected. Recognition of club-foot is of importance, because if
                    not treated early a change takes place in the shape of the bones of the foot,
                    which renders treatment much more difficult, and in some neglected cases it is
                    impossible to restore the foot to its normal shape.</p>
                <p>It is to Stromeyer in Germany (1837), and to Little and Adams in England, that we
                    owe a true understanding of the pathology and treatment of these affections.</p>
                <p>The following broad principles, which govern the treatment, are now universally
                    understood and adopted by surgeons:—(1) A subcutaneous division, by the
                    operation of tenotomy, of the contracted tendons; and (2) A stretching of the
                    newly formed embryonic tissue which is deposited between the cut extremities of
                    the tendons in the inter space, the result of their retraction after division.
                    This is managed by means of a mechanical appliance termed a club-foot boot.
                    Various forms of boot have been used by surgeons; in all the essential feature
                    is that the foot is fixed to the boot by sticking-plaster or by straps, and the
                    stretching is gradually accomplished by the elasticity of Indian-rubber bands,
                    or by steel springs, or by screws. In this way the foot gradually assumes a
                    normal appearance.</p>
                <p>As a general rule, after it is evident that the deformity is a persistent one,
                    the earlier the operation is performed the better. Only in exceptional cases
                    should interference be delayed beyond the third or fourth month of life. If a
                    change takes place in the bones, or if the child is allowed to walk before
                    treatment of the deformity, the cure is rendered more difficult and more
                    tedious. In many cases when the child is young the cutting operation will not be
                    necessary; the foot can be restored to its normal position by mechanical
                    appliances alone.</p>
                <p>Various rules lιave been laid down for the proper performance of tenotomy. The
                    simple rule to begin with the most tense tendon, and to divide it where it is
                    most tense, is of universal application. In <hi rend="italic">talipes
                    equinus</hi> the <hi rend="italic">tendo</hi><hi rend="italic">achillis,</hi> in
                    <hi rend="italic">talipes varus</hi> the <hi rend="italic">tibialis
                    posticus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">tibialis</hi><hi rend="italic">anticus</hi>
                    require division. In the common form.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n52/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0052-0043"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">talipes</hi><hi rend="italic">equlno-varus</hi><hi rend="italic
                    subscript"> i</hi> both groups must be operated on. Very frequently the plantar
                    fascia is shortened and has also to be divided. After the operation, which is
                    greatly facilitated by the administration of chloroform, the foot is kept at
                    rest with a bandage for three or four days until the small punctures are healed.
                    The boot is then carefully applied, and gradually the foot is restored to its
                    normal shape <hi rend="italic">without causing pain,</hi> which interferes with
                    the object in view, namely, a moulding (by stretching) of the newly-formed
                    tissue between the divided ends of the tendons If there is distinct paralysis
                    the appropriate remedies—friction, passive exercise, and the electric battery
                    —may be indicated. The boot should be worn for some time after the foot has
                    regained its normal appearance, because there is always a tendency for a
                    considerable period to the return of the deformity. (j. c.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
