<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0718-0685-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CUCKOO, or Cucκow</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 685</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="17" ref="fasttopic:903849">Eggs</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1128737">Sparrows</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1036179">Nests</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:952093">Hawks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1181567">Wrens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="17" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3d540">Eggs</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10z9f">Nests</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15v25">Sparrows</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tw3f">Hawking</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4736mb9b">Wrens</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qj2t">Hawks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55r4w">Weirs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n718/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CUCKOO, or Cucκow</label>, as the word was formerly and more
                    correctly spelt—changed without any apparent warrant except that accorded by
                    custom, while some of the more scholarly English ornithologists, as Montague and
                    Jenyns, have kept the older form—the common name of a well-known and often-heard
                    bird, the <hi rend="italic">Cuculus canorus</hi> of Linnaeus. Iiι some parts of
                    the United Kingdom it is more frequently called Gowk, and it is the Greek
                    κo'xκυξ, the Italian <hi rend="italic">Cuculo</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cucco,</hi> the French <hi rend="italic">Coucou,</hi> the German <hi
                    rend="italic">Kuckuk,</hi> the Dutch <hi rend="italic">Koekkoek,</hi> the Danish
                    <hi rend="italic">Kulcker or Gſòg,</hi> and the Swedish <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gök.</hi> The oldest English spelling of the name seems to have been <hi
                    rend="italic">Cuccu.</hi></p>
                <p>No single bird has perhaps so much occupied the attention both of naturalists and
                    of those who are not naturalists, or has had so much written about it, as the
                    common Cuckow, and of no bird perhaps have more idle tales been told. Its
                    strange and, according to the experience of most people, its singular habit of
                    intrusting its offspring to foster-parents is enough to account for much of the
                    interest which has been so long felt in its history; but, as will presently
                    appear, this habit is shared probably by many of its Old-World relatives, as
                    well as in the New World by birds which are not in any near degree related to
                    it. In giving here a short account of this species, there will be no need to
                    refute much of the nonsense about it which has found access to works even of
                    respectable authority; but, besides the known facts of its economy, there are
                    certain suppositions in regard to parts of its history that are unknown, which
                    suppositions are apparently probable enough to deserve notice.</p>
                <p>To begin with the known facts. The Cuckow is a summer-visitant to the whole of
                    Europe, reaching even far within the Arctic circle, and crossing the
                    Mediterranean from its winter-quarters in Africa at the end of March or
                    beginning of April. Its arrival is at once proclaimed by the peculiar and in
                    nearly all languages onomatopoeic cry of the cock—a true song in the technical
                    sense of the word, since it is confined to the male sex and to the season of
                    love. In a few days the cock, is followed by the hen, and amorous contests
                    between keen and loud-voiced suitors are to be commonly noticed, until the
                    respective pretensions of the rivals are decided Even by night they are not
                    silent; but as the season advances the song is less frequently heard, and the
                    Cuckow seems rather to avoid observation as much as possible, the more so since
                    whenever it shews itself it is a signal for all the small birds of the
                    neighbourhood to be up in its pursuit, just as though it were a Hawk, to which
                    indeed its mode of flight and general appearance give it an undoubted
                    resemblance—a resemblance that misleads some beings, who ought to know better,
                    into confounding it with the Birds-of-prey, instead of recognizing it as a
                    harmless if not a beneficial destroyer of hairy caterpillars. Thus pass away
                    some weeks. Towards the middle or end of June its “plain-song” cry alters; it
                    becomes rather hoarser in tone, and its first syllable or note is doubled. Soon
                    after it is no longer heard at all, and by the middle of July an old Cuckow is
                    seldom to be found in these islands, though a stray example, or even, but very
                    rarely, two or three in company, may occasionally be seen for a month longer.
                    This is about as much as is apparent to most people of the life of the Cuckow
                    with us. Of its breeding comparatively few have any personal experience. Yet
                    there are those who know that diligent search for and peering into the nests of
                    several of our commonest little birds—more especially the Pied Wagtail <hi
                    rend="italic">(Motacilla lugubris),</hi> the Titlark <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Anthus</hi><hi rend="italic">pratensis),</hi> the Reed-Wren <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Acrocepha</hi><hi rend="italic">lus</hi><hi rend="italic">streperus),</hi> and
                    the Hedge-Sparrow <hi rend="italic">(Accentor</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >modularis)</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> will be rewarded by the discovery of
                    the egg of the mysterious stranger which has been surreptitiously introduced
                    therein, and waiting till this egg is hatched they may be witnesses (as was the
                    famous Jenner in the last century) of the murderous eviction of the rightful
                    tenants of the nest by the intruder, who, hoisting them one after another on his
                    broad back, heaves them over to die neglected by their own parents, of whose
                    solicitous care he thus becomes the only object In this manner he thrives, and,
                    so long as he remains in the country of his birth, his wants are anxiously
                    supplied by the victims of his mother’s dupery. The actions of his
                    foster-parents become, when he is full grown, almost ludicrous, for they often
                    have to perch between his shoulders to place in his gaping mouth the delicate
                    morsels he is too indolent or too stupid to take from their bill. Early in
                    September he begins to shift for himself, and then follows the seniors of his
                    kin to more southern climes.</p>
                <p>Of the way in which it seems possible that this curious habit of the Cuckow may
                    have originated something has been already said (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Birds,</hi> vol. iii. p. 772). But in connection with its successful practice a
                    good deal yet remains tobe determined, most of which, however probable, is still
                    to be proved. So much caution is used by the hen Cuckow in choosing a nest in
                    vhich to deposit her egg that the act of insertion has been but seldom
                    witnessed. The nest selected is moreover often so situated, or so built, that it
                    would be an absolute impossibility for a bird of her size to lay her egg therein
                    by bitting upon the fabric as birds commonly do; and there have been a few
                    fortunate observers who have actually seen the deposition of the egg upon the
                    ground by the Cuckow, who, then takirg it in her bill, introduces it into the
                    nest. Of these, so far at least as this country is concerned, the earliest seem
                    to be two Scottish lads, sons of Mr Tripeny, a farmer in Coxmuir, who. as
                    recorded by Macgillivray <hi rend="italic">(Brit. Birds,</hi> iii. pp. 130,
                    131), from information communicated to him by Mr Durham Weir, saw most part of
                    the operation performed, June 24, 1838. But perhaps the most satisfactory
                    evidence &lt;n the point is that of Herr Adolf Müller, a fores <hi
                    rend="superscript"> j</hi> er at Gladenbach in Darmstadt, who says <hi
                    rend="italic">(Zoolog. Garten,</hi> 1866, pp. 374, 375) that through a telescope
                    he watched a Cuckow as she laid her egg on a bank, and then conveyed the egg in
                    her bill to a Wagtail’s nest. Cuckows too have been not unfrequently shot as
                    they were carrying a Cuckow’s egg, presumably their own, in their bill, and this
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n719/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0719-0686"/> has probably given rise to the vulgar, but
                    seemingly groundless, belief that they suck the eggs of other kinds of birds.
                    More than this, Mr Rowley, who has had much experience of Cuckows, declares <hi
                    rend="italic">(Ibis,</hi> 1865, p. 186) h:s opinion to be that traces of
                    violence and of a scuffle between the intruder and the owners of the nest at the
                    time of introducing the egg often appear, whence we are led to suppose that the
                    Cuckow ordinarily, when inserting her egg, excites the fury (already stimulated
                    by her Hawk ∏ke appearance) of the owners of the nest by turning out one or more
                    of the eggs that may be already laid therein, and thus induces the dupe to brood
                    all the more readily and more strongly what is left to her. Of the assertion
                    that the Cuckow herself takes any interest in the future welfare of the egg she
                    has foisted on her victim, or of its product, there is no evidence worth a
                    moment’s attention.</p>
                <p>But a much more curious assertion has also been made, and one that at first sight
                    appears so incomprehensible as to cause little surprise at the neglect it long
                    encountered. To this currency was first given more than a hundred years ago by
                    Salerne <hi rend="italic">(L</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Hist.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Nat.</hi> Ac., Paris: 1767, p. 42), who was, however, hardly a
                    believer in it, and it is to the effect, as he was told by an inhabitant of
                    Sologne, that the egg of a Cuckow resembles in colour that of the eggs normally
                    laid by the kind of bird in whose nest it is placed. In 1853 the same notion was
                    prominently and independently brought forward by Dr Baldamus <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Naumannia,</hi> 1853, pp. 307-325), and in time became known to English
                    ornithologists, most of whom were sceptical as to its truth, as well they might
                    be. since no likeness whatever is ordinarily apparent in the very familiar case
                    of the bluegreen egg of the Hedge-Sparrow and that of the Cuckow, which is so
                    often found beside it.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>
                    An instance to the contrary has been recorded, by Mr A. C. Smith <hi
                    rend="italic">(Zoologist,</hi> 1873, p. 3516) on Mr Brine’s
                    authority.</p></note> Dr Baldamus based his notion on a series of eggs in his
                    cabinet,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> This series
                    was seen in 1861 by the writer.</p></note> a selection from which he figured in
                    illustration of his paper, and, however the thing may be accounted for, it seems
                    impossible to resist, save on one supposition, the force of the testimony these
                    specimens afford, This one supposition is that the eggs have been wrongly
                    ascribed to the cuckow, and that they are only exceptionally large examples of
                    the eggs of the birds in the nests of which they were found, for it cannot be
                    gainsaid that some such abnormal examples are occasionally to be met with. But
                    it is well known that abnormally-large eggs are not only often deficient in
                    depth of colour, but still more often in stoutness of shell. Applying these
                    rough <hi rend="italic">criteria</hi> to Dr Baldamus’s series, most of the
                    specimens stand the test very well, and, though tìo doubt more precise and
                    delicate examination, than any to which they seem to have been submitted, were
                    desirable, there are some other considerations to be urged. For instance, Herr
                    Braune, a forester at Greiz in the principality of Reuss <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Naumannia, tom. cit.</hi> pp. 307, 313), shot a hen Cuckow as she was leaving
                    the nest of an Icterine Warbler <hi rend="italic">(JIypolais</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">icterina).</hi> In the oviduct of this Cuckow he found an egg
                    coloured very like that of the Warbler, and on looking into the nest he found
                    there an exactly similar egg, which there can be no reasonable doubt had just
                    been laid by that very Cuckow. Moreover Herr Grunack <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Journ.</hi><hi rend="italic">für</hi><hi rend="italic">0rn.,</hi> 1873, p.
                    454) has since found one of the most abnormally-coloured specimens, quite unlike
                    the ordinary egg of the Cuckow, to contain an embryo so fully formed as to show
                    the characteristic zygodactyl feet of the bird, thus proving unquestionably its
                    parentage. Now these being both of them extreme cases, Dr Baldamus may fairly
                    claim attention to his assertion; for short of absolutely disbelieving his word
                    we must admit that he has ground for it.</p>
                <p>On the other hand, we must bear in mind the numerous instances in which not the
                    least similarity can be traced— as in the not uncommon case of the Hedge-Sparrow
                    already mentioned, and if we attempt any explanatory hypothesis it must be one
                    that will fit all round. Such a one then seems to be this. We know that certain
                    kinds of birds resent interference with their nests much less than others, and
                    among them it may be asserted that the Hedge-Sparrow will patiently submit to
                    various experiments. She will brood with complacency the egg of a Redbreast <hi
                    rend="italic">(Eriilιacus</hi><hi rend="italic">rubecula),</hi> so unlike her
                    own, and for aught we know to the contrary may even be colour-blind. In the case
                    of such a species there would be no need of anything further to insure
                    success—the terror of the nest-owner at seeing her home invaded by a Hawk-like
                    giant, and some of her treasures tossed out, would be enough to stir her
                    motherly feelings so deeply that she would without misgiving, if not with joy
                    that something had been spared to her, resume the duty of incubation so soon as
                    the danger was past. But w ith other species it may be, nay doubtless it is,
                    different. Here assimilation of the introduced egg to those of the rightful
                    owner may be necessary, for there can hardly be a doubt as to the truth of Dr
                    Baldamus’s theory (the only theory, by the way, he has put forth), as to the
                    object of the assimilation being to render the Cuckow’s egg “less easily
                    recognized by the foster-parents as a substituted one.” But in this place it is
                    especially desirable to point out that theιe is not the slightest ground for
                    imagining that the Cuckow, or any other bird, can voluntarily influence the
                    colour of the egg she is about to lay. Over that she can have no control, but
                    its destination she can determine. It would seem also impossible that a Cuckow
                    having laid an egg, should look at it, and then decide from its appearance in
                    what bird’s nest she should put it. That the colour of an egg-shell can be in
                    some mysterious w ay affected by the action of external objects on the
                    perceptive faculties of the mother is a notion too wild to be seriously
                    entertained. Consequently, only one explanation of the facts can here be
                    suggested. Every one who has sufficiently studied the habits of animals will
                    admit the tendency of some of those habits to become hereditary. That there is a
                    reasonable probability of each Cuckow mostcommonly putting her eggs in the nest
                    of the same species of bird, and of this habit being transmitted to her
                    posterity, does not seem to be a very violent supposition. Without attributing
                    any wonderful sagacity to her, it does not seem unlikely that the Cuckow which
                    had once successfully foisted her egg on a Reed-Wren or a Titlark should again
                    seek for another Reed-Wren’s or another Titlark’s nest (as the case may be),
                    when she had another <hi rend="italic">egg to</hi> dispose of, and that she
                    should continue her practice from one season to another. It stands on record <hi
                    rend="italic">(Zoologist,</hi> 1873, p. 3648) that a pair of Wagtails built
                    their nest for eight or nine years running in almost exactly the same spot, and
                    that in each of those years they fostered a young Cuckow, while many other cases
                    of like kind, though not perhaps established on authority so good, are believed
                    to have happened. Such a habit could hardly fail to become hereditary, so that
                    the daughter of a Cuckow which always put her egg into a Reed-Wren’s, Titlark’s,
                    or Wagtail’s nest would do as did her mother. Furthermore it is unquestionable
                    that, whatever variation there may be among the eggs laid by different
                    individuals of the same species, there is a strong family likeness between the
                    eggs laid by the same individual, even at the interval of many years, and it can
                    hardly be questioned that the eggs of the daughter would more or less resemble
                    those of her mother. Hence the supposition may be fairly regarded that the habit
                    of laying a particular style of egg is also likely to become hereditary.
                    Combining this supposition with that as to the Cuckow’s habit of using the nest
                    of the same <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n720/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0720-0687"/> species becoming hereditary, it will be seen that
                    it requires but an application of the principle of “Natural Selection” to show
                    the probability of this principle operating in the course of time to produce the
                    facts asserted by the anonymous Solognot of the last century, and by Dr Baldamus
                    and others since. The particular <hi rend="italic">gens</hi> of Cuckow which
                    inherited and transmitted the habit of depositing in the nest of any particular
                    species of bird eggs having more or less resemblance to the eggs of that species
                    would prosper most in those members of the <hi rend="italic">gens</hi> where the
                    likeness was strongest, and the other members would <hi rend="italic">(caeteris
                    paribus)</hi> in time be eliminated. As already shewn, it is not to be supposed
                    that all species, or even all individuals of a species, are duped with equal
                    ease. The operation of this kind of natural selection would be most needed in
                    those cases where the species are not easily duped,—that is, in those cases
                    which occur the least frequently. Here it is we find it, for observation shows
                    that eggs of the Cuckow deposited in nests of the Red-Backed Shrike <hi
                    rend="italic">(Lanius</hi><hi rend="italic">collurio),</hi> of the Bunting <hi
                    rend="italic">(Emberiza miliaria),</hi> and of the Icterine Warbler approximate
                    in their colouring to eggs of those species—species in whose nests the Cuckow
                    rarely (in comparison with others) deposits eggs. Of species wſhich are more
                    easily duped, such as the Hedge-Sparrow, mention has already been made.</p>
                <p>More or less nearly allied to our Cuckow are many other forms of the genus from
                    various parts of Africa, Asia, and their islands, while one even reaches
                    Australia. How many of these deserve specific recognition will long be a
                    question among ornithologists which need not be discussed here. In some cases
                    the chief difference is said to lie in the diversity of voice—a character only
                    to be appreciated by those acquainted with the living birds, and though of
                    course some regard should be paid to this distinction, the possibility of birds
                    using different “dialects” according to the locality they inhabit (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Birds,</hi> vol. iii. p. 771, note 1) must make it a slender
                    specific diagnostic. All these forms are believed to have essentially the same
                    habits as our Cuckow, and, as regards parasiticism, the same is to be said of
                    the large Cuckow of Southern Europe and North Africa (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Coccystes</hi><hi rend="italic">glandarius)</hi> which victimizes Pies <hi
                    rend="italic">(Pica mauritanica</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cyanopica cooki)</hi>
                    and Crows <hi rend="italic">(Corvus comix).</hi> True it is that an instance of
                    this species, commonly known as the Great Spotted Cuckow, having built a nest
                    and hatched its young is on record, but the later observations of Dr A. E.
                    Brehm, Canon Tristram, Stafford Allen, and others tend to cast doubt on the
                    credibility of the ancient report. It is worthy of remark that the eggs of this
                    bird so closely resemble those of one of the Pies ìn whose nest they have been
                    found, that even expert zoologists have been deceived by them, only to discover
                    the truth when the Cuckow’s embryo had been extracted from the supposed Pie’s
                    egg. This species of Cuckow, easily distinguishable by its large size, long
                    crest, and the primrose tinge of its throat, has more than once made its
                    appearance as a straggler in the British Isles. Equally parasitic are many other
                    Cuckows, belonging chiefly to genera which have been more or less clearly
                    defined as <hi rend="italic">Cacomantis,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Chrysococcyx,</hi><hi rend="italic">Eudynamis, Oxylophus, Phaeni-cophaes,
                    Polyphasia, Surniculus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Zanclostoma,</hi> and
                    inhabiting parts of the Ethiopian, Indian, and Australian Regions;<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> Evidence tends to show that
                    the same is to be said of the curious Channel-bill <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Scythrops</hi><hi rend="italic">novte∙hollandice),</hi> but absolute proof
                    seems to be wanting.</p></note> but there are certain aberrant forms of
                    Old-World Cuckows which unquestionably do not ,shirk parental responsibilities.
                    Among these especially are the birds placed in or allied to the genera <hi
                    rend="italic">Centropus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Coua—</hi> the former having
                    a wide distribution from Egypt to New</p>
                <p>South Wales, living much on the ground and commonly called Lark-heeled Cuckows
                    (an obvious misnomer)—the latter bearing no English name, and limited to the
                    island of Madagascar. These build a nest, not perhaps in a highly-finished style
                    of architecture, but one that serves its end.</p>
                <p>Respecting the Cuckows of America, the evidence, though it has been impugned, is
                    certainly enough to clear them from the calumny which attaches to so many of
                    their brethren of the Old World. There are two species very well known in parts
                    of the United States and some of the West-Indian Islands <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Coccyzus</hi><hi rend="italic">amerιcanus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">C.
                    erythrophthalmus),</hi> and each of them has occasionally visited Europe. They
                    both build nests—remarkably small structures when compared with those of other
                    birds of their size—and faithfully incubate their delicate sea-green eggs. In
                    the south-western States of the Union and thence into Central America is found
                    another curious form of Cuckow <hi rend="italic">(Geococcyx)—</hi> the
                    Chapparal-cock of northern and Paisano of southern settlers. The first of these
                    names it takes from the low brushwood <hi rend="italic">(chapparaï)</hi> in
                    which it chiefly dwells, and the second is said to be due to its Pheasant-like
                    <hi rend="italic">(faisan</hi> corrupted into <hi rend="italic">paisano,</hi>
                    which is properly a countryman) appearance as it runs on the ground. Indeed, one
                    of the two species of the genus was formerly described as a <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phasianus.</hi> They both have short wings, and seem never to fly, but run with
                    great rapidity. Returning to arboreal forms, the genera <hi rend="italic"
                    >Neomorphus, Diplopterus, Saurothera,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Piaya</hi> (the
                    last two commonly called Rain-birds, from the belief that their cry portends
                    rain) may be noticed—all of them belonging to the Neotropical Region; but
                    perhaps the most curious form of American Cuckows is the Ani <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Crotophaga),</hi> of which three species inhabit the same Region. The
                    best-known species <hi rend="italic">C. ani)</hi> is found throughout the
                    Antilles and on the opposite continent. In most of the British colonies it is
                    known as the Black Witch, and is accused of various malpractices—it being, in
                    truth, a perfectly harmless if not a beneficial bird. As regards its propagation
                    this aberrant form of Cuckow departs as much in one directi¢nfrom the normal
                    habit of birds as do so many of our familiar friends of the Old World in the
                    other, for several females unite to lay their eggs in one nest. Full details of
                    its economy are wanting, but it is evident that incubation is carried on
                    socially, since an intruder on approaching the rude nest will disturb perhaps
                    half a dozen of its sable proprietors, who, loudly complaining, seek safety
                    either in the leafy branches of the tree that holds it, or in the nearest
                    available covert, with all the speed that their feeble powers of flight permit.
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
