<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0122-0103-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COCOA-NUT PALM (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    103)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:866134">Cocoa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1042338">Nuts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115719">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f3w">Cocoa</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kw57r0g">Nuts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n122/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COCOA-NUT PALM</label><hi rend="italic">(Cocos
                        nucifera),</hi> sometimes, and perhaps more correctly, called the coco-nut
                    palm, is a very beautiful and lofty palm-tree, growing to a height of from 60 to
                    100 feet, with a cylindrical stem which atta∙ns a thickness of 2 feet. The tree
                    terminates in a crown of graceful waving pinriate leaves. The leaf, which may
                    attain to 20 feet in length, consists of a strong mid-rib, whence numerous long
                    acute leaflets spring, giving the whole the appearance of a gigantic feather.
                    The flowers are arranged in branching spikes 5 or 6 feet long, enclosed in a
                    tough spathe, and the fruits mature in bunches of from 10 to 20. The fruits when
                    mature are oblong, and triangular in cross section, measuring from 12 to 18
                    inches in length and 6 to 8 inches in diameter. The fruit consists of a thick
                    external husk or rind of a fibrous structure, within which is the ordinary
                    cocoa-nut of commerce. The nut has a very hard, woody shell, enclosing the
                    nucleus or kernel, within which again is a milky liquid called cocoa-nut milk.
                    The palm is so widely disseminated throughout tropical countries that it is
                    impossible to distinguish its original habitat. It flourishes with equal vigour
                    on the coast of the East Indies, throughout the tropical islands of the Pacific,
                    and in the West Indies and tropical America. It, however, attains its greatest
                    luxuriance and vigour on the sea shore, and it is most at home in the
                    innumerable small islands of the Pacific seas, of the vegetation of which it is
                    eminently characteristic. Its wide distribution, and its existence in even the
                    smallest coral islets of the Pacific, have been favoured by the peculiar
                    triangular shape of the fruit, which dropping into the sea from trees growing on
                    any shores would be carried by tides and currents to be cast up and to vegetate
                    on distant coasts.</p>
                <p>The cocoa-nut palm, being the most useful of its entire tribe to the natives of
                    the regions in which it grows, and furnishing many valuable and important
                    commercial products, is the subject of careful cultivation in many countries. On
                    the Malabar and Coromandel coasts of India the trees grow in vast numbers; and
                    in Ceylon, which is peculiarly well suited for their cultivation, it is
                    estimated that twenty millions of the trees flourish. The wealth of a native in
                    Ceylon is estimated by his property in cocoa-nut trees, and Sir J. Emerson
                    Tennent notes a law case in a district court in which the subject in dispute was
                    a claim to the 2520th part of ten of the precious palms. The cultivation of
                    cocoa-nut plantations in Ceylon is thus described by Sir J. E. Tennent. “The
                    first operation in cocoa-nut planting is the formation of a nursery, for which
                    purpose the ripe nuts are placed in squares containing about 400 each; these are
                    covered an inch deep with sand and sea-weed or soft mud from the beach, and
                    watered daily till they germinate. The nuts put down in Appì are sufficiently
                    grown to be planted out before the rains of September, and they are then set out
                    in holes 3 feet deep and 20 to 30 feet apart.</p>
                <p>. . Before putting in the young plant it is customary to bed the roots with soft
                    mud and sea-weed, and for the first two years they must be watered and protected
                    from the glare of the sun under shades made of the plaited fronds of the
                    cocoa-nut palm, or the fan-like leaves of the palmyra.” The palm begins to bear
                    fruit from the fifth to the seventh year of its age, each stock carrying from 5
                    to 30 nuts, the tree maturing on an average 60 nuts yearly.</p>
                <p>The uses to which the various parts of the cocoa-nut palm are applied in the
                    regions of their growth are almost endless, The nuts supply no inconsiderable
                    proportion of the food of the natives, and the milky juice enclosed within them
                    forms a pleasant and refreshing drink. The juice drawn from the unexpanded
                    flower spathes forms “toddy,” which may be boiled down to sugar, or it is
                    allowed to ferment and is distilled, when it yields a spirit which, in common
                    with a like product from other sources, is known as “arrack.” The trunk yields a
                    timber (known in European commerce as porcupine wood) which is used for
                    building, furniture, firewood, &amp;c.; the leaves are plaited into cajan fans
                    and baskets, and used for thatching the roofs of houses; the shell of the nut is
                    employed as a .water vessel; and the external husk or rind yields the coir
                    fibre, with which are fabricated ropes, cordage, brushes, &amp;c. The cocoa-nut
                    palm also furnishes very important articles of external commerce, of which the
                    principal is cocoa-nut oil. It is obtained by pressure or boiling from the
                    kernels, which are first broken up into small pieces and dried in the sun, when
                    they are known as copperah or copra. It is estimated that 1000 full-sized nuts
                    will yield upwards of 500 ìb of copra, from which 25 gallons of oil should be
                    obtained. The oil is a white solid substance at ordinary temperatures, with a
                    peculiar, rather disagreeable odour, from the volatile fatty acids it contains,
                    and a mild taste. Under pressure it separates into a liquid and a solid portion,
                    the latter, cocoa-stearin, being extensively used in the manufacture of candles.
                    Cocoa-nut oil is also used in the manufacture of marine soap, which forms a
                    lather with sea water. Coir is also an important article of commerce, being in
                    large demand for the manufacture of coarse brushes, door mats, and woven coir
                    matting for lobbies and passages. A considerable quantity of fresh nuts is
                    imported, chiefly from the West Indies, and sold as a dainty among the poorer
                    classes, or used in the preparation of a kind of confection.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
