<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0511-0480-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COTTA (9th edition, volume 6, page 480)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw47w7c">Bavarians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46w96878">Diet</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7751w">Press</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136041">Students</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n511/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COTTA</label>, a family intimately connected with the history
                    of German literature.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Johann Georg Cotta</hi> was the founder of the illustrious
                    Cotta publishing-house. At the time of the Reformation the family (originally of
                    noble Italian blood) lived in Eisenach; and we hear of them later as being
                    settled in Dresden. Johann Georg started business at Tübingen in 1640</p>
                <p>His son, <hi rend="smallcaps">Johann Friedrich</hi> (1701-1779), born March 12,
                    1701, devoted himself to theological study, and began his public career as
                    lecturer in Jena University. He then travelled in Germany, France, and Holland,
                    and, after a stay of several years in London, became professor at Tübingen in
                    1733. In 1736 he removed to the chair of theology in the university of
                    Göttingen, which had been instituted as a seat of learning, two years before, by
                    George II. of England, in his capacity as elector of Hanover. In 1739, however,
                    he returned, as extraordinary professor of theology, to his Alma Mater, and,
                    after successively filling the chairs of history, poetry, and oratory, was
                    appointed ordinary professor of theology in 1741. Finally he died, as chancellor
                    of the university, on the 31st of December 1779. His learning was at once wide
                    and accurate; his theological views were orthodox, although he did not believe
                    in strict verbal inspiration. He was a voluminous writer. His chief works are
                    his edition of Johann Gerard’s <hi rend="italic">Loci Theologici,</hi> and the
                        <hi rend="italic">Kirchen</hi><hi rend="italic">Historie</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">des</hi><hi rend="italic">Neuen,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Testaments.</hi></p>
                <p>The most famous member of the family was <hi rend="smallcaps">Johann</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Friedrich Freiherr</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Cotta</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">von Cottendorf</hi> (1764- 1832), a grandson of the
                    theologian, who was born at Stuttgart April 27, 1764. He attended the gymnasium
                    of his native place, and originally meant to study theology, but became greatly
                    interested in the science of war. In 1782 he entered, as a student of
                    mathematics, in the university of Tübingen, and on the recommendation of
                    Professor Pfleiderer, was elected tutor of Prince Lubomirski in Warsaw. While
                    engaged in tuition, he continued his own studies with great enthusiasm; and, in
                    his zeal for self-culture, he spent a considerable time in Paris, studying
                    French and natural science, and mixing with distinguished literary men. After
                    practising as an advocate in one of the higher courts, Cotta, in compliance with
                    his father’s earnest desire, undertook to conduct the publishing business at
                    Tübingen, which, in the hands of subordinates, had very much declined. He
                    started in December 1787, and laboured incessantly to acquire familiarity with
                    all the details. The house connections rapidly extended; and, in 1793, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Allgemeine Zeitung,</hi> of which Schiller was to be editor,
                    was planned. Schiller was compelled to withdraw on account of his health; but
                    his friendship with Cotta deepened every year, and was a great advantage to the
                    poet and his family. Cotta awakened in Schiller so warm an attachment that, as
                    Doering tells us, when a bookseller offered him a higher price than Cotta for
                    the copyright of <hi rend="italic">Wallenstein,</hi> the poet firmly declined
                    it, replying, “Cotta deals steadily with me, and I with him.” In 1795 Schiller
                    and Cotta founded the <hi rend="italic">Horen,</hi> a periodical very important
                    to the student of German literature. The poet intended, by means of this work,
                    to infuse higher ideas into the common lives of men, by giving them a nobler
                    human culture, and“to reunite the divided political world under the banner of
                    truth and beauty.” The <hi rend="italic">Horen</hi> brought Goethe and Schiller
                    into most intimate relations with each other and with Cotta; and Goethe, while
                    regretting that he had already promised <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Meister</hi>
                    to another publisher, contributed the <hi rend="italic">Unterhaltung Deutscher
                        Ausgewanderten,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Roman Elegies,</hi> and a paper
                    on Literary Sansculottism. Fichte sent essays from the first; and the other
                    brilliant German authors of the time were also represented. In 1798 the <hi
                        rend="italic">Allgemeine Zeitung,</hi> which is still the leading daily
                    paper in Germany, appeared at Tübingen, being edited first by Posselt and then
                    by Huber. It soon wielded a mighty influence, and must prove a valuable
                    storehouse to the historian. In 1798 the editorial office was transferred to
                    Stuttgart, and in 1803 to Augsburg. In 1799 Cotta entered on his political
                    career, and was sent to Paris by the Würtemburg states as their representative,
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n512/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0512-0481"/> where he made friendships which proved very
                    advantageous for the <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Zeitung.</hi> In 1801 he paid
                    another visit to Paris, in a political capacity, when he carefully studied
                    Napoleon’s policy, and treasured up many hints which were useful to him in his
                    literary undertakings. He still, however, devoted most of his attention to his
                    own business, and, for many years, made all the entries into the ledger with his
                    own hand. He relieved the tedium of almost ceaseless toil by pleasant
                    intercourse with literary men. With Schiller, Huber, and Pfeffel he was on terms
                    of the warmest friendship; and he was also intimate with Herder, Schelling,
                    Fichte, Richter, Voss, Hebel, Tieck, Therese Huber, Matthissυn, the brothers
                    Humboldt, Johann Müller, Spittler, and others, whose works he published in whole
                    or in part. In the correspondence of Alexander von Humboldt with Varnhagen von
                    Ense we see the familiar relations in which the former stood to the Cotta
                    family. In 1795 appeared the <hi rend="italic">Politischen Annalen</hi> and the
                        <hi rend="italic">Jahrbücher der Baukunde,</hi> and in 1798 the <hi
                        rend="italic">Damenalmanach,</hi> along with some works of less importance.
                    In 1807 he issued the <hi rend="italic">Morgenblatt,</hi> to which Schorn’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Kunstblatt</hi> and Menzel’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Literaturblatt</hi> were afterwards added. In 1810 he removed to Stuttgart;
                    and from that time till his death he was loaded with honours. State affairs and
                    an honourable commission from the German booksellers took him to the Vienna
                    Congress; and in 1815 he was deputy-elect at the Wurtemberg Diet. In 1819 he
                    became representative of the nobility; then he succeeded to the offices of
                    member of committee and (1824) vice-president of the Würtemberg second chamber.
                    He was also chosen Prussian privy court counsellor, Bavarian chancellor, and
                    knight of the order of the Würtemberg Crown. Meanwhile such publications as the
                        <hi rend="italic">Polytechnische</hi><hi rend="italic">Journal,</hi> the <hi
                        rend="italic">Hesperus,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Würtember-gischen</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Jahrbücher,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Hertha,</hi> the <hi
                        rend="italic">Ausland,</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Inland</hi> issued
                    from the press. In 1828-29 appeared the famous correspondence between Schiller
                    and Goethe. Cotta was an unfailing friend of young struggling men of talent. In
                    addition to his high standing as a publisher, he was a man of great practical
                    energy, which flowed into various fields of activity. He was a scientific
                    agriculturist, and promoted many reforms in farming. He was the first
                    Wſtrtemberg landholder who did away with servitude on his estates. In politics
                    he was throughout his life a moderate liberal. In 1824 he set up a steam
                    printing press in Augsburg, and, about the same time, founded a literary
                    institute at Munich. In 1825 he started steamboats, for the first time, on Lake
                    Constance, and introduced them in the following year for the Rhine traffic. In
                    1828 he was sent to Berlin, on an important commission, by Bavaria and
                    Würtemberg, and was there rewarded with orders of distinction at the hands of
                    the three kings. He died on the 29th of December 1832.</p>
                <p>His son, <hi rend="smallcaps">Freiherr Georg</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Cotta</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">von Cottendorf,</hi> who was born in 1796,
                    and died in 1863, succeeded to the management of the business on the death of
                    his father. He was materially assisted by his brother-in-law, Chamberlain
                    Freiherr von Reischach. He greatly extended the connections of the firm; and, in
                    1865, the house had establishments for different kinds of publications at
                    Stuttgart, Augsburg, Leipsic, and Munich. The business is still in the hands of
                    the Cotta family. (τ. <hi rend="smallcaps">gi.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
