<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0479-0448-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COSSACKS (9th edition, volume 6, page 448)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:880643">Cossacks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1069177">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1138427">Sultans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079619">Protectionism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848897">Cataract</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp6g">Cossacks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xk84r7r">Caucasians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h12vb7j">Frontiers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6b80d">Cataract</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n479/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COSSACKS</label>, certain Russian tribes originally settled
                    on the southern frontiers of Russia in Europe, but now distributed through
                    various parts of the empire, and largely modified by successive intrusions of
                    alien blood. They probably derive their name, which in Russian appears as <hi
                        rend="italic">Kazak,</hi> from a word synonymous in Tartar with a freebooter
                    and in Turkish with a light-armed soldier. Ethnographically and historically
                    they are divided into two principal sections, the Cossacks of Little Russia, or
                    of the Dnieper, and the Cossacks of Great Russia, or of the Don.</p>
                <p>The former or Malo-Russian branch seems to have grown up in the 13th and 14th
                    centuries, and probably owed its existence to the confusion caused by the Tartar
                    invasion. Bands of hardy refugees from the surrounding regions, mainly with
                    Russian blood in their veins, gathered together for mutual defence in the
                    islands of the Dnieper, where the natural character of the situation of itself
                    afforded them considerable protection. Their numbers were rapidly increased, and
                    before long they formed a strong and active community. In the 16th century they
                    were enrolled among the vassals of Poland, but were permitted to retain a number
                    of privileges which put them on a level with tho Polish nobility. Their
                    constitution was consolidated, their territory extended, and their valour
                    utilized by the able policy of King Stephen Bathori. Meanwhile the more ardent
                    adventurers amongst them were united into a strict military confederation, not
                    unlike in many respects to those orders of knights which in similar
                    circumstances sprung up in Western Europe for the defence of Christendom. They
                    established their <hi rend="italic">setcha,</hi> or fortified camp, on an island
                    in the Dnieper, to the south of the <hi rend="italic">Porogi,</hi> or cataracts,
                    and from this circumstance acquired the name of Zaporogians, or Dwellers beyond
                    the Cataracts. The members were bound by a vow of celibacy; but as every one was
                    welcome to join the association who was willing to submit to its rules, so every
                    one was free to depart as soon as he found it irksome to obey. Freedom and
                    independence were of the first necessity to the Cossacks; their constitution was
                    purely democratic; their <hi rend="italic">hetmans</hi> or leaders were chosen
                    by popular election, and held their office only for one year. This independent
                    spirit was abundantly displayed in their policy; they lent their services now to
                    the king of Poland, now to Russia, now to the Sultan, and now, it might be, even
                    to the Tartar Khan himself. In 1571, when their leader was put to death by
                    Bathori for having invaded Moldavia on his own authority, thousands of his
                    followers left the country, and went to join their brethren on the Don; and in
                    the following century, the main body which had remained behind, after carrying
                    on a successful war against Poland under the astute Khmelnicky, put themselves
                    under the protection of Russia, whose right to the whole country of the
                    Cossacks, with the exception of a small portion to the west of the Dnieper, was
                    formally recognized by the peace of Radzine in 1681. In 1708 the famous Ivan
                    Stevanovitch Mazeppa, who had succeeded in raising himself to the office of
                    hetman, joined the standard of Charles XII. of Sweden; and this revolt brought
                    down on the Cossacks the vengeance of Peter tho Great, who ultimately deprived
                    them of all their privileges and abolished their military organization. The
                    Zaporrgians, who left the country after the capture of their seteka, were
                    recalled by the Empress Anne; but they proved so <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n480/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0480-0449"/> obstinately obstructive to the civil
                    settlement of the country that they had again to be expelled. They retired for
                    the most part to the Crimea, and on the incorporation of that district with the
                    Russian empire they were deported to Kuban to defend the frontiers against the
                    Caucasian tribes. A small band which had migrated to the Balkan, was recalled in
                    1828 by the Emperor Nicholas, and sent to form a sort of coast-guard on the Sea
                    of Azoff. The character of the Zaporogian fraternity which was thus destroyed
                    has been the object of very divergent judgments,—some writers seeing in it
                    little more than an organized band of ruffian adventurers, while others raise
                    its members to the dignity of patriots and martyrs who fought and died in
                    defence of national and religious liberty. The last view is well presented by
                    Kulish, one of the most recent of the historians of Little Russia, and it
                    receives no small support from the popular songs in which their virtues and
                    valour are still commemorated among the people of the Ukraine.</p>
                <p>The Cossacks of the Don have all along had more direct connection with the empire
                    than their brethren of the Dnieper; and their insurrections, though numerous,
                    have had less of the character of genuine revolt. About seven years after the
                    foundations of their capital Cherkask had been fixed in the marshes of the Don,
                    Ivan IV., irritated at their conduct, despatched against them his general
                    Murashkine. At the approach of the formidable invader the Cossacks dispersed;
                    one band under Yermak pushed eastwards, and effected the conquest of Siberia;
                    another company established themselves in the Ural Mountains and expelled the
                    Tartars from Jaik (Uralsk); while a third probably found a refuge in the
                    Caucasus, where their descendants are still known as the Grebenski, or Mountain
                    Cossacks. In 1637 the portion still left on the Don expelled the Turks from the
                    town of Azoff; and they managed to keep possession of it till 1642 without aid
                    from the Russian Government. Exasperated by the execution of some of their
                    number, and by an attempt to introduce alterations in their religion, they were
                    easily excited to rebellion by the freebooter Stenka (or Stephen) Razine; but
                    after it had risen to a formidable height, the insurrection was suppressed, and
                    its leader executed at Moscow in 1671. In the following century another
                    adventurer found in the discontent of the Cossacks a formidable means of
                    supporting his pretensions; but the success of Pugacheff was as temporary as
                    that of Razine, whom the local superstition imagined to have come to life in his
                    person. The result to the Cossacks was a serious diminution of their privileges,
                    and an extension of Russian control.</p>
                <p>Gradually brought under a more rigid military discipline, this restless and
                    warlike race has furnished the empire with one of the most valuable elements in
                    its national army; and their services in the protection of the frontiers from
                    the Caucasus to China are almost incalculable. They form a first-rate irregular
                    cavalry, and render excellent service as scouts and skirmishers; but their
                    steadiness can hardly be trusted in an important engagement. So great is their
                    superstition, that in the midst of a conflict they have been known to give chase
                    to a hare in order to avert the omen by its destruction, and they still retain a
                    large measure of the freebooter’s fondness for plunder.</p>
                <p>According to their present distribution the Cossacks are distinguished as
                    Cossacks of the Don, of the Azoff, of the Danube, of the Black Sea, of the
                    Caucasus, of the Ural, of Orenburg, of Siberia, of the Chinese frontiers, and of
                    Astrakhan. In their organization they retain the communistic habits of earlier
                    times. The territory is the common property of the stanitza or township; the hay
                    can only be cut after public notice by the Ataman; and no fish can be captured
                    except at prescribed periods, when the whole community join in the
                    enterprize.</p>
                <p>Among the privileges still retained by the Cossacks the most important are
                    freedom from taxes, and the right of distilling, brewing, hunting, and
                    fishing.</p>
                <p>See Houpel, “Sur les Cosaques,” in <hi rend="italic">Miscellanies du Nord,</hi>
                    1790; Lesur, <hi rend="italic">Hιstoiredes</hi><hi rend="italic">Kosaques,</hi>
                    Paris, 1814; Bronevski, <hi rend="italic">Istoria Donskova Voiska,</hi> St
                    Petersburg, 1834; Wagner, <hi rend="italic">Der Kaukasus und das Land der
                        Kosaken,</hi> 1850; Haxthausen, <hi rend="italic">Études sur la Russie,</hi>
                    Berlin, 1853, vol. iii.; Prosper Mérimee, <hi rend="italic">Les Cosaques
                        d'autrefois,</hi> dealing only with the insurrections of Chmielnicky, and
                    Stenka Razine, and based on the works of N. kostniarofl, the Malo-Russian
                    historian; Alfred Rambaud, “L’Ukraine et ses chansons historiques,” in. <hi
                        rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes,</hi> 1877.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
