<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0370-0341-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COORG (9th edition, volume 6, page 341)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j96094w">Seasons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r851">Tigers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897708">Dravidians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032276">Nairs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1138427">Sultans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110447">Seasons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850032">Cedar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n370/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COORG</label>, a province of Southern India, near the centre
                    of the Western Ghats, between ll <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 56' and 12° 45'
                    N. lat. and 75° 25' and 76° 13' E. long., is bounded by Mysore, Malabar, and
                    South Kanara, and has an area of 2000 square miles. It is a mountainous
                    district, presenting throughout a series of wooded hills and deep valleys; the
                    lowest elevations are 3000 feet above sea-level. The loftiest peak,
                    Tandiandamol, has an altitude of 5781 feet; Pushpagiri, another peak, is 5682
                    feet high. The principal river is the Cauvery, or Kaveri, which rises on the
                    eastern side of the Western Ghats, and with its tributaries drains the greater
                    part of Coorg. Besides these there are several large streams that take their
                    rise in Coorg. In the rainy season, which lasts during the continuance of the
                    southwest monsoon, or from June to the end of September, the rivers flow with
                    violence and great rapidity. In July and August the rainfall is excessive, and
                    the month of November is often showery. The yearly rainfall may exceed 160
                    inches; in the dense jungle tract it reaches from 120 to 150; in the bamboo
                    district from 60 to 100 inches. The climate, though humid, is on the whole
                    healthy; it is believed to have been rendered hotter and drier of late years by
                    the clearing of forest land. Coorg has an average temperature of about 60°
                    Fahr., the extremes being 52° and 82°. The hottest season is in April and May.
                    In the direction of Mysore the whole country is thickly wooded; but to the
                    westward the forests are more open. The flora of the jungle includes <hi
                        rend="italic">Miclιdia</hi> (Chumpak), <hi rend="italic">Mesita</hi>
                    (Iron-wood), <hi rend="italic">Diospyros</hi> (Ebony and other species), <hi
                        rend="italic">Cedrela Tomia</hi> (White cedar), <hi rend="italic"
                        >Chickrassia</hi><hi rend="italic">tubularis</hi> (Red cedar), <hi
                        rend="italic">Calophyllum angustifolium</hi> (Poon spar), <hi rend="italic"
                        >Canarium strictum</hi> (Black Dammar tree), <hi rend="italic">Artocarpus,
                        Dipterocarpus, Garcinia, Fuonymus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Cinnamomum
                        iners,</hi><hi rend="italic">Myristica,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Vaccinium,</hi><hi rend="italic">Myctaceae, Melastomaceae,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Rubus</hi> (three species), and a rose. In the undergrowth are
                    found cardamom, areca, plantain, canes, wild pepper, tree and other ferns, and
                    arums. In the forest of the less thickly-wooded bamboo country in the west of
                    Coorg the trees most common are the <hi rend="italic">Dιdbergia</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">latifolia</hi> (Black wood), <hi rend="italic">Pterocarpus
                        Marsupium</hi> (Kino tree), <hi rend="italic">Terminalia coriacea</hi>
                    (Mutti), <hi rend="italic">Lagerstròmia</hi><hi rend="italic">parυiflora</hi>
                    (Benteak), <hi rend="italic">Conocarpus</hi><hi rend="italic">latifolius</hi>
                    (Dindul), <hi rend="italic">Bassia</hi><hi rend="italic">latifolia,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Butea</hi><hi rend="italic">frondosa,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Nauclea parviflora,</hi> and several acacias, with which, in the eastern
                    part of the district, teak and sandalwood occur. Among the fauna may be
                    mentioned the elephant, tiger, tiger-cat, cheetah or hunting leopard, wild dog,
                    elk, bison, wild boar, several species of deer, hares, monkeys, the buceros and
                    various other birds, the cobra di capello, and a few alligators. The most
                    interesting antiquities of Coorg are the earth redoubts <hi rend="italic"
                        >(kunnidegs),</hi> which are from 15 to 25 feet high, and provided with a
                    ditch 10 feet deep by 8 or 10 feet wide. Their linear extent is reckoned at
                    between 500 and 600 miles. The exports of Coorg are mainly rice, coffee, and
                    cardamoms; and the only important manufacture is a kind of coarse blanket.
                    Fruits of many descriptions, especial <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> y oranges,
                    are produced in abundance, and are of excellent quality. The Coorgs, of whom the
                    Kodagas are the chief tribe, constitute thirteen castes. They are of Dravidian
                    origin, and retain the devil-worship of their ancestors; they speak a dialect of
                    Canarese. They are a well-formed, bold and active, but ignorant and
                    superstitious race. The strange institution of polyandry prevalent among them,
                    according to which the wives of the brothers of a family are common property,
                    appears to have arisen from the necessity of counteracting the exterminating
                    influence of wars by making the brothers of the slain the rightful husbands of
                    their widows. The principal towns of Coorg are Merkara, the capital, Fraserpett,
                    Somwarpett, Periapatam, and Verajenderpetta. In 1872 Coorg contained 510
                    villages, and its population numbered 168,312.</p>
                <p>Previous to its annexation to British India, Coorg was governed by a line of
                    rajahs of the Nair caste of Hindus, mentioned in history as early as the year
                    1583. The ascendency of the last family of these rulers dates from the year
                    1632. Its princes retained their independence till the year 1773, when Hyder
                    Ali, who had long sought the subjugation of the country, took advantage of a
                    dispute about the succession to seize upon the sovereignty, and imprisoned the
                    rajah. The latter subsequently effected his escape from captivity, and drove the
                    armies of Tippoo Sultan out of Coorg; and in the war against Tippoo in the year
                    1791 he proved a useful auxiliary to the British. On the defeat of Tippoo a
                    treaty was entered into between the East India Company and Viraraja of Coorg,
                    who dying in 1807, left the throne to his daughter Devammaji. Lin-garaja, her
                    uncle, who now usurped the throne, was succeeded in 1820 by his son, Viraraja.
                    This monarch’s misgovernment and oppression of Coorg brought upon him at length
                    the armed interference of Lord William Bentinck; in April 1834 he was deposed by
                    General Fraser, and his dominions were annexed to British territory. Since then
                    the revenue has improved, cultivation has been extended, and the general
                    prosperity of the country has steadily increased.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
