<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0764-0729-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CUSTOMS DUTIES (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    729)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:918764">Exports</term>
                    <term ref="fast:968197">Imports</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1017057">Merchants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933786">Fraud</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q43v">Economists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0h03c">Exports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s70x">Imports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tg7r">Rates</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n764/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CUSTOMS DUTIES</label> are taxes on the import and export of
                    commodities, and rank among the most ancient, as they continue to prevail as one
                    of the most common modes, in all countries, of levying revenue for public
                    purposes. In an insular country like the United Kingdom customs duties came in
                    process of time to be levied only or chiefly in the seaports, and thus applied
                    only to the foreign commerce, where they may be brought under the control of
                    fair and reasonable principles of taxation. But this simplification of customs
                    duties was only reached by degrees; and during a long period special customs
                    were levied on goods passing between England and Scotland; and the trade of
                    Ireland with Great Britain and with foreign countries was subjected to fiscal
                    regulations which could not now stand in the light of public reason. The taxes
                    levied, on warrant of some ancient grant or privilege, upon cattle or goods at a
                    bridge or a ferry or other point of passage from one county or province to
                    another, of which there are some lingering remains even in the United Kingdom,
                    and those levied at the gates of cities on the produce of the immediate country
                    —a not uncommon form of municipal taxation on the European continent—are all of
                    the nature of customs dues. It is from the universality of this practice that
                    our English term of “customs” appears to have been derived. In countries of
                    extensive land frontiers the system of taxation by duties on foreign commodities
                    becomes still more complicated. Custom-houses have to be established along the
                    land borders and at particular points on the rivers or the railways; and the
                    foreign and domestic tax-collectors are brought into immediate contact. Some
                    European Governments distinguish in their rates of duty between “dry” or land
                    ports and “wet” or sea ports; and others vary their dues on foreign commodities
                    according to the zones of the globe from which the commodities come. Nothing has
                    consequently been more perplexing to the merchant than customs duties. They are
                    a labyrinth through which he has had to steer with caution and circumspection;
                    while, atthe same time, it has offered to the more unscrupulous traders
                    temptations to fraud. The smuggling which proceeds under customs duties is only
                    to be checked by the most careful administration, by a system proceeding as far
                    as possible on the simplicity of generally recognized principles, and by duties
                    so moderate in amount as to reduce to a minimum the temptation of fraud.</p>
                <p>A customs duty on the <hi rend="italic">import</hi> of commodities has to be paid
                    by the domestic consumers of the commodities. The foreign producer will not sell
                    them at less than they cost, and the importing merchant will not bring them in
                    unless he obtain this cost, his own fair profit, and the import duty <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n765/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0765-0730"/> over and above these essential constituents
                    of the transaction. An import duty is thus in some cases a tax which consumers
                    may pay lightly or heavily as they choose, and has accordingly a flexibility
                    that is not unimportant in taxation. But if the commodity be one of domestic as
                    well as foreign supply, the effect of the customs duty is to raise the price of
                    the domestic supply in some proportion to the duty; and the consumer, in so far
                    as the commodity is one of necessity to him, has no choice. He has to pay the
                    tax, with the further dissatisfaction of knowing that it goes to no public
                    purpose, but only into the pockets of some of his own private neighbours. A
                    customs duty on the <hi rend="italic">export</hi> of commodities, on the other
                    hand, has to be paid by the foreign consumers, one of the most agreeable forms
                    of taxation to be conceived. But this desire of taxing foreigners for domestic
                    revenue is met by the competition of general commerce, and nations have to be
                    chary of levying duties on the export of the products of their own industry. It
                    is only where they have some special monopoly of the product that they can enter
                    upon such a course without the gravest disadvantage to themselves.</p>
                <p>Wherever the principle of free trade is recognized, these distinctions have to be
                    strictly observed; and in the past thirty years’ regime of free trade in the
                    United Kingdom, the whole system of customs duties, in its principles, its rates
                    of duty, and its administration, has undergone a complete revolution. Of many
                    hundreds of articles on which customs duty was levied in the seaports, only five
                    or six, of exclusively foreign origin, now remain to yield the customs revenue
                    of the kingdom. Yet this revenue has never declined. It is much larger than when
                    the whole elaborate system of customs duties was in force. The best literature
                    of this interesting subject, apart from the standard works of British, French,
                    and German economists, is to be found in the Budgets of the British Parliament
                    since 1842; in the Acts consolidating and reforming the custom-house
                    administration, particularly the Act of 1853 drawn by Mr Wilson, editor of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Economist,</hi> and then secretary of the treasury; in the
                    reports of the Hon. David Wells, late commissioner of revenue in the United
                    States; and in the annual reports of the British custom-house commissioners, in
                    which alone there is a magazine of the most valuable facts. Of recent years the
                    only controversy of the British public with the custom-house relates to what has
                    been deemed the too careless admission of adulterated or worthless commodities,
                    in respect to which there may have to be a further reform in the future. In the
                    case of commodities on which a duty is levied, aud must be paid before they pass
                    into consumption, there would seem to be a responsibility on the part of the
                    duty-levying power to ascertain that the commodity is what it is professed to
                    be.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
