<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0191-0164-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COLOSSIANS, The Epistle to the (9th edition, volume 6,
                    page 164)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1031671">Mystics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937112">Galatians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984280">Judaism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61d88">Judaism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw1m">Martyrs</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n191/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COLOSSIANS, <hi rend="smallcaps">The Epistle to
                        the</hi></label>, belongs to the third of the four groups under which the
                    Pauline epistles may be chronologically arranged,—a group which occupies a
                    midway position between the letters sent to Corinth, Galatia, and Rome, in the
                    apostle’s third missionary journey, and the letters known as the Pastoral
                    Epistles. By similarity of language and matter the epistle to the Colossians is
                    intimately connected with that to the Ephesians; and the notices of St Paul’s
                    companions, and of Onesimus and Archippus, which occur in the epistle to
                    Philemon, show that this last epistle was also written, and sent at the same
                    time as the other two. The epistle to the Philippians belongs to the same group,
                    and the most probable view is that it was from Rome that all four were written
                    by Paul, “the prisoner of Jesus Christ” (comp. Philem. 1; Col. iv. 10, 18; Eph.
                    iii. 1, iv. 1, vi. 20; Phil, i. 13, 14, iv. 22). Some critics—among whom may be
                    mentioned Schulz, Böttger, Thiersch, Meyer, and Reuss, whose opinion is strongly
                    advocated by De Pressensé in his <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Trois</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Premiers</hi><hi rend="italic">Siècles</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >—</hi> contend that at least three of the epistles were written from
                    Caesarea; but the traditional view that all four were written from Rome is
                    supported by most modern writers, and is freest from difficulties. The date of
                    the epistle to the Colossians may be placed about 62 or 63 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d.</hi> Assuming for the present its genuineness, we may gather from the
                    contents of the epistle itself its occasion and object. Epaphras, who is spoken
                    of in high terms by the apostle, and may with some probability be considered the
                    founder of the church at Colossae (i. 7), has brought tidings to St Paul which
                    make him anxious concerning the Christians in Colossae and its neighbourhood
                    (ii. 1, iv. 13). False teachers are there endeavouring to beguile them with
                    plausible talk (ii. 4), and Paul, as a minister of the gospel earnestly
                    labouring in the cause of proclaiming Christ to the nations (i. 24-29), feels
                    his heart called out towards those whose faith is being insidiously assailed,
                    although he is absent from them, and has never personally visited Colossae or
                    Laodicea (ii. 1). He accordingly writes an epistle the polemical purport of
                    which is patent. Paul’s polemic, however, is no mere negative protest. He sets
                    up, as against the “false philosophy” which he so strenuously repudiates (ii.
                    8), a “theological conception of the person of Christ,” which strikes at the
                    root of all vain speculations concerning the unseen world, and shows that the
                    work of reconciliation effected by Christ is complete, so that in Him Christians
                    are to see the one Mediator through whom God is to be known, approached, served.
                    The latter part of the epistle consists of various practical exhortations, both
                    general and specific; and it closes with several notices of a personal
                    character. Tychicus was the bearer of this letter (iv. 7), as he was also of
                    that known as the epistle to the Ephesians, which by some critics is identified
                    with “the letter from Laodicea’ (iv. 16).</p>
                <p>But are these letters genuine î There is no historical ground for doubting the
                    Pauline authorship, or for the theory which has been advanced that the two
                    epistles are inventions of a later age, or for the supposition that, whilst one
                    of them is genuine, the other is made up of materials derived from that one
                    which was really written by St Paul. The fact that opponents of the genuineness
                    of the letters do not agree as to which was the original is significant.
                    Mayerhoff thinks, indeed, both epistles to be spurious, but considers that the
                    epistle to the Colossians was compiled from that to the Ephesians; while De
                    Wette holds the epistle to the Ephesians to be a “verbose enlargement” of that
                    to the Colossians, and advocates the genuineness of the latter. The opponents of
                    the Pauline authorship rest mainly on three lines of argument, <hi rend="italic"
                        >viz.,</hi> the similarity of the two epistles, the peculiarity of their
                    contents, and peculiarities of style.</p>
                <p>The objection founded on the similarity of the language and matter of the two
                    epistles is one that cannot be substantiated. For whilst there are striking
                    resemblances, there are no less striking differences; and whilst the
                    resemblances can be very naturally accounted for by the contemporaneousness of
                    the letters, the differences are so markedly in accordance with the apparent
                    designs of the separate letters,—that to the Colossians being primarily polemic,
                    and that to the Ephesians being of a mystic and devotional character,—that we
                    may fairly use of each epistle the words applied by Meyer to the epistle to the
                    Colossians,—“The supposed forgery of such an epistle would be far more
                    marvellous and inexplicable than its genuineness.”</p>
                <p>Another objection brought forward is that in these epistles we have sentiments
                    that savour of heresies later than the apostolic age. This objection seems to be
                    based upon very superficial grounds, and to spring from prejudice rather than
                    from research. What definite ground is there for asserting that “Gnostic and
                    Montanist” sentiments are to be found in these epistles? While certain false
                    teachings and tendencies are alluded to, which evidently go beyond the more
                    naked Pharisaic Judaism controverted in the epistle to the Galatians, nothing
                    can be produced to show that the heretical teaching animadverted upon in the
                    epistle to the Colossians, or even in the later epistles of Paul to Timothy and
                    Titus, is <hi rend="italic">Gnosticism</hi> in the sense in which that term is
                    applied to later systematic theosophies and cosmologies, such as those of
                    Basilides and Valentinus. And would it not be natural, as Neander points out, to
                    postulate, even if we had no records to testify to the fact.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n192/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0192-0165"/>
                <p>the existence of certain transitional links between the <hi rend="italic"
                        >gnosis</hi> of the 2d century and the earlier stages of the apostolic
                    preaching <hi rend="italic">1</hi> Such links are found in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >incipient</hi> Gnosticism, if so it is to be called, of which we have
                    traces in the epistles of the imprisonment and the subsequent Pastoral
                    Epistles.</p>
                <p>A third objection has been made to the genuineness of the epistle to the
                    Colossians, as well as to the Ephesian epistle, on the ground of the peculiarity
                    of their style and of certain terms used in them, some of which are asserted to
                    be technical terms, as <hi rend="italic">aeon,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >pleroma,</hi><hi rend="italic">dec.,</hi> and others are words not
                    elsewhere used in the Pauline writings. The answer to this objection is that the
                    peculiar terms are not used in the sense which they acquired in heretical
                    writings of a later period, and that the unusual words are to be attributed
                    partly to the nature of the subject and partly to the disposition of the
                    writer’s mind at the time. If, indeed, we are to condemn any writing of an
                    author for containing peculiarities not exhibited in other writings of the same
                    author, the questions arise, whence are we to take our standard of judgment, or
                    how are we to know in what cases we should apply so vague a critical canon <hi
                        rend="italic">ì</hi> Bleek say?, sensibly enough, in view of this line of
                    objection, “We do not for a moment deny that the epistle to the Colossians
                    contains much which is peculiar to itself; but its contents, such as they are,
                    do not tell against its coming from the same author as the other epistles of St
                    Paul, for even those which Baur allows to be genuine contain much that is
                    distinctive and peculiar, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> the Galatians as compared
                    with the Corinthians, and 2 Corinthians as compared with 1 Corinthians.” The
                    fact is that in the Tübingen school “subjective criticism” has run to riot. The
                    phenomena to be investigated are interpreted according to a preconceived theory,
                    rather than fairly looked at, examined, and explained. The testimony of the
                    early church to the Colossian and Ephesian letters is unexceptionable. In the
                    case of the epistle to the Colossians, there are indications of its recognition
                    in allusions by Justin Martyr and Theophilus of Antioch; it occurs in the
                    Muratorian canon <hi rend="italic">(fore.</hi> 170 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d);</hi> it is cited by Irenaeus, Clement of Alexandria, Tertullian, and
                    Origen; Eusebius places it among the “acknowledged” books of the apostolical
                    writings; and it occurs in Marcion’s list, as given by Epiphanius. Nor is there
                    anything in the epistle itself that is out of accordance with the circumstances
                    of the apostle Paul, or the condition of the Asiatic churches in the seventh
                    decade of the 1st century.</p>
                <p>We must now briefly notice the character of the teaching against which St Paul
                    directed the controversial portion of the epistle to the Colossians (ii. 4-23).
                    His warnings are against a philosophy which is vain and fallacious; against a
                    system of multiplied religious observances and distinctions of meats; against an
                    arbitrary system of angel-worship; and against certain rigorous rules of
                    asceticism. The basis of this alien teaching was unmistakably Judaic, but the
                    Judäizing effort was of a mystic and ascetic type; and it is not unreasonable to
                    see in the theosophical speculations and ascetic ordinances, indicated in St
                    Paul’s picture of the dangers which beset the Colossian Christians, an admixture
                    of Jewish and Oriental elements. Professor Lightfoot has shown that Oriental
                    notions concerning the evil of matter and the need of rigid abstinence, together
                    with “an esoteric doctrine relating to angelic beings” and a tendency to sun
                    worship, appear in Essenism, which he suggests might be called Gnostic Judaism.
                    The Essene side of Judaism was doubtless represented among the Jews who were
                    settled in, or journeyed to and from, various places in Asia Minor; and all
                    mystic and ascetic ideas would find a congenial soil in Phrygia. The teaching
                    and tendencies alluded to in the epistle to the Colossians, and subsequently in
                    the Pastoral Epistles, form the intermediate link between the “Gnostic Judaism”
                    of the Essenes and teachers allied to them and the “Judaizing Gnosticism” of the
                    2d century.</p>
                <p>The question whether Paul himself planted the church at Colossae is one of minor
                    importance, which has been much discussed by commentators. Lardner argues
                    elaborately in favour of a visit by Paul to Colossae and Laodicea. He bases his
                    view upon a passage cited from Tlιeodoret, in which ch. ii. I is interpreted so
                    as to distinguish between the Colossians and Laodiceans on the one side and the
                    “as many as had not seen Paul’s face” on the other. This view has been
                    controverted in detail by Davidson, but is advocated by Wordsworth. Bleek
                    mentions Schulz, Wiggers, and others as following Theodoret, but he takes the
                    contrary view himself, as do also Alford, Conybeare and Howson, and Lightfoot.
                    The last-named commentator says that Theodoret’s interpretation is “opposed
                    alike to grammatical and logical considerations.”</p>
                <p>Another disputable though not very important point is whether the Ephesian or the
                    Colossian letter was written first. Critics are &lt;Jivided, and it is somewhat
                    difficult to gather from a comparison of the epistles which view is most
                    probable. We are inclined to favour the view that the briefer, more
                    controversial, and in some respects more vigorous letter was written first, and
                    was followed by the fuller and more mystic one. It has been said that this
                    epistle is characterized by a “ruggedness of expression and want of finish that
                    borders on obscurity” (Lightfoot), and it has been suggested that the absence of
                    personal connection on St Paul’s part with the Colossian church might partially
                    account for “the diminished fluency of this letter,” as compared with other and
                    earlier ones. We do not think this explanation a satisfactory one. The
                    “ruggedness” should rather be attributed to the intensity of feeling wherewith
                    the apostle, confined as he was in his far-off place of imprisonment, threw
                    himself into the controversy with the false teachers,—persons whom he must have
                    regarded as among the “grievous wolves,” of whom he had forewarned the elders at
                    Miletus some few years previously (Acts XX. 29, 30), men who should “arise out
                    of the Christian community itself, and speak perverse things to draw men after
                    them.” This explanation is somewhat corroborated by what Alford points out,
                    viz., that the majority of peculiar expressions in the epistle occur in the
                    second chapter. And Professor Lightfoot himself adds— “No epistle of St Paul is
                    more vigorous in conception or more instinct with meaning. It is the very
                    compression of thoughts which creates the difficulty. If there is a want of
                    fluency there is no want of force. Feebleness is the last charge which can be
                    brought against this epistle.”</p>
                <p>The value of this epistle to the church historian, to the Christian theologian,
                    and to any one who wishes fairly to estimate the “philosophic” bearings of
                    Christian dogma is very great. A commentator of the 17th century, H. Suicer,
                    mentioned by Walch in his <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Theologica,</hi> calls the epistle to the Colossians <hi rend="italic"
                        >theologice</hi><hi rend="italic">Christiance compendium.</hi></p>
                <p>Authorities for what has been said, and references to further literature upon the
                    subject, may be found in “Introductions,” such as those by Davidson and Bleek,
                    and in “Prolegomena” of commentators, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> Alford,
                    Wordsworth, and Braune in Lange’s <hi rend="italic">Bibehcerk,</hi> a treasury
                    of information made accessible to English readers in Dr Schaff’s edition,
                    published by T. &amp; T. Clark. Frequent reference has been made in the course
                    of this article to the recent very valuable commentary of Professor Lightfoot.
                    In addition to the exegetical notes, he gives us thorough dissertations on “the
                    churches of the Lycus,” the “Colossian heresy,” and “the Essenes.” There is also
                    a digest <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n193/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0193-0166"/> of the principal various readings, containing
                    an ingenious conjecture as to the original reading in chap. ii. 18. Attention is
                    drawn to the fact that the epistles to the Ephesians and the Colossians, alone
                    among the Pauline epistles, are exposed to those “harmonizing tendencies” in
                    transcribers which have had such an influence on the text of the gospels.
                    Professor Lightfoot deals, also, in a most exhaustive manner, with the subject
                    of the apocryphal letter to the Laodiceans (connected with Col. iv. 16), which
                    appears in a considerable number of MSS. of the New Testament, and shows it to
                    be “a cento of Pauline phrases strung together without any definite connection
                    or any clear object.” Paley, in his <hi rend="italic">llorae Paulinae,</hi> has
                    a very satisfactory section on the similarity of the epistles to the Ephesians
                    and the Colossians. On the character of the heretical tendencies in Asia Minor
                    the general reader will find all requisite information in Neander, <hi
                        rend="italic">History of the Planting, &amp;c., of Christianity,</hi> and
                    Pressensé, <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Trois</hi><hi rend="italic">Premiers</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Siècles</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">TÉglise
                        Chrétienne.</hi> Mansel, in his <hi rend="italic">Gnostic Heresies,</hi> has
                    a chapter devoted to Notices of Gnosticism in the New Testament. Both Neander
                    and Pressensé draw attention to the arbitrary and unsound theorizing of the
                    Tübingen school in respect to the group to which the epistle to the Colossians
                    belongs, (w. s. s.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
