<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0620-0587-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CRIMINAL LAW</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 587</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:882984">Crime</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1156290">Trials</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2t79r">Digestion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n620/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CRIMINAL LAW</label>. A crime is an offence which the law
                    punishes directly, as distinguished from an offence which it punishes indirectly
                    by giving an action for damages to the person injured. The criminal or penal law
                    is that portion of the law which deals with crimes. Sometimes it is attempted to
                    distinguish crimes fom civil injuries by saying that the former are offences
                    against the state, the latter offences against individuals, or again by saying
                    that the former are prosecuted by the state, the latter by private persons. But
                    all illegal acts are offences against the state, and in England the state is
                    not, nominally at least, the prosecutor of criminal offences. Civil injuries, or
                    torts, as they are called in the law of England, are offences for which the
                    injured person may sue in a court of justice. Torts and crimes do not therefore
                    necessarily exclude each other, for the same act may be both a tort and a crime
                    in the sense that the injured person may sue for damages, and the offender may
                    likewise be prosecuted and punished. Further, it should be observed <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0621-0588"/> that many offences which are crimes in the sense
                    of being directly punishable, are, so far as the morality of the act is
                    concerned, far removed from the class of crimes. To allow your chimney to go on
                    fire is a crime in the sense that it is punishable by fine, but it is not a
                    crime in the sense of the preceding article, or in the ordinary acceptation of
                    the term.</p>
                <p>The law of England on the subject of crimes is, like the rest of the law,
                    composed of a large number of enactments, resting on a basis of common law. Its
                    leading definitions and distinctions are derived from the common law, modified
                    by judicial interpretation and by statute. A few of the general principles of
                    the criminal law of England will be stated here; for information as to the law
                    relating to specific crimes reference should be made to the respective
                    heads.</p>
                <p>The absence of systematic arrangement and of any precise definition of crimes is
                    due to the historical character of the criminal law. “It is founded,” says a
                    high authority, “on a set of loose definitions and descriptions of crimes, the
                    most important of which are as old as Bracton. Upon this foundation there was
                    built, principally in the course of the 18th century, an entire and irregular
                    superstructure of Acts of Parliament, the enactments of which were for the most
                    part intended to supply the deficiencies of the original system. These Acts have
                    been re-enacted twice over in the present generation—once between 1826 and 1832
                    and once in 1861; besides which they were all amended in 1837. Finally, every
                    part of the whole system has been made the subject of judicial comments and
                    constructions occasioned by particular cases, the great mass of which have
                    arisen within the last fifty years.” <hi rend="italic">(</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >View of the Criminal Law of England,</hi> by J. Fitzjames Stephen).</p>
                <p>A crime being defined as an action specifically forbidden under penalty of direct
                    punishment, it may be stated, without entering into a minute analysis, that to
                    render a person liable to punishment he must have a guilty intention, or, as it
                    is called in English law, malice. This malice will be inferred from the fact
                    that the forbidden action has been done; a man will be presumed to have intended
                    the natural consequences of his own acts. The inference, however, may be
                    rebutted by evidence showing that the criminal intention required to constitute
                    a crime was not as a matter of fact present. And there are certain conditions
                    from which the law will infer the impossibility of any such intention. A child
                    under seven is held to bθ incapable of committing a crime. If a married woman
                    commits an alleged crime in presence of her husband, she will be held to have
                    acted under his compulsion. The state of mind described as insanity, also
                    excludes the possibility of criminal intention.</p>
                <p>Crimes are divided into treasons, felonies, and misdemeanours. The first class
                    includes offences against the state, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> violence to
                    the person of the king, or resistance to the authority of the sovereign power.
                    The distinction between felonies and misdemeanours is not so easily drawn, and
                    is founded if anything on the nature of the punishment and not of the crime in
                    such case. In the definitions of crime in Bracton, misdemeanours appear as a
                    less serious class of crimes, after the graver crimes of treason, crimen falsi,
                    homicide, mayhem, arson, rape, and theft have been described. They are “minor or
                    lighter crimes, prosecuted civilly as in personal actions for injuries.” They
                    are regarded as of the nature of wrongs done to the sovereign power. In a trial
                    for felony the jury are required to make true deliverance between the queen and
                    the prisoner at the bar. In atrial for misdemeanour they are to try the issue
                    joined between the queen and the defendant. The principal common law
                    misdemeanours—libel conspiracy, and nuisance— have an obviously direct reference
                    to the public peace, and may without much violence be regarded as grievances to
                    the sovereign power itself. In Russell <hi rend="italic">On Crimes,</hi> a
                    misdemeanour is said to be the name generally applied to offences for which the
                    law has not provided a particular name. But so many crimes have been created
                    misdemeanours by statute which do not differ in character from felonies, that no
                    distinction founded on the nature of the crime can be drawn between them. Nor
                    can they be distinguished by the greater or less severity of the punishment, for
                    some misdemeanours are punished more severely than felonies. Besides, however,
                    the differences in the mode of trial noted above, felonies differed from
                    misdemeanours inasmuch as they involved a forfeiture of property—a distinction
                    which no longer exists, since forfeiture for felony was abolished by 33 and 34
                    Vict. c. 23. And in general there are greater facilities for arresting the
                    criminal in case of felony than in misdemeanours.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> Any one who has obtained a drove of oxen or
                    a flock of sheep by false pretences may go quietly on his way and no one, not
                    even a peace officer, can apprehend him without a warrant, but if a man offers
                    to sell another a bit of dead fence supposed to have been stolen, he not only
                    may but is required to be apprehended by that person (Greaves, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Criminal Law Consolidation Acts).</hi></p></note> It is unfortunate that a
                    distinction so fundamental should be so utterly vague. All the crimes known to
                    the law may be divided into felonies and misdemeanours, for treason is after all
                    a case of felony, but it is impossible to say what felony is or what a
                    misdemeanour is without an enumeration of the specific crimes which are ranked
                    under each bead. The Consolidation Acts form a classification of crimes which is
                    more easily understood, although it does not cover the whole of the criminal
                    law. Thus the Acts of 1861 (24 and 25 Vict. cc. 96, 97, 98, 99, and 100) relate
                    respectively to larceny, malicious injuries to real property, forgery, coinage,
                    and offences against the person.</p>
                <p>The definitions of particular crimes are still to be sought in the common law and
                    the decisions of the judges. The Consolidation Acts for the most part leave them
                    as they stood, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> the Larceny Act does not define the
                    crime of larceny. The consequence is that exact definitions are very difficult
                    to frame, and the technical view of a crime sometimes includes more, sometimes
                    less, than it ought. Thus the crime of murder, as settled by the existing law,
                    would include offences of such very different moral gravity as killing a man
                    deliberately for the sake of robbing him, and killing a man accidentally in an
                    attempt to rob him. On the other hand, offences which ought to have been
                    criminal were constantly set aside by the judges as not being within their
                    definition of the particular crimes alleged, and the legislature has constantly
                    had to interfere. In this way the penalties of larceny were gradually extended
                    to embezzlement, frauds by trustees, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Attempts to commit crimes are themselves crimes. It is laid down in Russell <hi
                    rend="italic">On Crimes</hi> (vol. i. p. 189) that “an attempt to commit a
                    felony is a misdemeanour, and an attempt to commit a misdemeanour is a
                    misdemeanour, whether the offence be so by common law or by statute.” An attempt
                    to murder was at common law no more than a misdemeanour punishable by two years’
                    imprisonment. This was the case until 1861; but now by the 24 and 25 Vict. c.
                    100 (Offences against the Person Act), any person attempting by the means
                    specified therein, or by any other means, to commit murder, is guilty of felony
                    and punishable by penal servitude for life or for any term not less than three
                    years, &amp;c., or to be imprisoned for not less than two years with or without
                    hard labour or solitary confinement.</p>
                <p>Persons accused of a crime may be either principals or accessories, and these are
                    further distinguished into principals of the first and second degree, and
                    accessories before <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0622-0589"/> and after the fact. Principals in the first
                    degree are those who <hi rend="italic">have actually and with their own hands
                    committed the fact.</hi> Principals in the second degree are those who were
                    present <hi rend="italic">aiding</hi> and <hi rend="italic">abetting</hi> at the
                    commission. An accessory before the fact is one who, being absent at the time of
                    the offence committed, doth yet procure, counsel, command, or abet another to
                    commit a .felony. And an accessory after the fact is one who, knowing a felony
                    to have been committed by another, receives, relieves, comforts, or assists the
                    felon. Participation in the commission of a felonious act in any of these ways
                    is a felony (Russell <hi rend="italic">On Crimes,</hi> vol i. p. 156). By the
                    Accessories and Abettors Act (24 and 25 Vict. c. 94) accessories before the fact
                    may be tried and punished as principals, and accessories after the fact may be
                    indicted as such or as substantive felons.</p>
                <p>Criminal procedure in England is distinguished by several special features, the
                    most remarkable of which is its close similarity to procedure in ordinary civil
                    cases. Crimes are left, like civil injuries or breaches of contract, to be
                    prosecuted by the persons injured, and the nature of the trial, the character of
                    the tribunal, and the rules of evidence are the same as in an ordinary
                    litigation at common law. Mr J. F. Stephen, in the excellent treatise already
                    quoted, aptly distinguishes the English system as “litigious” from the
                    “inquisitorial” system prevailing in France and other countries.</p>
                <p>Preliminary jurisdiction in criminal cases is possessed by the justices of the
                    peace, who may also under special Acts convict in a summary manner for offences
                    of minor importance. When the justices are satisfied that there is a <hi
                    rend="italic">prima</hi><hi rend="italic">facie</hi> case they commit the
                    prisoner for trial either at the quarter sessions or at the assizes. (See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Courts.)</hi> The following cases are not liable at quarter
                    sessions :— Misprision of treason; offences against the queen’s person,
                    prerogative, &amp;c., or against Parliament; offences subject to the penalties
                    of praemunire; blasphemy;. unlawful oaths (administering or taking); perjury and
                    false affirmation; setting fire to crops of grain, wood, heath, &amp;c.; bigamy;
                    abduction; concealment of birth; bankruptcy offences; blasphemous libels;
                    bribery; conspiracies for offences not triable at sessions; stealing records or
                    documents, &amp;c. A trial at quarter sessions or assizes begins by the
                    presentation of an indictment to the grand jury, who are selected for the
                    occasion, to the number of from twelve to twenty-three, from the gentlemen of
                    standing within the district for which the court is sitting. The judge delivers
                    a charge to the grand jury, shortly pointing out the nature of their duties, and
                    directing their attention to any peculiarities in the cases that are to come
                    before them. The grand jury discuss each case <hi rend="italic">seriatim,,</hi>
                    and hear witnesses in private (in general only those for the prosecution), and
                    if they are satisfied that there is a <hi rend="italic">prima</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">facie</hi> case against the prisoner they return a true bill, and
                    the case goes to trial before the judge and a common jury. If the grand jury do
                    not return a true bill, the case is at an end, unless there has been a verdict
                    on a coroner’s inquisition, or unless it is a case which may be proceeded on by
                    way of information. A criminal trial in open court now differs in very few
                    points from any ordinary civil cause. For a long time prisoners were not allowed
                    to have the benefit of professional advocacy except in cases of high treason,
                    and the privilege was not conceded until the Prisoners’ Counsel Act of 1836. Sir
                    J. Stephen fixes at the same date the entire exemption of prisoners from
                    interrogation,—a practice which would appear to be connected, in legal reason,
                    with the rule which made a party to a cause an incompetent witness. In this
                    respect the contrast between a criminal trial in England and a criminal trial in
                    France is very striking. The constant interrogation and browbeating of the
                    prisoner by the judge, consistent as it may be with the inquisitorial theory of
                    their procedure, is always revolting to Englishmen, accustomed to see in every
                    criminal trial a fair fight between the prisoner and the prosecution.
                    Confessions, which are the object of many proceedings in a French inquisition,
                    are regarded with suspicion by the English law. During the spring assizes of
                    1877 a prisoner was charged with having committed a murder twenty years ago, and
                    the counsel for the prosecution, with the consent of the judge, withdrew from
                    the case because the only evidence, besides the prisoner’s own confession, was
                    that of persons who either had never known him personally or could not identify
                    him.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> “No confession
                    made by the prisoner is admissible which is made in consequence of any
                    inducement of a temporal nature, having reference to the charge against the
                    prisoner, held out by a person in authority” (Roscoe’s <hi rend="italic">Digest
                    of Criminal Evidence).</hi> Notwithstanding the general bearing of the law
                    against confessions, it is held that a confession obtained by artifice or by
                    spiritual solicitation may be used in evidence.</p></note> Although a prisoner
                    may have counsel to defend him if he can afford to pay the customary fee, no
                    provision is made by law for his being so represented. But the custom of the
                    courts has imposed upon judges exceptional care for the prisoner’s interests,
                    and on the prosecuting counsel exceptional forbearance when the prisoner is
                    undefended. It was often said before the Prisoners’ Counsel Act (and it is still
                    true) that the judge is the prisoner’s counsel. In exceptional circumstances the
                    judge will call on some member of the bar to undertake the prisoner’s
                    defence.</p>
                <p>As there is no provision made by law for the prisoner's defence, so there is no
                    public prosecutor. The absence of such an officer has long been an admitted
                    defect in the English system, but no successful attempt has yet been made to
                    deal with it. It is generally agreed that an official staff of prosecuting
                    counsel would not be desirable. But there certainly ought to be some public
                    officer charged with the preparation, if not of all criminal cases, at least of
                    those which the injured person does not wish to conduct himself. At present a
                    private person is bound over by the magistrates to prosecute at his own expense,
                    and the consequence often is that many persons will forego an injury rather than
                    submit to the trouble and risk of a prosecution. The prosecutor can recover bis
                    costs frem the county, unless they are disallowed by the judge. The county again
                    is entitled to be recouped by the Treasury, and between these two bodies there
                    has been a standing feud on the subject of criminal costs for some years.</p>
                <p>Properly speaking there is no appeal in criminal trials. The verdict of the jury
                    is final. Any substantial defect or informality in the procedure may be taken
                    before the Queen’s Bench by writ of error, but such cases are not now of
                    frequent occurrence. And if any question of law arises at the trial, the judge
                    may reserve it for the opinion of the court for the consideration of crown cases
                    reserved, by whom the conviction may be either quashed or confirmed.</p>
                <p>Punishments under the common law were excessively severe, but their operation was
                    mitigated by the singular privilege of <hi rend="smallcaps">Benefit of
                    Clergy</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.vſt.</hi> Blackstone laments that “among the
                    variety of actions which men are daily liable to commit, no less than 160 have
                    been declared by Act of Parliament to be felonies without benefit of clergy, or,
                    in other words, to be worthy of instant death.” The more atrocious punishments
                    have disappeared from the law, and the penalty of death is now practically
                    restricted to murder. Fine, imprisonment with or without hard labour and with or
                    without solitary confinement, and penal servitude,<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> ' <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> By 16 and
                    17 Vict. c. 99, all sentences of transportation were converted into penal
                    servitude.</p></note> are the most usual punishments, and a wide discretion is
                    left to the judges.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n623/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0623-0590"/>
                <p>By the Penal Servitude Act, 1864, the shortest period of penal servitude foi an
                    offence committed after the passing of the Act is five years, and where any
                    previous Act had fixed a maximum of less than five years, the period of five
                    years is to be substituted for such shorter term. The same Act gives the form of
                    licence under which a convict may be allowed to be at large during the remaining
                    portion of his time, subject to the condition of abstaining from crime and from
                    association with criminal characters, &amp;c., and of preserving and producing
                    his licence when called upon by a magistrate or officer. By the Prevention of
                    Crimes Act, 1871, every holder of a licence under the Penal Servitude Acts must
                    notify his residence and any change of residence to the police (section 6). The
                    Prevention of Crimes Act, 1871, likewise repeals the Habitual Criminals Act of
                    1869, and substitutes new provisions, of which the following are the most
                    important. Section 5 provides for the registering and photographing of
                    criminals.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> A Register
                    of Habitual Criminals in England and Wales for the years 1869-76 has recently
                    been printed in the printing works of Her Majesty’s prison, Brixton. “The list,”
                    says the <hi rend="italic">Times</hi> of March 7, 1877, “has been framed by
                    separating from the great mass of returns those which refer to persons who have
                    been convicted on indictment of a crime, and thereupon have had a previous
                    conviction proved against them. It is thus a complete register of habitual and
                    professional criminals, and has been printed for circulation among the police
                    and the authorities of prisons, in order to enable them to identify persons who
                    come under their charge.” The proportion of habitual criminals born in different
                    localities gives some curious results. Thus the town of Stafford heads the list
                    with 1 ’ 881 to every 1000, followed closely by Worcester, Taunton, and
                    Lancaster, all of them towns with under 20,000 inhabitants. On the other hand,
                    London, which produces the largest number (1503), stands at the rate of only
                    ‘461 to the 1000. Of the habitual criminals on the list 1082 come from Ireland,
                    and 158 from Scotland.</p></note> Section 7 specifies circumstances under which
                    a person who has been <hi rend="italic">twice</hi> convicted on indictment may,
                    within seven years of the expiration of the last of the two sentences, subject
                    himself to imprisonment with or without hard labour for a term not exceeding one
                    year,— <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> if it appears to a magistrate that “there
                    are reasonable grounds for believing that he is getting his livelihood by
                    dishonest means;” or if he refuses to give his name and address when charged
                    with an offence before the magistrates; or if he is found in any place public or
                    private under circumstances which satisfy the court that he was about to commit,
                    or waiting for an opportunity to commit, an offence; or if he is found in a
                    dwelling-house, &amp;c., without being able to give a satisfactory account of
                    his presence. By section 8, “where any person is convicted on indictment of a
                    crime, and a previous conviction of a crime is proved against him, the court
                    having cognizance of such indictment may, in addition to any other punishment
                    which it may award to him, direct that he is to be subject to the supervision of
                    the policefor a period of seven years, or such less period as the court may
                    direct, commencing immediately on the expiration of the sentence passed on him
                    for the last of such crimes.” Persons subject to police supervision, like
                    convicts out on ticket-of-leave, must notify their residence to the police, and
                    males must report themselves once a month. The Larceny Act of 1861 had made a
                    previous conviction for felony or indictable misdemeanour, or two summary
                    convictions, matter of aggravation on a charge of simple larceny; and section
                    116 of that Act provides for the trial of the quesion whether there has been
                    such a previous conviction. It is only after the prisoner has been found guilty
                    of the subsequent offence that the question whether he has been previously
                    convicted can bo gone into, unless he offers evidence of good character in the
                    trial for the offence, in which case the prosecutor may prove the previous
                    conviction. This section is adopted in the Prevention of Crimes Act, 1871.</p>
                <p>The prerogative of pardon, as exercised by the Home</p>
                <p>Secretary, occasionally has the effect of a rehearing of the case, <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> when new evidence is discovered after the trial, or the
                    verdict of the jury gives dissatisfaction to the public. In such cases the Home
                    Secretary, after consultation with the judge, or if necessary with such skilled
                    persons as he may select, decides on his own responsibility to grant or withhold
                    a pardon.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> A good
                    example will be found in the case of Smethurst, reported at length in Stephen’s
                    <hi rend="italic">View of the Criminal Law.</hi></p></note> This is not perhaps
                    the most satisfactory way of reviewing the sentence of a criminal court.</p>
                <p>The distinguishing feature of Scotch criminal law is the existence of a public
                    prosecutor. At common law persons injured have the right to prosecute, but
                    “private prosecution, except in the most trifling summary complaints, is now
                    wholly unknown in practice” (Macdonald’s <hi rend="italic">Criminal Law of
                    Scotland).</hi> The lord advocate and his deputies are the public prosecutors in
                    the Supreme Court; in the inferior courts the procurator-fiscal prosecutes. The
                    public prosecutor cannot be compelled to prosecute, nor can he be prevented from
                    prosecuting. <hi rend="smallcaps">(e. r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
