<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0431-0402-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CORK</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 402</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:878973">Cork</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:799938">Africans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:827573">Bark</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96096v">Bark</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55q5x">Liquids</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n431/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CORK</label> (perhaps from <hi rend="italic">cortex,</hi>
                    bark) is the outer layer of the bark of an evergreen species of oak <hi
                    rend="italic">{Quercus</hi><hi rend="italic">Suber).</hi> The tree reaches the
                    height of about 30 feet, growing in the south of Europe and on the North African
                    coasts generally; but it is principally cultivated in Spain and Portugal. The
                    outer layer of bark in the cork oak by annual additions from within gradually
                    becomes a thick soft homogeneous mass, possessing those compressible and elastic
                    properties upon which the economic value of the material chiefly depends. The
                    first stripping of cork from young trees takes place when they are from fifteen
                    to twenty years of age. The yield, which is rough, unequal, and woody in texture
                    is called virgin cork, and is useful only as a tanning substance, or for forming
                    rustic work in ferneries, conservatories, &amp;c. Subsequently the bark is
                    removed every eight or ten years, the quality of the cork improving with each
                    successive stripping; and the 'trees continue to live and thrive under the
                    operation for 150 years and upwards. The produce of the second barking is still
                    so coarse in texture that it is only fit for making floats for nets and for
                    similar applications. The operation of stripping the trees takes place during
                    the months of July and August. Two cuts are made round the stem,—one a little
                    above the ground, and the other immediately under the spring of the main
                    branches. Between these three or four longitudinal incisions are then made, the
                    utmost care being taken not to injure the inner bark. The cork is thereafter
                    removed in the sections into which it has been cut, by inserting under it the
                    wedge-shaped handle of the implement used in making the incisions. After the
                    outer surface has been scraped and cleaned, the pieces are flattened by heating
                    them over a fire and submitting them to pressure on a flat surface. In the
                    heating operation the surface is charred, and thereby the pores are closed up,
                    and what is termed “nerve” is given to the material. In this state the cork is
                    ready for manufacture or exportation.</p>
                <p>Cork possesses a combination of properties which peculiarly fits it for many and
                    diverse uses, for some of which it alone is found applicable. The leading
                    purpose for which it is used is for forming bungs and stoppers for bottles and
                    other vessels containing liquids. Its compressibility, elasticity, and practical
                    imperviousness to both air and water so fit it for this purpose that the term
                    cork is even more applied to the function than to the substance. Its specific
                    lightness, combined with strength and durability, recommend it above all other
                    substances for forming lifebuoys, belts, and jackets, and in the construction of
                    lifeboats and other apparatus for saving from drowning. On account of its
                    lightness, softness, and non-conducting properties it is used for hat-linings
                    and the soles of shoes, the latter being a very ancient application of cork. It
                    is also used in making artificial limbs, for lining entomological cases, for
                    pommels in leather-dressing, and as a medium for making architectural models.
                    Chips and cuttings are ground up and mixed with india-rubber to form kamptulicon
                    floor-cloth, a preparation now, however, almost superseded by linoleum, which
                    consists chiefly of a mixture of boiled linseed oil and ground cork applied over
                    a canvas backing. The inner bark of the cork-tree is a valuable tanning
                    material.</p>
                <p>Certain of the properties and uses of cork were known to the ancient Greeks and
                    Romans, and the latter, we find by Horace <hi rend="italic">{Odes,</hi> iii. 8),
                    used it as a stopper for winevessels :—</p>
                <p>“Corticem adstrictum pice dimovebit Amphorae ”—</p>
                <p>It appears, however, that cork was not generally used for stopping bottles till
                    so recent a period as near the end of the 17th century, and bottles themselves
                    were not employed for storing liquids till the 15th century. Many substitutes
                    have been proposed for cork as a stoppering agent; but except in the case of
                    aerated liquids none of these has recommended itself in practice. For aerated
                    water bottles several successful devices have recently been introduced. The most
                    simple of these is an Indian-rubber ball pressed upwards into the narrow of the
                    bottle neck by the force of the gas contained in the water; and in another
                    system a glass ball is similarly pressed against an Indian-rubber collar
                    inserted in the neck of the bottle.</p>
                <p>The cutting of corks by machinery has been found to be a matter of much
                    difficulty, owing to the liability of the cutting edges becoming blunt, and the
                    necessity of keeping them very sharp. Many machines have been proposed, but the
                    work is still almost entirely done by hand labour. Messrs Crawlιall &amp;
                    Campbell of Glasgow have recently introduced a machine which appears to be at
                    once simple, expeditious, and efficient. The apparatus cuts corks and bungs of
                    any diameter up to 3⅛ inches, either parallel or tapered, and an expert workman
                    can turn off about 6 gross of corks per hour.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
