<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0116-0097-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">COCHINEAL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 97</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:974074">Insects</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1110447">Seasons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1132220">Steam</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1012448">Matter</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198491">Essay</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w950r2g">Dyeing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qh88">Insects</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96094w">Seasons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b46t0gw81">Belief</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n116/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COCHINEAL</label>, a dye-stuff used for the production of
                    scarlet, crimson, orange, and other tints, and for the preparation of lake and
                    carmine. It consists of the females of <hi rend="italic">Coccus cacti,</hi>.an
                    insect of the order <hi rend="italic">Hemiptera,</hi> which feeds upon various
                    species of the <hi rend="italic">Cactaceae,</hi> more especially the nopal
                    plant, <hi rend="italic">Opuntia</hi><hi rend="italic">coccinellifera,</hi> a
                    native of Mexico and Peru. The dye was introduced into Europe from Mexico, where
                    it had been in use long before the entrance of the Spaniards in the year 1518,
                    and where it formed one of the staple tributes to the Crown for certain
                    districts, In 1523 Cortes received instructions from the Spanish court to
                    procure it in as large quantities as possible. It appears not to have been known
                    in Italy so late as the year 1548, though the art of dyeing then flourished
                    there. Cornelius van Drebbel, at Alkmaár, first employed cochineal for the
                    production of scarlet in 1650. Until about 1725 the belief was very prevalent
                    that cochineal was the seed of a plant, but Dr Lister in 1672 conjectured it to
                    be a kind of kermes, and in 1703 Leeuwenhoeck ascertained its true nature by aid
                    of the microscope. Since its introduction cochineal has supplanted kermes <hi
                    rend="italic">(Coccus</hi><hi rend="italic">ilicis)</hi> over the greater part
                    of Europe. The male of the cochineal insect is half the size of the female, and,
                    unlike it, is devoid of nutritive apparatus; it has long white wings, and a body
                    of a deep red colour, terminated by two diverging setae. The female is apterous,
                    and has a dark-brown plano-convex body; it is found in the proportion of 150 to
                    200 to one of the male insect. The dead body of the mother insect serves as a
                    protection for the eggs until they are hatched. Cochineal is now furnished not
                    only by Mexico and Peru, but also by Algiers and the S. of Spain. In Teneriffe
                    it was successfully cultivated in 1858, on the failure of the vines there
                    through disease, but the diminished value of cochineal of late years has much
                    affected its production in the Canaries Cochineal is collected thrice in the
                    seven months of the season. The insects are carefully brushed from the branches
                    of the cactus into bags, and are then killed by immersion in hot water, or by
                    exposure to the sun, steam, or the heat of an oven—much of the variety of
                    appearance in the commercial article being caused by the mode of treatment. The
                    dried insect has the form of irregular, fluted, and concave grains, -which weigh
                    about <hi rend="subscript"> 1</hi> ⅛ of a grain, as many as 70,000 insects being
                    estimated to weigh 1 It. Cochineal has a musty and bitterish taste There are two
                    principal varieties—silver cochineal, which has a greyish-red colour, and the
                    furrows of the body covered with a white bloom or fine down, and black
                    cochineal, which is of a dark reddish-brown, and destitute of bloom. Granilla is
                    an inferior kind, gathered from uncultivated plants. The best crop is the first
                    of the season, which consists of the unimpregnated females; the later crops
                    contain an admixture of young insects and skins, which contain proportionally
                    little colouring matter.</p>
                <p>Cochineal owes its tinctorial power to the presence of a substance termed <hi
                    rend="italic">cochinealin, or carminic acid,</hi> a compound of hydrogen,
                    carbon, and oxygen, which may be prepared from the aqueous decoction of
                    cochineal. The comparative value of different specimens of cochineal may be
                    ascertained by a method based upon the bleaching action of ferricyanide of
                    potassium upon a weak potash solution of the dye. The black variety of cochineal
                    is sometimes sold for silver cochineal by shaking it with powdered talc, or
                    heavy-spar: but these adulterations can be readily detected by means of a lens.
                    The duty on cochineal was <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n117/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0117-0098"/> repealed in 1845. In 1869 the exports of
                    cochineal from the Canaries reached 6,310,000 ft&gt;, value £842,921. Of this
                    amount 4,232,600 ft, consisting of <hi rend="italic">grana, granilla,</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">polro,</hi> were shipped to Great Britain, value £554,092.
                    More than half of this quantity was supplied by the Island of Grand Canary. In
                    three months ending 31st March 1876 the imports were 10,094 cwts, value
                    £112,534.</p>
                <p>For a monograph of the <hi rend="italic">Coccidae,</hi> including the cochineal
                    insect, see Signoret, <hi rend="italic">Ann. Soc. Ent. France,</hi> 1868-74. For
                    accounts of the cochineal insect consult also—Theis, <hi rend="italic"
                    >ibid.,</hi><hi rend="italic">^v.</hi> p. 1; Buπneisteι, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Handbuch der Entomologie</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Vincent, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ann.</hi><hi rend="italic">Sci.</hi><hi rend="italic">Nat.,</hi>
                    vol. viii., 1st <hi rend="italic">ger.;</hi> Westwood, <hi rend="italic">Modern
                    Classification of Bisects,</hi> pp. 448, 449. For a description of the
                    cultivation of cochineal in Java, see <hi rend="italic">Veth's Woordenboek van
                    Nederlandsch Indie—</hi><hi rend="italic">Cochenille.</hi> See also
                    “Observations on the Making of Cochineal in Jamaica,” in <hi rend="italic">Phil.
                    Tran.,</hi> 1691, pp. 502-3; and Royle’s <hi rend="italic">Essay on the
                    Productive Resources of India,</hi> pp. 47-65, 1840.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
