<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0270-0243-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CONCUBINAGE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 243</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bd98">Menus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vd88">Contractions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:964412">Husbands</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1076268">Priests</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1120522">Slaves</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:876969">Contracts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1016875">Menus</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204236">Israel</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210572">Iceland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n270/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CONCUBINAGE</label>, the state of a man and woman cohabiting
                    as married persons without the sanction of a legal marriage. In a scriptural
                    sense, it denotes cohabiting lawfully with a wife of second rank, who enjoyed no
                    other conjugal right but that of cohabitation, and whom the husband could
                    repudiate and dismiss with a small present (Gen. xxi.) In like manner he could,
                    by means of presents, exclude his children by her from the heritage (Gen. xxv.)
                    To judge from the conjugal histories of Abraham and Jacob, the immediate cause
                    of concubinage was the barrenness of the lawful wife, who in that case
                    introduced her maid-servant <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n271/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0271-0244"/> to her husband, for the sake of having children.
                    There was a singular practice authorized not only in Israel (Deut, χxv.), and
                    anciently in Athens and Sparta, but by the laws of Menu, that a brother should
                    raise up the name of the dead upon his inheritance,—obviously a relic of
                    polyandry. In process of time, however, concubinage appears to have degenerated
                    into a regular custom among the Jews; and the institutions of Moses were
                    directed to prevent excess and abuse in that respect.</p>
                <p>The Roman <hi rend="italic">concubinatus</hi> differed from <hi rend="italic"
                    >justae nuptiae</hi> in not giving the father the <hi rend="italic"
                    >potestas</hi> over his children, and from <hi rend="italic">contubernium,</hi>
                    which was the concubinage of slaves. It was a permanent monogamous relation,
                    free from some of the restrictions imposed by the civil law upon marriages.
                    Although the married woman had a more dignified position, concubinage was
                    thought the appropriate union for persons of different ranks, as a <hi
                    rend="italic">patronus</hi> and. <hi rend="italic">liberta.</hi> By imperial
                    legislation, <hi rend="italic">naturales liberi</hi> and concubines were
                    gradually admitted to limited rights of succession; and the legitimation <hi
                    rend="italic">per subsequens</hi><hi rend="italic">matrimonium</hi> completed
                    their status.</p>
                <p>Concubinage is also used to signify a marriage with a woman of inferior
                    condition, to whom the husband does not convey his rank. Such concubinage was
                    beneath marriage both as to dignity and civil rights, yet concubine was a
                    reputable title, and very different from that of “mistress” among us. The
                    concubine also might be accused of adultery in the same manner as a wife. By
                    French law the presence of a concubine in the house entitles the wife to a
                    divorce. This kind of concubinage is still in use in some countries,
                    particularly in Germany, under the title of <hi rend="italic">halb-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ehe</hi> (half-marriage), or left-hand marriage, in allusion to
                    the manner of its being contracted, namely, by the man giving the woman his left
                    hand instead of the right. This is a real marriage, though without the usual
                    solemnity; and the parties are both bound to each other for ever, though the
                    female cannot bear the husband’s name and title. Neither spouse has any right of
                    succession to the other, but the children take a third of the father’s estate,
                    if he leaves no lawful children.</p>
                <p>Du Cange observes that one may gather from several passages in the epistles of
                    the popes that they anciently allowed of such connections. The seventeenth canon
                    of the first Council of Toledo (400 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi> declares
                    that he who with a faithful wife keeps a concubine is excommunicated; but that
                    if the concubine serve him as a wife, so that he has only one woman, under the
                    title of concubine, he shall not be rejected from communion. This applied not
                    only to laymen, but to inferior priests, who were then allowed to marry. The
                    latter councils extend the name concubine to disreputable women not kept in the
                    house. That is also the meaning of the word in the 8th rubric of the concordat
                    of 1517 between Leo X. and Francis I. The Council of Nicaea refers to a class of
                    secret concubines, <hi rend="italic">superinductae,</hi> and St Augustine
                    denounces all irregular relations.</p>
                <p>It is certain the patriarchs had a great number of wives, and that these did not
                    all hold the same rank,—some being inferior to the principal wife. Solomon had
                    700 wives and 300 concubines. Q. Curtius observes that Darius was followed in
                    his army by 365 concubines, all in the equipage of queens.</p>
                <p>In most Mahometan and other polygamous countries, female slaves are used as
                    concubines and enjoy a certain status. Under the ancient <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fueros,</hi> which succeeded the <hi rend="italic">Lex</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Visigotharum</hi> in Spain, concubinage was recognized by the name of <hi
                    rend="italic">barragania.</hi> The parties entered into a contract <hi
                    rend="italic">(carta de mancebia e campanera),</hi> by which the man took the
                    concubine <hi rend="italic">por todos</hi><hi rend="italic">los</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">dios</hi><hi rend="italic">que</hi><hi rend="italic">yo</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">viae quiere,</hi> and she received right to bread, table, and
                    knife <hi rend="italic">(a pan, mesa, e cuchaelld).</hi> Apart from contract,
                    some <hi rend="italic">Fueros</hi> gave the faithful concubine a right of
                    succession to one-half of the man’s acquired property. The Council of Valladolid
                    (1228) reproved the <hi rend="italic">barragania</hi> of priests. Similarly the
                    <hi rend="italic">Gragaae,</hi> or ancient law of Iceland, recognized the <hi
                    rend="italic">frilla,</hi> or concubine, alongside of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >husfreyia,</hi> or lawful wife, though the two were not permitted to dwell in
                    the same house. According to the Danish <hi rend="italic">hand vesten,</hi> the
                    concubine who had publicly lived with a man and partaken his meals for three
                    winters became a lawful wife. The Celtic handfast marriage may also be referred
                    to. (w. c. s.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
