<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0173-0148-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">COLLINS, William</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 148</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b46688q84">Odes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2td33">Goldsmithing</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1043867">Odes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1174597">White</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n173/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COLLINS, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>
                    (1721-1759), who divides with Gray the glory of being the greatest English
                    lyrist of the 18th century, was born on the 25th of December, 1721, at
                    Chichester, of which city his father, a rich hatter, was the mayor. After some
                    childish studies in his native town, he was sent, in January 1733, to Winchester
                    College, where Whitehead and Joseph Warton were his schoolfellows. When he had
                    been nine months at the school, Pope paid Winchester a visit and proposed a
                    subject for a prize poem; it is legitimate matter or fancy to suppose that the
                    lofty forehead, the brisk dark eyes, and gracious oval of the childish face, as
                    we know it in the only portrait existing of Collins, did not escape the great
                    man’s notice, then not a little occupied with the composition of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Essay on Man.</hi> In 1734 it is supposed that the young poet
                    published his first verses, on <hi rend="italic">The Royal Nuptials,</hi> of
                    which, however, no copy has come down to us; another poem, probably satiric,
                    called <hi rend="italic">The Battle of the Schoolbooks,</hi> was written about
                    this time, and has also been lost. Fired by his poetic fellows to further feats
                    in verse, Collins produced, in his seventeenth year, those <hi rend="italic"
                    >Persian Eclogues</hi> which were the only writings of his that were valued by
                    the world during his own lifetime. They were not printed for some years, and
                    meanwhile Collins sent, in January and October 1739, some verses to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Gentleman's Magazine,</hi> which attracted the notice and
                    admiration of Johnson, then still young and uninfluential. In March 1740 he was
                    admitted a commoner of Queen’s College, Oxford, but did not go up to Oxford
                    until July 174.1, when he entered Magdalen College. At Oxford he continued his
                    affectionate intimacy with the Wartons, and gained the friendship of Gilbert
                    White. Early in 1742 the <hi rend="italic">Persian Eclogues</hi> appeared in
                    London. They were four in number, and formed a modest pamphlet of not more than
                    300 lines in all. Those pieces may be compared with Victor Hugo’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Les</hi><hi rend="italic">Orientales,</hi> to which, of course,
                    they are greatly inferior. Considered with regard to the time at which they were
                    produced, they are more than meritorious, even brilliant, and one at least —the
                    second—can be read with enjoyment at the present day. The rest, perhaps, will be
                    found somewhat artificial and effete. In November 1743 Collins was made bachelor
                    of arts, and a few days after taking his degree published his second work, an
                    <hi rend="italic">Epistle to Sir Thomas Hanmer.</hi> This poem, written in
                    heroic couplets, shows a great advance in individuality, and resembles, in its
                    habit of impersonifying qualities of the mind, the riper lyrics of its author.
                    For the rest, it is an enthusiastic review of poetry, culminating in a laudation
                    of Shakespeare. It is supposed that he left Oxford abruptly in the summer of
                    1744 to attend his mothers death-bed, and did not return. His indolence, which
                    had been no less marked at the university than his genius, combined with a fatal
                    irresolution to make it extremely difficult to choose for him à path in life.
                    The army and the church were successively suggested and rejected; and he finally
                    arrived in London, bent on enjoying a small property as an independent man about
                    town. He made the acquaintance of Johnson and others, and was urged by those
                    friends to undertake various important writings—a <hi rend="italic">History of
                    the Revival of Learning,</hi> several tragedies, and a version of Aristotle’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Poetics,</hi> among others —all of which he commenced ar&lt;l
                    lacked force of will to continue. He soon squandered his means, plunged, with
                    most disastrous effects, into profligate excesses, and sowed the seed of his
                    untimely misfortune. It was at this time, however, that he composed his
                    matchless odes, which appeared on the 20th of December 1746, dated 1747.</p>
                <p>The original project was to have combined them with the odes of Joseph Warton,
                    but the latter, now forgotten, proved at that time to be the more marketable
                    article. Collins’s little volume fell dead from the press, but it won him the
                    admiration and friendship of Thomson, with whom, until the death of the latter
                    in 1748, he lived on terms of affectionate intimacy. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Odes,</hi> in the volume of that name, were twelve in number; to their contents
                    we shall presently return. In 1749 Collins was raised beyond the fear of poverty
                    by the death of his uncle; and he left London to settle in his native city. He
                    had hardly begun to taste the sweets of a life devoted to literature and quiet,
                    before the weakness of his will began to develop in the direction of insanity,
                    and he hurried abroad to attempt to dispel the gathering gloom by travel. In the
                    interval he had published two short pieces of consummate grace and beauty—the
                    <hi rend="italic">Elegy on Thomson,</hi> in 1749, and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dirge in Cymbeline,</hi> later in the same year. In the beginning of 1750 he
                    composed the <hi rend="italic">Ode on the Popular Superstitions of the
                    Highlands,</hi> which was dedicated to the author of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Douglas,</hi> and not printed till long after the death of Collins, and an <hi
                    rend="italic">Ode on the Music of the Grecian Theatre,</hi> which no longer
                    exists, and in which our literature probably has sustained a severe loss. With
                    this poem his literary career closes, although he lingered in great misery for
                    nearly nine years. From Gilbert White we learn that his madness was occasionally
                    violent, and that he was confined for a time in an asylum at Oxford. But for the
                    most part he resided at Chichester, suffering from extreme debility of body when
                    the mind was clear, and incapable of any regular occupation. Music affected him
                    in a singular manner, and it is recorded that he was wont to slip out into the
                    cathedral cloisters during the services, and moan and howl in horrible
                    accordance with the choir. In this miserable condition he passed out of sight of
                    all his friends, and in 1756 it was supposed, even by Johnson, that he was dead;
                    in point of fact, however, his sufferings did not cease until the 12th of June
                    1759. No journal or magazine recorded the death of the forgotten poet, though
                    Goldsmith, only two months before, had commenced the laudation which was soon to
                    become universal.</p>
                <p>No English poet so great as Collins has left behind him so small a bulk of
                    writings. Not more than 1500 lines of his have been handed down to us, but among
                    these not one is slovenly, and few are poor. His odes are the most sculpturesque
                    and faultless in the language. They lack fire, but in charm and precision of
                    diction, exquisite propriety of form, and lofty poetic suggestion they stand
                    unrivalled. That one named <hi rend="italic">The Passions</hi> is the most
                    popular; that <hi rend="italic">To Evening</hi> is the greatest favourite with
                    imaginative persons. In reading this, and the <hi rend="italic">Ode to
                    Simplicity,</hi> one seems to be handling an antique vase of matchless delicacy
                    and elegance. Distinction may be said to be the crowning grace of the style of
                    Collins; its leading peculiarity is the incessant impersonification of some
                    quality of the character. In the <hi rend="italic">Ode on Popular
                    Superstitions</hi> he produced a still nobler work; this poem, the most
                    considerable in size which has been preserved, contains passages which are
                    beyond question unrivalled for rich melancholy fulness in our literature between
                    Milton and Keats. The life of Collins was written by Dr Johnson, he found an
                    enthusiastic admirer in Dr Langhorne; and more recently a kindly biographer in
                    Mr Moy Thomas. <hi rend="smallcaps">(e. w. g.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
