<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0165-0140-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">COLIC</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 140</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4086373f">Colic</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kb2c">Lead</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz9r">Pain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v97zt6b">Poisoners</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0636c">Matter</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1431877">Bakers</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:867057">Colic</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:994553">Lead</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1055033">Patients</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1050382">Pain</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1012448">Matter</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n165/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COLIC</label> (from <hi rend="italic">κωλov,</hi> the large
                    intestine). By this term is generally understood an attack of pain in the
                    abdomen, usually seated in the neighbourhood of the navel, of spasmodic
                    character, and attended for the most part with constipation of the bowels.
                    Various forms of this complaint are described by medical writers. The most
                    important are simple or flatulent colic and lead colic. The former of these
                    commonly arises from the presence in the alimentary canal of some indigestible
                    matter, which not only excites spasmodic contraction of the muscular coats of
                    the intestines, but also, by beginning to undergo decomposition, gives rise to
                    the presence of gases, which painfully distend the bowels and increase the
                    patient’s suffering. The pain of colic is relieved by pressure over the abdomen,
                    and there is no attendant fever—points which are of importance in distinguishing
                    it from inflammation.</p>
                <p>Attacks of this form of colic may occur in connection with a variety of causes
                    other than that above mentioned, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> from accumulations
                    of feculent matter in the intestines in the case of those who suffer from
                    habitual constipation; also as an accompaniment of nervous and hysterical
                    ailments, and not unfrequently as the result of exposure to cold and damp,
                    particularly where the feet become chilled as in walking through snow. Similar
                    attacks of colic are apt to occur in young infants, especially those who are fed
                    artificially; and in such cases it will generally be found that the food is
                    passing through them almost wholly undigested, and that a temporary change of
                    diet will be necessary. The duration of an attack of simple colic is seldom
                    long, and in general no ill consequences follow from it. It is, however, not
                    free from risk, especially that of sudden obstruction of the bowel from
                    twisting, or invagination of one part within another (intussusception) during
                    the spasmodic seizure, giving rise to the terrible disease known as ileus.</p>
                <p>Of greater importance and interest in a medical point of view is the disease
                    known as lead colic <hi rend="italic">(Syn.</hi> painters’ colic, <hi
                    rend="italic">colica Pictonum,</hi> Devonshire colic, dry belly-ache), from its
                    having been clearly ascertained to be due to the absorption of lead into the
                    system. This disease had been observed and described long before its cause was
                    discovered. Its occurrence in an epidemic form among the inhabitants of Poitou
                    was recorded by Francis Citois, in 1617, under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Novus et popularis apud Pictones dolor colicus biliosus.</hi> The disease was
                    thereafter termed <hi rend="italic">colica Pictonum.</hi> It was supposed to be
                    due to the acidity of the native wines, but it was afterwards found to depend on
                    lead contained in them. A similar epidemic broke out in certain parts of Germany
                    in the end of the 17th century, and was at the time believed by various
                    physicians to be caused by the admixture of acid wines with litharge to sweeten
                    them.</p>
                <p>About the middle of last century this disease, which had long been known to
                    prevail in Devonshire, was carefully investigated by Sir George Baker, who
                    succeeded in tracing it unmistakably to the contamination of the native
                    beverage, cider, with lead, either accidentally from the lead-work of the vats
                    and other apparatus for preparing the liquor, or from its being sweetened with
                    litharge.</p>
                <p>It has subsequently been made out that this complaint is apt to affect all
                    persons who work among lead or its preparations, especially lead-miners,
                    manufacturers of white lead, colour-grinders, and painters, also to a less
                    extent plumbers, potters, type-founders, &amp;c. It is said to have occurred in
                    persons who have slept for only a few nights in a newly-painted room. It has
                    frequently arisen from the use of drinking water containing salts of lead in
                    solution, as also from food and condiments adulterated with preparations of this
                    metal, and it has even been known to follow the habitual use of cosmetics
                    composed in part of white lead.</p>
                <p>The colic due to lead poisoning, which in its general characteristics is
                    essentially the same as ordinary colic, is only one of a train of symptoms
                    produced by the absorption of lead into the body. From prolonged exposure to the
                    action of this poison, the general nutrition of the body becomes deteriorated,
                    and serious nervous phenomena present themselves, sometimes in the form of
                    epilepsy and coma, but more usually as a variety of palsy. This palsy is of
                    local character, affecting in the first instance the muscles composing the ball
                    of the thumb, and also those muscles of the fore-arm which extend the wrist, and
                    giving rise to the condition known as “wrist-drop,” from the circumstance that
                    when the arm is extended the hand hangs down and cannot be raised by voluntary
                    effort. The affected muscles undergo atrophy while the paralysis continues. If
                    the patient is removed from further exposure to the influence of the lead
                    poison, and suitable treatment employed, complete recovery from all the ill
                    effects may take place; but otherwise all the symptoms become aggravated, the
                    health becomes completely ruined, and death may result.</p>
                <p>One of the phenomena which accompany lead poisoning is the existence of a blue
                    line along the margins of the gums where they meet the teeth. This is almost
                    never absent, and is an important aid to the diagnosis of the disease.</p>
                <p>The absorption of copper into the system produces a series of symptoms similar to
                    those of lead poisoning, including a form of colic. It is of comparatively rare
                    occur rence, being chiefly observed among workers in copper.</p>
                <p>The treatment of colic consists in means to relieve the spasmodic pain, and in
                    the removal, where possible, of the cause upon which it depends. The former of
                    these indications is fulfilled by the administration of opiates (except in the
                    case of children) and the application of warm fomentations to the abdomen. Where
                    the attack appears to depend on accumulations of irritating matter in the
                    alimentary canal, a brisk purgative will, in addition, be called for.</p>
                <p>In the case of lead colic it is imperatively necessary that the patient be
                    removed from the source of the lead poisoning. Here, too, the free evacuation of
                    the bowels by castor oil or saline purgatives is an important part of the
                    treatment. As an antidote to the lead absorbed into the system, the
                    administration of iodide of potassium is recommended, while for the paralysis
                    nerve tonics, such as quinine and strychnia, and the use of galvanism, will in
                    general yield good results. Where the patient’s occupation necessitates his
                    exposure to the constant influence of the lead poison, as in the case of
                    colour-grinders or manufacturers of white lead, the evil consequences can in
                    great measure bo averted by scrupulous attention to cleansing the body,
                    particularly before eating, by abstention from eating in the work places, and by
                    the habitual use of a drink slightly acidulated with sulphuric acid.</p>
                <p>The terms <hi rend="italic">hepatic colic</hi> and <hi rend="italic">renal
                    colic</hi> are applied to that violent pain which is produced, in the one case,
                    where a biliary calculus or gall stone passes down from the gall bladder into
                    the intestine, and in the other where a renal calculus descends from the kidney
                    along the ureter into the bladder. These affections are, however, entirely
                    different from true colic. <hi rend="smallcaps">(j.</hi> o. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
