<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0382-0353-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">COPROLITES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 353</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1115719">Shells</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1010360">Marl</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:926174">Fishers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:890865">Depositions</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c4k">Marl</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n382/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COPROLITES</label> (from <hi rend="italic">κ0πpoς,</hi> dung,
                    ∖ <hi rend="italic">ιθo&lt;i,</hi> stone), the fossilized excrements of extinct
                    animals. The discovery of their true nature was made by Dr William Buckland, who
                    observed that certain convoluted bodies occurring in the Lias of Gloucestershire
                    had the form which would have been produced by their passage in the soft state
                    through the intestines of reptiles or fishes. These bodies had long been known
                    as “fossil fir cones” and “bezoar stones.” Buckland’s conjecture that they were
                    of faecal origin, and similar to the <hi rend="italic">album, graecum</hi> or
                    excrement of hyaenas, was confirmed by Dr Prout, who on analysis found they
                    consisted essentially of calcium phosphate and carbonate, and not unfrequently
                    contained fragments of unaltered bone. The name “coprolites” was accordingly
                    given to them by Buckland, who subsequently expressed his belief that they might
                    be found useful in agriculture on account of the calcium phosphate they
                    contained. The Liassic coprolites are described by Buckland as resembling oblong
                    pebbles, or kidney-potatoes; they are mostly 2 to 4 inches long, and from 1 to 2
                    inches in diameter, but those of the larger Ichthyosauri are of much greater
                    dimensions. In colour they vary from ash-grey to black, and their fracture is
                    conchoidal. Internally they are found to consist of a lamina twisted upon
                    itself, and externally they generally exhibit a tortuous structure, produced,
                    before the cloaca was reached, by the spiral valve of a compressed small
                    intestine (as in skates, sharks, and dog-fishes); the surface shows also
                    vascular impressions and corrugations due to the same cause. Often the bones,
                    teeth, and scales of fishes are to be found dispersed through the coprolites,
                    and sometimes the bones of small Ichthyosauri, which were apparently a prey to
                    the larger marine saurians. Coprolites have been found at Lyme Regis, enclosed
                    by the ribs of Ichthyosauri, and in the remains of several species of fish; also
                    in the abdominal cavities of a species of fossil fish, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Macropoma</hi><hi rend="italic">Mantelli,</hi> from the chalk of Lewes.
                    Professor Jäger has described coprolites from the alum-slate of Gaildorf in
                    Würtemberg, assigned by him to the Keuper formation; and the fish-coprolites of
                    Burdiehouse and of Newcastle-under-Lyme are of Carboniferous age. The so-called
                    “beetle-stones” of the coal-formation of Newhaven, near Leith, which have
                    mostlya coprolitic nucleus, have been applied to various ornamental purposes by
                    lapidaries. The name “cololites” (from κωλov, the large intestine, <hi
                    rend="italic">λiθo&lt;i,</hi> stone) was given by Agassiz to fossil wormlike
                    bodies, found in the lithographic slate of Solenhofen, which he determined to be
                    either the petrified intestines or contents of the intestines of fishes. The
                    bone-bed of Λxmouth in Devonshire and Westbury and Aust in Gloucestershire, in
                    the Penarth or Rhaetic series of strata, contains the scales, teeth, and bones
                    of saurians and fishes, together with abundance of coprolites; but neither there
                    nor at Lyme Regis is there a sufficient quantity of phosphatic material to
                    render the working of it for agricultural purposes remunerative.</p>
                <p>The term coprolites has been made to include all kinds of phosphatic nodules
                    employed as manures, such, for example, as those obtained from the Coralline and
                    the Red Crag of Suffolk. At the base of the Red Crag in that county is a bed, 3
                    to 18 inches thick, containing rolled fossil bones, cetacean and fish teeth, and
                    shells of the Crag period, with nodules or pebbles of phosphatic matter derived
                    from the London Clay, and often investing fossils from that formation. These are
                    distinguishable from the grey Chalk coprolites by their brownish ferruginous
                    colour and smooth appearance. When ground they give a yellowish-red powder.
                    These nodules were at first taken by Professor Henslow for coprolites; they were
                    afterwards termed by Buckland “pseudo-coprolites.” “The nodules, having been
                    imbued with phosphatic matter from their matrix in the London Clay, were
                    dislodged,” says Buckland, “by the waters of the seas of the first period, and
                    accumulated by myriads at the bottom of those shallow seas where is now the
                    coast of Suffolk. Here they were long rolled together with the bones of large
                    mammalia, fishes, and with the shells of molluscous creatures that lived in
                    shells. From the bottom of this sea they have been raised to form the dry lands
                    along the shores of Suffolk, whence they are now extracted as articles of
                    commercial value, being ground to powder in the mills of Mr Lawes, at Deptford,
                    to supply our farms with a valuable substitute for guano, under the accepted
                    name of coprolite manure.” The phosphatic nodules occurring throughout the Red
                    Crag of Suffolk are regarded by Mr Prestwich as derived from the Coralline Crag.
                    The Suffolk beds have been worked since 1846; and immense quantities of
                    coprolite have also been obtained from Essex, Norfolk, and Cambridgeshire. The
                    Cambridgeshire coprolites are believed to be derived from deposits of Gault age;
                    they are obtained by washing from a stratum about a foot thick, resting on the
                    Gault, at the base of the Chalk Marl, and probably homotaxeous with the
                    Chloritic Marl. An acre yields on an average 300 tons of phosphatic nodules,
                    value £750. About £140 per acre is paid for the lease of the land, which after
                    two years is restored to its owners re-soiled and levelled. Plicatulae have been
                    found attached to these coprolites, showing that they were already hard bodies
                    when lying at the bottom of the Chalk ocean. The Cambridgeshire coprolites are
                    either amorphous or finger-shaped; the coprolites from the Greensand are of a
                    black or dark brown colour; while those from the Gault are greenish-white on the
                    surface, brownish-black internally. Samples of Cambridgeshire and Suffolk
                    coprolite have been found by Voelcker to give on analysis phosphoric acid
                    equivalent to about 55 and 52 ’ 5 per cent, of tribasic calcium phosphate
                    respectively <hi rend="italic">(shourn. R. Agric. Soc. Eng.,</hi> vol. xxi. p.
                    358, 1860). The following analysis of a saurio-coprolite from Lyme Regis is
                    given by Herapath <hi rend="italic">(ſbid.</hi> vol. xii. p. 91) :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Water</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3∙976</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Organic matter</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2O01</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Calcium sulphate</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2’026</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Calcium carbonate ...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>28∙121</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Calcium fluoride</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>not determined.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Calcium and magnesium
                            phosphate</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>53∙996</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Magnesium carbonate</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0∙423</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Aluminic phosphate</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1∙276</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Ferric phosphate</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6∙182</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Silica</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>0’733</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>98∙734</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>An ichthyo-coprolite from Tenby w as found to contain 15 ’ 4 per cent, of
                    phosphoric anhydride. The pseudo-coprolites of the Suffolk Crag have been
                    estimated by Herapath to be as rich in phosphates as the true ichthyo-coprolites
                    and saurio-coprolites of other formations, the proportion of P <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> contained varying
                    between 12 ’ 5 and 37 ’ 25 per cent., the average proportion, however, being 32
                    or 33 per cent.</p>
                <p>Coprolite is reduced to powder by powerful mills of peculiar construction,
                    furnished with granite and buhrstones, before being treated with concentrated
                    sulphuric acid. The acid renders it available as a manure by converting the
                    calcium phosphate, Ca <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> P <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi> O <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, that it contains into the soluble
                    monocalcic salt, CaH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> P <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>
                    O <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi>, or “superphosphate.” The phosphate thus produced
                    forms an efficacious turnip manure, and is quite equal in value to that produced
                    from any other source. The Chloritic Marl in the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n383/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0383-0354"/> Wealden district furnishes much phosphatic
                    material, which has been extensively worked at Froyle. In the vicinity of
                    Farnham it contains a bed of “coprolites” of considerable extent, and 2 to 15
                    feet in thickness. Specimens of these from the Dippen Hall pits, analyzed by
                    Messrs Paine and Way, showed the presence of phosphates equivalent to 55 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 96 of bone-earth <hi rend="italic">(Journ. R. Agric.
                    Soc. Eng.,</hi> vol. ix. p. 56). Phosphatic nodules occur also in the Chloritic
                    Marl of the Isle of Wight and Dorsetshire, and at Wroughton, near Swindon. They
                    are found in the Lower Greensand, or Upper Neocomitan series, in the Atherfield
                    Clay at Stopham, near Pulborough; occasionally at the junction of the Hythe and
                    Sandgate beds; and in the Folkeston beds, at Farnham. At Woburn, Leighton,
                    Ampthill, Sandy, Upware, Wicken, and Potton, near the base of Upper Neocomian
                    iron-sands, there is a band between 6 inches and 2 feet in thickness containing
                    “coprolites;” these consist of phosphatized wood, bones, casts of shells, and
                    shapeless lumps. The coprolitic stratum of the Speeton Clay, on the coast to the
                    N. of Flamborough Head, is included by Prof. Judd with the Portland beds of that
                    formation. In 1864 two phosphatic deposits, a limestone .3 feet thick, with beds
                    of calcium phosphate, and a shale of half that thickness, were discovered by Mr
                    Hope Jones in the neighbourhood of Cwmgynen, about sixteen miles from Oswestry.
                    They are at a depth of about 12 feet, in slaty shale containing Llandeilo
                    fossils and contemporaneous felspathic ash and scoriae. A specimen of the
                    phosphatic limestone analyzed byVoelcker yielded 34 ’ 92 per cent, of tricalcic
                    phosphate, a specimen of the shale 52*15 per cent. <hi rend="italic">(Report of
                    Brit. Assoc.,</hi> 1865).</p>
                <p>Herapath, <hi rend="italic">Chem. Gaz.</hi> 1849, p. 449; Buckland, <hi
                    rend="italic">Geology and Mineralogy,</hi> 4th ed., 1869; Fisher, <hi
                    rend="italic">Quart. Journ. Geol.Soc.</hi> 1873, p. 52; Teall, <hi rend="italic"
                    >On the Potton and</hi><hi rend="italic">Wicken</hi><hi rend="italic">Phosphatic
                    Deposits</hi> (Sedgwick Prize Essay for 1873), 1875; Bonney, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cambridgeshire Geology,</hi> 1875.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
