<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0586-0553-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CRASHAW, Richard</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 553</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1200824">Liberals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058664">Personalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gc8s">Fever</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vb4q">Liberalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44746v0f">Dueling</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n586/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CRASHAW, <hi rend="smallcaps">Richard</hi></label>
                    (1613-1650), the poet, styled “the divine,” was born in London in 1613. He was
                    the son of a strongly anti-papistical divine, Dr William Crashaw, who
                    distinguished himself, even in those times, by the excessive acerbity of his
                    writings against the Catholics. Richard Crashaw was originally put to school at
                    Charter House, butin July 1631 he was admitted to Pembroke College, Cambridge,
                    where he took the degree of B.A. in 1634. The publication of Herbert’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Temple</hi> in 1633 seems to have finally determined the bias of
                    his genius in favour of religious poetry, and next year he published his first
                    book, <hi rend="italic">Eρigra,mrnatunι</hi><hi rend="italic">Sacrorum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Liber,</hi> a volume of Latin verses. In March 1636 he removed to
                    Peterhouse, and was made a fellow of that college in 1G37. It was about this
                    time that he made the acquaintance and secured the lasting friendship of Cowley.
                    In 1641 he is said to have gone to Oxford, but only for a short time; for when
                    in 1643 Cowley left Cambridge to seek a refuge at Oxford, Crashaw remained
                    behind, and was forcibly ejected from his fellowship in 1644, In the confusion
                    of the civil wars he escaped to France, where he finally embraced the Catholic
                    religion, towards which he had long been tending. During his exile his religious
                    and secular poems were collected by an anonymous friend, and published under the
                    title of <hi rend="italic">Steps to tho Temple</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The
                    Delights of the Muses,</hi> in one volume, in 1646. This same year Cowley found
                    him in great destitution at Paris, and induced Queen Henrietta Maria to extend
                    towards him what influenco she still possessed. At her introduction he proceeded
                    to Italy, where he became secretary at Rome to Cardinal Palotta. In 1648 he
                    published two Latin hymns at Paris. He remained until 1649 in the service of the
                    cardinal, to whom he had a great personal attachment; but his retinue contained
                    persons whose violent and licentious behaviour were a source of ceaseless
                    vexation to the sensitive English mystic. At last his denunciation of their
                    excesses became so public that the animosity of those persons was excited
                    against him, and in order to shield him from their revenge, he was sent by the
                    cardinal in 1650 to Loretto, where he was made a canon of the Holy House. In
                    less than three weeks, however, he sickened of fever, and died, not without
                    gravo suspicion of having been poisoned. He was buried in tho Lady Chapel at
                    Loretto. A collection of his latest religious poems, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Carmen Deo Nostro,</hi> was brought out in 1652, dedicated at the dead poet’s
                    desire to the faithful friend of his sufferings, the countess of Denbigh.
                    Crashaw excelled in all manner of graceful accomplishments; besides being an
                    excellent Latinist and Hellenist, he had an intimate knowledge of Italian and
                    Spanish; and his skill in music, painting, and engraving was no less admired in
                    his lifetime than his skill in poetry. Cowley embalmed his memory in an elegy
                    that ranks among the very finest in our language, in which he, a Protestant,
                    well expressed tho feeling left on the minds of contemporaries by the character»
                    of the young Catholic poet :—</p>
                <p>His faith, perhaps, in some nice tenets might Be wrong; his life, Γm sure, was in
                    the right: And I, myself, a Catholic will be,</p>
                <p>So far at least, dear saint, to pray to thee!</p>
                <p>The poetry of Crashaw will be best appreciated by those who can with most success
                    freo themselves from the bondage of a traditional sense of tho dignity of
                    language. The custom of his age permitted the use of images and phrases which we
                    now justly condemn as incongruous and unseemly, and the fervent fancy of Crashaw
                    carried this licence to the most rococo excess. At the same time his verse is
                    studded with fiery beauties and sudden felicities of language, unsurpassed by
                    any lyrist between his own time and Shelley’s. There is no religious poetry in
                    English so full at once of gross and awkward images and imaginativo touches of
                    the most etherial beauty. The temper of his intellect seems to have been
                    delicate and weak, fiery and uncertain; he has a morbid, almost hysterical,
                    passion about him even when his ardour is most exquisitely expressed, and his
                    adoring addresses to the saints have an effeminate falsetto that makes them
                    almost repulsive. The faults and beauties of his very peculiar style can be
                    studied nowhere to more advantage than in the <hi rend="italic">Hymn to Saint
                    Theresa.</hi> Among the secular poems of Crashaw the best are <hi rend="italic"
                    >Music’s Duel,</hi> wſhich deals with that strife between the musician and. the
                    nightingale which has inspired so many poets, from Strada down to Coppée, and
                    <hi rend="italic">Wishes to his supposed Mistress.</hi> In his latest sacred
                    poems, the <hi rend="italic">Carmen Deo Nostro,</hi> sudden and eminent beauties
                    are not wanting, but the mysticism has become more pronounced, and the
                    ecclesiastical mannerism more harsh and repellant. The themes of Crashaw’s verse
                    are as distinct as possible from those of Shelley’s, but it may, on the whole,
                    be said that at his best moments he reminds the reader more closely of the
                    author of <hi rend="italic">Epipsychidion</hi> than of any earlier or later
                    poet.</p>
                <p>Crashaw’s works were first collected, in one volume, in 1858 by W. B. Turnbull.
                    In 1872 an edition, in 2 vols, was printed for private subscription by the Rev.
                    A. B. Grosart. (E. W. G. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
