<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0652-0619-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CROWN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 619</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91b3s">Gold</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp2k">Cross</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:813061">Arches</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:944368">Gold</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:884187">Crosses</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205049">Victoria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n652/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CROWN</label>, a circular ornament worn around the head. The
                    name is applied, at present, only to the head-dress worn by kings or emperors as
                    a badge of their dignity. Originally it was of much wider meaning. The simplest
                    and earliest form of the crown appears to have been a fillet or band, tied about
                    the head, and serving for use, as well as ornament, by keeping up the hair. The
                    name of crown is also given to garlands of leaves or branches, worn by the
                    guests at private banquets, and on almost auy occasion of more than common
                    festivity. It was natural that those who wished to mark a distinction between
                    themselves and their fellow-men should adopt a head-dress differing from that in
                    general use, just as they adopted different and distinctive garments. In
                    countries governed by a king, a special head-dress was, at a very early period,
                    one of the recognized symbols of royalty. A very simple form of the royal crown
                    was a diadem or fillet of gold fastened round the head and tied behind. This by
                    degrees became more and more elaborate in its structure and ornament, and
                    assumed a variety of forms, in most of which the original diadem is to be
                    traced, just as the diadem itself is a clear advance of the original ribbon or
                    garland.</p>
                <p>Crowns are often mentioned in Scripture; but the term was applied to other
                    ornaments for the head besides those worn exclusively by royal personages. For
                    example, the head-dress of the Jewish high-priest—a linen band with a plate of
                    gold fastened in front—is also called a crown.</p>
                <p>Among the kings of Egypt and of the East crowns were in common use. The crowns of
                    the Ptolemies were, in general, plain fillets of gold encircling the head, but
                    we find them sometimes making use of the more ornate radiated crown. The
                    Seleucidae of Syria used the plain golden fillet. But the crowns of the Oriental
                    kings have usually been much more ornate, sometimes of very massive
                    construction, and profusely adorned with pearls and gems.</p>
                <p>In the republics of historical Greece and Rome the crown long continued in use in
                    its first and most simple form. There is no mention made by Homer of the crown
                    as a royal distinction, nor does he seem to have known it at all except as an
                    ornamental wreath or garland. The most celebrated crowns among the Greeks were
                    the wreaths gained at the great inter-Hellenic games, by the victors in the
                    races and athletic contests. In the course of later Athenian history, we find
                    crowns of gold frequently bestowed in recognition of distinguished public
                    services. It was by Alexander the Great, and the successors of Alexander, that
                    the crown was first worn in Greece as the symbol of royal rank. The form used
                    was generally that of a simple band of gold.</p>
                <p>The early Roman kings are commonly represented with plain bands of gold
                    encircling their heads. During the historical period of Roman history, besides
                    the crown in private use at feasts and funerals, there were several kinds of
                    crowns bestowed for public services, and indeed in recognition of almost any
                    kind of honourable distinction. These were frequently so designed in shape or
                    material as to be symbolical of the service they commemorated. The corona
                    muralis, for instance, was a crown of gold, decorated with turrets, given to him
                    who had first scaled the walls of a besieged place; the corona vallaris,
                    decorated with pales, to him who had first forced an intrenchment; the corona
                    navalis, decorated in general with little figures of the prows of ships, to him
                    who had gained a signal victory at sea. The corona obsidionalis, given to a
                    general who had delivered a Roman army from blockade, was a crown of grass or
                    herbs plucked at the spot where this important service had been rendered. The
                    crowns of the Roman emperors were of several forms, regulated by the fancy of
                    the wearer, from the simple golden fillet to the radiated crown which marked an
                    admitted claim to divine honours.</p>
                <p>In the nations of modern Europe crowns have always been in general use among
                    personages of the highest rank. The most remarkable are the papal and the
                    imperial crowns. The papal crown is a lofty uncleft mitre, encircled by three
                    coronets rising one above the other, surmounted by a ball and cross, and with
                    ribbons at each side, similar to those of the mitre of an Italian bishop. This
                    form of crown was first assumed by Pope Benedict ΣII., 1344.</p>
                <p>The crowns that are most celebrated in connection with the imperial dignity are
                    the Imperial crown proper, the German crown, and the Italian or Lombard crown.
                    The first of these was of gold, rising into a semicircle above the head,
                    surmounted by a small cross, and adorned with pearls and precious stones. The
                    second is always spoken of as the silver crown, but it appears from the evidence
                    of eyewitnesses that its material was, in fact, gold. The third was known as the
                    iron crown, though it appears that the only iron in it was one of the nails used
                    or said to have been used at the crucifixion, and that in this case too the rest
                    of the material was gold. It was with this, or with a later imitation of it,
                    that Napoleon I. was crowned as king of Italy at Milan in 1805. The Imperial
                    crown, now in use in the empires of the Continent, in its form is very
                    remarkable, being cleft somewhat after the mauuer of a mitre, having also the
                    general contour of a modern convex mitre in its elevated part which rises above
                    the golden leafage that heightens the gemmed circlet. In the open space between
                    the two divisions formed by the cleft a single arch rises, surmounted by a mound
                    and cross.</p>
                <p>The English royal crown has gradually grown up <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n653/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0653-0620"/> from its early simple form into various aspects
                    of elaborate splendour. Before the Norman Conquest the headdress which appears
                    to have been habitually worn by the Anglo-Saxon princes was a fillet of pearls;
                    their coins, however, and illuminations in MSS. of their era,, show them to have
                    been by no means unfamiliar with a nearer approach to a true crown, in the form
                    of a radiated diadem. The great seals, the coinage, monumental effigies, and
                    various other contemporary representations, supply a complete series of examples
                    of the crown in its varieties of design and enrichment, from the time &lt; f the
                    Conqueror.</p>
                <p>In addition to several modifications in both the treatment and the grouping of
                    the adornments of the regal circlet, tho English crown has undergone a completo
                    change in the character of the figures with which the circlet has been
                    heightened; and it also has had its original aspect of an open crown completely
                    altered by its enriched circlet being arched over with jewelled bands of gold,
                    when the diadem thus inclosed was surmounted by a mound and cross.</p>
                <p>The crown worn by William I. and his successors was a plain circlet heightened
                    with four spikes having trefoilheads (fig. 1). Henry I. appears to have enriched
                    the circlet with gems (fig. 2), and on his great seal the trefoils of his
                    father’s crown assume a form resembling that of fleurs-de-lys. The effigies of
                    Henry II., Richard I., John, and their queens, show the crown to have made such
                    an advance in the dignity of its aspect as is shown in fig. 3. The crowns of
                    Richard and Berengaria, however, have four large leaves only heightening the
                    circlets, while the crowns of Henry, Alianore, John, and Isabella have four
                    smaller leaves alternating with the fo√*r larger ones. The crown of Henry III.
                    has a plain circlet heightened with trefoils, a slightly raised point
                    intervening between each pair of the leaves (fig. 4). A similar crown was worn
                    by Edward I., the trefoil-leaves being alternately large and comparatively
                    small. The truly beautiful crown of Edward II. (fig. 5), as it is represented in
                    his effigy, was formed of four large and as many smaller leaves of a deeply
                    serrated type, rising with graceful curves from the jewelled circlet, and having
                    eight small flowers alternating with the leaves. This form of crown appears to
                    have remained unchanged during the reigns of Edward III. and Richard II.</p>
                <p>It would seem from the crown, fig. 6, sculptured with elaborate care upon the
                    head of his effigy at Canterbury, that Henry IV. determined to distinguish the
                    accession of a Lancastrian prince by displaying an unprecedented magnificence in
                    the emblem of his sovereignty. The splendidly jewelled circlet of this crown is
                    heightened with eight large and rich leaves, and as many true
                    fleurs-de-lys—their first appearance on an English crown,—the whole alternating
                    with sixteen small clusters of pearls, three in each. The famous “Harry crown,”
                    of which this may be assumed to be a faithful representation, was broken up and
                    employed as security for the loan required by Henry V., when he was about to
                    embark on his expedition to France; but the costly fragments are recorded to
                    have been redeemed in the 8th and 9th years of Henry VI. The arched crown in its
                    earliest form (fig. 7), was introduced by Henry V.; and, with the arches
                    crosses, which from the time of Henry VI. always have been crosses pâtées,
                    appeared to supersede the earlier foliage upon the circlet. The arches at
                    different periods have varied both in number and in contour. At first they were
                    elevated almost to a point; then they were somewhat depressed at their
                    intersection; still later this depression was increased, the arches themselves
                    thus having an ogee contour, as in fig. 13; and finally, in the coronation crown
                    of Queen Victoria (fig. 16), the arches, which bend over almost at right angles,
                    are flattened where the mound rests on them at their intersection. The crown of
                    Henry VI. appears to have had three arches, or six semi-arches; and there are
                    the same number in the crown that ensigns the hawthorn-bush badge of Henry VII.
                    The crown of Edward IV. had two arches, or four semi-arches; and a crown arched
                    in the same manner (fig. 9) appears on the great seal of Richard III. Both
                    arched and open crowns are represented in sculpture, illuminations, and other
                    works, until the close of the reign i f Edward IV.; and, occasionally, as late
                    as the reign of Henry VIII. a royal shield displays an unarched crown. Whatever
                    other changes or modifications the English crown may have experienced since the
                    time of Henry V., the circlet has always been heightened with alternate crosses
                    pâtées and fleurs-de-lys, with some minor accessories of jewels; also, when the
                    crown has two arches, each of the four semi-arches always has risen from within
                    one of the crosses upon the circlet. Edward IV. sometimes has his royal shield
                    of arms ensigned with an open crown, its circlet heightened with eight crosses
                    and eight fleurs-de-lys. Upon his seal as earl of Chester, the same sovereign
                    has the circlet of his open crown heightened with fleurs-de-lys only,
                    alternating with small clusters of pearls (fig. 8). The crown actually worn by
                    Henry VII. appears, from his monument at Westminster, to have had two arches,
                    its circlet being heightened with four crosses and four fleurs-de-lys. A similar
                    crown (fig. 9) appears on the great seal of Henry VIII. During the reigns of
                    Edward VI., Mary, and Elizabeth, the crown experienced no change; but in her
                    great seal Elizabeth is represented wearing a small diadem having eight
                    semi-arches. In fig. 11, drawn from the royal achievement of Henry VII.,
                    sculptured with great spirit above the south entrance to King’s College Chapel,
                    Cambridge, the royal motto is inscribed upon the circlet. The interior of the
                    same noble building is enriched with numerous other splendid crowns executed in
                    full relief. In these examples of the crowns of Tudor sovereigns there are four
                    crosses and as many fleurs-de-lys; it must be added, however, that eight crosses
                    and the same number of fleurs-de-lys are commonly represented, though certainly
                    only as variations from the more authoritative number, on Tudor <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n654/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0654-0621"/> crowns. The form of arches shown iu fig. 12 for
                    the first time appears upon the great seal of Edward VI.</p>
                <p>The crown of the Stuart sovereigns, the first kings of Great Britain, James I.
                    and Charles I., had four arches, each of the eight semi-arches springing from
                    the alternating crosses and fleurs-de-lys of the circlet (fig. 10). This crown,
                    described to have been formed of massive gold, weighing 7 δ&gt; 6 oz,, and
                    valued at £1110, was in 1649 broken up and defaced, with other royal insignia.
                    The crown made for Charles II. (fig. 13), and also worn by James 11., William
                    III., and Anne, closely resembled an earlier type; and, indeed, it differed only
                    in its proportions from the crown of more recent times (fig. 14),—the crown of
                    Her Majesty’s immediate predecessors on the throne, which still forms a part of
                    the regalia of the British empire. The crown (fig. 16), made for the coronation
                    of Queen Victoria, has its entire surface completely covered with jewels, —its
                    circlet, crosses, fleurs-de-lys, arches, and mound being alike in displaying
                    varieties of the same precious constructive materials. This coronation crown is
                    lined with a cap of violet velvet, in accordance with a usage that first
                    appeared upon the great seal of Henry VIII; but in all the earlier crowns the
                    caps were of crimson or purple velvet. It only remains to direct attention to
                    the form, fig. 15, under which, with Her Majesty’s sanction, the crown of Queen
                    Victoria is represented, happily for its effective appearance without any cap or
                    lining, on all occasions of the ordinary use of the symbol of regal dignity and
                    power.</p>
                <p>The crown introduced into the English coinage by Henry VII I. in both gold and
                    silver, bears a crowned rose and crowned shield of arms, with the royal cipher.
                    The silver crown of Edward VI. has the king on horseback and the royal shield;
                    but that of Elizabeth substitutes a crowned bust for the equestrian figure. In
                    both these silver coins the royal shield is charged in pretence with a floriated
                    cross, which, extending beyond the shield, divides the legend into four parts.
                    The crown of Charles II. has four crowned shields of England, Scotland, France,
                    and Ireland in cross. The crown of recent years, that bears the device of St
                    George and the dragon, strangely represents the Christian champion under the
                    aspect of a nude classic warrior armed with a sword, instead of his appearing in
                    mediaeval armour, and piercing his adversary with a lance. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Heraldry. (c. b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
