<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0608-0575-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CREWE (9th edition, volume 6, page 575)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nr79">Carding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qf8jj4b">Cards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w237">Running</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639k84f">Farms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qp5f">Farming</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921422">Farms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1939006">Cards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847103">Carding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1101348">Running</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937529">Games</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n608/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CREWE</label>, a town of Cheshire, and an important station
                    on the London and North-Western Railway, to which it is altogether indebted for
                    its importance. It is the centre of six lines of railway, connecting it with
                    Manchester, Chester, Birmingham, and other large towns, and is 21 miles east by
                    south of Chester, and 54 miles north-west of Birmingham. It is inhabited
                    principally by persons in the employment of the railway companies, and is well
                    laid out. Crewe is not only one of the busiest railway junctions in the world,
                    but possesses an enormous establishment for the manufacture of everything used
                    in railways, steelworks, and engine and carriage factories on a great scale. It
                    has a mechanics’ institute, library, schools, baths, &amp;c. The country round
                    is flat and uninteresting. The town was built on an estate called Oak Farm in
                    the parish of Monk’s Coppenhall, and takes its name from the original stations
                    having been placed in the township of Crewe, in which *hθθseat of Lord Crewe is
                    situated. Population (1871), CRIBBAGE, a game at cards, of uncertain etymology.
                    A very similar game called noddy was formerly played: the game was fifteen or
                    twenty-one up, marked with counters, occasionally by means of a noddy board.
                    Cribbage seems to be an improved form of noddy.</p>
                <p>A complete pack of fifty-two cards is required, and a <hi rend="italic">cribbage
                        board</hi> and <hi rend="italic">four pegs.</hi> The board is drilled with
                    sixty <hi rend="italic">holes</hi> for each player (see diagram), and one
                    hole</p>
                <p>(called the <hi rend="italic">game hole),</hi> common to both. The divisions into
                    spaces of ten holes each are to facilitate counting. The game is marked by
                    inserting the pegs in the holes, commencing with the outer row at the game-hole
                    end, and going <hi rend="italic">up</hi> the board. When the thirtieth hole is
                    reached the player comes <hi rend="italic">down</hi> the board, using the inner
                    row of holes. The pegs belonging to one player should differ in colour from
                    those belonging to the other. When one peg has been used, and another score is
                    made by the same player, the second peg of the same colour is asserted ahead of
                    the first, according to the number of holes to be scored. This peg is called the
                        <hi rend="italic">foremost</hi> peg, the other the <hi rend="italic"
                        >hindmost</hi> peg. When a fresh score accrues the hindmost peg is taken out
                    and placed in front of the foremost (which now becomes the hindmost), and so on
                    until one player scores sixty-one holes or more, when he wins, and places his
                    foremost peg in the game hole. If the losing player fails to obtain thirty holes
                    his adversary wins a <hi rend="italic">double</hi> when so agreed.</p>
                <p>The game may be played by two players, five or six cards being dealt to each, and
                    each putting out two for crib; or by three players (with an extra board), five
                    cards being dealt to each, each putting out one for crib, and a card from the
                    top of the pack being dealt to complete the crib; or by four players (two being
                    partners against the other two, sitting and playing as at whist, and one partner
                    scoring for both), five cards being dealt to each, and each putting out one card
                    for crib. Twhanded five-card cribbage is the most scientific game. It is played
                    in the following manner.</p>
                <p>The players cut for deal. In cutting, whether for deal, to the dealer, or for
                    start, at least four cards must be cut, and at least four left in the bottom
                    packet. The player who cuts the lower card deals. The cards rank king (highest),
                    queen, knave, ten, down to the ace (lowest). At the two-handed five-card game
                    only, the non-dealer is entitled to score three holes (called <hi rend="italic"
                        >three for last)</hi> at any time during the game. Three for last is usually
                    scored while the dealer is dealing the first hand.</p>
                <p>The non-dealer cuts the pack; the dealer re-unites the packets, and gives one
                    card to his adversary, and then one to himself, and so on alternately until each
                    has five cards. The undealt portion of the pack is placed face downwards on the
                    table.</p>
                <p>The players then look at their hands and <hi rend="italic">lay out,</hi> each
                    putting two cards face downwards on the table, on the side of the board nearest
                    to the dealer. The four cards so laid out are called the <hi rend="italic"
                        >crib.</hi> A player must not take back into his hand a card he has laid
                    out, nor must the crib be touched during the play of the hand.</p>
                <p>After laying out, the non-dealer cuts the pack (when more than two play, the
                    player to the dealer’s left) and the dealer turns up the top card of the lower
                    packet, called the <hi rend="italic">start.</hi> If the start is a knave the
                    dealer marks two (called <hi rend="italic">two for his heels).</hi> The score is
                    forfeited if not marked before the dealer plays a card.</p>
                <p>The hands are then played. The non-dealer lays face upwards on the table on his
                    side of the board any card <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n609/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0609-0576"/> from his hand he pleases; the dealer then
                    does the same on his side of the board, and so on alternately. When more than
                    two play, the player to the leader’s left plays the second card, and so on round
                    to the dealer. As soon as the first card is laid down the player calls out the
                    number of pips on it; if a picture card, ten. When the second card is laid down,
                    the player calls out the sum of the pips on the two cards played, and so on
                    until all the cards are played, or until neither player has a card which will
                        <hi rend="italic">come in,</hi><hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     subscript"> i</hi> which can be played
                    without passing the number thirty-one. If one player has a card or cards that
                    will come in and the other has not, he is at liberty to play them; at the
                    six-card game he is bound to play as long as they can come in. When more than
                    two play, the player next in rotation is bound to play, and so on until no one
                    can come in. At the two-handed five-card game, when neither can come in the play
                    is at an end; but at the other games the cards already played are turned face
                    down, and the remainder of the hands are played in rotation, and so on until all
                    the cards are played out.</p>
                <p>The object of the play is to make pairs, fifteens, sequences, or the go, or to
                    prevent the adversary from scoring. Flushes formerly counted in play; but now
                    they do not.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pairs.—</hi> If a card is put down of the same denomination as
                    the one last played, the player <hi rend="italic">pairing</hi> is entitled to
                    score two holes. If a third card of the same denomination is next played a <hi
                        rend="italic">pair royal</hi> is made, and the maker of the pair royal is
                    entitled to score six holes. If a fourth card of the same denomination is next
                    played, twelve holes are similarly scored for the <hi rend="italic">double pair
                        royal.</hi> Kings pair only with kings, queens with queens, and so on with
                    knaves and tens, notwithstanding that they are all <hi rend="italic">tenth
                        cards</hi> in play, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> that the number called when
                    playing any of them is ten.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fifteens.—</hi> If either player during the play reaches
                    fifteen exactly, by reckoning the pips and tens of all the played cards, he is
                    entitled to mark two.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sequences.—</hi> If during the play of the hand three or more
                    cards are consecutively played which make an ascending or descending sequence,
                    the maker of the sequence marks one hole for each card forming the sequence or
                        <hi rend="italic">run.</hi> King, queen, knave, and ten reckon in sequence
                    in this order, notwithstanding that they are all tenth cards in play. The other
                    cards reckon in sequence according to the number of their pips. The ace is not
                    in sequence with king, queen. If one player obtains a run of three, and his
                    adversary puts down a card that is in sequence, he marks four, and so on. And,
                    be it observed, if there is a break in the sequence, and the break is filled up
                    during the play, without the intervention of a card not in sequence, the player
                    of the card that fills the break scores a run. An example will render this
                    clear. The cards are played in this order (A playing the first card, B the
                    second, and so on alternately},</p>
                <p>? ⅛ B <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> a</hi> gets a run of three, B a run of four.
                    Had B’s last 4, 3, 2, ace. <hi rend="superscript"> t5</hi> ’</p>
                <p>card been a five he would similarly have scored a run of four, as there is no
                    break. Had B’s last card been a four, he would have scored a run of three. The
                    cards need not be played in order; it is sufficient that the card last played
                    completes a sequence, although it may be an intermediate card. Thus the cards
                    being played in this order, 42536 ® marks a run of four for his last card
                    played, A a run of five. But suppose the cards played thus, 4 2 5 3 5 6^ B takes
                    a run of four for the fourth card played, but there is no run for any one else,
                    as the second five (which forms no part of the sequence) intervenes. Again, if
                    the cards at six-card cribbage are thus played, <hi rend="superscript"> A</hi>,
                    ® 3, 2, &lt;ace, <hi rend="superscript"> A</hi><hi rend="superscript"> takes a
                        run</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> of tlιree</hi> &gt; <hi
                        rend="superscript"> b</hi> a run of four, A a ran of five. B then playing
                    the deuce has no run, as the deuce he previously played intervenes. A then makes
                    a run of five, and lastly B has no run, the ace previously played blocking the
                    three.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">go, end hole,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">last card</hi> is
                    scored by the player who approaches most nearly to thirty-one during the play,
                    and entitles to a score of one. If thirty-one is reached exactly, it is a go of
                    two instead of one.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Compound Scores.—</hi> If often happens that more than one of
                    the above scores are made at the same time, when the player reckons both. Thus a
                    player pairing with the last card that will come in scores both pair and go.
                    Similarly a pair and a fifteen, or a sequence and a fifteen, can be reckoned
                    together.</p>
                <p>When the play is over, the hands are <hi rend="italic">shown</hi> and counted
                    aloud. The non-dealer has <hi rend="italic">first show,</hi> and scores first;
                    the dealer afterwards counts and scores what he has in hand and then what he has
                    in crib. In counting the hands and crib, the start is made use of by both
                    players to assist in forming combinations.</p>
                <p>The combinations in hand or crib which entitle to a score are fifteens, pairs or
                    pairs royal, sequences, flushes, and his nob.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fifteens.—</hi> All the different cards that, taken together,
                    make fifteen exactly, without counting all the same cards twice over in one
                    fifteen, entitle the holder to a score of two. Tenth cards count ten towards a
                    fifteen. For example a tenth card and a five reckon two, or <hi rend="italic"
                        >fifteen-two</hi> as it is often called. Another five in the hand or turned
                    up, would again combine with the tenth card, and entitle to another fifteen, or
                        <hi rend="italic">fifteen -four,</hi> if the other cards were a two and a
                    three, two other fifteens would be counted,—one for the combination of the three
                    and two with the tenth card, and one for the combination ot the two fives with
                    the three and two. Similarly, two tenth cards and two fives reckon
                    fifteen-eight; a nine and three threes give three different combinations, and
                    reckon fifteen-six; and so on for other cards.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pairs.—</hi> Pairs are reckoned as in play.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Sequences. —</hi> Three or more cards in sequence count, as in
                    play one for each card. If one sequence card can be substituted for another of
                    the same denomination, the sequence reckons again. For example 3, 4, 5, and a 3
                    turned up, reckon two sequences of three. At the six-card game or in crib, with
                    another 3 there would be three sequences of three, and so on for all cards that
                    can make a fresh combination.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Flushes.—</hi> If all the cards in hand are of the same suit,
                    one is reckoned for each card. If the start is also of the same suit, one is
                    reckoned for that also. In crib, no flush is reckoned, unless the start is of
                    the same suit as the cards in crib.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">His nob.—</hi> If a player holds the knave of the suit turned
                    up he counts one for his nob.</p>
                <p>A couple of examples will render the counting clear. Say the crib consists of 6,
                    7, 7, 8, 8. The score would be four fifteens (eight), two pairs (four), four
                    sequences of three (twelve); total twenty-four. Again, a hand of 4, <hi
                        rend="italic">5, 6</hi> (same suit) and a 5 turned up counts two fifteens
                    (four), a pair (two), two sequences of three (six), and a flush (three); total
                    fifteen.</p>
                <p>The points accrue in the following order :—two for his heels; points made in play
                    as soon as declared; nondealer’s show; dealer’s show (hand and crib).</p>
                <p>After the points in hand and crib are reckoned, the cards are put together and
                    shuffled, and the opponent of the last dealer deals, and so on alternately until
                    the game is won.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Hints to Players.</hi> —In laying cut, the nondealer should
                    discard such cards as are not likely to score in crib; the dealer should put out
                    good cards for his own crib. It is so important to <hi rend="italic">baulk</hi>
                    the crib that the non-dealer should often sacrifice scores in his own hand. Thus
                    with queen, knave, ten, four, ace, the dealer should put out the four and the
                    ace; the non-dealer the queen and ten. But towards the end of the game, if the
                    non-dealer has cards that will probably take him out, the consideration of
                    baulking the crib need not influence him. The best baulks are a king or an ace,
                    as those cards only reckon one waj iι. sequences. King with ten, nine (best
                    baulk), eight, seven, six, or ace, are good baulks; so is queen, with any of
                    these cards except the ten. Next to these wide even cards are good baulks (even
                    cards being less likely to score in fifteens than odd ones); and lastly cards
                    that are not in sequence. <hi rend="smallcaps">Two</hi> cards of the same suit
                    should not be put out by the non-dealer if there is as good a discard of cards
                    of different suits. The best cards for the dealer to put out (and therefore
                    those to be avoided by the non-dealer), are fives, five and six, five and a
                    tenth card, three and two, seven and eight, four and one, nine and six, pairs
                    (especially low pairs), and close cards. It is generally right to keep a
                    sequence in hand, as if the start is of the same denomination as one of those
                    kept, the dealer reckons eight at least. A pair royal is a good hand to
                    keep.</p>
                <p>In playing, the best card to begin with is ace, two, three, or four, as the only
                    chance of an adverse score is by pairing, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n610/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0610-0577"/> and pairing is always dangerous on account of
                    the possibility of its being capped by a pair royal. Pairing is often declined,
                    as it is common to open the play with a card of which a duplicate is held
                    (except with two fives). When leading from a sequence, the middle card should
                    not be led. If a close card is played to the one led it often happens that the
                    adversary wishes a run of three to be made against him, he holding a card that
                    will complete a run of four. Having the choice of pairing or of making fifteen,
                    prefer the latter; but if a seven or eight is led, and a fifteen is made, the
                    adversary has the chance of a run of three. During the play, a four should not
                    be added to a call of seven (making eleven), as if paired the opponent scores
                    four. All similar combinations should be avoided, as twelve made with a three,
                    twenty-seven with a four, twenty-eight with a three, and twenty-one with any
                    card, as then a tenth card (of which there are sixteen) comes in for two. It is
                    very desirable to win the go, as this makes a difference of at least two to the
                    score in each deal. The best chance of winning the go with two low cards and a
                    high one is to begin with a low card, with two high cards and a low one to begin
                    with a high one. The dealer has the best chance of making the go.</p>
                <p>The most important guide to the play is the score. The player who is ahead in the
                    game should endeavour to keep so by playing wide cards, declining pairs, and
                    declining to make fifteen with close cards. This is called <hi rend="italic"
                        >playing off.</hi> The one who is behind in the game should <hi
                        rend="italic">play on,</hi><hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> score whenever he
                    can, running the risk of a larger score being made against him. To calculate
                    whether to play on or play off, the average points scored should be kept in
                    mind. Each player ought to reckon slightly over six in hand and play and five in
                    crib, or seventeen and a half in two deals to be <hi rend="italic">at</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">hornae.</hi> A player who scores more than the average and
                    leaves his adversary six or seven points in arrear is <hi rend="italic">safe at
                        home.</hi> When at home it is best to play off; when the adversary is safe
                    at home it is best to play on.</p>
                <p>Near the end of the game and wanting points in play to play out, it is advisable
                    to keep two low cards and one high one.</p>
                <p>At six-card cribbage it is not so important to baulk the crib as at five-card.
                    The average scores are twelve for the non-dealer, seventeen for the dealer. At
                    the end of the second deal a player is at home at twenty-nine holes. In the
                    first deal it is an advantage to exceed the average, consequently both players
                    with fair hands should play on; but with poor hands they should play off.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Laws.—</hi><hi rend="italic">Cutting.—</hi> 1. There must be
                    a fresh cut for deal after every game, unless rubbers are played. 2. If in
                    cutting for deal or start more than one card is exposed, adversary may choose
                    which card he pleases. 3. Errors in cutting to the dealer necessitate a fresh
                    cut. <hi rend="italic">Dealing.—</hi><hi rend="italic">4.</hi> Cards must be
                    dealt by one at a time. If two are dealt together, error may be rectified, if it
                    can be done by moving one card only; otherwise non-dealer marks two holes, and
                    there must be a fresh deal. 5. If dealer exposes his own cards, no penalty. 6.
                    Faced card in pack necessitates a fresh deal. 7. Player dealing out of turn,
                    error can be rectified prior to start being turned up; otherwise not. 8.
                    Nondealer marks two holes, and has the option of a fresh deal—(a) if dealer
                    exposes any of non-dealer’s cards, and (δ) if dealer gives too many or too few
                    cards to either player. In δ cases non-dealer may look at his hand before
                    electing; if he elects to stand the deal when he has a surplus card he returns a
                    card unshown to the pack; if, when the dealer has a surplus card, he draws one
                    and looks at it; if when either has too few cards, imperfect hand is completed
                    from pack. <hi rend="italic">Laying out.—</hi> 9. If either player lays out when
                    he holds too many cards, adversary marks two holes, and has option of a fresh
                    deal. If he stands the deal he draws surplus card from offender’s hand and looks
                    at it. 10. If e⅛her player lays out with too few cards he must play with his
                    hand short. 11. If a player takes back a card laid out, adversary marks two
                    holes, and has option of fresh deal. 12. Crib must not be touched before hand is
                    played. <hi rend="italic">Playing.—·</hi> 13. Player playing with too many
                    cards, same penalty as in law 9. Playing with too few cards, no penalty. 14.
                    Card once played that will come in cannot be taken .</p>
                <p>up again. Card that will not come in shown in play, no penalty. 15. If two cards
                    are played together the one counted is deemed to be played. 16. If a player at
                    six-card cribbage or at three or four handed cribbage neglects to play a card
                    that will come in, adversary may require it to be played, or may mark two holes.
                    17. Miscounting during play no penalty. <hi rend="italic">Showing and
                        scoring.—</hi> 18. When reckoning, cards must remain exposed until adversary
                    is satisfied. If a player mixes his cards with the pack, or hand and crib
                    together, before adversary is satisfied, he forfeits score. 19. If a player
                    scores more than he is entitled to, adversary may correct his score, and add
                    points overscored to his own. This law applies also to placing peg in game hole
                    in error. Scoring two few, no penalty. Player is not entitled to any assistance
                    in reckoning. 20. If a player touches his opponent’s pegs except to correct an
                    overscore, or touches his own pegs when lie has no score to make, his adversary
                    marks two holes. 21. If <hi rend="italic">a</hi> player displaces his foremost
                    peg he must put it behind the other. If he displaces both, adversary may place
                    hindmost peg where he believes it to have been, and the other peg behind it.
                    _(H. J.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
