<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0266-0239-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CONCLAVE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 239</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47h15q">Oaths</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:841533">Bulls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1042646">Oaths</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n266/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CONCLAVE</label>. The word conclave is used to signify any
                    company of persons gathered together in consultation; its proper meaning is any
                    such gathering of persons <hi rend="italic">locked up together</hi> (from the
                    preposition <hi rend="italic">cum,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">clavis,</hi> a
                    key); and the technical meaning, which has superseded all other uses of the
                    word, save where some other significance is specially indicated, is the meeting
                    of the members of the Sacred College of Cardinals lor the purpose of electing a
                    Pope.</p>
                <p>The Pope, who is simply the bishop of Rome, was originally chosen by the entire
                    body of the people constituting the church at Rome. Gradually, and by a process
                    of encroachment, the several steps of which are, as might be expected, very
                    obscure, the right of nomination was confined to the clergy, the people still
                    retaining a right of objection, exercised very much in the same manner as the
                    forbidding banns of marriage is now exercised. The grasping tyranriy of the
                    clergy combined with the lawless turbulence of the laity, consisting no longer,
                    as originally, of a select body of religious men, but of the entire population,
                    to cause this participation of the laity also to fall into disuse. The next step
                    was to allow the privilege of the vote only to the chief among the clergy— <hi
                    rend="italic">cardinales—</hi> the cardinal clergy, so called as the principal
                    virtues were called cardinal virtues (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Cardinal).</hi>
                    During some centuries the emperor was understood to have a controlling voice in
                    the election, in such sort that his approbation was necessary for the validity
                    of it. But the practice varied much in this respect, according as the emperor
                    was or was not strong, near at hand, or interested in the election. The history
                    of this part of the subject is exceedingly obscure; but it is certain that at
                    least one Pope provided that the consent of the emperor should be necessary for
                    the election of his successor, and on the other hand that other elections were
                    made about the same period without the emperor’s participation.</p>
                <p>It was not till many years after the right of election had been abusively
                    confined to the cardinals, that the practice of shutting up those dignitaries
                    for the purpose of exercising that right was resorted to. And in the earliest
                    instances the ' <hi rend="superscript"> t</hi> conclave” seems to have been an
                    involuntary imprisonment imposed on them <hi rend="italic">ab</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">extra.</hi> In 1216 the Perugians constrained the nineteen
                    cardinals who elected Honorius III. to enter into conclave the day after the
                    death of Innocent III., who died at Perugia, keeping them imprisoned till the
                    election should be completed. Gregory IX. was similarly elected at Rome in 1227,
                    the cardinals having been shut up against their will by the senators and people
                    of Rome. In 1272 Gregory X. was elected at Viterbo by seventeen cardinals, who
                    had not only been shut up against their will, but from over whose heads the roof
                    of the building in which the conclave was held was removed by the citizens in
                    order to hasten their deliberations.</p>
                <p>This Gregory, in a council held at Lyons in 1274. promulgated a code of law for
                    the conducting of the Papal election, comprised in fifteen rules. And these
                    rules, though modified by subsequent pontiffs in some respects’ and supplemented
                    by a vast number of more minute regulations, remain to the present day the
                    foundation and origin of all the law and practice of Papal elections. The text
                    of this code is too lengthy to be given here. It may be read in the original
                    Latin in the <hi rend="italic">Life of Gregory</hi><hi rend="italic">X.,</hi> by
                    Pagi, as in many other works,—the <hi rend="italic">Notes to Platina</hi> by
                    Panvinius, &amp;c.;—or in English, slightly abbreviated, in a volume on the
                    Papal conclaves by T. A. Trollope (p. 64). The substance of some of the more
                    important provisions may be given summarily, as follows. Cardinals to go into
                    conclave on the tenth day after the Pope’s death, attended by one person only,
                    unless in a case of evident need, when two may be permitted. Cardinals to live
                    in conclave in common without separation between bed and bed by wall, curtain,
                    or veil (modified by subsequent rules to the present practice of a wooden cell
                    for each cardinal). No access to conclave to be permitted. An opening to be left
                    for food to be passed in. No vote shall be given save in conclave. Cardinals who
                    quit the conclave by reason of sickness cannot vote. Those who arrive after the
                    closing of it may enter and vote. Cardinals who may have been censured or
                    excommunicated cannot be excluded from conclave. An election can only be made by
                    a two-thirds majority of those present. Any man, lay or ecclesiastic, not a
                    heretic and not canonically incapacitated, may be elected Pope. No entreaties or
                    promises to be made by one cardinal to another with a view of influencing the
                    vote. All bargains, agreements, undertakings, even though corroborated by an
                    oath, having such an object to be of no validity; and “let him that breaks such
                    be deemed worthy of praise rather than of the blame of perjury.”</p>
                <p>Very many popes have sought to enforce and make yet <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n267/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0267-0240"/> more stringent this last all-important rule, by
                    reiterated fulminations of excommunication <hi rend="italic">ipso facto,</hi> in
                    any and every case of its contravention. The most solemn forms of oath that
                    language can devise have been prescribed. The Bulls condemning all simoniacal
                    bargainings have been ordered to be invariably read with every circumstance of
                    solemnity in every conclave before the business of the meeting is entered on.
                    And the result of all these multiplied precautions, precepts, prohibitions, and
                    menaces has been that a study of the history of the Papal conclaves leaves the
                    student with the conviction that no election untainted by simony has ever yet
                    been made, while in a great number of instances the simony practised in the
                    conclave has been of the grossest, most shameless, and most overt kind.</p>
                <p>The form of oath, as practised at the present day, which the cardinal pronounces
                    in the act of delivering his vote, is as follows: “Testor Christum Dominum, qui
                    me judicaturus est, me eligere quem secundum Deum judico eligi debere ”—“I call
                    to witness Christ our Lord, who shall be my judge, that I am electing him who
                    before God I think ought tobe elected.” The words seem at first sight to have
                    been chosen and put together with the view of rendering them as solemn and as
                    binding on the conscience of the elector as possible. Yet a little examination
                    of them will show that they are well adapted to afford room for a whole host of
                    equivocations. And, in fact, volumes of subtle casuistry have been written on
                    the exact sense of the terms of the cardinal’s oath, and on the degree of
                    literalness in which it must be assumed to be binding on the conscience; <hi
                    rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> it is the opinion of conclave tacticians that an
                    elector may often injure the final chance of success of a candidate by voting
                    for him at those first scrutinies, which are not intended really to result in
                    any election, but are a mere exploring of the ground and trial of strength. Is
                    an elector, then, to injure the chance of the man he deems the fittest to be
                    elected by voting for him at such times î Again a man may, doubtless often does,
                    conscientiously believe himself to be the fittest man to be elected. Must he
                    invalidate his own election by voting for himself 1 Or must he vote for some
                    other, whom he does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> think the fittest man 1 It has
                    been asked, may a man vote for a candidate whom he does not think the fittest
                    man, when it is clear that that candidate will be elected 1 The answer has been
                    in the affirmative, “because it is fitting that an election be made with concord
                    and without giving rise to evil passions.” In fact, it is wellnigh certain that
                    if every elector at every scrutiny voted for the man whom he thought fittest to
                    be elected, there could not be any election by a two-thirds majority at al‡— so
                    absolutely and necessarily a matter of compromise is every election!</p>
                <p>The present practice is for such cardinals as are present in Rome to enter
                    conclave on the tenth day after the Pope’s death. Each cardinal finds a boarded
                    cell constructed in the Quirinal or Vatican,—recently the Quirinal, henceforward
                    necessarily the Vatican,—assigned to him by lot. Every morning and every evening
                    they proceed to a scrutiny, <hi rend="italic">iae.,</hi> to a solemn voting by
                    specially prepared voting papers (which conceal the name of the voter, to be
                    opened only in the case of an election being made at that scrutiny) in the
                    Sistine or in the Paoline Chapel. After each scrutiny an “accessit” takes
                    place;— <hi rend="italic">iae.,</hi> after the number of the votes for each
                    candidate has been declared, it is open to every voter to declare by a similar
                    secret vote that he “accedes” to such or such a candidate. If no election is
                    thus arrived at, the same process is repeated every morning and every evening,
                    till some cardinal is found to have the requisite majority of two-thirds of
                    those who are present, <hi rend="italic">plus</hi> one, the candidate’s own vote
                    being subtracted. Thereupon the ‘ adoration” immediately takes place, and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Habemus Pontificem</hi> is proclaimed <hi rend="italic"
                    >“Urbi</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Orbiſk</hi> (τ. A. τ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
