<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0547-0516-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">COURT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 516</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="45" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:830288">Benches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1091659">Records</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:936105">Functionals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hc3p">Appeal</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n547/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COURT</label>. This name is now usually restricted to
                    judicial tribunals, almost the only exception being the household of the king,
                    which is still called the Court. All courts are not even now purely judicial in
                    character; the County Court, for instance, is still the assembly of the
                    freeholders of the county in which representatives and certain officers are
                    elected. Such assemblies in early times exercised political and legislative as
                    well as judicial functions. But these have now been almost entirely separated
                    everywhere, and only judicial bodies are now usually called courts. In every
                    court, says Blackstone, there must be three parts,—an <hi rend="italic"
                    >actor</hi> or plaintiff, <hi rend="italic">reus</hi> or defendant, and <hi
                    rend="italic">judex,</hi> or judge.</p>
                <p>The language of legal fictions, which English lawyers invariably use in all
                    constitutional subjects, makes the king the ultimate source of all judicial
                    authority, and assumes his personal presence in all the courts.</p>
                <p>“As by our excellent constitution,” says Blackstone, “the sole executive power of
                    the laws is vested in the person of the king, it will follow that all courts of
                    justice, which are the medium by which he administers the laws, are derived from
                    the power of the Crown. For whether created by Act of Parliament or letters
                    patent, or subsisting by prescription (the only methods by which any court of
                    judicature can exist), the king’s consent in the two former is expressly, in the
                    latter impliedly given. In all these courts the king is supposed in
                    contemplation of law to be always present; but as that is in fact impossible, he
                    is then represented by his judges, whose power is only an emanation of the royal
                    prerogative. ’</p>
                <p>These words, which are still printed in modern editions of the commentaries,
                    might give a false impression of the historical and legal relations of the
                    courts and the Crown, if it is not remembered that they are nothing more than
                    the expression of a venerable fiction. The administration of justice was,
                    indeed, one of the functions of the king in early times; the king himself sat on
                    circuit so late ascthe reign of Edward IV.,and even after regular tribunals were
                    established, a reserve of judicial power still remained in the king and his
                    council, in the exercise of which it was possible for the king to participate
                    personally. The last judicial act of an English king, if such it can be called,
                    was that by which James I. settled the dispute between the Court of Chancery and
                    Courts of Common Law, Since the establishment of Parliamentary government the
                    courts take their law directly from the legislature, and the king is only
                    connected with them indirectly as a member of the legislative body. The king’s
                    name, however, is still used in this as in other departments of state action.
                    The courts exercising jurisdiction in England are divided by certain features
                    which may here be briefly indicated.</p>
                <p>1. We may distinguish between courts exercising general and those exercising
                    special jurisdiction. The latter are the Admiralty, Ecclesiastical, and
                    University Courts, the limits of which are sufficiently indicated by their
                    names. These administer principles of justice founded on the canon and civil
                    law, but the extent of their jurisdiction is ascertained by the Common Law
                    Courts. 2. Superior and inferior courts. The former are the Courts of Common Law
                    at Westminster, and the Court of Chancery, now High Court of Justice. The latter
                    are the local or district courts, County Courts, &amp;c. 3, Courts of record and
                    courts not of record. “A court of record is one whereof the Acts and judicial
                    proceedings are enrolled for a perpetual memory and testimony, which rolls are
                    called the records of the court, and are of such high and supereminent
                    authority, that their truth is not to be called in question. For it is a settled
                    rule and maxim that nothing shall be averred against a record, nor shall any
                    plea or even proof be admitted to the contrary. And if the existence of the
                    record shall be denied it shall be tried by nothing but itself; that is, upon
                    bare inspection whether there be any such record or no; else there would be no
                    end of disputes. All courts of record are the courts of the sovereign in right
                    of the Crown and royal dignity, and therefore any court of record has authority
                    to fine and imprison for contempt of its authority” (Stephen’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Blackstone).</hi> 4. Courts may also be distinguished as civil or criminal. 5.
                    A further distinction is to bo made between courts of first instance and courts
                    of appeal. In the former the first hearing in any judicial proceeding takes
                    place; in the latter, the judgment of the first court is brought under review,
                    Of the superior courts, the High Court of Justice in its various divisions is a
                    court of first instance. Over it is the Court of Appeal, and over that again the
                    House of Lords. The High Court of Justice is (through divisional courts) a court
                    of appeal for inferior courts. 6. There is a special class of local courts,
                    which do not appear to fall within either the first or second of the classes
                    above-mentioned. Some, while administering the ordinary municipal law, have or
                    had jurisdiction exclusive of their superior courts; such were the Common Pleas
                    of Durham and Lancaster (now transferred to the High Court of Justice), and such
                    still is the Chancery Court of the duchy of Lancaster. Others have concurrent
                    jurisdiction with the superior courts; such are the Lord Mayor’s Court of
                    London, the Passage Court of Liverpool, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The distribution of judicial business among the various courts may be exhibited
                    as follows.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Criminal Courts;—</hi> 1. The lowest is that of the justice of
                    the peace, sitting singly, but more usuallyin petty sessions of two or more,
                    tode∙ termine in a summary way certain specified minor offences. In populous
                    districts, such as London, Manchester, &amp;c., stipendiary magistrates are
                    appointed, generally with enlarged powers. Besides punishing by summary
                    conviction, justices may commit prisoners for trial at the assizes. 2. The
                    justices in Quarter Sessions are commissioned to determine felonies and other
                    offences. The 5 and 6 Viet c. 38 contains a list of offences <hi rend="italic"
                    >not</hi> triable at Quarter Sessions —treason, murder, forgery, bigamy,
                    &amp;c., (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Quarter Sessions).</hi> The corresponding
                    court in boroughs is presided over by the recorder. 3. The more serious offences
                    are reserved for the judges of the superior courts sitting under a commission of
                    oyer and terminer or gaol delivery for each county. The Assize Courts, as they
                    are called, sit in general in each county twice a year, following the division
                    of circuits; but winter assizes are now held under 39 and 40 Vict. c. 57, which
                    permits several counties to be united together for that purpose. London, which
                    occupies an exceptional position in all matters of judicature, has a high
                    criminal court of its own, established by 4 and 5 Will. IV. c. 36, under the
                    name of tho Central Criminal Court. Its judges usually present are a rota
                    selected from the superior judges of common law, the recorder, common sergeant,
                    and the judge of the City of London Court. The Court of Queen’s Bench (now
                    Queen's Bench Division) has a general superintendence over all other courts of
                    criminal jurisdiction, and criminal cases may be moved into the Queen’s Bench by
                    the writ of <hi rend="italic">certiorari.</hi> By 11 and 12 Vict. c. 78, the
                    Court for Crown Cases Reserved was established, to which any question of law
                    arising on the trial of a prisoner may after conviction be remitted by the judge
                    in his discretion.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Civil Courts.—</hi> In certain special cases, civil claims of
                    small importance may be brought before justices or stipendiaries. Otherwise, and
                    excepting the special and peculiar jurisdictions above mentioned, the civil
                    business of the country may be said to be divided between the County Courts
                    (taking small cases) and the High Court of Justice (taking all others). Before
                    the constitution of the High Court of Justice the judges of the common law
                    courts sat separately with a jury to try cases at Nisi Prius, the sittings being
                    at Westminster for Middlesex, at Guildhall for the City of London, and according
                    to circuits for the rest of the country; and this arrangement is still followed
                    by the divisions corresponding to the common law courts.</p>
                <p>The effect of the recent Judicature Acts on the constitution of the superior
                    courts may be briefly stated. There is now one Supreme Court of Judicature,
                    consisting of two permanent divisions called the High Court of Justice and the
                    Court of Appeal. The former takes the jurisdiction of the Court of Chancery, the
                    three Common Law Courts, the Courts of Admiralty, Probate, and Divorce, the
                    Courts of Pleas at Lancaster and Durham, and the courts created by commissions
                    of assize, oyer and teιminer, and gaol delivery. The latter takes the
                    jurisdiction of the Court of Appeal in Chancery (including Chancery of
                    Lancaster), the Court of the Lord Warden of the Stannaries, and of the Exchequer
                    Chamber, and the appellate jurisdiction in admiralty and heresy-matters of the
                    judicial committee; and power is given to the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n548/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0548-0517"/> Queen to transfer the remaining jurisdiction of
                    that court to the Court of Appeal. By the appellate Jurisdiction Act of 1876,
                    the House of Lords is now enabled to sit for the hearing of appeals from the
                    English Court of Appeal and the Scotch and Irish courts during the prorogation
                    and dissolution of Parliament. The lords of appeal, of whom three must he
                    present, are the lord chancellor, the lords of appeal in ordinary, and peers who
                    have held “high judicial office” in Great Britain or Ireland. The lords in
                    ordinary are an innovation in the constitution of the House. They hold the rank
                    of baron for life only, have a right to sit and vote in the House during tenure
                    of office only, and a salary of £6000 per annum.</p>
                <p>Among obsolete or decayed courts, besides those incidentally mentioned above, the
                    following are the most noticeable :—-</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Court Leet,</hi> an old local court described as the most
                    ancient known to the law. It was a court of record, and exercised civil as well
                    as criminal jurisdiction. Its origin and nature are fully discussed in Seri ven
                    <hi rend="italic">On Copyhold.</hi><hi rend="italic">Court Baron,</hi> the court
                    of a manor, presided over by the lord, and of which the free tenants of the
                    manor are suitors.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Court of</hi><hi rend="italic">Pié Poudre</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(pedis pulverisati),</hi> having jurisdiction in fairs and markets.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Court of Chivalry,</hi> or Knights’ Court, held by the lord
                    high constable, in matters relating to jousts and tournaments.</p>
                <p>The Court of the Marshalsea of the Household of the Kings of England, and the
                    Court of our Lady the Queen, of the Palace of the Queen at Westminster, and Her
                    Majesty’s Court of Record for the Honour of Peveril are abolished by the 12 and
                    13 Viet, c. 101.</p>
                <p>The history of English courts affords a remarkable illustration of the continuity
                    that characterizes our institutions. It would hardly be too much to say that all
                    the courts now sitting in England may be traced back to a common origin, and at
                    any rate the higher courts are all offshoots from the same original judicature.
                    Leaving out of account the local courts, we find the higher jurisdiction after
                    the Conquest concentrated along with all other public functions in the king and
                    council. The first sign of a separation of the judicial from the other powers of
                    this body is found in the recognition of a Curia Regis, which may be described
                    as the king’s council, or a portion of it, charged specially with the management
                    of judicial and revenue business. In relation to the revenue it became the
                    Exchequer, under which name a separate court grew up whose special field was the
                    judicial business arising out of revenue cases. By the Great Charter, the
                    inconvenience caused by the curia following the king’s person was remedied, in
                    so far as private litigation was concerned, by the order that common pleas
                    (Communia Placita) should be held at some fixed place; and hence arose the Court
                    of Common Pleas. The Curia Regis, after having thrown off these branches, is
                    represented by the Queen’s Bench, so that from the same stock we have now three
                    courts, differing at first in functions, but through competition for business,
                    and the ingenious use of fictions, becoming finally the coordinate Courts of
                    Common Law of our later history. Tn one line of development the council becomes,
                    by the addition of representatives from counties and boroughs, the Parliament in
                    its two Houses of Lords and Commons. But an inner circle of counsellors still
                    surrounded the king, and in his name claimed to exercise judicial as well as
                    other power; hence the chancellor’s jurisdiction, wſhich became, partly in
                    harmony with the supra-legal power claimed from which it sprang, and partly
                    through the influence of the ecclesiastical chancellors by whom it was first
                    administered, the Equity of English law. Similar developments of the same
                    authority were the Court of Requests (which was destroyed by a decision of the
                    Common Pleas) and the Court of Star Chamber,—a Court of Criminal Equity, as it
                    has been called, which, having been made the instrument of tyranny, was
                    abolished in 1641. Even then the productive power of the council was not
                    exhausted; the judicial committee of the Privy Council, established by 2 and 3
                    Will. IV. c. 92, superseding tho previous Court of Delegates, exercises the
                    jurisdiction in appeal belonging to the king in cou::cil.</p>
                <p>The appellate jurisdiction of the Lords rests on their claim to be the
                    representatives of the ancient great council of the realm. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(e. r.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
