<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0541-0510-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">COUNCIL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 510</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn8z">Synods</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p527">Basel</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1085685">Questioning</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:937256">Gallicanism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n541/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COUNCIL</label>. Early in its history the Christian church
                    gave outward expression to a sense of the mutual dependence of its members by
                    summoning Councils, or Synods, where on common ground the spokesmen of the
                    Christian community sought, w ith zeal and acumen, but often not without
                    passion, prejudice, and diplomacy all too human, to discover the mind of the
                    Spirit. There prevailing practices were approved or reprehended, and the dim
                    persuasions of the few or the many were sharpened into dogmatic statement
                    binding on all. On the great movements of Christian thought, much has ever been
                    reserved for individuals to accomplish, the collective church gradually and
                    unofficially recognizing the indefeasible power of some one spiritual or
                    ecclesiastical genius; but the councils have deeply left their mark on the
                    doctrine and on the constitution c,f the church. The minor synods, forming a
                    well-balanced system of regularly recurring assemblies, served as an important
                    organ for the administration of ecclesiastical business; and the greater
                    councils, summoned to meet pressing emergencies, often proved turning-points in
                    the church’s history. At them the pulse of the visible church beat high. The
                    councils have not inaptly been called “the pitched battles of church history;”
                    but while they have at times caused the forces of the heretics to draw more
                    closely together, and have more than once precipitated schism, or rendered it
                    more determined and persistent, it is not the less true that the synods of the
                    church universal have been her great legislative assemblies, when discussion and
                    decision, more or less full and deliberate, have restored into one channel the
                    main stream of ecclesiastical life, and have brought home, alike to those within
                    and to those without the pale, a sense of the church’s corporate oneness.</p>
                <p>It is characteristic of the church of Christ that it was left free to mould its
                    constitution according to its circumstances. The founders of Christianity left
                    no detailed constitutional code. And as in other regards, so it was here;
                    neither Christ nor the apostles prescribed a synodal system for the infant
                    church, or enacted when and where councils should assemble, how they should be
                    constituted, and what they should determine. Much zealous labour has been spent
                    in proving that the councils, even as a developed organization, are a divine
                    institution,—a difficult task certainly, if it be necessary to agree that what
                    is human is therefore not divine, but accidental and “invented.” The most
                    various Christian parties have with one consent sought the prototype of all
                    Christian councils in that assembled at Jerusalem under the apostles; and from
                    its scanty record in Acts. xv. (the other apostolic assemblies reported in Acts
                    i., vi., xxi., being passed by as irrelevant) the advocates of the most
                    divergent systems have extracted precise rules for the convening and the
                    guidance of ecclesiastical assemblies. But even if we fully accept the
                    historical accuracy of the report, it is impossible to decide with certainty the
                    relation of the apostles to the “presbyters,” and of both to the “brethren;” and
                    the decree embodying the decision of the Jerusalem Council contains rather a
                    practical compromise, the arrangement of a <hi rend="italic">modus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">vivendi</hi> in the spirit of peace and mutual forbearance, than a
                    final settlement on grounds of principle of the grave and long-lasting problem
                    as to what should be the relations between the new Christian church and the old
                    Jewish law. It points to temporary concession, not to the formulation of a
                    permanent creed.</p>
                <p>It is not till after the middle of the 2d century that we find the example of
                    Jerusalem followed, and councils called to solve questions that threatened the
                    unity and well-being of the Christian church and community. The earliest
                    councils historically attested are those convened in Asia Minor against the
                    Montanists; though it is by no means unlikely that at a much earlier period the
                    Christian Greeks gave scope, in ecclesiastical affairs, to their instinct for
                    organization, for taking common action in regard to matters affecting the public
                    good. Near the end of the 2d century again, varying views as to the celebration
                    of Easter led to councils in Palestine, at Borne, in Pontus, Gaul, Mesopotamia,
                    and at Ephesus. These councils were all specially called to consider particular
                    questions. But before the middle of the 3d century, it seems that in Asia Minor
                    at least the councils or synods had become a standing institution, and met
                    yearly. About the same time we find councils in the Latin Church of North
                    Africa. Before the end of this century there were councils meeting regularly in
                    almost every province in Christendom, from Spain and Gaul to Arabia and
                    Mesopotamia; and by extension and further organization, there was soon formed a
                    system of mutually correspondent synods that gave to the church the aspect of a
                    federative republic.</p>
                <p>The developing episcopal system suggested plainly enough a gradation of rank and
                    functions for the various synods. A synod composed of all the clergy under one
                    bishop, with their bishop as president, stood at the bottom, of the scale, and
                    is commonly named the <hi rend="italic">diocesan</hi> synod. The <hi
                    rend="italic">metropolitan</hi> synod, or <hi rend="italic">provincial</hi>
                    council, met under the presidency of the metropolitan, and included all the
                    bishops of his ecclesiastical province. Such metropolitan synods the Council of
                    Nicaea recommended to be held, twice a year. When all the bishops of a
                    patriarchate met under the patriarch, or all those of a nation under its primate
                    or first metropolitan, the council was <hi rend="italic">patriarchal</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">national</hi> or <hi rend="italic">primatial</hi> (not
                    infrequently termed <hi rend="italic">concilium generale</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">plenarium).</hi> Occasionally the bishops of adjoining provinces
                    met, the senior metropolitan presiding, for the consideration of matters common
                    to a district of wider area than the one ecclesiastical province. The συvoδoι
                    tvδyp,ovσαt held at Constantinople by the metropolitan, who invited as many
                    bishops to meet him as chanced to be then in the city, though not irregular,
                    corresponded to no territorial division of the church. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Concilia mixta,</hi> held chiefly during the Middle Ages in Germany, England,
                    Spain, and Italy, were constituted not less of temporal than of spiritual
                    princes, and resolved questions not solely ecclesiastical. <hi rend="italic"
                    >General</hi> synod was usually the name for an assembly of the bishops from all
                    portions either of the Western or of the Oriental division of the church. Such a
                    synod was that of Arles, whither, in 314 A.D., Constantine summoned the bishops
                    of the Western Church. But the minor councils were soon overshadowed by the <hi
                    rend="italic">oecumenical</hi> councils, at which the whole of Christendom was
                    held to be represented, and which by universal agreement came ultimately to be
                    regarded as having authority for the whole church.</p>
                <p>At the diocesan synods, presbyters were members as well as the bishop, but they
                    had only a <hi rend="italic">votum</hi><hi rend="italic">consιdtativum.</hi> The
                    regular members of the higher synods were the bishops alone or their
                    representatives, and exercised the <hi rend="italic">votum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >decisivum.</hi> But other clergy, deacons, doctors of theology and of canon
                    law, and abbots, were invited to assist the bishops with their advice, and it
                    seems that sometimes at least the abbots were permitted to give a decisive vote.
                    Laics, especially emperors, kings, and their commissioners, were often present,
                    and to some English councils even abbesses were admitted. Save at the Councils
                    of Constance and Basel, the voting was by count of heads; but at Const nice the
                    voting was according to nations, in order to counteract the numerical
                    predominance of the Italian Bishops. A similar method was adopted at the Council
                    of Basel.</p>
                <p>It has never been settled beyond dispute which of the councils are to be regarded
                    as truly and authoritatively rtq presentative of the Christian <hi rend="italic"
                    >oi.Kovpi.vq.</hi> And of those that may fairly be called oecumenical, one
                    differs widely from <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n542/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0542-0511"/> another not merely in its catholicity of spirit
                    and in the abiding interest of the questions discussed, but in the width of area
                    from which its members were drawn, and the extent •of territory throughout which
                    its authority was at the time recognized. At the earliest universal councils the
                    representatives of the Western Church were a small minority; at Nicaea hardly 10
                    of the 318 (?) bishops were of the Latinspeaking church. The council at
                    Constantinople in 381 was at first only a general synod of the Oriental church;
                    and it was not till the Gth century that it was recognized as oecumenical in the
                    West. Some councils, such as those summoned to Pavia and Siena, were designed to
                    be oecumenical, but led to no such result. The whole Greek Church acknowledges
                    still but seven oecumenical councils. The English Church after the Reformation
                    practically recognized the first five. The doctrinal definitions of the first
                    four councils became the common property of the churches of the Reformation, but
                    Protestant authors rarely refer to the later councils save polemically. The
                    Latins even are not entirely agreed amongst themselves. The claims of the
                    council at Sardica in 393 to universal authority have been asserted but seldom
                    conceded. Some Catholics have protested against the aecumenicity of the synod in
                    1311 at Vienne, generally reckoned the 15th oecumenical. Most Catholics,
                    including some of those most anxious to promote reforms, refused to admit the
                    Gallican claim in favour of the council summoned to Pisa in 1409; and its rank
                    as a universal council has never been allowed by the most approved Catholic
                    theologians. The Gallicans wished to have the Council of Constance recognized as
                    oecumenical throughout; good Catholics acknowledge only the sittings held after
                    Pope Martin V. was chosen, or such earlier decrees as were afterwards sanctioned
                    by this Pope. Some Gallicans regard the Council of Basel as oecumenical from
                    beginning to end; most insist on regarding it as legitimate only till it was
                    transferred to Ferrara; many Catholics, amongst others Bellarmine, decline to
                    admit the aecumenicity of any of its decrees. The Council of Ferrara-Florence, a
                    Papal continuation of that at Basel, was at first protested against by the
                    Gallican party, but is fully accepted by most Catholic theologians and
                    canonists. The Gallicans were also slow to admit the binding authority of the
                    5th Lateran synod, the 18th oecumenical council.</p>
                <p>The question as to the number of councils is naturally of most consequence to the
                    only section of the church that still assumes the right to summon councils and
                    to call them oecumenical. The view that prevails in the Roman Catholic Church
                    may best be shown by giving a list of the councils accepted as oecumenical by
                    Hefele <hi rend="italic">(Conciliengeschiclde,</hi> 2d ed. vol. i. pp. 59,
                    60).</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The Council at Nicaea -</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>A.D.</p><p>325</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 1st Council at
                            Constantinople...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>381</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The Council at Ephesus</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>431</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The Council at Chalcedon</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>451</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 2d at Constantinople</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>553</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 3d at Constantinople</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>680</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 2d at Nicaea</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>787</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 4th at Constantinople</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>869</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 1st Lateran Council</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1123</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 2d Lateran Council</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1139</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 3d Lateran Council</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1179</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 4th Lateran Council</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1215</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 1st Council at Lyons</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1245</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 2d Council at Lyons</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1274</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The Council at Vienne</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1311</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The Council of Constance
                            (partially)</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1414-1418</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>17α.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The Council of Basel
                            (partially)</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1431-1438</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>175.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The Council of Ferrara-Florence
                            (a</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>continuation of that at
                            Basel)....</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1438-1442</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>18.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The 5th Lateran Council</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1512-1517</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>19.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The Council of Trent</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1545-1563</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Vatican Council</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1869-1870</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>These oecumenical councils fall naturally into several groups or series. The
                    first eight, including that at Constantinople in 869, were summoned by the
                    emperors, all the later ones by the popes,—and this though the analogy of the
                    inferior councils seems to demand that the representative assemblies of the
                    universal church should be summoned by the head of the church alone. Catholics
                    always assert that no council can be oecumenical unless called by the Pope, or
                    by a temporal prince with and by the Pope’s assent obtained before or after; and
                    Catholic authors have been at pains to attempt a proof that, even at the
                    councils undoubtedly summoned by the emperors, the bishop of Rome stood to the
                    calling of them in a relation different from that of the other patriarchs. In
                    the case of the 3d oecumenical council, for example, Hefele contends that the
                    Pope did not merely, like the other bishops, passively assent, but actively
                    sanctioned the summons.</p>
                <p>The exclusive right of the popes to preside was^ unhesitatingly admitted at all
                    the later councils; but at the earlier ones, where manifestly emperors,
                    empresses, or their commissioncts were the formal presidents, Catholic canonists
                    have persuaded themselves that such presidency was merely in regard to external
                    matters, and that the true president was always episcopal. Even at the Council
                    of Nicaea, they argue, Hosius and the two Roman presbyters who signed the
                    decrees first must have done so as deputies of the Roman bishop, and as such
                    must have been the true presidents.</p>
                <p>The first eight councils differed from the rest in that, whereas all others met
                    within the bounds of the Western Church, they were all held in the East.
                    Further, the great majority of those who attended them were Greeks, and spoke
                    Greek alone; and the chief subjects of debate at several turned on distinctions
                    not safely translatable into the Western tongues. The first six of these eight
                    councils were occupied mainly, though by no means exclusively, with aspects of
                    the great trinitarian and christological controversies, and their decrees are
                    accordingly of high dogmatical interest.</p>
                <p>Of councils held in the West a well-defined sub-group includes the 9th (the lst
                    Lateran) to the 15th (at Vienne in 1311). The first of these is significantly
                    enough concerned with the dispute about the right of investiture; and though
                    some of this series of seven discussed or defined dogmas, as did the brilliant
                    4th Lateran Council, they were for the most part busied with matters pertaining
                    to the rights and dignity of the popes and with questions concerning their
                    election. Indeed several of them have less the aspect of free and independent
                    councils than of assemblies gathered for the official ratification of the
                    proceedings of Pope and Curia.</p>
                <p>The reasons for the calling of universal synods are of various kinds. When a
                    serious heresy or schism has arisen, when it is doubtful w <hi
                    rend="superscript"> j</hi> hich of two opposing popes is legitimate, when it is
                    proposed to undertake some grand design against the enemies of the church, when
                    the Popo is accused of heresy or other grave fault, when the cardinals will not
                    or cannot elect a Pope, and when a root and branch reformation of the church is
                    in view,—councils may or must be summoned. It was the last of these grounds for
                    assembling the universal church that led to tho 16th, 17th, and 18th oecumenical
                    councils; and the 19th, that of Trent, though the sufficiency of the reforms
                    agreed to by it was unanimously denied by Protestant reformers, must also be
                    reckoned amongst the reforming councils.</p>
                <p>The Vatican Council is the last of those claiming to be oecumenical; and in
                    decreeing the infallibility of the Pope, it has appeared to many that the 20th
                    council has shown cause why, for all essential purposes, there needs never bo
                    another. The very institution of councils seems in itself an admission that
                    apart from them there was no source of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n543/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0543-0512"/> accessible and infallible authority on disputed
                    points. If the assembly at Jerusalem was really a council, then even where Paul
                    and at least one of the original twelve apostles were present, the settlement of
                    a question with vast doctrinal and practical issues was arrived at by means of
                    open debate amongst the members of the synod. Unhesitating belief in frequent
                    and miraculous manifestations of the divine will was universal for centuries;
                    yet when the illumination of the Holy Spirit was most urgently needed for the
                    establishment of Christian truth, recourse was had to the collective opinion of
                    assembled representatives, to discussion more or less calm and candid, and to
                    the counting of votes,—a most noteworthy feature in the development of the
                    church. And it deserves to be remarked that thus, in times of allembracing
                    despotism, the church secured for the representatives of the Christian community
                    one side of corporate and individual freedom, a measure of independence such as
                    could not fail to keep alive a feeling hostile to the extension of imperial,
                    though Christian, tyranny into at least one of the provinces of thought and
                    action.</p>
                <p>The infallibility of universal councils, ultimately admitted by the whole
                    Catholic Church, was early claimed. “It seemed good to the Holy Ghost and to
                    us,” words occurring in the Jerusalem decree, could not but suggest to the
                    successors of the apostles that the synods assembled under them were favoured by
                    the special superintendence of the Holy Ghost; and this was distinctly asserted
                    by Cyprian. But the sanction of the Pope has always been held by modern
                    Catholics as necessary to the infallibility of any council; and the decrees even
                    of the minor councils attain to infallibility if approved by the Pope and
                    accepted by the church at large. A limitation of synodical authority that merely
                    recognized the Pope as an integral part of the church might be agreed to even by
                    those who asserted that oecumenical councils are superior to the popes, a theory
                    long and vehemently contended for and against in the church. That the councils
                    are above the popes was the view of the Councils of Constance and Basel, and was
                    formulated as one of the four Gallican propositions; whereas at the 5th Lateran
                    Council Pope Leo X. roundly asserted the authority of the Pope over all
                    councils.</p>
                <p>Yet the infallibility of universal councils w as most confidently accepted by the
                    very parties in the church which were least disposed to concede absolute
                    authority to any other ecclesiastical institution,—notably by the Gallicans and
                    by the German Reformers in the early stages of the Reformation. And the
                    institution of councils, both of occasional councils called for special purposes
                    and of those meeting statedly, was inherited by the Protestant churches. The
                    Synod of Dort is an instance of a general council of churches adhering to the
                    Reformed confessions; the Westminster Assembly was designed to be a national
                    council. It is of course in the Presbyterian churches that councils have
                    received their most systematic development, and, without claiming infallible
                    authority, retain the most extended powers as legislative, administrative, and
                    judicial. In the Church of Scotland the regular gradation of kirk sessions,
                    presbyteries, provincial synods, and general assembly of representative
                    ministers and elders supervises and regulates all the functions of the church,
                    and forms a compact and balanced system of constitutional government. In
                    non-presbyterian churches synods have various degrees of deliberative or
                    decisive authority. Even now the reorganization of the synodical system of the
                    United Protestant Church of Prussia is regarded both by churchmen and by
                    statesmen in Germany as one of the ecclesiastical questions of the day.</p>
                <p>The chief collections of the Acts of the Councils of the Catholic Church are that
                    by Hardouin, published at Paris in 1715 in 12 folios and. the still more
                    complete one by Mansi (Floι <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> cnce and</p>
                <p>Venice, 1758-1799) in 31 folio vols, but extending only to the 15th century. By
                    far the most elaborate recent work on the Councils is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Conciliengeschichte</hi> of Dr Hefele, bishop of Rottenburg (7 vols. 1st ed.
                    1⅛55-1874; 2d ed. 1873, <hi rend="italic">sqq.</hi><hi rend="italic">).</hi> (D.
                    P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
