<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0109-0090-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COBRA (9th edition, volume 6, page 90)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v97zt6b">Poisoners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3821v">Poisons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cs62">Hoods</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43r0q26k">Snakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1068139">Poisoners</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068184">Poisons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068142">Poisoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1121833">Snakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032283">Najas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865969">Cobras</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n109/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COBRA</label><hi rend="italic">(Naja</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >tripudians),</hi> a poisonous Colubrine Snake, belonging to the family <hi
                        rend="italic">Elapidae,</hi> known also as the Hooded Snake, or Cobra di
                    Capello. In this species the anterior ribs are elongated, and by raising and
                    bringing forward these, the neck, which otherwise is not distinct from the head,
                    can be expanded at will into a broad disc or hood, the markings on which bear a
                    striking resemblance to a pair of barnacles, hence the name “Spectacle Snake”
                    also applied to the cobra. It possesses two rows of palatine teeth in the upper
                    jaw, while the maxillary bones bear the fangs, of which the anterior one only is
                    in connection with the poison gland, the others in various stages of growth
                    remaining loose in the surrounding flesh until the destruction of the poison
                    fang brings the one immediately behind to the front, which then gets auchylosed
                    to the maxillary bone, and into connection with the gland secreting the poison,
                    which in the cobra is about the size of an almond. Behind the poison fangs there
                    are usually one or two ordinary teeth. The cobra attains a length of nearly 6
                    feet and a girth of about 6 inches, and with the exception of the markings on
                    the hood is of a uniform brown colour above and bluish-white beneath. There are,
                    however, many distinct varieties, in some of which the spectacle markings on the
                    hood are awanting. The cobra may be regarded as nocturnal in its habits, being
                    most active by night, although not unfrequently found in motion during the day.
                    It usually conceals itself under logs of wood, ⅛ the roofs of huts, and in holes
                    in old walls and ruins, "where it is often come upon inadvertently, inflicting a
                    death wound before it has been observed. It feeds on small quadrupeds, frogs,
                    lizards, insects, and the eggs of birds, in search of which it sometimes ascends
                    trees. When seeking its prey it glides slowly along the ground, holding the
                    anterior third of its body aloft, with its hood distended, on the alert for
                    anything that may come in its way. “This attitude,” says Sir J. Fayrer, “is very
                    striking, and few objects are more calculated to inspire awe than a large cobra
                    when, with his hood erect, hissing loudly, and his eyes glaring, he prepares to
                    strike.” It is said to drink large quantities of water, although, like reptiles
                    iu general it will live for many months without food or drink. The cobra is
                    oviparous; and its eggs, which are from 18 to 25 in number, are of a pure white
                    colour, somewhat resembling in size and appearance the eggs of the pigeon, but
                    sometimes larger. These it leaves to be hatched by the heat of the sun. It is
                    found in all parts of India from Ceylon to the Himalayas, where it occurs at a
                    height of 800.0 feet, and it is justly regarded as the most deadly of the Indian
                    Thanatophidia. A large proportion of the deaths from snake bite, where the
                    species inflicting the wound has been ascertained, is shown to be due to the
                    cobra; and it is estimated that fully one-half of the 20,000 deaths that
                    annually occur in India from this cause may be attributed to this unluckily
                    common species. The bite of a vigorous cobra will often prove fatal in a few
                    minutes, and as there is no known antidote to the poison, it is only in rare
                    instances that such mechanical expedients as cauterizing, constriction, or
                    amputation can be applied with sufficient promptitude to prevent the virus from
                    entering the circulation. Of late years, owing to a small reward offered by the
                    Indian Government for the head of each poisonous snake, great numbers of cobras
                    have been destroyed; but only low caste Hindus will engage in such work the
                    cobra being regarded by the natives generally with superstitious reverence, as a
                    divinity powerful to injure, and therefore to be propitiated; and thus
                    oftentimes when found in their dwellings this snake is allowed to remain, and is
                    fed and protected. “Should fear,” says Sir J. Fayrer, “and perhaps the death of
                    some inmate bitten by accident prove stronger than superstition, it may be
                    caught.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n110/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0110-0091"/>
                <p>tenderly handled, and deported to some field, where it is released and allowed to
                    depart in peace, not killed” <hi rend="italic">(Thanatoqshidia of India).</hi>
                    Great numbers, especially of young cobras, are killed by the adjutant birds and
                    by the mungoos—a small mammal which attacks it with impunity, apparently not
                    from want of susceptibility to the poison, but by its dexterity in eluding the
                    bite of the cobra. Mere scratching or tearing does not appear to be sufficient
                    to bring the poison from the glands; it is only when the fangs are firmly
                    implanted by the jaws being pressed together that the virus enters the wound,
                    and in those circumstances it has been shown by actual experiment that the
                    mungoos, like all other warm-blooded animals, succumbs to the poison. In the
                    case of reptiles, the cobra poison takes effect much more slowly, while it has
                    been proved to have no effect whatever on other venomous serpents. The cobra is
                    the snake usually exhibited by the Indian jugglers, who show great dexterity in
                    handling it, even when not deprived of its fangs. Usually, however, the front
                    fang at least is extracted, the creature being thus rendered harmless until the
                    succeeding tooth takes its place, and in many cases all the fangs, with the
                    germs behind, are removed—the cobra being thus rendered innocuous for life. The
                    snake charmer usually plays a few simple notes on the flute, and the cobra,
                    apparently delighted, rears half its length in the air and sways its head and
                    body about, keeping time to the music. The cobra, like almost all poisonous
                    snakes, is by no means aggressive, and when it gets timely warning of the
                    approach of man endeavours to get out of his way. It is only when trampled upon
                    inadvertently, or otherwise irritated, that it attempts to use its fangs. It is
                    a good swimmer, often crossing broad rivers, and probably even narrow arms of
                    the sea, for it has been met with at sea at least a quarter of a mile from
                    land.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
