<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0702-0669-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CRYPTOGRAPHY (9th edition, volume 6, page 669)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659h24">Ciphers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4g44hq0f">Cipher</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x770">Vanes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dk8v">Secretion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:861549">Ciphers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018631">Methodism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n702/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CRYPTOGRAPHY</label> (from <hi rend="italic">κpvπτtιv,</hi>
                    to hide), or writing in cipher (from Arabic <hi rend="italic">ciſr,</hi> empty,
                    void), called also steganography (from <hi rend="italic">στeyavη,</hi> a
                    covering), is the art of writing messages, &amp;c., in such a way as to be
                    understood by those only who possess the key to the characters employed. The
                    unravelling of the writing is called deciphering. Cryptography having become a
                    distinct art, Bacon classed it (under the name <hi rend="italic">ciphers)</hi>
                    as a part of grammar. Secret modes of communication have been in use from the
                    earliest times. The Lacedemonians, according to Plutarch, had a method which has
                    been called the <hi rend="italic">scytale,</hi> from the staff <hi rend="italic"
                        >(σκvτaλη)</hi> employed in constructing and deciphering the message. When
                    the Spartan ephors wished to forward their orders to their commanders abroad,
                    they wound slantwise a narrow strip of parchment upon the σκυταλy so that the
                    edges met close together, and the message was then added in such a way that the
                    centre of the line of writing was on the edges of the parchment. When unwound
                    the scroll consisted of broken letters; and in that condition it was despatched
                    to its destination, the general to whose hands it came deciphering it by means
                    of a <hi rend="italic">σκvτaλη</hi> exactly corresponding to that used by the
                    ephors. Polybius has enumerated other methods of cryptð-graphy.</p>
                <p>The art was in use also amongst the Romans. Upon the revival of letters methods
                    of secret correspondence were introduced into private business, diplomacy,
                    plots, &lt;fcc.; and as the study of this art has always presented attractions
                    to the ingenious, a curious body of literature has been the result.</p>
                <p>John Trithemius, the abbot of Spanheim, was the first important writer on
                    cryptography. His <hi rend="italic">Poligraphia,</hi> published in 1500, has
                    passed through many editions, and has supplied the basis upon which subsequent
                    writers have worked. It was begun at the desire of the duke of Bavaria; <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n703/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0703-0670"/> but Trithemius did not at first intend to
                    publish it, on the ground that it would be injurious to public interests. The
                    next treatises of importance were those of John Baptist Porta, a Neapolitan
                    mathematician, who wrote <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >furtivis</hi><hi rend="italic">literarum</hi><hi rend="italic">notis,</hi>
                    1563; and of Blaise de Vigenere, whose <hi rend="italic">Traité des
                        chiffres</hi> appeared in Paris, 1587. Lord Verulam proposed an ingenious
                    system of cryptography on the plan of what is called the double cipher; but
                    while thus lending to the art the influence of his great name, he gave an
                    intimation as to the general opinion formed of it and as to the classes of men
                    who used it. For when prosecuting the earl of Somerset in the matter of the
                    poisoning of Overbury, he urged it as an aggravation of the crime that the earl
                    and Overbury “had cyphers and jargons for the king and queen and all the great
                    men,—things seldom used but either by princes and their ambassadors and
                    ministers, or by such as work or practise against or, at least, upon princes.”
                    Other eminent Englishmen were afterwards connected with the art. John Wilkins,
                    subsequently bishop of Chester, published in 1641 an anonymous treatise entitled
                        <hi rend="italic">Mercury, or The Secret and Swift Messenger,—</hi> a small
                    but comprehensive work on the subject, and a timely gift to the diplomatists and
                    leaders of the civil war. The deciphering of many of the royalist papers of that
                    period, such as the letters that fell into the hands of the Parliament at the
                    battle of Naseby, has by Henry Stubbe been charged on the celebrated
                    mathematican Dr John Wallis <hi rend="italic">(Athen.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Oxon.,</hi> iii. 1072), whose connection with the subject of cipher-writing
                    is referred to by himself in the Oxford edition of his mathematical works, 1689,
                    page 659; as also by John Davys. Dr Wallis elsewhere states that this art,
                    formerly scarcely known to any but the secretaries of princes, &lt;fcc., had
                    grown very common and familiar during the civil commotions, “so that now there
                    is scarce a person of quality but is more or less acquainted with it, and doth,
                    as there is occasion, make use of it.” Subsequent writers on the subject are
                    John Falconer <hi rend="italic">(Cryptomenysis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Patefacta),</hi> 1685; John Davys <hi rend="italic">(An Essay on the Art of
                        Decyphering: in which is inserted a Discourse of Dr Wallis),</hi> 1737;
                    Philip Thicknesse <hi rend="italic">(A Treatise on the Art of</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Decyγ&gt;hering</hi><hi rend="italic">and of Writing in
                        Cypher),</hi> 1772; William Blair (the writer of the comprehensive article
                    “Cipher” in Rees’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia),</hi> 1819; and G. von Marten
                        <hi rend="italic">(Cours Diplomatique),</hi> 1801 (a fourth edition of which
                    appeared in 1851). Perhaps the best modern work on this subject is the <hi
                        rend="italic">Kryptographik</hi> of J. L. Kliiber (Tübingen, 1809), who was
                    drawn into the investigation by inclination and official circumstances. In this
                    work the different methods of cryptography are classified. Amongst others of
                    lesser merit who have treated on this art, may be named Gustavus Selenus <hi
                        rend="italic">(iae.,</hi> Augustus, duke of Brunswick), 1624; Cospi,
                    translated by Niceron in 1641; the marquis of Worcester, 1659; Kircher, 1663;
                    Schott, 1665; Hiller, 1682; Comiers, 1690; Baring, 1737; Conrad, 1739,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>Schemes of cryptography are endless in their variety. Bacon lays down the
                    following as the “virtues” to be looked for in them :—“that they be not
                    laborious to write and read; that they be impossible to decipher; and, in some
                    cases, that they be without suspicion.” These principles are more or less
                    disregarded by all the modes that have been advanced, including that of Bacon
                    himself, which has been unduly extolled by his admirers as “one of the most
                    ingenious methods of writing in cypher, and the most difficult to be decyphered,
                    of any yet contrived” (Thicknesse, p. 13).</p>
                <p>The simplest and commonest of all the ciphers is that in which the writer selects
                    in place of the proper letters certain other letters in regular advance. This
                    method of transposition was used by Julius Caesar. He “per quartam elementorum
                    literam,” wrote <hi rend="italic">d</hi> for <hi rend="italic">a, e</hi> for <hi
                        rend="italic">b,</hi> and so on.</p>
                <p>There are instances of this arrangement in the Jewish rabbis, and even in the
                    sacred writers. An illustration of it occurs in Jeremiah (xxv. 26), where the
                    prophet, to conceal the meaning of his prediction from all but the initiated,
                    writes <hi rend="italic">Sheshach</hi> instead of Babel (Babylon), the place
                    meant; <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> in place of using the second and twelfth
                    letters of the Hebrew alphabet <hi rend="italic">(b, b,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >I)</hi> from the beginning, he wrote the second and twelfth <hi
                        rend="italic">(sh, sh, ch)</hi> from the end. To this kind of cipher-writing
                    Buxtorf gives the name Athbash (from <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> the first letter
                    of the Hebrew alphabet, and <hi rend="italic">th</hi> the last; <hi
                        rend="italic">b</hi> the second from the beginning, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >h</hi> the second from the end). Another Jewish cabalism of like nature was
                    called Albarn; of which an example is in Isaiah vii. 6, where Tabeal is written
                    for Remaliah. In its adaptation to English this method of transposition, of
                    which there are many modifications, is comparatively easy to decipher. A rough
                    key may be derived from an examination of the respective quantities of letters
                    in a typefounder’s bill, or a printer’s “case.” The decipherer’s first business
                    is to classify the letters of the secret message in the order of their
                    frequency. The letter that occurs oftenest is e; and the next in order of
                    frequency is <hi rend="italic">t.</hi> The following groups come after these,
                    separated from each other by degrees of decreasing recurrence:— <hi
                        rend="italic">a, o, n,</hi><hi rend="italic">i;</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >r,</hi><hi rend="italic">s, h;</hi><hi rend="italic">d, I; c, w, u, m; f,
                        y, g,</hi><hi rend="italic">p,</hi><hi rend="italic">b;</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">v,^k</hi><hi rend="italic">; x, q, j, z.</hi> All the single
                    letters must be <hi rend="italic">a, I,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">0.</hi>
                    Letters occurring together are <hi rend="italic">ee, oo, ff, ll, ss,</hi>
                    &amp;c. The commonest words of two letters are (roughly arranged in the order of
                    their frequency) <hi rend="italic">of, to, in, it, is, be, he, by, or, as, at,
                        an, so,</hi> Ac. The commonest words of three letters are <hi rend="italic"
                        >the</hi> and <hi rend="italic">and</hi> (in great excess), <hi
                        rend="italic">for, are, but, all, not,</hi> Ac.; and of four letters— <hi
                        rend="italic">that, with, from, have, this, they,</hi> &amp;c. Familiarity
                    with the composition of the language will suggest numerous other points that are
                    of value to the decipherer. He may obtain other hints from Poe’s tale called <hi
                        rend="italic">The Gold Bug.</hi> As to messages in the Continental languages
                    constructed upon this system of transposition, rules for deciphering may be
                    derived from Breithaupt’s <hi rend="italic">Ars</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >decifratoria,</hi> 1737, and other treatises.</p>
                <p>Bacon remarks that though ciphers were commonly in letters and alphabets yet they
                    might be in words. Upon this basis codes have been constructed, classified words
                    taken from dictionaries being made, to represent complete ideas. In recent years
                    such codes have been adapted by merchants and others to communications by
                    telegraph, and have served the purpose not only of keeping business affairs
                    private, but also of reducing the excessive cost of telegraphic messages to
                    distant markets. Obviously this class of ciphers presents greater difficulties
                    to the skill of the decipherer.</p>
                <p>Figures and other characters have been also used as letters; and with them ranges
                    of numerals have been combined as the representatives of syllables, parts of
                    words, words themselves, and complete phrases. Under this head must be placed
                    the despatches of Giovanni Michael, the Venetian ambassador to England in the
                    reign of Queen Mary,—documents which have only of late years been deciphered.
                    Many of the private letters and papers from the pen of Charles I. and his queen,
                    who were adepts in the use of ciphers, are of the same description. One of that
                    monarch’s letters, a document of considerable interest, consisting entirely of
                    numerals purposely complicated, was in 1858 deciphered by Professor Wheatstone,
                    the inventor of the ingenious crypto-machine, and printed by the Philobiblon
                    Society. Other letters of the like character have been published in the <hi
                        rend="italic">First Report of the Royal Commission on Historical
                        Manuscripts,</hi> 1870. In the second and subsequent reports of the same
                    commission, several keys to ciphers have been catalogued, which seem to refer
                    themselves to the methods of cryptography under <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n704/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0704-0671"/> notice. In this connection also should be
                    mentioned the “characters,” which the diarist Pepys drew up when clerk to Sir
                    George Downing and secretary to the earl of Sandwich and to the Admiralty, and
                    which are frequently mentioned in his journal. Pepys describes one of them as “a
                    great large character,” over which he spent much time, but which was at length
                    finished, 25th April 1660; “it being,” says he, “very handsomely done and a very
                    good one in itself, but that not truly alphabetical.”</p>
                <p>Shorthand marks and other arbitrary characters have also been largely imported
                    into cryptographic systems to represent both letters and words, but more
                    commonly the latter. This plan is said to have been first put into use by the
                    old Roman poet Ennius. It formed the basis of the method of Cicero’s freedman,
                    Tiro, who seems to have systematized the labours of his predecessors. A large
                    quantity of these characters have been engraved in Gruter’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Inscriptiones.</hi> The correspondence of Charlemagne was in part made up
                    of marks of this nature. In Rees’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi> specimens
                    were engraved of the cipher used by Cardinal Wolsey at the court of Vienna in
                    1524, of that used by Sir Thomhs Smith at Paris in 1563, and of that of Sir
                    Edward Stafford at Madrid in 1586; in all of which arbitrary marks are
                    introduced. The first English system of shorthand— Bright’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Characterie</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> 1588—almost belongs to
                    the same category of ciphers. A favourite system of Charles I., used by him
                    during the year 1646, was one made up of an alphabet of twenty-four letters,
                    which were represented by four simple strokes varied in length, slope, and
                    position. This alphabet is engraved in Clive’s <hi rend="italic">Linear System
                        of Shorthand,</hi> 1830, having been found amongst the royal manuscripts in
                    the British Museum. An interest attaches to this cipher from the fact that it
                    was employed in the well known letter addressed by the king to the earl of
                    Glamorgan, in which the former made concessions to the Roman Catholics of
                    Ireland.</p>
                <p>Complications have been introduced into ciphers by the employment of “dummy”
                    letters,—“nulls and insignificants,” as Bacon terms them. Other devices have
                    been introduced to perplex the decipherer, such as spelling words backwards,
                    making false divisions between words, &amp;c. The greatest security against the
                    decipherer has been found in the use of elaborate tables of letters, arranged in
                    the form of the multiplication table, the message being constructed by the aid
                    of preconcerted key-words. Details of the working of these ciphers may be found
                    in the treatises named in this article. The deciphering of them is one of the
                    most difficult of tasks. A method of this kind is explained in the Latin and
                    English lives of Dr John Barwick, whose correspondence with Hyde, afterwards
                    earl of Clarendon, was carried on in cryptography. In a letter dated 20th
                    February 1659-60, Hyde, alluding to the skill of his political opponents in
                    deciphering, says that “nobody needs to fear them, if they write carefully in
                    good cyphers.” In his next he allays his correspondent’s apprehensiveness as to
                    the deciphering of their letters.</p>
                <p>“I confess to you, as I am sure no copy could be gotten of any of my cyphers from
                    hence, so I did. not think it probable that they could be got on your side the
                    water. But I was as confident, till you tell me you believe it, that the devil
                    himself cannot decypher a letter that is well written, or find that 100 stands
                    for Sir H. Vane. I have heard of many of the pretenders to that skill, and have
                    spoken with some of them, but have found them all to be mountebanks; nor did I
                    ever hear that more of the King’s letters that were found at Naseby, than those
                    which they found decyphered, or found the cyphers in which they were writ, were
                    decyphered. And I very well remember that in the volume they published there was
                    much left in cypher which could not be understood, and which I believe they
                    would have explained if it had been in their power.”</p>
                <p>An excellent modification of the key-word principle was ¢onstructed by the late
                    Admiral Sir Francis Beaufort; it has been recently published in view of its
                    adaptation to telegrams and post-cards.</p>
                <p>Ciphers have been constructed on the principle of altering the places of the
                    letters without changing their powers. The message is first written
                    Chinese-wise, upward and downward, and the letters are then combined in given
                    rows from left to right. In the celebrated cipher used by the earl of Argyle
                    when plotting against James IL, he altered the" positions of the words.
                    Sentences of an indifferent nature were constructed, but the real meaning of the
                    message was to be gathered from words placed at certain intervals. This method,
                    which is connected with the name of Cardan, is sometimes called the trellis or
                    cardboard cipher.</p>
                <p>The wheel-cipher, which is an Italian invention, the string-cipher, the
                    circle-cipher, and many others are fully explained, with the necessary diagrams,
                    in the authorities named above,—more particularly by Klüber in his <hi
                        rend="italic">Krypto-graphüc.</hi>. (j. <hi rend="smallcaps">e. b.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
