<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0271-0244-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CONDÉ, Princes of (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    244)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:962708">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n271/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CONDÉ, <hi rend="smallcaps">Princes of</hi></label>. The
                    title of prince of Condé (assumed from the ancient town of Condé, noticed above)
                    was borne by a branch of the House of Bourbon. The first who assumed it was the
                    famous Huguenot leader, Louis de Bourbon, the fifth son of Charles de Bourbon,
                    duke of Vendome (see next article). His son, Henry, prince of Condé (1552-1588),
                    also belonged to the Huguenot party. Fleeing to Germany, he raised a small army,
                    with which in 1575 he joined Alençon. He became leader of the Huguenots, but
                    after several years’ fighting was taken prisoner of war. Not long after he died
                    of poison, administered, according to the belief of his contemporaries, by his
                    wife, Catherine de la Trémouille. This event, among others, awoke strong
                    suspicions as to the legitimacy of his heir and namesake, Henry,prince of
                    Condé(1588-1646). King Henry IV.,however, did not take advantage of the scandal.
                    In 1609 he caused the prince of Condé to marry Charlotte de Montmorency, whom
                    shortly after Condé was obliged to save from the king’s persistent gallantry by
                    a hasty flight, first to Spain and then to Italy. On the death of Henry, Condé
                    returned to France, and intrigued against the regent, Mary de Medici; but he was
                    seized, and imprisoned for three years.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n272/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0272-0245"/>
                <p>There was at that time before the court a plea for his divorce from his wife, but
                    she now devoted herself to enliven his captivity at the cost of her own liberty.
                    During the rest of his life Condé was a faithful servant of the king. He strove
                    to blot out the memory of the Huguenot connections of his house by affecting the
                    greatest zeal against Protestants. His old ambition changed into a desire for
                    the safe aggrandizement of his family, which he magnificently achieved, and with
                    that end he bowed before Richelieu, whose niece he forced his son to marry. His
                    son Louis, the great Condé, is separately noticed below. The next in succession
                    was Henry Jules, prince of Condé (1643-1709), the son of the great Condé and of
                    Clémence de Maillé, niece of Richelieu. He fought with distinction under his
                    father in Franche-Comté and the Low Countries; but he was heartless, avaricious,
                    and undoubtedly insane. The end of his life was marked by singular
                    hypochondriacal fancies. He believed at one time that he was dead, and refused
                    to eat till some of his attendants dressed in sheets set him the example. His
                    grandson, Louis Henry, duke of Bourbon (1692-1740), who did not assume the title
                    of prince of Condé which belonged to him, was member of the council of regency
                    which ruled during the minority of Louis XV., and first minister from the death
                    of the duke of Orleans in 1723 to 1726, when he was superseded by Cardinal de
                    Fleury. He greatly enriched his family and his mistress, De Prie, by taking
                    every advantage of his position; but he made himself unpopular by the weight of
                    taxes which he imposed. The son of the duke of Bourbon, Louis Joseph, prince of
                    Condé (1736-1818), after receiving a good education, distinguished himself in
                    the Seven Years’ War, and most of all by his victory at Johannisberg. As
                    governor of Burgundy he did much to improve the industries and means of
                    communication of that province. At the Revolution he took up arms in behalf of
                    the king, became commander of the “army of Condé,” and fought in conjunction
                    with the Austrians till the peace of Campo Formio in 1797, being during the last
                    year in the pay of England. He then served the emperor of Russia in Poland, and
                    after that (1800) returned into the pay of England, and fought in Bavaria. In
                    1800 Condé arrived in England, where he resided for several years. On the
                    restoration of Louis XVIII. he returned to France. He died at Paris in 1818. He
                    wrote <hi rend="italic">Essai sur</hi><hi rend="italic">la Vie du grand
                        Condé</hi> (1798).</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">L'Histoire de</hi><hi rend="italic">l'</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Armée de</hi><hi rend="italic">Condé,</hi> by Muret; <hi
                        rend="italic">Vie de Louis Joseph, prince de Condé,</hi> by Chamballand; <hi
                        rend="italic">Histoire des trois derniers</hi><hi rend="italic">princes de
                        la maison de Condé,</hi> by Crétineau-Joly; and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de la maison de Condé,</hi> by the Duc
                    d’Aumale (translated by R. B. Borthwick, 1872).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
