<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0572-0539-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CRABBE, George</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 539</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1042815">Objectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hv6n">Defectives</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h10">Sermons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n572/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CRABBE, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label> (1754-1832),
                    was born at Aidborough, in Suffolk, December 24, 1754, and was the son of an
                    officer of the customs. He appears to have been designed by his father first for
                    an employment similar to his own, and afterwards for the medical profession. He
                    was apprenticed to an apothecary, and received an education merely sufficient to
                    qualify him for such an occupation, and by no means to advance him in that
                    literary career in which he became eventually distinguished. His poetical taste
                    was first elicited by the casual perusal of some verses in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Philosophical Magazine,</hi> which his father, who was a mathematician and
                    averse to poetry, had separated from the scientific portions of that periodical,
                    and thrown aside as unworthy. The spark thus kindled burnt steadily; and even
                    while a schoolboy he versified much, and made sundry ambitious attempts in the
                    highest walks of composition. The attainment of a prize offered by the editor of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Lady’s Magazine</hi> for a poem on Hope, although a humble
                    species of success, sufficed to encourage him to renewed exertions; and in 1778
                    he quitted the profession of medicine, which ho had always disliked, and
                    repaired to London, determined to apply himself to literature. His early efforts
                    in his new career were attended with disheartening circumstances. The first poem
                    he offered for publication could find no publisher. From the first that was
                    printed he obtained no profit, in consequence of the publisher’s bankruptcy. It
                    was entitled <hi rend="italic">The Candidate, a Poetical Epistle to the Authors
                    of the Monthly Review,</hi> and appeared anonymously in 1780. Soon afterwards he
                    became acquainted with Burke, an acquaintance from which may be dated the dawn
                    of his literary rise. "Without an introduction, and impelled by distress, he
                    applied to Burke, who kindly took him by the hand, afforded him the advantage of
                    his criticism and advice, recommended him to Dodsley the publisher, invited him
                    to his house, and made him known to many distinguished men of that time, among
                    whom were Reynolds, Johnson, and Fox. Crabbe’s first published poems, after the
                    commencement of his acquaintance with Burke, were <hi rend="italic">The
                    Library</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Village,</hi> both of wſhich received the
                    benefit of Burke’s observations, and the second of which was in a great measure
                    composed at Beaconsfield. In 1781 Crabbe, who by the recommendation of Burke had
                    been qualifying himself for holy orders, w as ordained a deacon, and he took
                    priest’s orders the following year. After serving a short time as curate at
                    Aidborough, through the influence of this generous and distinguished friend he
                    was introduced to the duke of Rutland and became his domestic chaplain. Nor did
                    Burke’s kindness stop here; for he obtained for him from Lord Thurlow, in 1783,
                    a presentation to tho rectory of FromeSt Quintin, in Dorsetshire, which he held
                    for six years, About this time he married, and resided <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n573/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0573-0540"/> for some time at Swelling, county of Suffolk,
                    officiating as curate to the minister of Great Yarmouth. About 1789 he was
                    presented, through the instrumentality of the duchess of Rutland, to the
                    rectories of Muston in Leicestershire and West Allington in Lincolnshire. In
                    1813 he was preferred to the rectory of Trowbridge, county of Wilts, which,
                    together with the smaller living of Croxton Kerrial, in Leicestershire, he held
                    to the time of his death. After <hi rend="italic">The Village,</hi> published in
                    1783, which had received the corrections and commendations of Dr Johnson, Crabbe
                    next produced <hi rend="italic">The Newspaper,</hi> published in 1785. After
                    this time his poetical labours were long suspended, owing probably to the
                    dedication of his time to domestic affairs and the duties of his profession, or,
                    as he himself ascribes it, to the loss of those early and distinguished friends
                    who had given him the benefit of their criticism. He had, however, the
                    satisfaction of seeing his next work, <hi rend="italic">The Parish
                    Register,</hi> published in 1809, read and approved by Fox. The success obtained
                    by these poems, which far exceeded that which had attended his earlier efforts,
                    encouraged him to write again; and in 1810 he published one of his best poems,
                    <hi rend="italic">The Borough,</hi> and in 1812 <hi rend="italic">Tales in
                    Verse.</hi> His last publication was entitled <hi rend="italic">Tales of the
                    Hall,</hi> and appeared in 1819. The latter years of his life he spent in the
                    tranquil and amiable exercise of his domestic and clerical duties, at his
                    rectory of Trowbridge, esteemed and admired by his parishioners, among whom he
                    died, after a short illness, on the 8th February 1832, aged seventy-seven. He
                    was buried in the chancel of Trowbridge Church. Crabbe’s only prose publications
                    were a <hi rend="italic">Funeral Sermon on Charles, duke of Rutland,</hi>
                    preached at Belvoir, and an essay on the natural history of the vale of Belvoir,
                    written for Nichols’s <hi rend="italic">History of Leicestershire,</hi> in which
                    it is thankfully acknowledged. His fame rests solely on his poems, of which <hi
                    rend="italic">The Parish Register</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Borough</hi>
                    are destined to a reputation, if not as brilliant, yet probably as enduring as
                    that of any other contemporary productions.</p>
                <p>Crabbe is one of the most original of our poets; and his originality is of that
                    best kind, which displays itself not in tumid exaggeration or flighty
                    extravagance—not in a wide departure from the sober standard of truth—but in a
                    more rigid and uncompromising adherence to it than inferior writers venture to
                    attempt. He is pre-eminently the poet of reality in humble life; and to its
                    representation he has applied himself with a rigorous fidelity which startled
                    the timid fastidiousness of many readers. He discarded the aid of those pleasing
                    illusions with which humble life had previously been enveloped; condemned as
                    fictitious the prevalent representations, and in their stead fearlessly
                    exhibited the stern, harsh, naked truth, and determined to rely for popularity
                    on the fidelity and vigour of his delineations. His chief characteristics are
                    force and accuracy; and through these, and the originality of his style, he
                    compels us to bestow our attention on objects that are usually neglected. His
                    poetry, unlike that of others, directs our sympathy where it is well for the
                    cause of humanity that it should be directed, but whence the squalidness of
                    misery and want too frequently repels it. Much of his success arises from his
                    graphic delineation of external objects, but more from his knowledge of the
                    human heart, and his powerful treatment of the passions. Both the milder and the
                    more violent emotions are portrayed with ability, but in the latter he is most
                    strikingly successful. Despair and remorse are exhibited with a tragic strength
                    that has been rarely equalled; and madness has been seldom drawn with a more
                    powerful hand than in his poem of <hi rend="italic">Sir Bustace Grey.</hi> He
                    has been called the satirist of the poor; but we must be careful lest we attach
                    to this expression too harsh an acceptation. It is true he discountenances those
                    romantic day-dreams which associate virtue inseparably with poverty, and an
                    Arcadian innocence with rural life. He shows that demoralization is the
                    attendant of distress, and that villagers may be equally dissipated, and more
                    dishonest than the profligates of a wealthier class; but he shows this in a
                    spirit rather of pity than of anger; and whilst he denounces and exposes crime,
                    he makes us interested not so much in its punishment, as, what is still better,
                    in its prevention. He spares not the vices of the poorer classes; but at the
                    same time he does more justice to their virtues, and renders them more important
                    objects of consideration than perhaps any other imaginative writer.</p>
                <p>With many sterling merits as a poet, Crabbe has numerous defects. His
                    descriptions are forcible and exact, but they are too detailed. They have too
                    much of the minuteness of a Dutch picture; and it is a minuteness exhibited in
                    the representation of disgusting objects. He never shrinks from the irksome task
                    of threading the details of vice and misery. Abject depravity is a too favourite
                    subject of his pen; and he does not seem sufficiently aware that there is a
                    species of wickedness which counteracts our sympathy with suffering, and a
                    degree of insignificance which extinguishes our interest in guilt. His skill in
                    displaying the morbid anatomy of our moral nature has rendered him too prone to
                    that unpleasing exercise of his talents; and his habit of tracing the
                    deformities of character has given to his expositions too much the appearance of
                    invective. His taste is very inferior to his other powers. Even with subjects
                    naturally pleasing he is apt to blend disagreeable images. His descriptions of
                    natural scenery, graphic as they are, have little in them of elevation. There is
                    no genial glow about them, as if the contemplation of nature had warmed and
                    inspired him. His deficiency of taste displays itself also sometimes in his
                    humour, which is apt to verge upon buffoonery. His style is little to be
                    commended. It is too often clumsy and ungraceful,—diffuse without freedom,
                    homely without being easy, and antithetical without being pointed. His diction
                    is frequently harsh and quaint, and compels us to feel that the merit of his
                    works resides rather in their ideas than in the dress in which he clothes them.
                    His lines are deficient in refinement and polish, and frequently offend the ear
                    by something uncouth and prosaic in the sound, and the absence of musical
                    rhythm. Such are the defects which have conduced to deprive him of that
                    popularity <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> wlιich his merits would otherwise have
                    obtained for him. (τ. <hi rend="smallcaps">h. li.)</hi></p>
                <p>A complete edition of Crabbe’s works was published in 1834, in 8 volumes 12mo,
                    the first volume containing his Life by his son, the Rev. George Crabbe. A
                    reprint, in one volume roval 8vo, was issued in 1867.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
