<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0573-0540-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CRACOW (9th edition, volume 6, page 540)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1069177">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104215">Salt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104337">Salts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079619">Protectionism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86t6p">Mining</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b6k">Bohemianism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n573/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CRACOW</label> (Polish, <hi rend="italic">Krakov;</hi>
                    German, <hi rend="italic">Krakau),</hi> a city of the crownland of Galicia,
                    Austria, the capital anciently of Poland, and more recently of a small Polish
                    republic which bordered on the Prussian, Austrian, and Russian dominions where
                    they meet. The city stands in a fertile plain on the left bank of the Vistula,
                    where the stream of the Rudowa joins it, nearly 200 miles north-east of Vienna
                    in latitude (of observatory) 50° 3' 50" N., longitude 19’ 57' 30" E., and at an
                    elevation of 650 feet above the sea. The main railway line of Galicia, called
                    the Carl Ludwig’s Bahn, uniting the system of Germany along the outskirts of the
                    Carpathian range with the lines about the Lower Danube, crosses the Vistula at
                    Cracow. A line of detached forts has been built round the city, and a castle on
                    a height commands the town. Promenades occupying tho place of the old walls,
                    planted with trees, divide the old town from the seven extensive suburbs of
                    Stradom, Ribaki, Kleparz, Piasek, Wesola, Smolensk, and Wielopole; and an arm of
                    the Vistula cuts off the Jewish quarter of Kasimierz. In the old town the
                    extensive castle of the Polish kings on the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n574/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0574-0541"/> rock of Wawel, dating from the 14th century,
                    has been for the most part rebuilt to serve as barracks and for a hospital. The
                    Stanislas Cathedral (Lady Church), built in 1359, contains many interesting
                    antiquities relating to the kingdom of Poland; the monarchs were crowned in this
                    edifice, which also holds the mausoleum of the Sigismunds, the silver coffin of
                    the holy Stanislas, and the remains of John Sobieski, of Poniatowski, and of
                    Kosciusko; it is adorned by sculptures by Thorwaldsen, and a wooden carved altar
                    (1472-1484) by Veit Stoss, who was a native of</p>
                <p>Cracow. There are forty churches in the city, with twenty-three convents of monks
                    and nuns. In the Ringplatz stand the old Gothic cloth booths and the ancient
                    Rathhaus with a fine tower. A relic of the old wall remains in the Floriane gate
                    on the esplanade. The university of Cracow, founded by Casimir the Great, and
                    carried out by Jagellon in 1401, has sixty-nine professors and about 450
                    students, and possesses a library of 140,000 volumes and numerous MSS. Attached
                    to it are an observatory, botanic gardens, natural, historical, and medical
                    museums, a laboratory, and medical schools. Cloth, leather, and agricultural
                    implements are manufactured to some extent in Cracow, and a busy traffic in
                    grain, wood, salt, wine, linen, and pigs is carried on by the Vistula. In the
                    neighbourhood thero are coal and zinc mines. Besides a bridge over the old
                    Vistula, the Franz Joseph Bridge on five stone piers and the railway bridge
                    cross the river to the villages of Podgorze and Stawisko on the opposite bank.
                    Three miles northwest of Cracow a huge mound 125 feet in height was raised in
                    1824 to the memory of Kosciusko, and this has now been utilized as the site of a
                    fort. The village of Krzezowice in this direction is a favourite resort of
                    Cracow people, and has a fine castle, a Gothic church, sulphur baths, and iron
                    and zinc mines. Eight miles south-east of Cracow, united to it by a branch
                    railway, are the village and famous salt-mines of Wieliczka; about 1000 miners
                    are constantly employed here, and the annual yield of salt amounts to more than
                    a million cwts. Population (1869), 49,835, including about 10,000 Jews.</p>
                <p>Cracow takes its name from the Polish Prince Krak or Krakus, and dates from about
                    the year 700. Perhaps no city has suffered greater vicissitudes. It was taken in
                    1039 by the Bohemians, in 1241 by the Mongols, by the Swedes in 1655 and in
                    1702, and by the Russians in 1768. It remained the capital of Poland from 1320
                    till 1609, when the seat of government was transferred to Warsaw, but the kings
                    of Poland were crowned in it till 1764. On the third partition of Poland in 1795
                    Austria took possession of this portion; but in his campaign of 1809 Napoleon
                    wrested it from that power, and incorporated it with the duchy of Warsaw, which
                    was placed under the rule of Saxony. In the campaign of 1812 the Emperor
                    Alexander made himself master of this and the other territory which formed the
                    duchy of Warsaw. At the general settlement of the affairs of Europe by the great
                    powers in 1815, it was agreed that Cracow and the adjoining territory should be
                    formed into a free state; and, by the General Treaty of Congress signed at
                    Vienna in 1815, “the town of Cracow, with its territory, is declared to be for
                    ever a free, independent, and strictly neutral city, under the protection of
                    Russia, Austria, and Prussia.’’ In February 1846, however, an insurrection broke
                    out in Cracow, apparently a ramification of a widely-spread conspiracy
                    throughout Poland. The senate and the other authorities of Cracow were unable to
                    subdue the rebels or to maintain order, and, at their request, the city was
                    occupied by a corps of Austrian troops for the protection of the inhabitants.
                    The three powers, Russia, Austria, and Prussia, made this a pretext for
                    extinguishing this independent state; and having established a conference at
                    Vienna (November 1846) the three courts after due deliberation, contrary to the
                    assurance previously given, and in opposition to the expressed views of the
                    British and French Governments, came to the conclusion to extinguish the state
                    of Cracow and to incorporate it with the dominions of Austria.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
