<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0268-0241-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CONCORDAT (9th edition, volume 6, page 241)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874117">Concordats</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1012448">Matter</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n268/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CONCORDAT</label> is an agreement between the Pope, as
                    representing the Catholic Church, and a temporal sovereign, with reference to
                    the rights of the church within the territory of the latter. It must be borne in
                    mind that the pretensions of Hildebrandism (1074 to 1300 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >λ.d.)</hi> were very great; they included a power of absolving sovereigns
                    and subjects from their oaths, a large feudal revenue collected abroad, a
                    peculiar status for the Catholic clergy. Against these, temporal sovereigns
                    claimed what were called <hi rend="italic">jura</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >majestatis</hi><hi rend="italic">circa sacra,—</hi> viz., <hi rend="italic"
                        >jus</hi> (Schutzrecht), or the supreme patronage of the national church;
                        <hi rend="italic">jus</hi><hi rend="italic">cavendi</hi> (Recht der
                    Versorge), or right of considering whether ecclesiastical regulations conflict
                    with civil duties; and <hi rend="italic">jus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >inspiciendi,</hi> or general right of superintending the morals of the
                    church and the administration of its property. The great historical assertions
                    of Papal supremacy were made in the Decretals :—“<hi rend="italic"
                        >Venerabilem,”</hi> sent in 1197 by Innocent III. to the majority of the
                    imperial electors who had chosen Philip of Swabia; <hi rend="italic">“Ad
                        Apostolicae,”</hi> by which Innocent IV. in 1245 deposed Frederick II. from
                    the imperial throne on the ground of perjury, sacrilege, and heresy; <hi
                        rend="italic">“</hi><hi rend="italic">Clericis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Laicos”</hi> and “<hi rend="italic">Unam Sanctam</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >”</hi> (1296 and 1302), which dealt with the taxation of church property,
                    and laid down the principle “oportet autem gladium esse sub gladio.” The same
                    claims appear in the Extravagant “<hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Consuetudine,”</hi> issued by John XXII. in 1322, and in the frequently
                    published Bull <hi rend="italic">“In Caena Domini”</hi> (1773). The Encyclical
                    Letter “<hi rend="italic">Quanta Curaſt</hi> and relative Syllabus of 1864, and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Costituzione “Pastor Aetemus”</hi> of 1870 contain the
                    latest expression by the Pope of his international functions. It was after the
                    empire had, by the decree of Frankfort (1338), declared that Papal confirmation
                    and coronation were unnecessary, and the reformatory councils of Constance and
                    Basel had increased the controlling power of the whole church, and diminished
                    the appeals and <hi rend="italic">annates</hi> which caused so much discontent,
                    that pragmatic sanctions and concordats began to be used to regulate the
                    relations between the different European powers and the Papacy. The French
                    Pragmatic of 1268, which defended the local jurisdictions and rights of
                    presentation, and prohibi-tedPapal imports exceptforpious,rational,and
                    urgentcauses, and the Pragmatic Sanction which in 1438 at the Council of Bruges
                    the French clergy composed in imitation of the Basel decrees, were largely
                    modified in favour of Rome by the concordat entered into in 1510 between Francis
                    I. and Leo X. This arrangement left the nomination of bishops with the Crown,
                    which had before merely given a <hi rend="italic">conge</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >d’élire</hi> for the election by chapter, but assigned no term within which
                    the Pope must institute. The consequence was that whenever it suited his purpose
                    the Pope delayed institution. After a long period of irritating dispute the
                    French clergy, Γed by Le Pellier and Bossuet, in their famous declaration of
                    1682, formally asserted what are now called Cismontane or national church
                    principles. Louis XIV. had considerably enlarged the Crown right of <hi
                        rend="italic">Regale,</hi> which included the revenues of vacant churches,
                    but he was now (1693) ignominiously compelled to write a letter to Innocent XI.,
                    in which he undertook not to enforce the edict of 1682. The suppression of the
                    Jesuits, in 1773, was a heavy blow to. the temporal influence of Rome. It was
                    mainly brought about by the behaviour of Clement XIII. The duke of Parma had
                    prohibited appeals from his territory to Rome in questions about the benefices
                    of Parma, and had also republished the principle, familiar in the common law of
                    Europe, that no Papal rescript should take effect in Parma without receiving the
                    ducal <hi rend="italic">exaequatur.</hi> Clement then fired off the “Monitorio
                    di Parma,” excommunicating in terms of the Bull “<hi rend="italic">In
                        Coena”</hi> all concerned in the Parmesan edict. The indignant reaction
                    which followed in all the courts of Catholic Europe decided the triumph of
                    Ganganelli and the Regalisti party, who were opposed at the Vatican by the
                    Ultramontane party of Zelanti. Under the civil constitution which the French
                    Church received from the Revolution, the bishops received institution from their
                    metropolitan. In 1801, a concordat was arranged between Napoleon as first consul
                    and Pius VII. Under this the consul nominated and the Pope appointed bishops,
                    who were all required to swear allegiance to the republic<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> Several bishops, who refused this oath,
                            were driven from France, and formed in England La Petite Eglise, which
                            existed for some time (see <hi rend="italic">The Guardian,</hi> 4 Feb.
                            1852).</p></note>. The much more important matters of the verification
                    of Bulls by <hi rend="italic">Exaequatur, Placitum,</hi> or Letters of <hi
                        rend="italic">Pareatis,</hi> the position of the delegates of the church,
                    the effect to be given to the decrees of councils held out of France, and the
                        <hi rend="italic">Appel</hi><hi rend="italic">comme</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >d’Abus,</hi> were all settled by the “Regulations of the Gallican Church,”
                    better known as the Organic Articles, with regard to which the Pope was not
                    consulted. Shortly afterwards Napoleon, by the decree of Schönbrunn (1809),
                    annexed the Papal dominions to France, and imprisoned the Pope at Fontainebleau,
                    where the “false” concordat of 1813 was signed. The main provision of this was
                    to devolve the right of institution on the metropolitan bishop, if not exercised
                    by the Pope within six months. In 1817 the Bourbons tried to negotiate a
                    retrograde concordat, but the attempt was fortunately frustrated. The political
                    attitude of Guizot and Napoleon III. towards Gregory XVI. and Pius IX. was
                    friendly, but in 1870 the Prussian victories brought to an <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n269/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0269-0242"/> end the French occupation of the Papal States
                    which had begun in the intervention of 1849, and had been continuous from 1864.
                    By the Italian statute of guarantees (13th May 1871) personal inviolability and
                    the honours of a sovereign are secured to the Pope. He has also a large income
                    and several residences, and a private postal and telegraphic service; and he is
                    allowed to receive diplomatic agents from foreign states. The same statute gives
                    complete freedom to the church, but deprives it of coercive jurisdiction. The
                    royal <hi rend="italic">Placet</hi> is relinquished as unnecessary, but a
                    stringent penal law (7th June 1871) is directed against seditious words,
                    writings, or acts of the clergy.</p>
                <p>In the empire the earliest concordat is the Concordatum Calixtinum of 1122,
                    between Henry V. and Pope Calixtus II. The benefits of the Basel Decrees were in
                    great measure lost by the concordat entered into in 1448 between Frederick III.
                    and Nicholas V. The political position of the Pope was much altered by the
                    Treaty of Westphalia, which, without his consent, and even against his protests,
                    conceded the right to certain nations of freely exercising the Protestant
                    religion.</p>
                <p>Early in the 18th century the cause of the national church in Austria, and of the
                    immediate divine right of Episcopacy, was placed on solid foundations of
                    learning and argument by the writings of Van Espen <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Lus</hi><hi rend="italic">ecclesiasticum, universum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >hodiernae</hi><hi rend="italic">disciplinoe,</hi> Cologne, 1702; <hi
                        rend="italic">Tractatus</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >promulgatione legum</hi><hi rend="italic">ecclesiasticarτιm).</hi> The
                    abuses of the permanent <hi rend="italic">Nuntiatura,</hi> maintained by the
                    Pope, called forth the <hi rend="italic">Punctation</hi> of the four archbishops
                    who met at Ems, 25th August 1786. Joseph II. had already carried out large
                    reforms, but these episcopal resolutions recommended still further changes in
                    the “Recursus ad Principem,” or prohibition of appeals to Rome, the power of
                    dispensation and of granting faculties, the administration of conventual
                    property and charitable funds, the reservation of benefices and their
                    transmission by inheritance, the exaction of <hi rend="italic">annates</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> money, &amp;c. Under the decrees of Joseph
                    II. in 1781, no Papal Bulls or rescripts were allowed to be published, except
                    such as had received the Placitum Regium, and had been effected through the
                    intervention of the imperial and royal agency at Rome. In 1850, however, both
                    the bishops and the faithful under their charge were allowed to have recourse to
                    the Pope in spiritual matters, and to receive the decisions of his Holiness
                    without the previous consent of the secular authorities. With the exception of
                    the three archbishoprics of Olmütz, Salzburg, and Breslau, where the archbishop
                    is elected by the chapter, the practice was, on a bishopric becoming vacant, for
                    the emperor to propose three candidates from whom the Pope selects one— a
                    selection subsequently ratified by the emperor. The same decree of 1850,
                    proceeding on the anti-revolutionary imperial patent of 4th March 1849 (§ 2),
                    permits Catholic bishops to issue admonitions and ordinances, without consent of
                    the civil power, to decree ecclesiastical punishments which do not affect purely
                    civil rights, to suspend and remove from ecclesiastical office, and to declare
                    emoluments forfeited, and to control education in primary and intermediate
                    schools and in the universities. This arrangement was sealed by the concordat of
                    18th August 1855 (printed fully in <hi rend="italic">Times,</hi> 20th November
                    1855), which, however, was repealed by the series of Church Acts passed by
                    Prince Auersperg in 1874, in imitation of the Falk legislation of Prussia.</p>
                <p>The relations of Belgium with Rome were of course at one time determined by the
                    decree of the French N ational Assembly (1791), and the concordat between Pius
                    VII. and Napoleon (1801). On 18th June 1827, William I., Protestant king of the
                    Netherlands, entered into a concordat with Pope Leo XII., which confirmed and
                    extended the provisions of the earlier concordat relating to the institution of
                    bishops by letters apostolic. The power which the Crown then reserved of
                    striking out objectionable names from the list of candidates prepared by the
                    chapter was entirely renounced by the 16th Article of the Belgian Constitution
                    of 1830, which declares that the -state has no jight to interfere with the
                    nomination or installation of any religious ministers, or to prevent them from
                    corresponding with their superiors or from publishing their Acts. But then the
                    Government has this indirect control, that all the salaries of the Catholic
                    clergy are voted in the annual budget, and do not belong to the church. The
                    concordat of 1827 was never in force in Holland, where the fundamental law of
                    1848 (§ 65) declares that no Dutchman can accept titles without the permission
                    of the king, and where public opinion has prevented the creation of Catholic
                    bishops.</p>
                <p>Spain, although the most Catholic of powers, has, at least since the accession of
                    the Austrian dynasty, zealously defended its national church rights against the
                    Pope. In 1568, Philip II. claimed as royal prerogative the right to present to
                    all Spanish bishoprics, and created a Board, “Supremo Consejo de ]a Camara,” to
                    preserve the royal jurisdiction, to protect the canons, and to watch over the
                    external policy in ecclesiastical matters. The Pope having sided with Austria in
                    the Succession War, the breach between Spain and Rome widened during the 18th
                    century. The principles that no causes should be carried before a judge outside
                    the kingdom, that benefices should be conferred only on natives, that sovereigns
                    are not subject to interdict or spiritual censure, that all Bulls should, before
                    publication, be subject to the royal <hi rend="italic">Cedula,</hi> were loudly
                    and angrily proclaimed; and in 1805 the king attacked the secret influences of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Curia</hi> by directing that all applications to Rome for
                    grants and dispensation should receive the <hi rend="italic">Visto Bueno</hi> of
                    the royal agent at Rome. The estrangement continued in the 19th century, when
                    till 1848 the Pope refused to recognize the succession of Isabella II. under the
                    Pragmatic Sanction of 1830. From 1753 to 1851, matters had stood on a concordat
                    which the eminent statesman, De Carbajal, persuaded Ferdinand VI. to negotiate
                    with Clement XII. It gave the king the right of presentation to vacant
                    bishoprics (patronatos), and to the Pope 22,000,000 reales as compensation for
                    the loss of <hi rend="italic">annates</hi> and fees on briefs. The concordats of
                    1851 and 1859 are more favourable to Rome; but the attempt of Canovas del
                    Castillo and the Cardinal Simeoni to procure a recognition of the 1851
                    concordat, in 1875, was defeated by General Jovellar.</p>
                <p>In non-Roman Catholic states, of course, no valid concordat could be framed.
                    Accordingly, as in the cases of Prussia (1821) and Hanover (1824), edicts
                    relating to the adjustment of dioceses, or other matters not purely spiritual,
                    were issued by the Pope under the name of Bullae Circumscriptionis. These were
                    formally sanctioned by th© Home Government, and directed to be printed in the
                    collection of laws.</p>
                <p>The most important sources of information on this subject are the reports
                    presented to Parliament in 1816 and 1851, on the “Regulation of Roman Catholic
                    Subjects in Foreign Countries,” which have been summarized in the 2d volume of
                    Sir R. Phillimore’s <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on International Law.</hi>
                    The works of Van Espen and the <hi rend="italic">Enchiridion</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Juris</hi><hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastici</hi> of George
                    Rechberger (1809) are standard works. The French concordats have been
                    elaborately discussed by Μ. de Pradt, at one time archbishop of Malines, in <hi
                        rend="italic">Les Quatres Concordats,</hi> 3 vols., Brussels, 1815, and <hi
                        rend="italic">Suite</hi><hi rend="italic">des Quatre</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Concordats,</hi> 1 vol., Paris, 1820. The works of the eminent jurist
                    Portalis, who took an active part in the discussion of the lattet French
                    concordats, may also be consulted,— <hi rend="italic">Discours,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Rapports, el</hi><hi rend="italic">Travaux inédits sur le
                        Concordat de</hi> 1801, <hi rend="italic">les Articles Organiques,</hi>
                    &amp;c. (W. C. S.) <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n270/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0270-0243"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
