<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0383-0354-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">COPTS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 354</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mv15">Sects</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gh9bg6t">Mussulmans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:943906">Gnosticism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916956">Eutychians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1353199">Grammar</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1025507">Monks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110714">Sects</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n383/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COPTS</label>, the name given to the descendants of the
                    native inhabitants of Egypt after the Mahometan conquest, supposed by some to be
                    descended from the ancient Egyptians or else from the mixed race which inhabited
                    the country under the Roman empire. They are Christians, and are said to
                    comprise less than one fourteenth of the whole population. Although numerous,
                    their numbers continue to dwindle, and they are being gradually, by marriage or
                    conversion, absorbed in the Mussulman population of the country. Their name
                    Kubt, or Kubti, is supposed to be derived either from Aegyptos or Egypt, or else
                    from the town of Coptos, or even lakobitai. Although scarcely distinguishable
                    from the other inhabitants, they are said to have large and elongated black
                    eyes, high cheek-bones, the lobe of the ear high, the nose straight and spread
                    at the end, black and curiy hair, thick and spread lips, and large chin. In
                    height they are rather under the middle size; they have in general little <hi
                    rend="italic">embonpoint,</hi> slender limbs, and pale or bronze complexion, and
                    a sullen expression; but they differ considerably, those who have embraced Roman
                    Catholicism resembling more Greeks or Syrians, while the others of the Said
                    retain their primitive type. Their dress is like that of the Mahometans, except
                    that their turban is of a black-greyish or light-brown colour, and they often
                    wear a black coat or gown over their other dress. In their general customs they
                    follow the rules of the other inhabitants; the women veil their faces, both in
                    public and at home when male visitors are present. In religion they are
                    followers of the Eutychian heresy or Jacobite sect, so called from Jacobus
                    Baradaeus, a Syrian, who propagated the doctrine; and in 1840 there were 150,000
                    of this sect, while 5000 were said to be Roman Catholics, and as many of the
                    Greek faith. The Jacobites are monophysites and monothelites. They have
                    altogether about 130 churches or convents. Their religious orders are a
                    patriarch, a metropolitan of the Λbyssinians, bishops, arch-priests, priests,
                    deacons, and monks. The “patriarch,” called “of Alexandria,” resides at Cairo,
                    and is generally chosen by lot out of eight or nine monks of the convent of St
                    Antony in the eastern desert designated as capable of filling the office, but he
                    may be appointed by his predecessor. The metropolitan is appointed by the
                    patriarch, and the twelve bishops are selected by preference from the monks.
                    They generally baptize their children within the year, and some circumcise them
                    about eight years of age; this rite was evidently handed down by their
                    ancestors, as it is represented in Egyptian sculptures of the Pharaonic period.
                    In their schools the Coptic language is taught imperfectly. In their prayers
                    appear to be many repetitions, and they pray in this manner riding or walking.
                    Their churches are divided into five compartments, the most important of which
                    is the chancel <hi rend="italic">(heykel).</hi> They observe many fasts and
                    festivals, and some perform pilgrimages to Jerusalem. They also abstain from
                    parts of the flesh of the pig and camel, and from that of animals which have
                    been strangled and from blood. They do not perform military service. In their
                    habits and customs they follow those of the other populations of Egypt; they
                    rarely intermarry with any other sect; in their marriages they employ a
                    go-between <hi rend="italic">vakel,</hi> and two-thirds of the dowry is settled
                    upon the wife during her life. The marriages take place on Saturday night, and
                    the festivities sometimes are kept up for eight days. At these a singular custom
                    prevails of attaching two cascabels to the wings of two pigeons, whereby the
                    birds fly about till they are giddy, and then placing them in two hollow balls
                    of sugar, each set on a dish; the balls are afterwards broken and the pigeons
                    fly about the room. The preparations for the marriage consist of ablution, a
                    procession of the bride covered with a shawl, attended by musicians, to the
                    house of the bridegroom, stepping over the blood of a slaughtered lamb at the
                    door, the crowning of the bride and bridegroom, and subsequent entertainments,
                    much abridged or even omitted when a widow is married. The etiquette is not to
                    leave the house for a year to pay visits. Divorces are only given for adultery
                    on the part of the wife. The Copts are exceedingly bigoted, prone to be
                    converted to Islamism, sullen, as Ammianus Marcellinus describes the Egyptians,
                    false, faithless, and deceitful, but extremely useful as secretaries and
                    accountants and skilful workmen. In their funeral ceremonies they follow
                    Mussulman customs, but pay special visits on two days of the year to the
                    sepulchres, and give away a slaughtered bullock and other viands. Both in their
                    physical type and in some of their ceremonies they retain a resemblance to their
                    ancestors, the ancient Egyptians.</p>
                <p>Seventy years after their conquest by the Mahometans, 640, unsuccessful in
                    revolt, they suffered the persecution of their masters. The monks were branded
                    in the hand, civilians oppressed with heavy taxation, churches demolished,
                    pictures and crosses destroyed, 722-23. A few years later all Copts were so
                    branded. Degrading dresses were imposed upon them, 849-50. Later, under El
                    Hakim, 997, they were compelled to wear heavy crosses and black turbans as an
                    ignominious distinction; churches were destroyed, and many of the Copts
                    converted. In 1301, the blue turban was introduced, but many Copts preferred a
                    change of religion to the adoption of this head-dress. In 1321 a dreadful
                    religious strife, attended by the destruction of churches and mosques and great
                    loss of life, raged at Cairo between the Copts and the Mohametans; but in
                    1354-55 great numbers embraced Islamism, and they appear to have gradually
                    declined.</p>
                <p>The language of the Copts, or so-called Coptic, is that of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n384/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0384-0355"/> the last stage of ancient Egyptian civilization,
                    and that in use at the time of the Romans. In the course of centuries the old
                    Egyptian rapidly changed, especially at the time of the 19th dynasty, when
                    foreign conquests and high civilization had introduced into it a number of
                    Semitic words, principally of the Aramaean family. This continued till the time
                    of the 26th dynasty, or about the 7th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi>
                    when the old forms had almost died out, and not only a great number of new words
                    but also a difference of structure appeared in the Egyptian, which approached
                    more nearly to the modern Coptic. This continued till the Ptolemies, under whose
                    government a fresh infusion of words (many of them Greek) considerably altered
                    the language, as they displaced the ancient words, and some new grammatical
                    forms appeared; a considerable difference took place in the prefixes and affixes
                    at that period. After the conversion of Egypt to Christianity the old demotic
                    alphabet fell into disuse, and another was substituted—twenty-four letters of
                    the Greek alphabet, to which were added seven others, supposed to be borrowed
                    from the older demotic to represent sounds not found in the Greek. The language
                    was written in this character from the end of the 4th or beginning of the 5th
                    century, in all works relating to Christianity, and in this condition has been
                    handed down to the present day in three different dialects, called the Sahidic
                    or that of Upper Egypt, the Memphitic or that spoken in the neighbourhood of
                    Memphis, and the Bashmuric or dialect of the Lake Menzaleh and its environs.
                    Great difference of opinion has prevailed as to the relative antiquity of these
                    dialects, some considering the Memphitic and others the Sahidic to be the most
                    ancient. The Sahidic is softer than the Memphitic, has none of the harder
                    aspirations, and is more intermixed with Greek. It chiefly differs, however, in
                    construction and the use of vowels. The Bashmuric is intermediate between the
                    two, but is softer than the Memphitic, and one great peculiarity is the use of
                    <hi rend="italic">I</hi> for r, which last letter was not known to the ancient
                    Egyptians. The Coptic or Egyptian was in use at the 9th century, but had ceased
                    to be intelligible in Middle Egypt in the 12th. It survived, however, as a
                    spoken dialect till the 17th, an old man who spoke it having died only in 1633.
                    In the Coptic Church, however, it is still in use for the religious services,
                    and is read, although not understood except by an Arabic interpretation or
                    glossary. It is partly studied by the Copts, and an attempt to revive the
                    ancient language was made by the missionary Lieder at Cairo, who founded schools
                    within the last half century. The discovery of the mode of reading hieroglyphs
                    has rehabilitated the Coptic language, and there is no doubt that it is
                    essentially the same as the Egyptian of the time of the Pyramids, and has
                    retained many words of that and succeeding epochs. Like the Egyptian it is
                    intermediate between the Aryan and Semitic languages in its <hi rend="italic"
                    >copia verborum,</hi> and partly resembles the Semitic in its construction, in
                    which, however, it is more closely allied to the African languages than the
                    older Egyptian, while it differs greatly in the <hi rend="italic">copia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">verborum</hi> from them. The Psalms and some other portions of the
                    Scriptures had been translated into Coptic as early as Pachomius, 303, and from
                    that time a succession of works, chiefly religious, were compiled in it. The
                    commencement of the knowledge of Coptic in modern Europe is due to Kircher, who
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Prodromus</hi><hi rend="italic">Coptus</hi> in
                    1636. He was followed by Blumberg, who compiled a grammar, called <hi
                    rend="italic">Fundamenta Linguae Copticae,</hi> in 1716. A Copt, named Tuki,
                    bishop of Arsinoe, gave out another, the <hi rend="italic">Rudimenta</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Linguae Copticae,</hi> in 1778, in Arabic and Latin, out still in
                    a very uncritical condition. Scholz’s grammar, edited by Woide in the same year,
                    was a remarkable work for the time; in 1783 Calusius published another grammar;
                    but these chiefly related to the Memphitic dialect, the Sahidic being
                    imperfectly known, and the Bashmuric quite unknown,—the first grammar of the
                    three dialects bein&lt;* that of Tattam in 1830. Another more critical grammar,
                    prepared by Champoilion, was edited by Rosellini and Ungarelli, and another by
                    Peyron in 1841, which was succeeded by the work of Schwartze in 1847. The
                    literature chiefly consists of religious works,—the Pentateuch, Psalms, Kings,
                    minor prophets, and book of Daniel, existing in Coptic, and few fragments in
                    Sahidic of the book of Chronicles, and several unedited portions in that
                    dialect. Besides these several of the apocryphal gospels and some Gnostic works,
                    as the <hi rend="italic">Pistis Sophia,</hi> are found in the same language; the
                    Acts of the Apostles, sermons, homilies, martyrologies, and many liturgical
                    compositions, and Acts of Councils occur. A great mine of this literature is
                    found in the <hi rend="italic">Catalogus Codicum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Copticorum Manuscriptorum in</hi><hi rend="italic">Museo</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Borgiano,</hi> 4to, Romae, 1810, and other sources. A great number of
                    fragmentary inscriptions on calcareous stone or pottery, chiefly found at
                    Elephantine, exist in the different museums of Europe. Altogether the Coptic
                    literature is not interesting to general students beyond the relation it bears
                    to the ancient Egyptian and its connection with exegetical theology.</p>
                <p>Clot-Bey, <hi rend="italic">Aperçu général sur l'Egypte</hi> (Paris, 1840, p.
                    158, 243); Lane, <hi rend="italic">The Modem</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Egyptians</hi> (8vo, Lond. 1860, p. 529); Peyron, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Grammatica</hi><hi rend="italic">linguoe Copticae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >introductio,</hi> 1841; Quatremère, <hi rend="italic">La langue et la</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">literature</hi><hi rend="italic">de l’Égypte,</hi> 1808; Prichard,
                    <hi rend="italic">Physical History of Mankind,</hi> Lond. 1875, p. 202, foil.
                    (S. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
