<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0171-0146-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COLLINS, Anthony (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    146)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1432098">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:951448">Hares</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140317">Swifts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wr06">Hares</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64900">Soul</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n171/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COLLINS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Anthony</hi></label>
                    (1676-1729), an English writer on theology and philosophy, born at Heston, near
                    Hounslow in Middlesex, on the 21st June 1676, was the son of a country gentleman
                    of good fortune. After being educated at Eton, and at King’s College, Cambridge,
                    he was entered at the Middle Temple, but he did not pursue the profession of the
                    law. The most interesting episode of his life was his intimacy with Locke, who
                    in his letters speaks of him with the most affectionate regard. During a visit
                    to Holland, made, it is said, in order to escape the storm raised by the <hi
                        rend="italic">Discourse of Freethinláng,</hi> he also made the <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n172/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0172-0147"/> acquaintance of Leclerc and several other
                    Dutch scholars. Iu 1715 he settled in Essex; and he was in that county appointed
                    to the offices of justice of the peace and deputylieutenant, which he had before
                    held in Middlesex. His open expression of his opinions, with all its freedom,
                    was, as he owns, carefully kept “within the bounds of doing himself no harm ;”
                    he always published anonymously, though the authorship of his books never
                    appears to have been long a secret; and the independence of his position,
                    together with his pure and genial character, saved him from all personal
                    annoyance. The only attack reported to have been made upon him, otherwise than
                    by means of the press, was the fruitless petition presented by Whiston, while
                    smarting under his criticism, praying that he might be removed from the
                    commission of the peace. Collins died at his house in Harley Street, London, on
                    December 13, 1729, at the age of fifty-three.</p>
                <p>The first work of note published by Collins was his <hi rend="italic">Essay
                        concerning the Use of Reason in Propositions the Evidence whereof depends on
                        Human Testimony</hi> (1707). He demands that the revelation of God should be
                    conformable to man’s natural ideas of God, but draws a distinction between what
                    is contrary to reason and what is merely contrary to our experience. ∙</p>
                <p>Six years later appeared his most famous work, <hi rend="italic">A Discourse of
                        Freethinking, occasioned by the Rise and Growth of a Sect called
                        Freethinkers</hi> (1713). Notwithstanding the ambiguity of its title, and
                    though it attacks the priests of all churches without moderation, it contends
                    for the most part, at least explicitly, for no more than must be admitted by
                    every Protestant, or than is maintained in such works as Taylor’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Liberty of Prophesying;</hi> and it points out forcibly that
                    the first introduction of Christianity, and the success of all missionary
                    enterprise, involve freethinking (in its etymological sense) on the part of
                    those converted. In England this essay, which was regarded and treated as a plea
                    for deism, made a great sensation, calling forth several replies, among others
                    from Whiston, Bishop Hare, Bishop Hoadly, and Richard Bentley, who, under the
                    signature of <hi rend="italic">Phileleutherus Lipsiensis,</hi> roughly handles
                    certain arguments carelessly expressed by Collins, but triumphs chiefly by an
                    attack on his scholarship. Swift also, being satirically referred to in the
                    book, made it the subject of a caricature. In France, where it was answered by
                    Crousaz, it produced a still deeper impression.</p>
                <p>In 1724 Collins published his extraordinary <hi rend="italic">Discourse on the
                        Grounds and Reasons of the Christian Religion,</hi> with <hi rend="italic"
                        >An Apology for Free Debate and Liberty of Writing</hi> prefixed. Ostensibly
                    it is written in opposition to Whiston’s attempt to show that the passages of
                    the Old Testament prophecies quoted in the New had since the time of Christ been
                    corrupted by the Jews, and with the object of proving that the fulfilment of
                    prophecy by the events of Christ’s life is all “secondary, secret, allegorical,
                    and mystical,” since the original and literal reference is always to some other
                    fact. To explain this “allegorical” reading, he quotes from the Dutch Hebraist
                    Surenhusius ten methods according to which the authors of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gemara</hi> and other allegorical writers among the Jews interpret
                    difficult parts of the Scriptures, and which are asserted to have been used in
                    the New Testament. Of these methods the gentlest is altering the points, and the
                    most severe is “changing the order of words, adding words, and retrenching
                    words, which is a method often used by Paul ;” and the true purpose of the book
                    would appear to have been to show, in a veiled satire, that the fulfilment of
                    prophecy in the New Testament is of the same kind as that contrived by the
                    rabbis. And further, as he strives to prove that the fulfilment of prophecy is
                    the only valid proof of Christianity, he thus secretly aims a blow at
                    Christianity as a revelation. The canonicity of the New Testament he ventures
                    openly to deny, on the ground that the canon could only be fixed by men who were
                    inspired. No less than thirty-five answers were directed against this book, the
                    most noteworthy of which were those of Bishop Edward Chandler, Arthur Sykes,
                    Clarke, and Sherlock. To these, but with special reference to the work of
                    Chandler, which maintained that a number of prophecies were literally fulfilled
                    in Christ, Collins replied by his <hi rend="italic">Scheme of Literal Prophecy
                        Considered,</hi> 1727. An appendix contends against Whiston that the book of
                    Daniel was forged in the time of Antiochus Epiphanes.</p>
                <p>In philosophy, Collins takes a foremost place as a defender of Necessitarianism.
                    His brief <hi rend="italic">Inquiry Concerning Human Liberty</hi> (1715) gives,
                    in a remarkably clear and concise form, all the important arguments in favour of
                    his theory, with able and suggestive replies to the chief objections that have
                    been urged against it Little, in fact, of moment has been added by modern
                    determi nists. One of his arguments, however, calls for special criticism,—his
                    assertion that it is self-evident that nothing that has a beginning can be
                    without a caus <hi rend="superscript"> k</hi> e is an unwarranted assumption of
                    the very point at issue. Collins’s position was attacked in an elaborate
                    treatise by Samuel Clarke, in whose system the freedom of the will is made
                    essential to religion and morality. During Clarke’s lifetime, fearing perhaps
                    (as has been suggested) to be branded as an enemy of religion and morality,
                    Collins gave no reply, but in 1729 he published an answer, entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">Liberty and Necessity.</hi></p>
                <p>The other of Collins’s two purely philosophical treatises is <hi rend="italic">A
                        Letter to Mr Dodwell.</hi> A controversy was then being carried on between
                    Clarke, who asserted the natural immortality of the soul, and Dodwell, who held
                    that the soul is mortal till baptism confers immortality upon it; and Collins
                    entered the lists to suggest other possibilities. Adopting Locke’s suggestion,
                    he maintained that it is conceivable that the soul may be material; and,
                    secondly, that if the soul be immaterial it does not follow, as Clarke had
                    contended, that it is immortal; indeed in no way, he argues, can philosophy
                    prove its immortality.</p>
                <p>Two of Collins’s early works yet remain to be mentioned— his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vindication of the Divine Attributes,</hi> in which he attacks a sermon of
                    King, archbishop of Dublin, and maintains that from our knowledge of human
                    qualities we can attain to a true, if limited, knowledge of the divine
                    attributes; and his <hi rend="italic">Priestcraft in Perfection, or a Detection
                        of the Fraud of inserting and continuing the Clause, “The Church hath power
                        to decree Rites and Ceremonies and Authority in Controversies of Faith,” in
                        the Twentieth Article of the Church of England</hi> (1709), to which—as the
                    question excited a very active controversy—he added, early in the next year, a
                    second pamphlet on the same subject. (τ. <hi rend="smallcaps">μ. w.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
