<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0360-0331-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">COOKERY</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 331</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="45" ref="fasttopic:1013210">Meat</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:921787">Fat</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:930458">Food</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:879476">Cornish</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="45" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pq8x">Meat</term>
                    <term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4jm23f50">Fat</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gk5r">Fats</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cp19">Food</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n360/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COOKERY</label>. In the condition in which man finds most of
                    the natural substances used as food they are difficult of digestion. By the
                    application of heat he can change the character of his food, and make it more
                    palatable and more easily digestible. The application of heat to animal and
                    vegetable substances for the purpose of attaining these objects constitutes the
                    science and art of cookery. Innumerable discussions have taken place among
                    scientific; men as to the natural food of man. Too much importance is, perhaps,
                    attached to meat, but it is now generally accepted that a mixed animal and
                    vegetable diet is best.</p>
                <p>If we take a common vegetable food, such for instance as the potato, we find that
                    in 1000 parts we have 760 of water, 200 parts of starch, and some mineral salts
                    and albuminous compounds. In cooking the starch cells absorb water, and the
                    greater number of them burst. This disintegration of the starch cells is
                    preparatory and necessary to more important changes. The starch in all vegetable
                    substances must undergo a similar change before it can mix with the various
                    fluids developed in the mouth and the walls of the alimentary canal. Some of
                    these fluids, such as the saliva and pancreatic fluid, change the starch into
                    dextrin and then into glucose or grape sugar, and this change appears necessary
                    before the carbon and hydrogen can be oxidized. Without the preliminary
                    operation of cooking this change would in all cases be imperfect and often
                    impossible; and the thorough cooking of all starchy foods is <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n361/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0361-0332"/> of the utmost importance. When this is
                    imperfectly done the albuminoid envelope which incloses the starch granule has
                    to be dissolved by the gastric juice, which is often difficult and even
                    impossible. Much indigestion probably arises from the imperfect cooking of
                    starchy foods.</p>
                <p>The chief constituents of animal food are albumen, fibrin, and fat, with mineral
                    salts and juices. The flavour of meat is due to the osmazυne, and some methods
                    of cooking, such as roasting and broiling, appear to increase this flavour.
                    Albumen and fibrin form about one-fifth of the meat. The former always
                    coagulates by heat, and the expansion of the juices tends to separate the solid
                    fibres, and this separation depends very much on the methods of cooking. Albumen
                    is as constant a constituent of all animal food as starch is of vegetable, but
                    these bodies differ greatly in their chemical composition and in the changes
                    which they undergo in the stomach. Albumen is taken into the system as an
                    insoluble substance, but in contact with the gastric fluid it becomes soluble—a
                    condition necessary for every kind of food before it can nourish the body.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Broiling.—</hi> The earliest method of cooking was probably
                    burying seeds and flesh in hot ashes, a kind of broiling on all the surfaces at
                    the same time, which when properly done is the most delicate kind of cooking.
                    Broiling is no ,v done over a clear uniform charcoal fire extending at least 2
                    inches beyond the edges of the gridiron, which should slightly incline towards
                    the cook. It is usual to rub the bars with a piece of suet for meat, and chalk
                    for fish, to prevent the thing broiled being marked with the bars of the
                    gridiron. In this kind of cookery the object is to coagulate as quickly as
                    possible all the albumen on the surface, and seal up the pores of the meat so as
                    to keep in all the juices and flavour. It is, therefore, necessary to thoroughly
                    warm the gridiron before putting on the meat, or the heat of the fire is
                    conducted away while the juices and flavour of the meat run into the fire.
                    Broiling is a simple kind of cookery, and one well suited to invalids and
                    persons of delicate appetites. There is no other way in which small quantities
                    of meat can be so well and so quickly cooked, and for persons who dine alone it
                    is the most convenient method of cookery. Broiling cannot be well done in front
                    of an open fire, because one side of the meat is exposed to a current of cold
                    air. A pair of tongs should be used instead of a fork for turning all broiled
                    meat and fish.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Roasting.—</hi> Two conditions are necessary for good
                    roasting—a clear bright fire and frequent basting. Next to boiling or stewing it
                    is the most economical method of cooking. The meat at first should be placed
                    close to a brisk fire for five minutes to coagulate the albumen. It should then
                    be drawn back a short distance and roasted slowly. If a meat screen be used it
                    should be placed before the fire to be moderately heated before the meat is put
                    to roast. The centre of gravity of the fire should be a little above the centre
                    of gravity of the joint. No kitchen can be complete without an open range, for
                    it is almost impossible to have a properly roasted joint in closed kitcheners.
                    The heat radiated from a good open fire quickly coagulates the albumen on the
                    surface, and thus to a large extent prevents that which is fluid in the interior
                    from solidifying. The connective tissue which unites the fibres is gradually
                    converted into gelatine, and rendered easily soluble. The fibrin and albumen
                    appear to undergo a higher oxidation and are more readily dissolved. The fat
                    cells are gradually broken, and the liquid fat unites to a small extent with the
                    chloride of sodium and the tribasic phosphate of sodium contained in the serum
                    of the blood. It is easily seen that roasting by coagulating the external
                    albumen keeps together the most valuable parts of the meat, till they have
                    gradually and slowly undergone the desired change. This surface coagulation is
                    not sufficient to prevent the free access of the oxygen of the surrounding air.
                    The empyreumatic oils generated on the surface are neither wholesome nor
                    agreeable, and these are perhaps better removed by roasting than any other
                    method except broiling. The chief object is to retain as much as possible all
                    the sapid juicy properties of the meat, so that at the first cut the gravy flows
                    out of a rich reddish colour, and this can only be accomplished by,a quick
                    coagulation of the surface albumen. The time for roasting varies slightly with
                    the kind of meat and the size of the joint. As a rule beef and mutton require a
                    quarter of an hour to the pound; veal and pork about 17 minutes to the pound. To
                    tell whether the joint is doue, press the fleshy part with a spoon; if the meat
                    yield easily it is done. With poultry or game the flesh of the leg may be tried
                    in the same way. Some attach importance to occasional jets of steam drawing to
                    the fire. Roasting, when well done (and the way to do it can only be learned by
                    careful practice), is a wholesome method of cooking.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Baking</hi> meat is in many respects objectionable, and should
                    never be done if any other method is available. The gradual disuse of open
                    grates for roasting has led to a practice of first baking and then browning
                    before the fire. This method completely reverses the true order of cooking by
                    beginning with the lowest temperature and finishing with the highest. Baked meat
                    has never the delicate flavour of roast meat, nor is it so digestible. The
                    vapours given off by the charring of the surface cannot freely escape, and the
                    meat is cooked in an atmosphere charged with empyreumatic oil. A brick or
                    earthenware oven is preferable to iron, because the porous nature of the bricks
                    absorbs a good deal of the vapour. When potatoes are baked with meat, they
                    should always be first parboiled, because they take a longer time to bake, and
                    the moisture rising from the potatoes retards the process of baking, and makes
                    the meat sodden. A baked meat pie, thoi gh not always very digestible, is far
                    less objectionable than plain baked meat. In the case of a meat pie the surfaces
                    of the meat are protected by a bad conductor of heat from that charring of the
                    surface which generates empyreumatic vapours, and the fat and gravy, gradually
                    rising in temperature, assist the cooking, and such cooking more nearly
                    resembles stewing than baking. The process may go on for a long time after the
                    removal of the meat from the oven, if surrounded with flannel, or some bad
                    conductor of heat. The Cornish pasty is the best example of this kind of
                    cooking. Meat, fish, game, parboiled vegetables, apples, or anything that fancy
                    suggests, are surrounded with a thick flour and water crust and slowly baked.
                    When removed from the oven, and packed in layers of flannel, the pastry will
                    keep hot for hours. When baked dishes contain eggs, it should be remembered that
                    the albumen becomes harder and more insoluble, according to the time occupied in
                    cooking. About the same time is required for baking as roasting.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Boiling</hi> is one of the easiest methods of cooking, but a
                    successful result depends on a number of conditions which, though they appear
                    trifling, are nevertheless necessary. The fire must be watched so as properly to
                    regulate the heat. The saucepan should be scrupulously clean and have a
                    closely-fitting lid, and be large enough to hold sufficient water to well cover
                    and surround the meat, and all scum should be removed as it comes to the
                    surface; the addition of small quantities of cold water will assist the rising
                    of the scum. For all cooking purposes clean rain water is to be preferred. Among
                    cooks a great difference of opinion exists as to whether meat should be put into
                    cold water and gradually brought to the boiling point, or should be put into
                    boiling water. This, like many other unsettled questions in cookery, is best
                    decided by careful scientific experiment and observation. If a piece of meat be
                    put into water at a temperature of 60°, and gradually <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n362/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0362-0333"/> raised to 212 <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi>, the
                    meat is undergoing a gradual loss of its soluble and nutritious properties,
                    which are dissolved in the w ater. From the surface to the interior the albumen
                    is partially dissolved out of the meat, the fibres become hard and stringy, and
                    the thinner the piece of meat the greater the loss of all those sapid
                    constituents which make boiled meat savoury, juicy, and palatable. To put meat
                    into cold water is clearly the best method for making soups and broth; it is the
                    French method of preparing the <hi rend="italic">pot</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >au</hi><hi rend="italic">feu;</hi> but the meat at the end of the operation has
                    lost much of that juicy sapid property which makes boiled meat so acceptable.
                    The practice of soaking fresh meat in cold water before cooking is for the same
                    reasons highly objectionable; if necessary, wipe it with a clean cloth. But in
                    the case of salted, smoked, and dried meats soaking for several hours is
                    indispensable, and the water should be occasionally changed. The other method of
                    boiling meat has the authority of the late Baron Liebig, who recommends putting
                    the meat into water when in a state of ebullition, and after five minutes the
                    saucepan is to be drawn aside, and the contents kept at a temperature of 162°
                    (50° below boiling). The effect of boiling water is to coagulate the albumen on
                    the surface of the meat, which prevents, but not entirely, the juices passing
                    into the water, and meat thus boiled has more flavour and has lost much less in
                    weight. To obtain well-flavoured boiled meat the idea of soups or broth must be
                    a secondary consideration. It is, however, impossible to cook a piece of meat in
                    water without extracting some of its juices and nutriment, and the liquor should
                    in both cases be made into a soup.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Stewing.—</hi> When meatis slowly cooked in a close vessel it
                    is said to be stewed; this method is generally adopted in the preparation of
                    made dishes. Different kinds of meat may be used, or only one kind according to
                    taste. The better the meat the better the stew; but by carefully stewing the
                    coarsest and roughest parts will become soft, tender, and digestible, which
                    would not be possible by any other kind of cooking. The only objection to
                    stewing is the length of time; but a dinner may be prepared in this way the day
                    before it is required. Odd pieces of meat and trimmings and bones can often be
                    purchased cheaply, and may be turned into good food by stewing. Bones, although
                    containing little meat, contain from 39 to 49 per cent, of gelatine. The large
                    bones should be broken into small pieces, and allowed to simmer till every piece
                    is white and dry. Gelatine is largely used both in the form of jellies and
                    soups. It is said by some authorities to be comparatively valueless as a food,
                    but more recent investigations seem to prove that gelatine, although not of the
                    same food value as albumen, leaves the body as urea, and must therefore have
                    taken part in nutrition. Lean meat, free from blood, is best for stewing, and,
                    when cut into convenient pieces, it should be slightly browned in a little
                    butter or dripping. Constant attention is necessary during this process, to
                    prevent burning. The meat should be covered with soft water or, better, a little
                    stock, and set aside to simmer for four or five hours, according to the nature
                    of the material. When vegetables are used, these should also be slightly browned
                    and added at intervals, so as not materially to lower the temperature. Stews may
                    be thickened by the addition of pearl barley, sago, rice, potatoes, oatmeal,
                    flour, &amp;c., and flavoured with herbs and condiments according to taste.
                    Although stewing is usually done in a stewpan or saucepan with a closely-fitting
                    cover, a good stone jar, with a well-fitting lid, is preferable in the homes of
                    working people. This is better than a metal saucepan, and can be more easily
                    kept clean; it retains the heat longer, and can be placed in the oven or covered
                    with hot ashes. The common red jar is not suitable; it does not stand the heat
                    so well as a grey jar; and the red glaze inside often gives way in the presence
                    of salt. The lid of a vessel used for stewing should be removed as little as
                    possible. An occasional shake will prevent the meat sticking. At the end of the
                    operation all the fat should be carefully removed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Frying.—</hi> Lard, oil, butter, or dripping may be used for
                    frying. There are two methods of frying,—the dry method, as in frying a pancake,
                    and the wet method, as when the thing fried is immersed in a bath of hot fat. In
                    the former case a frying pan is used, in the other a frying kettle or stewpan.
                    It is usual for most things to have a wire frying basket; the things to be fried
                    are placed in the basket and immersed at the proper temperature in the hot fat.
                    The fat should gradually rise in temperature over a slow fire till it attains
                    nearly 400° Fahr. Great care is required to fry properly. If the temperature is
                    too low the things immersed in the fat are not fried, but soddened; if, on the
                    other hand, the temperature is too high, they are charred. The temperature of
                    the fat varies slightly with the nature of things to be fried. Fish, cutlets,
                    croquets, rissoles, and fritters are well fried at a temperature of 380° Fahr.
                    Potatoes, chops, and white bait are better fried at a temperature of 400° Fahr.
                    Care must be taken not to lower the temperature too much by introducing too many
                    things. The most successful frying is when the fat rises two or three degrees
                    during the frying. Fried things should be of a golden brown colour, crisp, and
                    free from fat. When fat or oil has been used for fish it must be kept for fish.
                    It is customary first to use fat for croquets, rissoles, fritters, and other
                    delicate things, and then to take it for fish. Every thing fried in fat should
                    be placed on bibulous paper to absorb any fat on the surfaces. (j. c. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
