<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0466-0435-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CORPULENCE, or Obesity</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 435</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:952743">Health</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1058667">Personality</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1058664">Personalism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1058861">Persons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1142825">Tanners</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:804171">Albas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:921787">Fat</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jm23f50">Fat</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gk5r">Fats</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b46w96878">Diet</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cp19">Food</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h70803d">Vinegar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n466/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CORPULENCE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Obesity</hi></label>, is
                    a condition of the body characterized by the over-accumulation of fat under the
                    skin and around certain of the internal organs. In all healthy persons a greater
                    or less amount of fat is present in these parts, and serves important
                    physiological ends, besides contributing to the proper configuration of the
                    body. Even a considerable measure of corpulence, however inconvenient, is not
                    inconsistent with a high degree of health and activity, and it is only when in
                    great excess or rapidly increasing that it can be regarded as a morbid state.
                    The extent to which obesity may proceed is illustrated by numerous
                    well-authenticated examples recorded in medical works, of which only a few can
                    be hero mentioned. Thus Bright, a grocer of Maldon, in Essex, who died in 1750,
                    in his twenty-ninth year, weighed 616 lb. Dr F. Dancel records the case of a
                    young man of twenty-two, who died from excessive obesity, weighing 643 B&gt;. In
                    the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi> for 1813 a case is
                    recorded of a girl of four years of age who weighed 256 lb. But the most
                    celebrated case is that of Daniel Lambert of Leicester, who died in 1809 in his
                    fortieth year. He is said to have been the heaviest man that ever lived, his
                    weight being 739 lb (52 st. 11 lb). Lambert had publicly exhibited himself for
                    some years prior to his death, which occurred suddenly at Stamford. At the inn
                    where he died two suits of his clothes were preserved, from which some idea of
                    his enormous dimensions may be obtained, when it is stated that his waistcoat
                    could easily inclose seven persons of ordinary size. Lambert ate moderately,
                    drank only water, and slept less than most persons. He is said, to have had an
                    excellent tenor voice.</p>
                <p>Health cannot be long maintained under excessive obesity, for the increase in
                    bulk of the body, rendering exercise more difficult, leads to relaxation and
                    defective nutrition of muscle, while the accumulations of fat in the chest and
                    abdomen occasion serious embarrassment to the functions of the various organs in
                    those cavities. In general the mental activity of the highly corpulent becomes
                    impaired, although there have always been many notable exceptions to this
                    rule.</p>
                <p>Various causes are assigned for the production of corpulence, but it must be
                    admitted that in many cases it cannot <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n467/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0467-0436"/> be accounted for. In some families there exists
                    an hereditary predisposition to an obese habit of body, the man’festation of
                    which no precautions as to living appear capable of averting. But beyond this it
                    is unquestionable that certain habits favour the occurrence of corpulence. A
                    luxurious, inactive, or sedentary life, with over-indulgence in sleep and
                    absence of mental occupation, are well recognized predisposing causes. The more
                    immediate exciting causes are over-feeding and the large use of fluids of any
                    kind, but especially alcoholic liquors. Fat persons are not always great eaters,
                    though many of them are, while again, leanness and inordinate appetite are not
                    infrequently associated. Still, it may be stated generally that indulgence in
                    food, beyond what is requisite to repair daily waste, goes towards the increase
                    of flesh, particularly of fat. This is more especially the case when the
                    non-nitrogenous (the fatty, saccharine, and starchy) elements of the food are in
                    excess. Although it is still undetermined whether the fat of the body is derived
                    alone from these, or also from the nitrogenous (albuminous) elements of the
                    food, it seems certain that while an excess of the latter constituents
                    accelerates the oxidation and metamorphoses of the fatty tissues, an excess of
                    the non-nitrogenous retards these changes, and thus tends directly to the
                    production of obesity (Parkes). The want of adequate bodily exercise will in a
                    similar manner produce a like effect, and it is probable that many cases of
                    corpulence are to be ascribed to this cause alone, from the well known facts
                    that many persons of sedentary occupation become stout, although of most
                    abstemious habits, and that obesity frequently comes on in the middle-aged and
                    old, who take relatively less exercise than the young, in whom it is
                    comparatively rare. Women are more prone to become corpulent than men, and
                    appear to take on this condition more readily after the cessation of the
                    function of menstruation.</p>
                <p>For the prevention of corpulence and the reduction of superfluous fat many
                    expedients have been resorted to, and numerous remedies recommended. It is
                    unnecessary to allude to these in detail, further than to state that they
                    embrace such regimen as bleeding, blistering, purging, starving, the use of
                    different kinds of baths, and of drugs innumerable, most of which means have
                    been found utterly to fail in accomplishing the desired object. The drinking of
                    vinegar was long popularly supposed to be a remedy for obesity. It is related of
                    the marquis of Cortona, a noted general of the duke of Alba, that by drinking
                    vinegar he so reduced his body from a condition of enormous obesity that he
                    could fold his skin about him like a garment. Such a remarkable result was only
                    a proof of the injury done to his health by the excessive use of vinegar. There
                    is no evidence, whatever, that this liquid has any power to remove fat, while
                    its pernicious effects upon the health, when taken in large quantity, are well
                    known to medical men. Another medicinal agent, which has been proposed on the
                    high authority of Dr T. King Chambers, is the <hi rend="italic">liquor
                    potassce.</hi> This medicine, which is recommended on the ground of the chemical
                    affinity of the alkalis for fats, is directe I to be taken in teaspoonful doses
                    in milk twice or thrice daily, at the same time that a restricted diet and
                    abundant exercise is enjoined. But even this plan, although occasionally
                    yielding good results, cannot be said to have been widely successful. The more
                    rational and hopeful system of treatment appears to be that which is directed
                    towards regulating the quality as well as the quantity of nutriment ingested.
                    This method has of late years received much attention, chiefly in consequence of
                    the publication, in 1863, of a pamphlet entitled <hi rend="italic">Letter on
                    Corpulence, Addressed to the Publicly William Banting,</hi> in which was
                    narrated the remarkable experience of the writer in accomplishing the reduction
                    of his own weight in a short space of time by the adoption of a particular kind
                    of diet. Mr Banting describes the condition of obesity in which he was in August
                    1862, and which, although certainly less than those examples above mentioned,
                    appears to have been sufficient to prove a source of much discomfort and even of
                    actual suffering. After trying almost every known remedy without effect, he was
                    induced, on the suggestion of Ali-Harvey, a London aurist, to place himself upon
                    an entirely new form of diet, which consisted chiefly in the removal, as far as
                    possible, of all saccharine, starchy, and fat food, the reduction of liquids,
                    and the substitution of meat or fish and fruit in moderate quantity at each
                    meal, together with the daily use of an antacid draught. Under this regimen his
                    weight was reduced 46 ft&gt; in the course of a few weeks, while his health
                    underwent a marked improvement. Mr Banting’s recorded experience, as might have
                    been expected, induced many to follow his example, and in numerous instances the
                    effects were all that could be desired. But in many cases the diminution in
                    weight was found to be attended with such a serious impairment of health as to
                    render the carrying out of this system impossible. It is probable that in some
                    at least of these cases the unfavourable effects might have been avoided had the
                    change in diet been more gradually brought about. There seems little reason to
                    doubt that this method, founded as it is on well-recognized principles of
                    physiological chemistry, is that which is most likely to yield the best results
                    in the treatment of corpulence. It evidently cannot, however, be safely adopted
                    in all cases, and ought not to be attempted to be carried out except under
                    medical advice and observation; for however desirable it be to get rid of
                    superabundant fat, it w ould be manifestly no gain were this to be achieved by
                    the sacrifice of the general health. An important element in the treatment of
                    obesity is the due regulation of the amount of bodily exercise, and this, too,
                    ought to be made the subject of the physician’s careful attention.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cursory Remarks on Corpulence, or Obesity considered as a
                    Disease,</hi> by William Wadd, 3d ed., London, 1816; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Corpulence or Excess of Fat in the Human Body,</hi> by Dr. T. King Chambers,
                    London, 1850; <hi rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi rend="italic">théoriqzie</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">pratique del'</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >obésité,</hi> by Dr F. Dancel, Paris, 1863; <hi rend="italic">Letter on
                    Corpulence, addressed to the Public by William Banting,</hi> 3d ed., London,
                    1864; <hi rend="italic">The Practice of Medicine,</hi> by Dr Tanner, London, 6th
                    ed., London, 1869, (J. 0. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
