<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0252-0225-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">COMPASS, The Mariner’s (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    225)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nr79">Carding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qf8jj4b">Cards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4057cw1n">Magnetism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4222rc0p">Magnets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40v89k12">Compassion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g04r">Compass</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zt57">Badger</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1939006">Cards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:847103">Carding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1005823">Magnetics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1005854">Magnetization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1005921">Magnets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:871385">Compassion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:871379">Compass</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n252/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">COMPASS, <hi rend="smallcaps">The Mariner’s</hi></label>,
                    consists of three principal parts,—the card, the needle on its lower surface,
                    and the case. The whole is enclosed in the compass-box, or binnacle. The term
                    compass is said to have been applied to the instrument because the card involves
                    or compasses the whole plane of the horizon, or because the needle indicates the
                    whole circle of possible variations of direction. The surface of the card is
                    divided by radiating lines into 32 parts, each containing 1 l <hi
                        rend="superscript"> o</hi> 15'; these constitute the 32 points or rhumbs;
                    the half-points and quarters are subdivisions of the same. The north pole is
                    denoted on the card by a <hi rend="italic">fleur-de-lis</hi><note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>According to Mr T. S.
                            Davies, this may originally have been an ornamented cross</p></note><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> and the line which joins the north and south poles
                    passes through the axis of the needle. The points are named according to their
                    proximity to the four cardinal points; for instance, the point mid-way between
                    N. and N.E. is called north-north-east, being nearer north than east, and is
                    marked N.N.E; the point mid-way between N. and N.N.E. is termed north by east,
                    and is marked N. by E. The circumference of the card is sometimes divided into
                    360°. The divisions of the card are shown in the accompanying figure. The card
                    is directed by the needle, which, with it, is pivoted on a vertical axis. With a
                    little variation, the needle points nearly to the geographical north, and hence
                    the mode of steering by the compass. Four or more parallel magnets, with like
                    poles pointing in like directions, may be combined to form the needle; and by
                    this arrangement the magnetic moment is increased for a given weight of steel.
                    The needle is usually suspended on a central cap of ruby or agate, the point of
                    suspension being of a similar hard material. On the inside of the compass-box is
                    a vertical line known as lubber’s point; and since this and the pivot of the
                    card are in the same plane with the ship’s keel, the point on the circumference
                    of the card opposite to lubber’s point shows the angle the ship’s course makes
                    with the magnetic meridian. The compass is kept horizontal by the use of a
                    gimbal, or ring moving freely on an axis, wſlthin which it swings on an axis at
                    right angles. In the azimuth compass the circumference of the card is divided
                    into degrees and parts by a vernier, and is fitted up with sight-vanes to take
                    amplitudes and azimuths, for the purpose of determining the variation of the
                    compass by observation. The variation is applied to the magnetic course shown by
                    the steering compass, and thus the true course with respect to the meridian
                    becomes known.</p>
                <p>The conditions that chiefly affect the use of the mariner’s compass are those of
                    the magnetic declination and deviation. The declination is the angle contained
                    between the geographical or true and the magnetic meridian; or, as Barlowe
                    defines it, the swerving of the pointing of the magnetical needle in the horizon
                    from the meridian line there. The angle of declination varies according to
                    locality, and must be ascertained at sea by means of the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n253/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0253-0226"/> azimuth compass. The discovery of the
                    variation of declination was made by Stephen Burrowes when voyaging between the
                    north cape of Finmark and Vaigatch (Vay-gates),and was afterwards determined by
                    Gillebrand, professor of geometry at Gresham College. In 1683, in a
                    communication to the Royal Society <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans.,</hi> June
                    16, p. 214), Dr E. Halley shows that the irregularity observed in the variations
                    of the compass at sea is not due to the attraction of the land, and comes to the
                    conclusion that the whole globe of the earth is one great magnet, having four
                    magnetical poles or points of direction. The declination for any place is
                    subject to secular variations: thus, at Paris in 1681, it was 2° 30' to the W.,
                    in 1865 it was 18° 44' W. Halley, in a paper entitled “Account of the Cause of
                    the Change of the Variation of the Magnetical Needle” <hi rend="italic">(Phil.
                        Trans.,</hi> Oct. 19, 1692, pp. 563-578), points out, with other instances
                    of secular variation, that between 1580 and 1692 the direction of the needle at
                    Loudon changed from ll <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi> 15' E. to 6° W., or more
                    than 17°, and demonstrates that.the direction is in no place fixed or constant,
                    though in some places it changes faster than in others. Besides the secular,
                    there are annual and diurnal variations of small amount. The existence of the
                    latter was discovered by Mr Graham about 1719. The deviation of the compass is
                    the departure of the north and south line from the magnetic meridian, owing to
                    the magnetism of the ship itself, or that induced in it by the earth’s magnetic
                    force. It was first observed during 1772— 74 by Mr Wales, the astronomer of
                    Captain Cook. When surveying along the coast of New Holland in 1801 and 1802,
                    Captain Matthew Flinders made the discovery that there was a difference in the
                    direction of the magnetic needle, according as his ship’s head pointed to the E.
                    or W. —westerly in the former, easterly in the latter case. When the ship’s head
                    was N. or S. the needle took the same direction, or nearly so, that it would on
                    shore, and showed a variation from the true meridian which was about a medium
                    between that given by it when east and when west. He found, also, that the error
                    in variation was nearly proportionate to the number of points which the ship’s
                    head was from the north or south. <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1805, p.
                    186.) The deviation in wooden shipscan be practically obviated, but in iron
                    ships it has to be partly allowed for, partly compensated. Barlow used a
                    correcting plate of iron to overcome the directive action on the compass due to
                    the magnetism of wooden vessels. On Professor Airy’s method, the permanent
                    magnetism of ships is compensated by a steel magnet placed at a given distance
                    below the compass; it is, however, liable to changes of intensity, occasioned by
                    shocks, vibration, unequal heating, and other causes, a fact which led the late
                    Dr Scoresby to propose the employment of a compass aloft, out of the region of
                    the ship’s influence. The induced magnetism of ships can be only imperfectly
                    compensated, since it varies according to the ship’s bearing, and as she rolls
                    and pitches; but corrections can be made for the heeling error. The discovery of
                    the dip of the magnetic needle is ascribed by Gilbert to Robert Norman, a
                    nautical instrument maker at Wapping, who, about 1590, introduced the employment
                    of a sliding weight on the needle for the correction of the dip at different
                    points of the earth’s surface.</p>
                <p>The earliest references to the use of the compass are to be found in Chinese
                    history, from which we learn how, in the sixty-fourth year of the reign of
                    Ho-ang-ti (2634 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> the emperor Hiuan-yuan, or
                    Ho-ang-ti, attacked one Tchi-yeou, on the plains of Tchou-lou, and finding his
                    army embarrassed by a thick fog raised by the enemy, constructed a chariot
                    (Tchi-nan) for indicating the south, so as to distinguish the four cardinal
                    points, and was thus enabled to pursue Tchi-yeou, and take him prisoner.
                    (Klaproth, <hi rend="italic">Lettre à</hi><hi rend="italic">Μ.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">le</hi><hi rend="italic">Baron Humboldt</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >sur l'invention de la Boussole,</hi> Paris, 1834. See also Mailla, <hi
                        rend="italic">Histoire générale de la Chine,</hi> torn i. p. 316, Paris,
                    1777.) Several other allusions to the compass are contained in early Chinese
                    records, <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> ∏ιe power of the loadstone to
                    communicate polarity to iron is said to be for the first time explicitly
                    mentioned in a Chinese dictionary, finished in 121 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d.,</hi> where the loadstone is defined as “a stone with which an
                    attraction can be given to the needle.” The first mention of the use of the
                    compass for the purpose of navigation—an art that has apparently retrograded
                    rather than advanced among the Chinese—occurs in the Chinese encyclopaedia, <hi
                        rend="italic">Ρoei-wen-yun-fou,</hi> in which it is stated that under the
                    Tsin dynasty, or between 265 and 419 A.D., “there were ships directed to the
                    south by the needle.” The Chinese, Mr Davis informs us, once navigated as far as
                    India, but their most distant voyages at present extend not further than Java
                    and the Malay Islands to the south <hi rend="italic">(The Chinese,</hi> vol.
                    iii. p. 14, London, 1844). According to an Arabic manuscript, a translation of
                    which was published by Eusebius Renaudot (Paris, 1718), they traded in ships to
                    the Persian Gulf and Red Sea in the 9th century. Staunton, in vol. i. of his <hi
                        rend="italic">Embassy to China</hi> (London, 1797), after referring to the
                    early acquaintance of the Chinese with the property of the magnet to point
                    southwards, remarks (p. 445), “The nature and the cause of the qualities of the
                    magnet have at all times been subjects of contemplation among the Chinese. The
                    Chinese name for the compass is <hi rend="italic">ting-nan-ching,</hi> or needle
                    pointing to the south; and a distinguishing mark is fixed on the magnet’s
                    southern pole, as in European compasses upon the northern one.” “The sphere of
                    Chinese navigation,” he tells us (p. 447), “is too limited to have afforded
                    experience and observation for forming any system of laws supposed to govern the
                    variation of the needle. . . . The Chinese had soon occasion to perceive how
                    much more essential the perfection of the compass was to the superior navigators
                    of Europe than to themselves, as the commanders of the ‘Lion’ and ‘H indostan,’
                    trusting to that instrument, stood out directly from the land into the sea. The
                    number of points of the compass, according to the Chinese, is twenty-four, which
                    are reckoned from the south pole; the form also of the instrument they employ is
                    different from that familiar to Europeans. The needle is peculiarly poised, with
                    its point of suspension a little below its centre of gravity, and is exceedingly
                    sensitive; it is seldom more than an inch in length, and is less than a line in
                    thickness. It appears thus sufficiently evident that the Chinese are not
                    indebted to Western nations fortheir knowledge of the use of the compass. “It
                    may be urged," writes Mr T. S. Davies, “that the different manner of
                    constructing the needle amongst the Chinese and European navigators shows the
                    independence of the Chinese of us, as theirs is the <hi rend="italic">worse</hi>
                    method, and had they copied from us, they would have used the better one ’’
                    (Thomson’s <hi rend="italic">British Annual,</hi> 1837, p. 291). On the other
                    hand, it does not seem improbable that a knowledge of the mariner’s compass was
                    communicated by them directly or indirectly to the early Arabs, and through the
                    latter was introduced into Europe. Sismondi has remarked <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Literature of Europe,</hi> vol i. ) that it is peculiarly characteristic
                    of all the pretended discoveries of the Middle Ages that when the historians
                    mention them for the first time they treat them as things in general use.
                    Gunpowder, the compass, the Arabic numerals, and paper, are nowhere spoken of as
                    discoveries, and yet they must have wrought a total change in war, in
                    navigation, in science, and in education. Tiraboschi <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Storia</hi><hi rend="italic">della Letteratura Italiana,</hi> tom. iv.
                    lib. ii. p. 204, <hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">seq.,</hi> ed. 2.,
                    1788), in support of the conjecture that the compass was introduced into Europe
                    by the Arabs, adduces their superiority in scientific learning, and their early
                    skill in navigation. He quotes a passage on the polarity of the loadstone from a
                    treatise translated by Albertus Magnus, attributed by the latter to Aristotle,
                    but apparently only an Arabic compilation from the works of various
                    philosophers. As the terms <hi rend="italic">Zoron</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Aphron,</hi> used there to signify the south and north poles, are neither
                    Latin nor Greek, Tiraboschi suggests that they may be of Arabian origin, and
                    that the whole passage concerning the loadstone may have been added to the
                    original treatise by the Arabian translators.</p>
                <p>Dr W. Robertson asserts <hi rend="italic">(Historical Disquisition concerning
                        Ancient India,</hi> p. 227) that the Arabs, Turks, and Persians have no
                    original name for the compass, it being called by them <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bossola,</hi> the Italian name, which shows that the thing signified is
                    foreign to them as well as the word. The Rev. G. P. Badger has, however, pointed
                    out <hi rend="italic">(Travels of Ludovico di Varthema,</hi> trans., J. W.
                    Jones, ed. G. P. Badger, Hakluyt Soc., 1863, note, pp. 31 and 32) that the name
                    of Bushla or Busba, from the Italian <hi rend="italic">Bussola,</hi> though
                    common among Arab sailors in the Mediterranean, is very seldom used in the
                    Eastern seas,— <hi rend="italic">Daïrah</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Beit
                        el-Ibrah</hi> (the Circle, or House of the Needle) being the ordinary
                    appellatives in the Red Sea, whilst in the Persian Gulf <hi rend="italic"
                        >Kiblah-nâmeh</hi> is in more general use. Robertson quotes Sir J. Chardin
                    as boldly asserting “that the Asiatics are beholden to us for this wonderful
                    instrument, which they had from Europe a long time before the Portuguese
                    conquests. For, first, their compasses are exactly like ours, and they buy them
                    of Europeans as much as they can, scarce daring to meddle with their needles
                    themselves. Secondly, it is certain that the old navigators only coasted it
                    along, which I impute to their want of this instrument to guide and instruct
                    them in the middle of the ocean I have nothing but argument to offer <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n254/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0254-0227"/> touching this matter, having never met with
                    any person in Persia or the Indies to inform me when the compass was first known
                    among them, though I made inquiry of the most learned men in both countries. I
                    have sailed from the Indies to Persia in Indian ships, when no European has been
                    aboard but myself. The pilots were all Indians, and they used the forestaff and
                    quadrant for their observations. These instruments they have from us, and made
                    by our artists, and they do not in the least vary from ours, except that the
                    characters are Arabic. The Arabs are the most skilful navigators of all the
                    Asiatics or Africans; but neither they nor the Indians make use of charts, and
                    they do not much want them; some they have, but they are copied from ours, for
                    they are altogether ignorant of perspective." The observations of Chardin, who
                    flourished between 1643 and 1713, cannot be said to receive support from the
                    testimony of some earlier authorities. That the Arabs must have been acquainted
                    with the compass, and with the construction and use of charts, at a period
                    nearly two centuries previous to Chardin's first voyage to the East, may be
                    gathered from the description given by Barros of a map of all the coast of
                    India, shown to Vasco da Gama by a Moor of Guzerat (about the 15th July 1498),
                    in which the bearings were laid down “after the manner of the Moors,’ or “with
                    meridians and parallels very small (or close together), without other bearings
                    of the compass; because, as the squares of these meridians and parallels were
                    very small, the coast was laid down by these two bearings of N. and S., and E.
                    and W., with great certainty, without that multiplication of bearings of the
                    points of the compass usual in our maps, winch serves as the root of the
                    others/’ Further, we learn from Osorio that the Arabs at the time of Gama “were
                    instructed in so many of the arts of navigation, that they did not yield much to
                    the Portuguese mariners in the science and practice of maritime matters.' (See
                        <hi rend="italic">The Three Voyages of Vasco da Gama,</hi> Hakluyt Soc.,
                    1869; note to chap, xv by the Hon. H. E. J. Stanley, p. 138.) Also the Arabs
                    that navigated the Red Sea at the same period are shown by Varthema to have used
                    the mariner’s chart and compass <hi rend="italic">(Travels,</hi> p. 31)</p>
                <p>Again, it appears that compasses of a primitive description, which can hardly be
                    supposed to have been brought from Europe, were employed in the East Indies
                    certainly as early as several years previous to the close of the 16th century In
                    William Barlowe's <hi rend="italic">Navigator's Supply,</hi> published in 1597,
                    we read:—“Some fewe yeeres since, it so fell out that I had severall conferences
                    with two East Indians which were brought into England by master Candish [Thomas
                    Cavendish], and had learned our language: The one of them was of Mamil∏a
                    [Manilla] in the Isle of Luzon, the other of Miaco in Japan. I questioned with
                    them concerning their shipping and manner of sayling. They described all things
                    farre different from ours, and shewed, that in steade of our Compas, they use a
                    ιnag-neticall needle of sixe ynches long, and longer, upon a pinne in a dish of
                    white <hi rend="italic">China</hi> earth filled with water; In the bottome
                    whereof they have two crosse lines, for the foure principali windes; the rest of
                    the divisions being reserved to the skill of their Pilots.’ <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> Baïlak Kibdjaki, also, an Arabian writer, shows
                    in his <hi rend="italic">Merchant's Treasure,</hi> a work given to the world in
                    1282, that the magnetized needle, floated on water by means of a splinter of
                    wood or a reed, was employed on the Syrian seas at the time of his voyage from
                    Tripoli to Alexandria (1242), and adds :—“They say that the captains who
                    navigate the Indian seas use, instead of the needle and splinter, a sort of fish
                    made out of hollow iron, which, when thrown into the water, swims upon the
                    surface, and points out the north and south with its head and tail” (Klaproth,
                        <hi rend="italic">Lettre,</hi> p. 57). Furthermore, although the sailors in
                    the Indian vessels in which Niccola de’Conti traversed the Indian seas in 1420
                    are stated to have had no compass, still, on board the ship in which Varthema,
                    less than a century later, sailed from Borneo to Java, both the mariner’s chart
                    and compass were used; it has been questioned, however, whether in this case the
                    compass was of Eastern manufacture <hi rend="italic">{Travels of Varthema,</hi>
                    Introd, xciv., andp. 249). We have already seen that the Chinese as iate as the
                    end of the 18th century made voyages with compasses on which but little reliance
                    could be placed; and it may perhaps be assumed that the compasses early used in
                    the East were mostly too imp,erfect to be of much assistance to navigators, and
                    were therefore often dispensed with on customary routes. The simple
                    water-compass is said to have been used by the Coreans •so late as the middle of
                    the 18th century; and Dr T. Smith, writing in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Philosophical Transactions</hi> for 1683-4, says of the Turks (p. 439),
                    “They have no genius for Sea-voyages, and consequently are very raw and
                    unexperienced in the art of Navigation, scarce venturing to sail out of sight of
                    land. I speak of the natural <hi rend="italic">Turks,</hi> who trade either into
                    the <hi rend="italic">Hack Sea</hi> or some part of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Morea,</hi> or between <hi rend="italic">Constantinople</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Alexandria,</hi> and not of the Pyrats of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Barbary,</hi> who are for the most part Renegade’s, and learnt their skill
                    in Christendom The Turkish compass consists but of 8</p>
                <p>points, the four Cardinal and the four Collateral.” That the value of the compass
                    was thus, even in the latter part of the 17th century, so imperfectly recognized
                    in the East may serve to explain how in earlier times that instrument, long
                    after the first discovery of its properties, may have been generally neglected
                    by navigators.</p>
                <p>The Saracen geographer, Edrîsi, who lived about 1100, is said by Boucher to give
                    an account, though in a confused manner, of the polarity of the magnet (Hallam,
                        <hi rend="italic">Mid. Ages,</hi> vol. iii. chap. 9, part 2); but the
                    earliest definite mention as yet known of the use of the mariner’s compass in
                    the Middle Ages occurs in a treatise entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Utensilibus,</hi> written by Alexander Neckam in the 12th
                    century. He speaks there of a needle carried on board ship which, being placed
                    on a pivot, and allowed to take its own position of repose, shows mariners their
                    course when the polar star is hidden. In another work, <hi rend="italic"
                        >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Naturis</hi><hi rend="italic">Herum,</hi> lib. ii.
                    c. 89, he writes,— “Mariners at sea, when, through cloudy weather in the day
                    which hides the sun, or through the darkness of the night, they lose the
                    knowledge of the quarter of the world to which they are sailing, touch a needle
                    with the magnet, which will turn round till, on its motion ceasing, its point
                    will be directed towards the north" (W. Chappell, <hi rend="italic">Nature,</hi>
                    No. 346, June 15, 1876). The magnetical needle, and its suspension on a stick or
                    straw in water, are clearly described in <hi rend="italic">La Bible Guiot,</hi>
                    a poem probably of the 13th century, by Guiot de Provins, wherein we are told
                    that through the magnet <hi rend="italic">(la manette</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >Vamanière),</hi> an ugly brown stone to which iron turns of its own accord,
                    mariners possess an art that cannot fail them. A needle touched by it, and
                    floated by a stick on water, turns its point towards the pole-star, and a light
                    being placed near the needle on dark nights, the proper course is known <hi
                        rend="italic">{Hist,</hi><hi rend="italic">littéraire</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >de la France,</hi> tom. ix. p. 199; Barbazan, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fabliaux,</hi> tom. ii. p. 328). Cardinal Jacques de Vitry, bishop of Aeon
                    in Palestine, in his <hi rend="italic">History</hi> (cap. 89), written about the
                    year 1218, speaks of the magnetic needle as “most necessary for such as sail the
                        sea;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Adamas in India
                            reperitur Ferrum occulta quadam natura ad se trahit. Acus ferrea
                            postquam adamantem contigerit, ad stellam septentrionalem semper
                            convertitur, unde valde necessarius est navigantibus in
                        mari.</p></note><hi rend="superscript"> j</hi> and another French crusader,
                    his contemporary, Vincent de Beauvais, states that the adamant (loadstone) is
                    found in Arabia, and mentions a method of using a needle magnetized by it which
                    is similar to that described by Kibdjaki. From quotations given by Antonio
                    Capmany <hi rend="italic">(Questiones Criticas)</hi> from the <hi rend="italic"
                        >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Contemplatione</hi> of Raymond Lully, of the date
                    1272, it appears that the latter was well acquainted with the use of the magnet
                    at sea;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p> Sicut acus per
                            naturam vertitur ad septentrionem dum sit tacta a magnete.—Sicut acus
                            nautica dirigit marinarios in sua navigatione.</p></note> and before the
                    middle of the 13th century Gauthier d’Espinois alludes to its polarity, as if
                    generally known, in the lines :—</p>
                <p>“Tous autres! comme 1 aimant déçoit [détourné] L’aiguillette par force de
                    vertu,</p>
                <p>A ma dame tor le mont [monde] retenue Qui sa beauté connoit et aperçoit.”</p>
                <p>Guido Guinizzelli, a poet of the same period, writes :—“In those parts under the
                    north are the mountains of loadstone, which give the virtue to the air of
                    attracting iron; but because it [the loadstone] is far off, [it] wishes to have
                    the help of a similar stone to make it [the virtue] work, and to direct the
                    needle towards the star. ’<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p> Ginguené, <hi rend="italic">Hist.</hi><hi rend="italic">lit. de
                                tItalie,</hi> t. i. p. 413.</p></note> Brunetto Latini also makes
                    reference to the compass in his encyclopaedia <hi rend="italic">Livres</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">don trésor,</hi> composed about 1260; and a letter written in
                    1269, attributed to Peter Adsiger, shows that the declination of the needle had
                    already been observed at that date. From Torfaeus we learn that the compass,
                    fitted into a box, was already in use among the Norwegians about the middle of
                    the 13th century <hi rend="italic">(Hist. Per. Norvegicarum,</hi> iv. c. 4, p.
                    345, Hafniae, 1711); and it is probable that the use of the magnet at sea was
                    known in Scotland at or shortly subsequent to that time, though King Robert, in
                    crossing from Arran to Carrick in 1306, as Barbour writing in 1375 informs us,
                    “na nedill had na stane," but steered by a fire on the shore.</p>
                <p>From the above it will have been evident that, as Barlowe remarks concerning the
                    compass, “the lame tale of one Flavius at Amelphus, in the kingdome of Naples
                    [Flavio Gioja of Amalphi, cir 1307], for to have devised it, is of very slender
                    probabilitie ;” and as regards the assertion of Dr Gilbert, of Colchester <hi
                        rend="italic">(De</hi><hi rend="italic">Magnete,</hi> p 4, 1600), that Marco
                    Polo introduced the compass into Italy from the East in 1260,<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“According to all the
                            texts he returned to Venice in 1295 or, as is more probable, in
                            1296.”—Yule.</p></note> we need only quote the words of Col. Yule <hi
                        rend="italic">(Book of Marco Polo)</hi> “Respecting the mariner’s compass
                    and gunpowder, 1 shall say nothing, as no one now, I believe, imagines Marco to
                    have had anything to do with their introduction."</p>
                <p>When and by whom the card was added are still matters of conjecture; but the
                    thirty-two points or rhumbs into which it is divided were recognized at least as
                    early as the time of Chaucer, who, in 1391, wrote, “Now is thin Orisonte
                    departed in xxiiii partiez by thi azymutz, in significacion of xxiiii partiez of
                    the world; al be it so that ship men rikne thilke partiez in xxxii” <hi
                        rend="italic">(Treatise on the Astrolabe,</hi> ed. Skeat, Early Eng. Text
                    Soc., Lond. 1872).</p>
                <p>The improvement of the compass has been but a slow process. <hi rend="italic">The
                        Libel of English Policie,</hi> a poem of the first half of the 15th century,
                    says with reference to Iceland (chap, x.)—</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n255/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0255-0228"/>
                <p>“Out of Bristowc, and costes many one, Men haue practised by nedle and by stone
                    Thider wardes within a litle while.”</p>
                <p>Hakluyt, <hi rend="italic">Principal Navigations,</hi> p. 201, Lond. 1599.</p>
                <p>From this it would seem that the compasses used at that time by English mariners
                    were of a very primitive description. Barlowe, in his treatise <hi rend="italic"
                        >Magnetical Advertisements,</hi> printed in 1616 (p. 66), complains that
                    “the Compasse needle, being the most admirable and usefull instrument of the
                    whole world, is both amongst ours and other nations for the most part, so
                    bungerly and absurdly contrived, as nothing more.” The form he recommends for
                    the needle is that of “a true circle, having his Axis going out beyond the
                    circle, at each end narrow and narrower, unto a reasonable sharpe point, and
                    being pure steele as the circle it seife is, having in the middest a convenient
                    receptacle to place the capitell in.” In 1750 Dr Gowan Knight found that the
                    needles of merchant-ships were made of two pieces of steel bent in the middle
                    and united in the shape ot a rhombus, and proposed to substitute straight steel
                    bars of small breadth, suspended edgewise, and hardened throughout. He also
                    showed that the Chinese mode of suspending the needle conduces most to
                    sensibility. In 1820 Prof. Barlow reported to the Admiralty that half the
                    compasses in the Royal Navy were mere lumber, and ought to be destroyed. Since
                    then many improved varieties of ships’ compasses have been introduced, of which
                    may be mentioned, those of Pope, Preston, Walker, Dent, Stebbing, Gowland, Gray,
                    Duchemin, and Harris. In the last the needle turns upon a point which is the
                    centre of a doubly-curved bar of copper, fixed as a diameter to a ring of the
                    same metal. In the Admiralty compass the bowl is of copper, the card of mica;
                    and compound magnetic bars, as proposed by Scoresby, are employed.</p>
                <p>The most remarkable and, as shown by trial, most satisfactory form of the
                    compassis that patented in 1876 by Sir William Thomson (see fig. 2). The card
                    consists of a central boss and an outer rim, both of aluminium, connected
                    together by fine silk cords. Eight or twelve small magnets, 2 to 3 inches long,
                    having their corresponding ends tied together by threads of equal lengths, are
                    suspended by silk cords from the rim, to which is attached thin paper marked
                    with the points of the compass and degrees. The Concentration, in this wise, of
                    the greater part of the weight in the rim gives a long period of free
                    oscillation, and consequently great steadiness; and as the card of a 10-ineh
                    compass, with its suspended needle and sapphire, weighs only 178 grains, the
                    frictional error is very slight. Owing to the smallness of the needles, a
                    perfect correction for all latitudes of a quadrantal error of 5 or 6 degrees for
                    a 10-inch, and of 11 or 12 degrees for a 7-inch compass can be effected by means
                    of a couple of iron globes not more than 6 inches in diameter, fixed on opposite
                    sides of the binnacle. The thwart-ship and the fore-and-aft components of the
                    ship’s magnetic force are neutralized by two adjustable correctors placed one
                    over the other, and so arranged that in their zero position the middle line of
                    both is vertically under the centre of the compass. Each corrector consists of
                    two bar magnets movable round a common horizontal axis perpendicular to their
                    lengths. To correct the heeling error, an adjustable magnet is applied below the
                    compass in a line through its centre perpendicular to the deck. For taking
                    bearings, a new instrument, the azimuth mirror, is provided, whereby the image
                    of the object reflected from a plane mirror is thrown, as in a camera lucida, on
                    the graduated circle of the compass card, and is seen through a convex lens.
                    Another improvement is the use of knife edges instead of journals for supporting
                    the gimbals. A hemispherical space below the compass-case, nearly filled with
                    castor-oil, serves to calm the vibrations of the bowl.</p>
                <p>See articles <hi rend="smallcaps">Magnetism</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Navigation;</hi> Cavallo, <hi rend="italic">Treatise on Magnetism,</hi> 2d
                    ed., Lond. 1800; Macpherson, <hi rend="italic">Annals of Commerce,</hi> 1805;
                    Airy, <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi> 1839, and 1846, part i., and <hi
                        rend="italic">Magnetism,</hi> sect, x., 1870; Johnson, <hi rend="italic">On
                        the Deviations of the Compass,</hi> 1852; Evans, <hi rend="italic">Phil.
                        Trans.</hi>, 1860; Scoresby, <hi rend="italic">The Compass in Iron
                        Ships,</hi> 1855, &amp;c.; Evans and Smith, <hi rend="italic">The Admiralty
                        Manual of the Compass;</hi> Merrifield, <hi rend="italic">Magnetism and the
                        Deviation of the Compass,</hi> part ii., 1872; Harris, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Rud. Treat, on Magnetism,</hi> 1872; Thomson, in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nature,</hi> vol. x. p. 388, 1874. (F. H. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
