<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0493-0481-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ROSICRUCIANS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 481</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1100561">Rosicrucians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1005463">Magi</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110714">Sects</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:998642">Lighting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:998476">Light</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s868">Rosicrucians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mv15">Sects</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rn1g">Light</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r31v">Lighting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=493" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ROSICRUCIANS</label> the name of a sect of philosophers,
                    called hermetical philosophers, who arose, as it has been said, or at least
                    became first conspicuous, in Germany, in the beginning of the fourteenth
                    century. They bound themselves together by a solemn secret, which they all swore
                    inviolably to preserve; and obliged themselves, at their admission into the
                    order, to a strict observance of certain established rules. They pretended to
                    know all sciences, and chiefly medicine, of which they professed themselves <pb
                    break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=494"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0719-0494-0482"/>the restorers. They pretended to be masters of
                    important secrets, and, amongst others, that of the philosopher’s stone; all
                    which they affirmed to have received by tradition from the ancient Egyptians,
                    Chaldaeans, the Magi, and Gymnoso-phists. They have been distinguished by
                    several names, accommodated to the several branches of their doctrine. Because
                    they pretended to protract the period of human life, by means of certain
                    nostrums, and even to restore youth, they were called <hi rend="italic"
                    >Immortales;</hi> as they pretended to know all things, they have been called
                    <hi rend="italic">Illuminati;</hi> and because they have made no appearance for
                    several years, unless the sect of Illuminated which lately started up on the
                    Continent derives its origin from them, they have been called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Invisible Brot}ters.</hi> Their society is frequently signed by
                    the letters F. R. C. which by some amongst them are interpreted <hi
                    rend="italic">Fratres Roris Cocti;</hi> it being pretended, that the matter of
                    the philosopher’s stone is dew concocted or exalted. Some, who are no friends to
                    free-masonry, make the present flourishing society of free-masons a branch of
                    Rosicrucians, or rather the Rosicrucians themselves under a new name or
                    relation, namely, as retainers to building.</p>
                <p>Notwithstanding the pretended antiquity of the Rosicrucians, it is probable that
                    the alchemists, Paracelsists, or fire-philosophers, who spread themselves
                    through almost all Europe about the close of the sixteenth century, assumed
                    about this period the obscure and ambiguous title of Rosi-crucian brethren,
                    which commanded at first some degree of respect, as it seemed to be borrowed
                    from the arms of Luther, which were a cross placed upon a rose. But the
                    denomination evidently appears to be derived from the science of chemistry. It
                    is not compounded, as many imagine, of the two words <hi rend="italic">rosa</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">crux,</hi> which signify rose and cross, but of the latter
                    of these words, and the Latin <hi rend="italic">τos,</hi> which signifies dew.
                    Of all natural bodies, dew was deemed the most powerful dissolvent of gold; and
                    the cross, in the chemical language, is equivalent to light, because the figure
                    of a cross exhibits, at the same time, the three letters of which the word <hi
                    rend="italic">lux,</hi> or light, is compounded. Now <hi rend="italic">lux</hi>
                    is called, by this sect, the seed or menstruum of the red dragon, or, in other
                    words, that gross and corporeal light, which, when properly digested and
                    modified, produces gold. Hence it follows, if this etymology be admitted, that a
                    Ro-sicrucian philosopher is one who, by the intervention and assistance of the
                    dew, seeks for light, or, in other words, the substance called the philosopher’s
                    stone. The true meaning and energy of this denomination did not escape the
                    penetration and sagacity of Gassendi, as appears by his <hi rend="italic">Examen
                    Philosophiae Fluddanae,</hi> sect. 15, tom. iii. p. 261; and it was more fully
                    explained by Renaudot, in his <hi rend="italic">Conferences Publiques,</hi> tom.
                    iv. p. 87.</p>
                <p>At the head of these fanatics were Robert Fludd, an English physician, Jacob
                    Bohm, and Michael Mayer. The common principles which serve as a kind of centre
                    of union to the Roβicrucian society are the following. They all maintain that
                    the dissolution of bodies by the power of fire is the only way by which men can
                    arrive at true wisdom, and come to discern the first principles of things. They
                    all acknowledge a certain analogy and hanpony between the powers of nature and
                    the doctrines of religion; and believe that the Deity governs the kingdom of
                    grace by the same laws with which he rules the kingdom of nature, and hence they
                    are led to use chemical denominations to express the truths of religion. They
                    all hold that there is a sort of divine energy, or soul, diffused through the
                    frame of the universe, which some call the <hi rend="italic">archcus,</hi>
                    others the <hi rend="italic">universal spirit,</hi> and which others mention
                    under different appellations. They all talk in the most superstitious manner of
                    what they call the signatures of things, of the power of the stars over all
                    corporeal beings, and their particular influence upon the human race, of the
                    efficacy of magic, and the various ranks and orders of demons. These de mons
                    they divide into two orders, <hi rend="italic">sylphs</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >gnomes;</hi> which supplied the beautiful machinery of Pope’s Rape of the Lock.
                    In fine, the Rosicrucians and all their fanatical descendants agree in proposing
                    the most crude and incomprehensible notions and ideas, in the most obscure,
                    quaint, and unusual expressions.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
