<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0603-0591-06" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">RUTLANDSHIRE</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 591</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41z41v4m">Clover</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p91c">Wheat</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1006685">Males</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:864888">Clover</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1174325">Wheat</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=603" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">RUTLANDSHIRE</label>, an English county, nearly in the centre
                    of the kingdom, and the smallest of all the divisions so denominated. It is
                    bounded by Lincolnshire on the east and north-east, by Leicestershire on the
                    north-west and west, and by Northamptonshire on the south. Its length from north
                    to south is sixteen, and its breadth from east to west is twelve miles. The
                    square contents are 149 square statute miles, or 95,360 acres. It is divided
                    into five hundreds, and contains two market-towns, Uppingham and Okeham, and
                    forty-nine parishes; being a greater number, in proportion to its extent, than
                    any other county in the kingdom.</p><p>It gives only one title at present, that of duke, to the family of Manners; two
                    former peerages, that of Ferrars of Okeham, and Noel of Exton, being extinct.
                    Only two members are returned to the House of Commons from the county, and none
                    from either of the towns. In judicial affairs it is on the midland circuit of
                    the judges; and in ecclesiastical matters it has formed, since the year 1541, a
                    portion of the bishopric of Peterborough.</p><p>The appearance of this small county is pleasing to the traveller. It is much
                    diversified by ranges of moderate hills running from east to west, in some parts
                    well timbered. Between these ranges of hills, the valleys, of about half a mile
                    in breadth, are luxuriant and verdant. The principal vale, called Catmose, is in
                    the centre of the county, having to the north a tract of table-land overlooking
                    the well-wooded plains of Leicester, Lincoln, and Nottinghamshire. The eastern
                    part is more diversified; the southern division of it consisting of a beautiful
                    valley, stretching towards Northamptonshire, and the western, bordering on
                    Leicestershire; being abundantly wooded.</p><p>The soil on the eastern and south-eastern parts is chiefly shallow, resting upon
                    a basis of limestone, composed of clays and loams. The other parts consist
                    principally of a tenacious but fertile loam; but the vale of Catmose enjoys a
                    most fertile soil of good clay, or red loam, or a grateful mixture of both these
                    earths. A peculiarity of the soil is a redness, which generally prevails, and
                    which tinges all the waters of the country.</p><p>Mr Parkinson, surveyor for the Board of Agriculture, estimates the land of the
                    county in the following manner, viz. pasture land, 34,861 acres; arable land,
                    42,536; wastes, 30; woods, 2815; meadows, 9356; commons, 693; plantations, 65;
                    lakes and ponds, 44 acres.</p><p>The woods of this county were far more extensive in former ages than they are at
                    present. The ancient forest of Leafield, and the chase of Beaumont, though now
                    under the plough, once occupied a great portion of the surface. The climate is
                    generally accounted peculiarly soft and healthy; and the elevation is of that
                    medium kind which equally exempts it from the pernicious effects of moist
                    exhalations and cold mountain fogs.</p><p>The agriculture, though it has partaken of some modern , improvements, is not,
                    upon the whole, conducted in the <pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=604" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0604-0592"/>best manner. In some parts, the reprobated system of two corn crops succeeding
                    a fallow is still continued. In other , parts, after a fallow, barley is sown
                    with clover; the clover is mowed in two years, or sometimes fed the second year,
                    and then, after one ploughing, the land is sown with wheat. In some cases, on
                    the lighter lands, the four-course system of turnips, barley, clover, and wheat,
                    is followed. The wheat of Rutlandshire is highly valued for seed, and is much in
                    request in even very distant counties. Nearly two thirds of the land are tithe
                    free, and in all the late enclosures, provisions to that end have been inserted
                    in the acts of parliament for effecting them. The cows of Rutlandshire are
                    remarkable for the richness of their milk, though they yield but a small
                    quantity. The rich cheese commonly known as Stilton is chiefly made in the
                    dairies of this county. As many oxen are brought from the more northern
                    countries, and fattened in Rutlandshire, as are bred within it, the annua!
                    number of each being from 2700 to 3000. The sheep are more numerous in
                    proportion than horned cattle. Mr Parkinson calculated them to be about 80,000;
                    consisting of old and new Leicesters, of Southdowns, and a few Lincolnshires. It
                    has been remarked, that though the quality of the wool has increased in
                    fineness, the diminution in the weight of the fleeces has of late years more
                    than counterbalanced that advantage.</p><p>The small rivulets that water this district run into the two rivers, the Guash,
                    or Wash, which passes through it, or the Walland, which forms its southern
                    boundary. The latter river is navigable only to Stamford, on the confines of
                    Rutlandshire; but is useful in opening a communication with the ocean. A canal
                    has been constructed from Okeham to Melton-Mowbray, by which a supply of coals
                    has been drawn from the mines of Leicestershire.</p><p>Rutlandshire is neither a manufacturing nor a mineral district, but depends
                    exclusively on its agriculture. By the returns of 1801 the inhabitants were
                    16,356, viz. 7978 males, and 8378 females; in 1811 the numbers were 16,380, viz.
                    7931 males, and 8+19 females; in 1821 they were 18,487, viz. 9223 males, and
                    9264 females; and in 1831 the numbers were 19,385, viz. 9721 males, and 9664
                    females. Of these there were 2299 families chiefly employed in agriculture; 1102
                    families chiefly employed in trade, manufactures, and handicraft; and 790 not
                    comprised in any of these classes.</p></div></body></text></TEI>