<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0018-0008-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RADCLIFFE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 8</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1201065">Publications</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1083449">Publicity</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41834b98">Wards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vq2sk1z">Condottieri</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=18" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RADCLIFFE</label><hi rend="smallcaps">Mrs. Ann,</hi> the
                    celebrated author of the <hi rend="italic">Romance of the Forest,</hi> and the
                    <hi rend="italic">Mysteries of Udolpho,</hi> was born in London on the 9th of
                    July 1764. She was the daughter of William and Ann Ward, who, though in trade,
                    were respectably connected, and nearly the only persons of their two families
                    not living in handsome, or at least easy independence. Her paternal grandmother
                    was a Cheselden, the sister of the celebrated surgeon, of whose kind regard her
                    father had a grateful recollection; and her maternal grandmother was Anne Oates,
                    sister of Dr. Samuel Jebb of Stratford, the father of Sir Richard, on which side
                    she was also related to Dr. Halifax, bishop of Gloucester, and to a gentleman of
                    the same name, who was physician to the king. Of the history of her early years,
                    during which the mind usually gives indications of its prevailing tendencies, no
                    record whatever has been preserved. About the time of her twentieth year,
                    however, she is described as possessing a figure exquisitely proportioned, a
                    fine complexion, a beautiful and expressive countenance, and tastes which led
                    her to take delight in contemplating the glories of creation, particularly the
                    grander features they display, listening to music skilfully performed, hearing
                    passages from the Greek and Latin classics recited and translated, and
                    preferring the pleasures of meditation to those of society.</p>
                <p>Thus respectably born and connected, Miss Ward, at the age of twenty-three,
                    acquired the name which she subsequently rendered so celebrated, by marrying Mr.
                    William Radcliffe, a graduate of Oxford, and then a student of law. This
                    gentleman, however, renounced the prosecution of his legal studies, and
                    afterwards became proprietor and editor of the <hi rend="italic">English
                    Chronicle.</hi> Mrs. Radcliffe having thus a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=19" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0019-0009"
                    />strong inducement to cultivate her literary powers, first came before the
                    public as a novelist in 1789, two years after her marriage, and when she was yet
                    only twenty-five years of age. The romance which she then produced, however,
                    gave but a faint indication of the eminent powers afterwards displayed by the
                    author. In the <hi rend="italic">Castles of Athlin and Dun-bayne,</hi> the scene
                    is laid in Scotland during the dark ages, but without any attempt to delineate
                    the peculiar manners or scenery of that country; and although we may trace some
                    germs of that talent for the wild, the romantic, and the mysterious, which she
                    afterwards employed with so much effect, yet, on the whole, this production
                    cannot be regarded as at all worthy of her pen. Mrs. Radcliffe’s genius,
                    however, was more advantageously displayed in the <hi rend="italic">Sicilian
                    Romance,</hi> which appeared in 1790, and attracted a considerable share of
                    public attention. This work displays the exuberant fertility of imagination
                    which formed the principal characteristic of the author’s mind. Adventures
                    heaped on adventures, in rapid and brilliant succession,with all the
                    hair-breadth charms of escape or capture, hurry the reader along with them;
                    whilst the imagery and scenery by which the action is relieved, resemble those
                    of a splendid oriental tale. Still the work bore marked traces of the defects
                    incident to an unpractised author. The scenes were inartificially connected, and
                    the characters hastily sketched, without any attempt at individual distinctions;
                    the staple materials consisted of ardent lovers and tyrannical parents, with
                    domestic ruffians, guards, and others, who had wept or stormed through the
                    scenes of romance, without much change of character or features, for half a
                    century before. Nevertheless, this praise may be claimed for Mrs. Radcliffe,
                    that she was the first to introduce into her prose fictions a beautiful and
                    fanciful tone of natural description and impressive narrative, which had
                    hitherto been exclusively applied to poetry. Her style was as full of
                    imagination as her subject, and she established a clear title to be considered
                    as the first poetess of romantic fiction, that is, taking poetry in its true
                    acceptation, apart from the mere accessory of rhythm.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Romance of the Forest appealed</hi> in the year 1791,and at
                    once raised the author to that pre-eminence in her own style of composition,
                    which her works have ever since maintained. In this new effort, her fancy was
                    more regulated, and subjected to the fetters of a regular story. The characters,
                    too, were depicted with skill far superior to that which the author had hitherto
                    displayed, and the work attracted the public attention in proportion. That of La
                    Motte, indeed, is sketched with particular talent, and the interest of the piece
                    mainly depends upon the vacillations of a character, which weakness and vice are
                    at every moment on the point of rendering an agent in the greatest atrocities.
                    He is the exact picture of the needy man who has known better days; one who,
                    spited at the world, from which he had been driven with contempt, and condemned
                    to seek an asylum in a desolate mansion full of mysteries and horrors, avenges
                    himself by playing the gloomy despot within his own family, and tyrannising over
                    those who were subjected to him only by their strong sense of duty. The heroine,
                    too, has some pleasant touches of originality, which she displays in her
                    grateful affection for the La Motte family, and her reliance on their truth and
                    honour, when the wife had become unkind, and the father treacherous. But this
                    was not the department of art on which Mrs. Radcliffe’s popularity rested. “The
                    public,” says Sir Walter Scott, “were chiefly aroused, or rather fascinated, by
                    the wonderful conduct of a story, in which the author so successfully called out
                    the feelings of mystery and awe, while chapter after chapter, and incident after
                    incident, maintained the thrilling attraction of awakened curiosity and
                    suspended interest. Of these every reader felt the force, from the sage in his
                    study, to the family group in middle life, which assembles round the evening
                    taper, to seek a solace from the toils of ordinary existence, by an excursion
                    into the regions of imagination. The tale was the more striking, because varied
                    and relieved by descriptions of the ruined mansion, and the forest with which it
                    is surrounded, under so many different points of view, now pleasing and serene,
                    now gloomy, now terrible; scenes which could only have been drawn by one to whom
                    nature had given the eye of a painter, with the spirit of a poet.”</p>
                <p>In 1798 Mrs. Radcliffe visited the scenery on the Rhine, and it is supposed that
                    the <hi rend="italic">Mysteries of Udolpho</hi> were written, or at least
                    corrected, after the period of this journey; the mouldering castles of the
                    robber-chivalry of Germany, situated on the romantic banks of that celebrated
                    stream, having, it is thought, given a bolder flight to her imagination, and a
                    more glowing character to her colouring. The scenery on the Lakes of
                    Westmoreland, which Mrs. Radcliffe had about the same period visited, was also
                    calculated to awaken her fancy; nature having in these wild but beautiful
                    regions, realised the descriptions in which she delighted toin-dulge. Her
                    remarks upon the countries through which she travelled were given to the public
                    in 1793, under the title of a <hi rend="italic">Journey through Holland,</hi>
                    &amp;c. This, however, was merely a sort of intercalary production. As already
                    hinted, her next effort in the province of romance, was the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mysteries of Udolpho,</hi> Of this much was of course expected; and the
                    booksellers felt themselves authorised in offering for the work, what was then
                    considered as an unprecedented sum, namely, L.500. But although a writer’s
                    previous reputation often proves the greatest enemy he has to encounter in a
                    second attempt upon public favour, yet Mrs. Radcliffe’s popularity stood the
                    test, and was enhanced rather than abated by the <hi rend="italic">Mysteries of
                    Udolpho. “</hi> The very name,” says Scott, “was fascinating; and the public,
                    who rushed upon it with all the eagerness of curiosity, rose from it with
                    unsated appetite.” The author pursuing her own favourite bent of composition,
                    and again waving her wand over the world of wonder and imagination, had
                    judiciously employed a spell of broader and more potent command. Every thing in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Mysteries of Udolpho</hi> is on a larger and more sublime
                    scale than in the <hi rend="italic">Romance of the Forest.</hi> The interest is
                    of a more agitating and tremendous nature; the scenery is of a wilder and more
                    terrific description; the characters are distinguished by fiercer and more
                    gigantic features. “Mon-toni, a lofty-souled desperado, and captain of
                    Condottieri, stands beside La Motte and his Marquis, like one of Milton’s fiends
                    beside a witch’s familiar. Adeline is confined within a ruined mansion-house;
                    but her sister-heroine, Emily, is imprisoned in a huge castle, like those of
                    feudal times. The one is attacked and defended by bands of armed banditti; the
                    other only threatened by a visit from constables and thief-takers. The scale of
                    the landscape is equally different; the quiet and limited woodland scenery of
                    the one work, forming a contrast with the splendid and high-wrought descriptions
                    of Italian mountain grandeur which occur in the other. In a word, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Mysteries of Udolpho</hi> was, at its first appearance, considered
                    as a step beyond Mrs. Radcliffe’s former work, high as it had justly raised her;
                    and this impression has been confirmed by subsequent comparative perusal.”</p>
                <p>The next production by which Mrs-Radcliffe arrested the attention of the public,
                    was destined to be her last. The <hi rend="italic">Italian,</hi> which appeared
                    in 1797, was purchased by the booksellers for L.800, and favourably received by
                    the public. Sir Walter Scott praises the author for her judgment “in taking such
                    a point of distance and distinction, that while employing her own peculiar
                    talent, and painting in the style of which she may be considered the inventor,
                    she cannot be charged with repeating or copying herself.” But mere change of
                    subject, or taking a point of distance and distinction, as remote as possible
                    from the scenes in which her imagination had previously expatiated, does not
                    necessarily imply originality of invention in the construction and <pb
                    break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=20"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0719-0020-0010"/>development of her story. On the contrary, she
                    selected a species of machinery afforded her by the most vulgar conceptions
                    entertained of the Catholic religion, when established in its paramount
                    superiority; and instead of contemplating it calmly as reflected in the glass of
                    history, she adopted all the conventional and ready-made horrors that came in
                    her way; and had thus at her disposal the usual apparatus of monks, spies,
                    dungeons, the mute obedience of the familiars of the Inquisition, and the dark,
                    domineering spirit of the crafty emissaries of Rome. “This fortunate adoption,”
                    as Sir Walter Scott calls it, “placed in the hands of the authoress, a set of
                    agents powerful enough to act forcibly on imaginations in which they were
                    associated with all imaginable kinds of atrocity and wickedness, and furnished
                    at once the means of producing a strong effect, without the trouble of inventing
                    new characters, or creating original combinations. But it may be questioned
                    whether such agents, with all their conventional attributes, were suited to the
                    purposes for which they were employed, or whether, even by their
                    instrumentality, any tinge of probability could be imparted to those parts of
                    the story which are most at variance with the ordinary course of human actions
                    and events.” The <hi rend="italic">Italian,</hi> however, was well received by
                    the public, to whom delineations which flatter their religious pride or hatred
                    are always welcome; and after its publication in 1797, the world were not
                    favoured with any more of Mrs. Radcliffe’s works. “Like an actress in full
                    possession of applauded powers, she chose to retire from the stage in the very
                    blaze of her fame; and, for more than twenty years, an imagination naturally so
                    prolific, was, for reasons which we are left in vain to conjecture, condemned to
                    inaction and sterility.”</p>
                <p>The tenor of Mrs. Radcliffe’s domestic life seems to have been peculiarly calm
                    and sequestered. She appears to have declined the notoriety which, in London
                    society, usually attaches to persons of literary distinction; and perhaps no
                    author whose works were so universally read and admired, was so little known
                    personally, even to the most bustling of that class who rest their pretensions
                    to fashion upon the selection of literary society. She no doubt consulted her
                    own feelings, happy in equally avoiding the stare of the curious or the scrutiny
                    of the malignant. Nor did it at all disturb her domestic comforts, although many
                    of her admirers believed, that from brooding over imaginary terrors, her reason
                    had at length been overcome, and that the gifted author of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mysteries of Udolpho</hi> existed only as the inmate of a private madhouse. For
                    this belief, however, there neither was, nor ever had been the most distant
                    foundation; although the rumour on which it was founded had been generally
                    spread, and confidently repeated in print as well as in conversation. During the
                    last twelve years of her life, Mrs. Radcliffe suffered from a spasmodic asthma,
                    which considerably affected both her health and her spirits. This chronic
                    disorder, however, at length took a more fatal turn, on the 9th of January 1823,
                    and on the 7th of February ensuing, it terminated the life of this ingenious and
                    gifted woman, at her own house in London.</p>
                <p>Mrs. Radcliffe, considered as an author, is fully entitled to take her place
                    amongst those who have been distinguished as the founders of a class or school.
                    She led the way in a species of composition, which has since been attempted by
                    many, but in which no one has attained, or even approached the excellencies of
                    the original inventor. The species of romance which she introduced bears nearly
                    the same relation to the novel that a melodrama does to the legitimate drama. It
                    does not appeal to the judgment, by searching delineations of human feeling, nor
                    stir the passions by scenes of deep pathos, nor awaken the fancy, by tracing out
                    the higher marks of life and manners, nor excite mirth, by strong
                    representations of the ludicrous or the humorous. It attains its interest
                    neither by the path of comedy nor by that of tragedy; and yet it has,
                    notwithstanding, a deep, decided, and powerful effect, gained by means
                    independent of both; in other words, by an appeal to the passion of fear,
                    whether excited by natural dangers, or by the suggestions of superstition. The
                    force of the production consists in the delineation of external incidents,
                    whilst the character of the agents are entirely subordinate to the scenes in
                    which they are placed, and only distinguished by such outlines as to make them
                    seem appropriate to their respective situations. The persons introduced bear the
                    features, not of individuals, but of the class to which they belong; and if they
                    be dressed in the proper costume, and converse in language sufficiently
                    appropriate to their stations and qualities, nothing more is required. The
                    primary object is the generation of awe and terror, and everything ministers to
                    the production of this effect. It is enough if the characters be truly and
                    forcibly sketched in outline; they are accessaries rather than principals, and
                    for the most part rather passive than active, so that in throwing upon them and
                    their actions just enough of that dubious light which mystery requires, Mrs.
                    Radcliffe does all that is requisite for the accomplishment of her object. It
                    were easy to find fault with a proceeding like this, which, dispensing with
                    scenes of passion such as those of Richardson, or delineations of life and
                    manners, as in the pages of Fielding and Smollett, carries us back to the fare
                    of the nursery, and gorges us with the wild and improbable fictions of an
                    overheated imagination. And there might be some truth in this, if it were only
                    predicated of the crowd of copyists who came forward as imitators of Mrs.
                    Radcliffe, and assumed her wand, without having the power of wielding it with
                    the same magical effect. But no author can be arraigned for the deficiencies of
                    servile imitators, who present an obscure, distorted, and indistinct outline of
                    what is in itself clear, precise, and distinct; nor can it be truly said that
                    the applause with which the romances of Mrs. Radcliffe were received, argued a
                    great and increasing degradation of the public taste, the corruption of which is
                    almost never the consequence of power and originality; whilst the inferiority of
                    the servile race is much more likely to put the style they imitate out of
                    fashion, than to engraft its peculiarities upon that of a nation. [See Sir
                    Walter Scott’s <hi rend="italic">Biographical Notice of Mrs Ann
                    Radcliffe.]</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
