<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0095-0085-09" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">REEVE, Clara</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 85</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839101">Britons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=95" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">REEVE, Clara</label>, the ingenious authoress of <hi
                    rend="italic">The Old English Baron,</hi> was the daughter of the Reverend
                    William Reeve, rector of Freston, and of Kerton, in Suffolk, and perpetual
                    curate of St Nicholas. Her mother’s maiden name was Smithies, daughter of Mr
                    Smithies, goldsmith and jeweller to George I. The father of Miss Reeve was “an
                    old Whig,” and from him she learned all that she knew; he was her oracle, and
                    used to make her readl the parliamentary debates whilst he smoked his pipe after
                    supper. Under the same paternal tuition, she also read Rapin’s History of
                    England, Cato’s Letters, the Greek and Roman histories, and Plutarch’s Lives, at
                    an age when few people of either sex can read their own names. Mr Reeve, himself
                    one of a family of eight children, had the same number of offspring; and hence
                    it is probable that Clara’s strong natural turn for study, rather than any
                    degree of exclusive care which his partiality could bestow, enabled her to
                    acquire such a stock of early information.</p>
                <p>After the death of Mr Reeve, his widow resided in Colchester with three of his
                    daughters; and it was here that Clara first became an authoress, by translating
                    from the original Latin Barclay’s fine old romance of Argenis, which was
                    published in 1762, under the title of <hi rend="italic">The Phoenix.</hi> It was
                    not, however, until 1767, five years afterwards, that she produced her first and
                    most distinguished work, which was published by Mr Dilly of the Poultry, under
                    the title of <hi rend="italic">The Champion of Virtue.</hi> The sum given for
                    the copyright was only ten pounds; but in the following year the work came to a
                    second edition, and was then first called <hi rend="italic">The Old English
                    Baron,</hi> for what reason we do not pretend to conjecture. This production is
                    inscribed to Mrs Brigden, the daughter of Richardson, who is stated to have lent
                    some assistance in the revision and correction of the work.</p>
                <p>The success of The Old English Baron encouraged Miss Reeve to devote more of her
                    leisure hours to literary composition, and accordingly she published in
                    succession, The Two Mentors, The Progress of Romance, The Exile, The School for
                    Widows, Plans of Education, and Memoirs of Sir Roger de Clarendon, a natural son
                    of the Black Prince, with Anecdotes of many other eminent persons of the
                    fourteenth century. To these works there remains to be added another, the
                    interest of which turned upon supernatural appearances. In a preface to a
                    subsequent edition of The Old English Baron, Miss Reeve informs the public that,
                    in compliance with the suggestion of a friend, she had composed <hi
                    rend="italic">Castle Connor,</hi> an Irish story, in which apparitions were
                    introduced. But the manuscript being intrusted to some careless or unfaithful
                    person, fell aside, and was never recovered. The various novels produced by this
                    lady are all marked by excellent good sense, pure morality, and a considerable
                    command of those qualities requisite to constitute a good romance. They were,
                    generally speaking, favourably received at the time; but none of them took the
                    same strong possession of the public mind as The Old English Baron, upon which
                    the fame of the author may be considered as now exclusively rested, and by which
                    alone 6he will be known to posterity.</p>
                <p>Miss Reeve led a retired life, affording no materials for biography, until the
                    beginning of December 1803, when she died at Ipswich, her native city, at the
                    advanced age of seventy-eight years, and was buried in the churchyard of St
                    Stephens, according to her particular direction. Such are the only particulars
                    that have been collected concerning this accomplished and excellent woman; and,
                    in their simplicity, the reader may remark that of her life and her character.
                    The following critical observations, confined entirely to her most celebrated
                    work, which first established her fame, and upon which alone it will in all
                    probability rest, are extracted from the biographical notice of Miss Reeve by
                    Sir Walter Scott, to which we have also been in-* debted for the foregoing
                    particulars of her life.</p>
                <p>“The authoress has herself informed us that The Old English Baron is the *
                    literary offspring of The Castle of Otranto ;’ and she has obliged us by
                    pointing out the different and more limited view which she had adopted, of the
                    supernatural machinery employed by Horace Walpole. She condemns the latter for
                    the extravagance of several of his conceptions; for the gigantic size of his
                    sword and helmet; and for the violent fictions of a walking picture, and a
                    skeleton in a hermit’s cowl. A ghost, she contends, to be admitted as an
                    ingredient in romance, must behave himself like ghosts of sober demeanour, and
                    subject himself to the common rules still preserved in grange and hall, as
                    circumscribing beings of his description.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=96"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0719-0096-0086"/>
                <p>“We must, however, notwithstanding her authority, enter our protest against
                    fettering the realm of shadows by the opinions entertained of it in the world of
                    realities. If we are to try ghosts by the ordinary rules of humanity, we bar
                    them of their privileges entirely. For instance, why admit the existence of an
                    aerial phantom, and deny it the terrible attribute of magnifying its stature?
                    why admit an enchanted helmet, and not a gigantic one? why allow as an
                    impressive incident the fall of a suit of armour, thrown down, we must suppose,
                    by no mortal hand, and at the same time deny the same supernatural influence the
                    power of producing the illusion (for it is only represented as such) upon
                    Manfred, which gives seeming motion and life to the portrait of his ancestor? It
                    may be said, and it seems to be Miss Reeve’s argument, that there is a verge of
                    probability, which even the most violent figment must not transgress; but we
                    reply by the cross question, that if we are once to subject our preternatural
                    agents to the limits of human reason, where are we to stop? We might, under such
                    a rule, demand of ghosts an account of the very circuitous manner in which they
                    are pleased to open their communications with the living world. We might, for
                    example, move a <hi rend="italic">quo warranto</hi> against the spectre of the
                    murdered Lord Lovel, for lurking about the eastern apartment, when it might have
                    been reasonably expected, that if he did not at once impeach his murderers to
                    the next magistrate, he might at least have put Fitzowen into the secret, and
                    thus obtained the succession of his son more easily than by the dubious and
                    circuitous route of a single combat. If there should be an appeal against this
                    imputation, founded on the universal practice of ghosts, in such circumstances,
                    who always act with singular obliquity in disclosing the guilt of which they
                    complain, the matter becomes a question of precedent; in which view of the case,
                    we may vindicate Horace Walpole for the gigantic exaggeration of his phantom, by
                    the similar expansion of the terrific vision of Fa-doun, in Blind Harry’s Life
                    of Wallace; and we could, were we so disposed, have paralleled his moving
                    picture, by the example of one with which we ourselves had some acquaintance,
                    which was said both to move and to utter groans, to the great alarm of a family
                    of the highest respectability.</p>
                <p>“Where, then, may the reader ask, is the line to be drawn? or what are the limits
                    to be placed to the reader’s credulity, when those of common sense and ordinary
                    nature are once extended? The question admits only one answer, namely, that the
                    author himself, being in fact the magician, shall evoke no spirits whom he is
                    not capable of endowing with manners and language corresponding to their
                    supernatural character. Thus Shakspeare, drawing such characters as Caliban and
                    Ariel, gave them reality, not by appealing to actual opinions, which his
                    audience might entertain respecting the possibility or impossibility of their
                    existence, but by investing them with such attributes as all readers and
                    spectators recognised as those which must have corresponded to such
                    extraordinary beings, had their existence been possible. If he had pleased to
                    put into language the ‘ squeaking and gibbering* of those disembodied phantoms
                    which haunted the streets of Rome, no doubt his wonderful imagination could have
                    filled up the sketch which, marked by these two emphatic and singularly
                    felicitous expressions, he has left as characteristic of the language of the
                    dead.</p>
                <p>“In this point of view, our authoress has, with equal judgment and accuracy,
                    confined her flight within those limits on which her pinions could support her;
                    and though we are disposed to contest her general principle, we are willing to
                    admit it as a wise and prudent one, so far as applied to regulate her own
                    composition. In no part of The Old English Baron, or of any other of her works,
                    does Miss Reeve show the possession of a rich or powerful imagination. Her
                    dialogue is sensible, easy, and agreeable, but neither marked by high flights of
                    fancy nor strong bursts of passion. Her apparition is an ordinary fiction, of
                    which popular superstition used to furnish a thousand instances, when nights
                    were long, and a family, assembled round a Christmas log, had little better to
                    do than to listen to such tales. Miss Reeve has been very felicitously cautious
                    in showing us no more of Lord Lovel’s ghost than she needs must; he is a silent
                    apparition, palpable to the sight only, and never brought forward into such
                    broad daylight as might have dissolved our reverence. And so far, we repeat, the
                    authoress has used her own power to the utmost advantage, and gained her point
                    by not attempting a step beyond it. But we cannot allow that the rule which, in
                    her own case, has been well and wisely adopted, ought to circumscribe a bolder
                    and more imaginative writer.</p>
                <p>“In what may be called the costume, or keeping, of the chivalrous period in which
                    tile scene of both is laid, the language and style of Horace Walpole, together
                    with his intimate acquaintance with the manners of the middle ages, form an
                    incalculable difference betwixt The Castle of Otranto and The Old English Baron.
                    Clara Reeve, probably, was better acquainted with Plutarch and Rapin than with
                    Froissart or Olivier de la Marche. This is no imputation on the taste of that
                    ingenious lady. In her days, Macbeth was performed in a general’s full uniform,
                    and Lord Hastings was dressed like a modern high chamberlain going to court. Or,
                    if she looked to romances for her authority, those of the French school were
                    found introducing, under the reign of Cyrus or of Faramond, or in the early
                    republic at Rome, the sentiments and manners of the court of Louis XIV. In the
                    present day more attention to costume is demanded, and authors, as well as
                    players, are obliged to make attempts, however fantastic or grotesque, to
                    imitate the manners on the one hand, and the dress on the other, of the times in
                    which the scene is laid. Formerly, nothing of this kind was either required or
                    expected; and it is not improbable that the manner in which Walpole
                    circumscribes his dialogue (in most instances) within the stiff and stem
                    precincts prescribed by a strict attention to the manners and language of the
                    times, is the first instance of such restrictions. In The Old English Baron, on
                    the contrary, all parties speak and act much in the fashion of the seventeenth
                    century; employ the same phrases of courtesy; and adopt the same tone of
                    conversation. Baron Fitzowen <hi rend="subscript">1</hi> and the principal
                    characters, talk after the fashion of country squires of that period, and the
                    lower personages like gaffers and gammers of the same era. And ‘ were but the
                    combat in the lists left out,’ or converted into a modem duel, the whole train
                    of incidents might, for any peculiarity to be traced in the dialect or
                    narration, have taken place in the time of Charles II., or in either of the two
                    succeeding reigns. As it is, the story reads as if it had been transcribed into
                    the language, and remodelled according to the ideas, of this latter period. Yet
                    we are uncertain whether, upon the whole, this does not rather add to than
                    dimmish the interest of the work; at least it gives an interest of a different
                    kind, which, if it cannot compete with that which arises out of a highly exalted
                    and poetical imagination, and a strict attention to the character and manners of
                    the middle ages, has yet this advantage, that it reaches its point more surely
                    than had a higher, more difficult, and more ambitious line of composition been
                    attempted.</p>
                <p>“He that would please the modern world, yet present the exact impression of a
                    tale of the middle ages, will repeatedly find that he will be obliged, in
                    despite of his utmost exertions, to sacrifice the last to the first object, and
                    eternally expose himself to the just censure of the rigid antiquary, because he
                    must, to interest the readers of the present time, invest his characters with
                    language and sentiments unknown to the period assigned to his story; and <pb
                    break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=97"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0719-0097-0087"/>thus his utmost efforts only attain a sort of
                    composition ' between the true and the fictitious, just as the dress of Lear, as
                    performed on the stage, is neither that of a modem sovereign, nor the cerulean
                    painting and bear-hide with which the Britons, at the time when that monarch is
                    supposed to have lived, tattooed their persons, and sheltered themselves from
                    cold. All this inconsistency is avoided by adopting the style of our
                    grandfathers and great-grandfathers, sufficiently antiquated to accord with the
                    antiquated character of the narrative, yet copious enough to express all that is
                    necessary to its interest, and to supply that deficiency of colouring which the
                    more ancient times do not afford.</p>
                <p>“It is no doubt true that The Old English Baron, written in the latter and less
                    ambitious taste, is sometimes tame and tedious, not to say mean and tiresome.
                    The total absence of peculiar character (for every person introduced is rather
                    described as one of a genus than as an original, discriminated, and individual
                    person) may have its effect in producing the tedium which loads the story in
                    some places. This is a general defect in the novels of the period, and it was
                    scarce to be expected that the amiable and accomplished authoress, in her
                    secluded situation, and with acquaintance of events and characters derived from
                    books alone, should have rivalled those authors who gathered their knowledge of
                    the human heart from having, like Fielding and Smollett, become acquainted, by
                    sad experience, with each turn of ‘ many-coloured life.’ Nor was it to be
                    thought that she should have emulated in this particular her prototype Walpole,
                    who, as a statesman, a poet, and a man of the world, ‘ who knew the world like a
                    man,’ has given much individual character to his sketch of Manfred. What we here
                    speak of is not the deficiency in the style and costume, but a certain creeping
                    and low line of narrative and sentiment; which may be best illustrated by the
                    grave and minute accounting into which Sir Philip Harclay and the Baron Fitzowen
                    enter, after an event so unpleasant as the judgment of heaven upon a murderer,
                    brought about by a judicial combat, and that combat occasioned by the awful and
                    supernatural occurrences in the eastern chamber, where we find the arrears of
                    the estate gravely set off against the education of the heir, and his early
                    maintenance in the baron’s family. Yeteven these prolix, minute, and unnecessary
                    details are precisely such as would occur in a similar story told by a grandsire
                    or grandame to a circle assembled round a winter’s fire; and while they take
                    from the dignity of the composition, and would therefore have been rejected by a
                    writer of more exalted imagination, do certainly add in some degree to its
                    reality, and bear in that respect a resemblance to the art with which De Foe
                    impresses on his readers the truth of his fictions, by the insertion of many
                    minute and immaterial or unnatural circumstances, which we are led to suppose
                    could only be recorded because they are trae. Perhaps, to be circumstantial and
                    abundant in minute detail, and, in one word, though an unauthorized one, to be
                    somewhat <hi rend="italic">prosy,</hi> is a secret mode of securing a certain
                    necessary degree of credulity from the hearers of a ghost-story. It gives a sort
                    of quaint antiquity to the whole, as belonging to the times of <hi
                    rend="superscript">,</hi> superstitious elde ;’ and those whom we have observed
                    to excel in oral narratives of such a nature, usually study to secure the
                    attention of their audience by employing this art. At least, whether owing to
                    this mode of telling her tale, or to the interest of the story itself, and its
                    appeal to the secret reserve of superstitious feeling which maintains its
                    influence in most bosoms, The Old English Baron has always produced as strong an
                    effect as any story of the kind, although liable to the objections which we have
                    freely stated, without meaning to impeach the talents of the amiable authoress.”
                    (a.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
