<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0719-0250-0240-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">RIENZI</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 240</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zd0b">Ghosts</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0341g">Customs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942434">Ghosts</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:920123">Fame</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=250" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">RIENZI</label> Nicholas Gabrini de, one of the most singular
                    characters of the fourteenth century, was born at Rome, but it is not certainly
                    known in what year. His father, as some affirm, was a vintner, but, according to
                    others, a miller, and his mother was a laundress, yet they found means to give
                    their son a liberal education; and to a fine natural understanding he added
                    uncommon application. He was well acquainted with the laws and customs of
                    nations; and had a vast memory, which enabled him to retain much of Cicero,
                    Valerius Maximus, Livy, the two Senecas, and, in particular, Caesar’s
                    Commentaries, which he constantly perused. This extensive erudition proved the
                    foundation of his future rise. He acquired the reputation of a great antiquary,
                    from the time which he spent among the inscriptions to be found at Rome, and
                    these inspired him with exalted ideas of the liberty, the grandeur, and justice
                    of the old Romans. He even persuaded himself, and found means to persuade
                    others, that he should one day be the restorer of the Roman republic. The
                    credulity of the people was powerfully encouraged and strengthened by his
                    advantageous stature, by the attractions of his countenance, and by that air of
                    consequence which he could assume at pleasure. The joint energy of all these
                    prepossessing qualities made a deep and almost indelible impression on the minds
                    of his hearers.</p>
                <p>Nor was his fame merely confined to the vulgar, for he even ingratiated himself
                    into the good opinion of many distinguished personages belonging to the
                    administration. The Romans chose him one of their deputies to Pope Clement VI.
                    then at Avignon. The purport of this mission was to persuade his holiness that
                    his absence from the capital was inimical to its interest. His commanding
                    eloquence and gay conversation charmed the court of Avignon; and Rienzi was thus
                    encouraged to tell the pope, that the great men of Rome were public thieves,
                    robbers, adulterers, and profligates, by whose example the most horrid crimes
                    were sanctioned. This ill-timed freedom of speech made Cardinal Colonna his
                    enemy, though the friend of genuine merit, because he thought that some of his
                    family were included in this flagrant accusation. Rienzi was disgraced, and fell
                    into extreme misery, vexation, and sickness, which, by being united with
                    indigence, brought him to a hospital. But <pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=251" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0251-0241"
                    />as the cardinal was compassionate, the offender was again brought before the
                    pope, who, being informed that Rienzi was a good man, and the strenuous advocate
                    of equity and justice, gave him higher proofs of his esteem and confidence than
                    before. He was appointed apostolic notary, and sent back to Rome loaded with the
                    effects of papal munificence.</p>
                <p>The functions of this office he executed in such a manner as to become the idol
                    of the people, whose affections he laboured to secure by exclaiming against the
                    vices of the great, rendering them as odious as possible; for which imprudent
                    liberties he was dismissed from office. In this situation of his affairs he
                    endeavoured to kindle and keep alive in the minds of the people a zeal for their
                    ancient liberties, displaying emblems of the former grandeur and present decline
                    of the city, accompanied with harangues and many expressive predictions. Such an
                    intrepid, and at the same time extraordinary conduct, made some regard him as a
                    lunatic, while others hailed him as their guardian and deliverer. When he
                    supposed that the numbers attached to his interest were sufficiently strong, he
                    called them together, and gave them a dismal picture of the state of the city,
                    overrun with debaucheries, which their governors had neither capacity to correct
                    nor to amend. He declared that the pope could, even at the rate of fourpence,
                    raise 100,000 florins by fuel, an equal sum by salt, and as much more by the
                    customs and other duties; insinuating that he did not seize on the revenues
                    without the consent of his holiness.</p>
                <p>This artful tale so powerfully animated his hearers, that they signified their
                    determination to secure these treasures for whatever purposes might be most
                    convenient, and that to his will they would cheerfully devote themselves. This
                    resolution he caused them confirm by an oath; and it is said that he had the
                    address to procure from the pope’s vicar the sanction of his authority. On the
                    20th of May, being Whitsunday, he averred that he did nothing but in consequence
                    of the particular inspiration of the Holy Ghost, and about nine o’clock he came
                    out of the church with his head bare, attended by the pope’s vicar, and about a
                    hundred men in armour. Having proceeded directly to the capitol, he declared
                    from the rostrum, with even more than his wonted boldness and energy, that the
                    hour of their emancipation was at length arrived; that he himself was to be
                    their glorious deliverer, and that he poured contempt on the dangers to which he
                    might be exposed in the service of his holiness, and for the happy deliverance
                    of the people. The laws of the “good establishment” were next ordered to be
                    read; and he rested assured that the Romans would resolve to observe those laws,
                    in consequence of which he pledged himself to re-establish them in a short time
                    in their ancient grandeur and magnificence.</p>
                <p>Plenty and security were the blessings promised by the good establishment,
                    together with the humbling of the nobles, who were regarded as common
                    oppressors. Such ideas filled the people with transport, and they became
                    zealously attached to the fanaticism of Rienzi. The multitude declared him to be
                    sovereign of Rome, to whom they granted the power of life and death, of rewards
                    and punishments, of making and repealing laws, of treating with foreign powers,
                    and a full and absolute authority over all the Roman territories.</p>
                <p>Having thus arrived at the zenith of his ambition, he concealed his artifice as
                    much as possible, and pretended to be extremely averse to accept of their
                    proffered honours, unless they would make choice of the pope’s vicar to be his
                    coadjutor, and find means to procure the sanction of the pope himself. His wish
                    to have the vicar, bishop of Or-vieto, as his coadjutor was readily complied
                    with, while all the honours were paid to Rienzi, the duped bishop enjoying but a
                    mere nominal authority. Rienzi was seated in his triumphal chariot, and the
                    people were dismissed, overwhelmed with joy and expectation. This strange
                    election was ratified by the pope, although it was impossible that he could
                    inwardly approve of it; and to procure a title exclusive of the prerogative of
                    his holiness, was the next object of Rienzi’s ambition. He sought, therefore,
                    and readily obtained the title of magistrate, which was conferred on him and his
                    coadjutor, with the addition of <hi rend="italic">deliverers of their
                    country.</hi> The conduct of Rienzi immediately subsequent to this elevation
                    justly procured him esteem and respect, as well from the Romans as from
                    neighbouring states; but as his beginning was mean and obscure, he soon became
                    intoxicated with his sudden, his extraordinary elevation, and the incensed
                    nobles having conspired against him, succeeded in their attempt to drive him
                    from an authority which he had not the prudence or address to retain more than
                    six months. At this critical period, his life was only preserved by flight, and
                    by the disguises to which he afterwards had recourse.</p>
                <p>Having made an ineffectual effort at Rome to regain his authority, he proceeded
                    to Prague to Charles king of the Romans. In consequence of this rash step he was
                    sent as a prisoner to Avignon, where he continued for three years. When he
                    procured his enlargement, Pope Innocent IV., who succeeded Clement, well knew
                    that many of the Romans were still attached to Rienzi, and therefore he made
                    choice of him as a fit object for assisting him in his design of humbling the
                    other petty tyrants of Italy. In short, he was set at liberty, and appointed
                    governor and senator of Rome. It was hoped that his chastisement would teach him
                    more moderation in future, and that gratitude would induce him to preserve an
                    inviolable attachment to the holy see during the remainder of his life. He met
                    with considerable opposition in assuming his new authority, but cunning and
                    resolution enabled him to overcome it. But gratifying his passions, which were
                    violent in the extreme, and disgracing his office and character by acts of
                    cruelty, he was murdered on the 8th of October 1354.</p>
                <p>Thus died Nicholas Rienzi, one of the most extraordinary characters of the age in
                    which he lived; who, having formed a conspiracy big with extravagance, and
                    carried it into execution nearly in the face of the whole world, with such
                    remarkable success as to become sovereign of Rome; having blessed the Romans
                    with plenty, liberty, and justice; having afforded protection to some princes,
                    and proved a terror to others; having become the arbiter of crowned heads,
                    established the ancient majesty and power of the Roman republic, and filled all
                    Europe with his fame; finally, having procured their sanction whose authority he
                    had usurped in opposition to their interests, he fell at last a sacrifice to the
                    nobles whose ruin he had vowed, and to those vast projects, the execution of
                    which was only prevented by his death,</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
