<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0235-0225-04" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">RHONE</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 225</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43j39453">Silk</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42805001">Troubadours</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:878993">Corn</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1118724">Silk</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:845230">Canals</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:983135">Jews</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1157538">Troubadours</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=235" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">RHONE</label>, a department of France, formed out of the
                    ancient districts of the Lyonnois and the Beaujolais. It is situated between 45.
                    26. and 46. 25. of north latitude, and between 4. 12. and 4. 37. of east
                    longitude. It extends over 1090 square miles, and is divided into two
                    arrondissements, which in the year 1836 contained twenty-five cantons and 253
                    communes, with 482,024 inhabitants, who mostly adhere to the Catholic Church.
                    The face of the country is irregular, in all parts hilly, and in some
                    mountainous. The vales <pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=236" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0236-0226"/>226 R H O</p><p>Rhone, between the several elevations are narrow, and have a soil v—' poor and
                    stony, except in that division on the rivers Saone and Rhone which includes some
                    level tracts of greater extent, well cultivated, adorned with fine trees, and
                    presenting a mixture of corn-fields, meadows, and vineyards. The chief rivers
                    are the Rhone and the Saone, the latter of which falls into the former near
                    Lyons, having received the water of the Izeron, the Garon, the Gier, with that
                    of several smaller streams, which empty themselves at length into the
                    Mediterranean Sea. Both the Rhone and the Saone are navigable through the whole
                    of their course within this department. The climate is mild, but, from the
                    vicinity of the mountains, is very variable, and from the same cause vegetation
                    is late in the spring. The productions are, the common domestic animals, wax,
                    honey, and abundance of game, wild fowl, and fish. The produce of corn is
                    deficient for tile annual supply by about six weeks’ consumption. Hemp, flax,
                    poppies, rapeseed, saffron, almonds, chestnuts, and potatoes, are extensively
                    grown. The vine is extensively cultivated, and those on the banks of both the
                    Saone and Rhone have, under a variety of names taken from the respective
                    districts, acquired great celebrity. There are some, but not considerable, mines
                    of copper, and others of vitriol and of coal. The manufacturing industry is
                    great. The silk manufacture is the most extensive, and is chiefly carried on in
                    and around the city of Lyons, the capital of the department.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Rhone,</hi><hi rend="italic">Mouths of the,</hi> a
                    department in the south of France, formed out of the western part of the ancient
                    province. It extends in north latitude from 43. 12. to 44. 1., and in east
                    longitude from 4. 18. to 4. 46., comprehending 2003 square miles, or 512,991
                    hectares, equal to 1,282,382 English acres. It is bounded on the north by the
                    department of Vaucluse, on the east by that of the Var, on the south by the
                    Mediterranean, and on the west by the department of Gard. It is divided into
                    three arrondissements, and these into twenty-seven cantons and 106 communes,
                    containing, in 1836, 362,325 inhabitants. They chiefly adhere to the Romish
                    church, though there are about 5000 Protestants, and in the city of Marseilles
                    many Jews. They speak a peculiar patois, nearly the same as, in the time of the
                    Troubadours, was the written language of Provence.</p><p>The surface of the eastern and southern portions of the department is
                    mountainous. A range of hills extends from the department of the Var. Of one of
                    them, San Venture, the height is 3120 feet. In the northern part is a chain of
                    hills extending from Vaucluse, beginning on the banks of the Durance, and
                    stretching from east to west to the neighbourhood of the Rhone, and rising to
                    the height of 2500 feet above the level of the sea. The south-west part is
                    wholly a level plain, full of morasses, and including the island of Camargue and
                    the island Plan, in which, though some spots are fertile, yet the greater
                    portion exhibits either heaps of pebbles or unhealthy marshes. The river Rhone
                    is the chief stream, into which many others empty themselves before it reaches
                    the sea. The navigation of that river is hazardous on account of its having
                    three outlets, the passages through which are very variable, sometimes one being
                    passable, and then in a few days nearly closed, when another is opened. To
                    remedy this inconvenience, a canal has been opened from Arles to the small haven
                    of Bouc, near the sea. There are several smaller canals, which serve partly for
                    the purpose of communication, and in some measure for those of irrigation. One
                    of the most important public works recently undertaken in France is the
                    navigable canal which terminates in this department. It connects together the
                    two great rivers the Rhine and the Rhone. It was begun in 1804, and was
                    originally called the Canal Napoleon: it was afterwards designated the Canal of
                    Monsieur; and it now bears the more appropriate name of the Canal of the Rhine
                    and Rhone. It was completed in 1832,</p><p>R H U</p><p>at an expense of'26,640,000 francs, or about L.1,200,000. Rhubarb. The whole
                    length is about 210 miles; and in its progress it comes into direct
                    communication with other great rivers.</p><p>It is divided into four portions. The first commences at the Saone, and proceeds
                    to Dole, where it joins the Doubs.</p><p>The second portion is connected with Orchamps, Besan-con, Baume, Clival, Lisle,
                    and Vougeancourt, where it terminates. The third portion passes by Montbeliard,
                    Bu-rogne, Valdieu, Mulhausen, Brisach, and Grapenstadt, where the canal enters
                    the river Die, which falls into the Rhine half a mile above Strasburg. The
                    fourth part consists of branches from Mulhausen to Basel and Huningen, fed by
                    water from the Rhine at the latter place. There is a sanguine anticipation that
                    this last branch will form a cheap communication between Switzerland and the
                    Mediterranean. In one part of its progress it communicates with the Seine, and
                    is thus adapted to supply articles of great weight and little original cost,
                    such as iron, wood, and stone, to the city of Paris.</p><p>As nearly one third of the surface of this department, consisting of mountains,
                    small lakes, and morasses, is uncultivated, it does not produce a sufficient
                    supply of corn for its own consumption. The corn is not thrashed, but, as in
                    other warm countries, is trodden out by oxen. Neither cows nor horses are
                    numerous, though on the island of Camargue many of the latter, of a small race,
                    sire bred, almost in a state of wildness. The sheep are numerous, and are moved
                    to the hills or to the plains, according; to the state of the pasturage. The
                    chief agricultural productions on which the department depends for procuring the
                    means of subsistence, are oil, wine, and silk. The olive-trees are abundant, but
                    some severe winters have destroyed many of them, and diminished the price of oil
                    one third.</p><p>Besides wine, the vineyards yield a great quantity of raisins of various
                    excellent descriptions, which form an important source of wealth, as do other
                    dried fruits, especially plums. A large portion of the grapes is converted into
                    brandy. The cultivation of silk is very much diffused, but nowhere an exclusive
                    pursuit, and does not yield more than 100,000 pounds of raw silk. The
                    sea-fishery gives employment to a great number of persons; and salt being
                    plentitvilly produced by natural evaporation, much of the fish taken in this
                    department is cured for exportation. The only mines are those of coal; nor does
                    their annual produce exceed 5000 tons. There are manufactures of silk, cotton,
                    and other articles, chiefly confined to die cities of Marseilles and Aix, which
                    likewise carry on the principal export trade, including the productions already
                    noticed, and also figs, almonds, capers, coral, and essences of flowers,
                    together with wool.</p></div></body></text></TEI>