<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0128-0118-06" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">RENFREWSHIRE</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 19, page 118</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1053582">Parishes</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:865087">Coal</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:865671">Coaling</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="10" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w90n">Carts</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nn40">Mosses</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=128" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">RENFREWSHIRE</label>, a county in Scotland, lying between 55.
                    40. 40. and 55. 58.10. north latitude, and 4.15. and 4. 52. 30. west longitude,
                    is bounded on the east by Lanarkshire, on the south by Ayrshire, and on the
                    north and west by the river and frith of Clyde, which separate it from the
                    shires of Dumbarton and Argyle, excepting a section of about 1300 imperial
                    acres, which is situated on the north bank of the Clyde, opposite the town of
                    Renfrew. Its greatest length is thirty-one miles and a half, and its greatest
                    breadth thirteen miles and a fourth. Its area is 241 square miles, or 154,240
                    acres, of which about 100,000 are cultivated, 20,000 uncultivated, and 34,240
                    unprofitable. Notwithstanding the small extent of this shire, its manufactures
                    and commerce render it one of the most important in Scotland.</p><p>At the epoch of the Roman invasion, in the first century of the Christian era,
                    this part of Scotland was inhabited by a Celtic tribe, called by the invaders
                    the Damnii. After the withdrawal of the Romans, it was comprehended in the
                    British kingdom of Strathdyde.</p><p>The district which now forms the county of Renfrew, at least the greater part of
                    it, was denominated, from one of its rivers, Strathgryfe, the valley of the
                    Gryfe, and at one time formed part of the shire of Lanark or Clydesdale. It was
                    the chief patrimony of the great stewards of Scotland, to whom it was granted by
                    the sovereign in the twelfth century. Afterwards it was called the barony of
                    Renfrew, from the burgh of that name, where the stewards long had their
                    principal residence. In 1404, thirty-three years after the accession of the
                    house of Stewart to the Scottish throne, King Robert III. granted this barony,
                    and the other portions of the estates of the steward, to his son and heir James;
                    since which time the eldest son of the sovereign has, besides his other titles,
                    bome that of “Baron of Renfrew.” Soon afterwards this barony was erected into a
                    distinct sheriffdom, the courts of which were held at Renfrew till the year
                    1705, when they were, for convenience sake, removed to Paisley. In 1815 the
                    county was formed into two wards, termed the Upper and the Lower, with a
                    sheriff-substitute for each, Paisley and Greenock being the seats of their
                    respective courts.</p><p>Renfrew shire comprehends twenty-one parishes, besides small portions of those of
                    Beith and Dunlop in Ayrshire, and Govan in Lanarkshire. Two of the parishes,
                    Eagle-sham and Catheart, belong to the presbytery of Glasgow; the other nineteen
                    composed the presbytery of Paisley for a long time prior to the year 1834, when
                    two presbyteries were formed; that of Paisley, consisting of twelve of these
                    nineteen parishes; and that of Greenock, consisting of the <pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=129" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0129-0119"/>other seven, with the addition of Cumbraes in Buteshire, and Largs in
                    Ayrshire, both of which parishes formerly belonged to the presbytery of Irvine.
                    In the above enumeration of parishes, those which are so <hi rend="italic">quoad
                    sacra</hi> only have not been taken into account.</p><p>About two thirds of this county, comprehending the western and southern sides,
                    are hilly, the medium elevation being from 500 to 600 feet. Mistylaw, on the
                    west, which is about 1240 feet above the level of the sea, has been represented
                    as the highest hill in the county; but it is now ascertained that a neighbouring
                    height, called the Hill of Staik, is entitled to that distinction, being a few
                    feet higher. This last was one of the points of observation in the general
                    trigonometrical survey of the kingdom. Balagiech and Dun-wan are the highest
                    hills on the south-east side, being about 1000 feet above the sea-level. The
                    hilly district is in general kept in pasture, for which it is better adapted, by
                    the nature of its surface, than for tillage; though, as it has a free light
                    soil, which readily absorbs water, it is seldom injured by moisture. The
                    cultivated land, which forms the gently-rising district, lies on the north and
                    north-east, and in the centre of the county on both sides of the Black Cart of
                    this the greater part consists of low, detached eminences, which swell in
                    endless variety. These being interspersed with copses, and often watered at the
                    bottom by winding streams, present views remarkable for richness and variety.
                    Indeed it will be difficult to point to a more beautiful surface anywhere in
                    Scotland. Much of this tract has a close subsoil of small stones and coarse
                    clay, almost impenetrable to water, though there are here many flat holms of
                    great fertility. It is only between Paisley and the Clyde that the country sinks
                    down into a plain, forming the flat district known by the name of “the
                    Laighlands.” The length of this beautiful level tract is about six miles, its
                    breadth about three, and its area 12,000 acres. Here the soil is generally a
                    deep rich loam of a dark-brown colour, sometimes of the nature of what is called
                    “carse clay ;” and much of it seems to have been formed by the deposition of
                    vegetable mould from the higher grounds. Moss prevails in the first and last
                    divisions, but is not found in the second one, where the soil is pretty
                    uniform.</p><p>Like the other western counties of Scotland, Renfrewshire has a moist climate,
                    with frequent rains; and the prevailing wind is from the south-west. At Largs, a
                    village in Ayrshire, near the western extremity of this county, the yearly
                    quantity of rain in 1809 and 1810 was 38U inches; at Glasgow, near the eastern
                    extremity, for thirty years, from 1761 to 1790, it was 29∙65 inches.</p><p>Besides the Clyde, which, as has been already mentioned, flows along the northern
                    and western boundaries of this county, the principal rivers are the White Cart,
                    the Black Cart, and the Gryfe. The White Cart, which rises in Lanarkshire,
                    enters Renfrewshire from the south, and pursues a winding course, first westerly
                    towards Paisley, through which it passes, and then northerly towards the Clyde.
                    It is joined at Inchinnan Bridge by the Black Cart, which had previously
                    received the waters of the Gryfe at Walkinshaw, above Barnsford Bridge; and
                    these united streams, which contain nine tenths of the water of the county, fall
                    into the Clyde about three miles below Paisley. By means of a short canal, which
                    was cut to avoid the shallows at Inchinnan Bridge in 1786, the White Cart is
                    navigable up to Paisley. Other improvements upon this river are in progress.
                    Like some other Scottish streams, it was once famous for the pearls which were
                    found in its bed, but these have disappeared since the beginning of the
                    eighteenth century. The</p><p>Black Cart rises from Loch Winnoch, or, as it is usually called, from an
                    adjoining estate, Castle-Semple Loch, a lake in the south-western extremity of
                    the county. The Gryfe rises in the west, amongst the high lands of the parish of
                    Greenock. All these streams, and several others of smaller size, independently
                    of their importance to agriculture, are, in almost every part of their course,
                    applied by the industrious and ingenious inhabitants to the various purposes of
                    manufactures. A ready supply of water is secured by means of reservoirs, some of
                    which are of the size and appearance of considerable lakes; or by enlarging the
                    natural lakes themselves, of which there are many. These streams and lakes
                    contain the kinds of fish that are common in this quarter of the country.</p><p>Two railways, which will traverse the county, are now (March 1839) in course of
                    being formed. Commencing at Glasgow, they will have a common line to Paisley,
                    from which the one will lead north-westwards to Greenock, and the other
                    westwards to several places in Ayrshire. These ways of transport must prove of
                    incalculable value to the trade and commerce of the county. It is expected that
                    they will be opened in 1840. The Paisley and Renfrew railway, and the canal from
                    Glasgow to Johnston, have been noticed in the account of Paisley.</p><p>The minerals of Renfrewshire are of great importance, and constitute the main
                    source of its manufactures and commerce; but we can only advert to them very
                    generally. Coal, limestone, and sandstone, are wrought at Neilston, one of the
                    parishes of the hilly district; and both coal and lime have been found in the
                    flat district near Renfrew; but it is in the middle division that mines are
                    wrought to the greatest extenl. of coal there are generally about twelve
                    different works carried on, of which the most extensive and valuable are at
                    Polmadie, on the north-east boundary; at Hurlet, three miles south-east from
                    Paisley, where it has been wrought for more than three hundred years; and at
                    Quarrelton, south-east from Johnston, on the Black Cart, near the centre of the
                    county. The coal at this latter place consists of five contiguous strata; the
                    thickness of the whole, measured at right angles to their surface, is upwards of
                    fifty feet; but as in some places the seam forms a considerable angle with the
                    horizon, the thickness of the whole in these places, measured vertically, is
                    about fifteen fathoms. In consequence of this great depth, it is wrought in
                    floors or stories. Limestone abounds in various parts, and is commonly wrought
                    at eight different quarries. Ironstone in beds and balls is found in great
                    profusion. Considerable quantities of pyrites are found in the stratum of coal
                    at Hurlet and Househill, and manufactured into sulphate of iron or green
                    vitriol. Alum is obtained at Hurlet, from the decomposed schistus which forms
                    one of the strata of its coal-mines. Excellent freestone, lying near the
                    surface, is wrought at various places in the middle district. Greenstone, or, as
                    it is provincially called, <hi rend="italic">whinstone,</hi> exists in immense
                    masses. <note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Much valuable
                    and interesting information on the geology of Renfrewshire will be found in an
                    essay by Mr William Montgomery, younger of Cloak, factor, Castle-Semple,
                    inserted amongst the Prize Essays and Transactions of the Highland and
                    AgriculturalSociety of Scotland for December 1838, p. 421. </p></note></p><p>The annual value of real property in Renfrewshire, as assessed in 1815, was
                    L.265,534 sterling. The valued rent in 1674 was L.69,172 Scots. This, exclusive
                    of small properties occupied by <hi rend="italic">feuars,</hi> chiefly as
                    gardens, was, in 1810, divided among 350 proprietors, the estates of eighty-one
                    of whom were above the valuation of L.100 Scots, and only six were above L.2000
                    Scots. At that time nearly half the valuation belonged to estates held under
                    entail, and by corporations, which were not therefore allowed to be brought to
                    market. Landed property in Renfrewshire underwent great changes during the forty
                    years which preceded 1810,</p><pb break="no" facs="ht:wu.89119129625&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=130" xml:id="kp-eb0719-0130-0120"/><p>nearly one third part of the whole shire having been sold within that period.
                    There are about thirty seats of noblemen and gentlemen, besides villas belonging
                    to merchants and tradesmen. There are also many remains of ancient structures,
                    which formed the seats of powerful or respectable families. This shire was
                    anciently covered with wood. Even now it is ornamented with many woods and
                    plantations; and it is in general well enclosed.</p><p>As an agricultural district, this does not rank so high as some others in
                    Scotland. Farms are generally small, seldom exceeding 100 acres on the arable
                    land, and 400 or 500 acres on the hills. In 1811 the average rent per English
                    acre was about fifteen shillings, varying from two or three shillings to four or
                    five pounds; partly owing to situation, but still more to the different degrees
                    of the natural fertility of the soil. The usual period of leases here, as in
                    other parts of Scotland, is nineteen years; but many are now shorter. The mode
                    of farming is such as every year to leave more than a half of the arable land in
                    grass, on which the stock chiefly kept is cows, the most part of whose milk is
                    made into butter. There are few cheese-dairies. The corn chiefly raised here
                    consists of oats and bear. Wheat, barley, beans, and pease, are sown, but not in
                    great quantities. Clover and rye-grass are sown only for hay. Turnips are much
                    grown as a field crop. Potatoes are skilfully and extensively cultivated, the
                    vast population of the district creating an extraordinary demand for a root so
                    cheap and wholesome. A flock of Merino sheep was brought to this county from
                    Spain in the year 1810, but the experiment proved unsuccessful.</p><p>It is by its manufactures and commerce that this county is most distinguished.
                    Goods of silk, and cotton, and muslin fabrics, are the principal articles
                    manufactured. Cotton-mills, bleachfields, and printfields, furnish employment to
                    a large portion of the inhabitants. Paisley and its environs form the chief seat
                    of the manufactures. At Greenock and Port-Glasgow the foreign and coasting trade
                    of the county, and, indeed, a great proportion of the foreign trade of Scotland,
                    are carried on. To prevent repetition, we refer to the articles Paisley,
                    Gbeenock, and Port-Glasgow, for information concerning the manufactures and
                    commerce of Renfrewshire.</p><p>The other more considerable towns and villages, with their population in 1831,
                    are as follow: Johnston, 5617; Pollockshaws, a burgh of barony, 4267;
                    Lochwinnoch, 2645; Barrhead and Newton Ralston, 2640; Kilbarchan, 2333;
                    Neilston, 1137; and Elderslie, 1099.</p><p>In 1755 tile population of the county was only 26,645; in 1831 itamounted to
                    133,443. The increase, therefore, in seventy-six years has been 106,995, being
                    upwards of 400 per cent., which exceeds that of any other county in
                    Scotland.</p><table><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="1" rows="2" role="data"><p>YEARS.</p></cell><cell cols="3" rows="1" role="data"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell><cell cols="3" rows="1" role="data"><p>OCCUPATIONS.</p><p>. ί</p></cell><cell cols="3" rows="1" role="data"><p>PERSONS.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>Inhabited.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>I Familice.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>tc</p><p>.S</p><p>is</p><p>‘5</p><p>pa</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>Families chiefly employed in</p><p>Agricul
                            ture.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>Families chiefly em. ployed in Trade,
                            Manufactures, and Handicraft</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>Families not com-prised in the two preceding
                            classes.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>Males.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>Females.</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>1811</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>8,229</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>19,798</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>38</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>1,847</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>15,959</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>1,992</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>41,960</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>50,636</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>92,596</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>1821</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>10,490</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>23,977</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>55</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>2,725</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>15,780</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>5,472</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>51,178</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>60,997</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>112,175</p></cell></row><row role="data" rows="1" cols="1"><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>1831</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>11,153</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>28,204</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>828</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>2,016</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>21,071</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>5,117</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>61,154</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>72,289</p></cell><cell cols="1" rows="1" role="data"><p>133,443</p></cell></row></table></div></body></text></TEI>