<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0156-0145-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">QUAeSTOR (9th edition, volume 20, page 145)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb7v">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0652b">Consulates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:876196">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093581">Relationism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936105">Functionals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:936106">Functions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n156/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">QUAeSTOR</label> was the title of a Roman magistrate whose
                    functions, at least in the later times of the republic, were mainly financial.
                    The origin of the quaestorship is somewhat obscure, but on the whole it was
                    probably instituted simultaneously with the consulship in 509 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Plutarch <hi rend="italic">{Popl.,</hi> 12) states that the office was
                    instituted by the first consul. Tacitus, on the other hand <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Ann.,</hi> xi. 22), says that it dated from the time of the kings, but his
                    ground is merely that they were mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Lex</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Curiata</hi><hi rend="italic">of</hi> the consul Brutus, which
                    Tacitus assumes to have been identical with that of the kings.</p></note> The
                    number of the quaestors was originally two, but this was successively increased
                    to four (in 421 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> eight (in 267 or 241 B.c.), and
                    by Sulla (in 81 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> to twenty. Caesar raised the
                    number to forty (in 45 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> but Augustus reduced it
                    again to twenty, which remained the regular number under the empire. When the
                    number was raised from two to four in 421 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> the
                    office was thrown open to the plebeians, and it was the first office that was so
                    opened. It was the lowest of the great offices of state, and hence it was
                    regularly the first sought by aspirants to a political career. Towards the close
                    of the republic, if not earlier, the successful candidate was bound to have
                    completed his thirtieth year before he entered on office, but Augustus lowered
                    the age to twenty-five. Originally the quaestors seem to have been nominated by
                    the consuls independently, but later, perhaps from the fall of the decemvirs
                    (449 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> they were elected by the people assembled
                    in tribes <hi rend="italic">(comitia tributa)</hi> and presided over by a consul
                    or another of the higher magistrates. The quaestors held office for one year,
                    but, like the consuls and praetors, they were often continued in office with the
                    title of proquaestor. Indeed it was a regular rule that the quaestor attached to
                    a higher magistrate should hold office as long as his superior; hence, when a
                    consul regularly presided over the city for one year, and afterwards as
                    proconsul governed a province for another year, his quaestor also regularly held
                    office for two years. Before the election of the quaestors the senate decided
                    the duties to be undertaken by them, and after election these duties were
                    distributed amongst the new quaestors either by lot or by the choice of the
                    higher magistrates to whom a quaestor was assigned. A peculiar burden laid on
                    the quaestors, not so much as an official duty, but rather as a sort of fee
                    exacted from all who entered on the political career, was the paving of the high
                    roads, for which Claudius substituted the exhibition of gladiatorial games.
                    Various classes of quaestors may be distinguished according to the duties they
                    had respectively to discharge. Up to 421 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> there
                    were only two quaestors, and when fresh ones were added the two original
                    quaestors were distinguished by the appellation of urban quaestors <hi
                    rend="italic">(quaestores urbani),</hi> doubtless because they were bound to
                    remain in Rome during their term of office.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">The Urban Quaestors.—</hi> Originally the duties of the
                    quaestors, like those of the consuls, were of a general and undefined nature;
                    specialization of function had not yet arisen—the consuls were simply the
                    superior, the quaestors simply the inferior magistrates of the republic. From a
                    very early time, however, the quaestors possessed criminal to the exclusion of
                    civil jurisdiction. The very name “quaestor” (from <hi rend="italic"
                    >quaerere,</hi> “to search out”) means “investigator,” “inquisitor.” In the code
                    of the Twelve Tables they are designated <hi rend="italic">qxιaestores</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">parricidii,</hi> “inquisitors of parricide or murder”;<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The etymology and original
                    meaning of <hi rend="italic">parricidium</hi> are doubtful. In the latter part
                    of the word we have, of course, the same root as in <hi rend="italic"
                    >caedere,</hi> “to kill,” but whether or not the former part is from <hi
                    rend="italic">pater,</hi> “a father,” or from the same root that we have in <hi
                    rend="italic">per-ρeram, per-jurium,</hi> is a moot point. Mommsen takes the
                    latter view.</p></note> and perhaps originally this was their full title, which
                    was afterwards abbreviated into quaestors when their functions as criminal
                    judges fell into the background. In addition to parricide or murder we can
                    hardly doubt that all other crimes fell within the jurisdiction of the
                    quaestors; political crimes only seem to have been excepted. The criminal
                    jurisdiction of the quaestors appears <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n157/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0157-0146"/> only to have terminated when towards the close of
                    the republic trial by permanent courts <hi rend="italic">(quaestiones
                    perpetuae)</hi> was extended to criminal cases.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>It is often supposed that the <hi
                    rend="italic">quaestores</hi><hi rend="italic">parricidii</hi> were an old
                    magistracy quite distinct from the ordinary quaestors. For the identification of
                    the two, see Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">Römisches Staatsrecht,</hi> ii., pt. 1,
                    p. 506.</p></note></p>
                <p>The quaestors had also charge of the public treasury <hi rend="italic"
                    >(aerarium)</hi> in the temple of Saturn, and this was in the later times of the
                    republic their most important function. They kept the keys of the treasury and
                    had charge of its contents, including not only coin and bullion but also the
                    military standards and a large number of public documents, which in later times
                    comprised all the laws as well as the decrees of the senate. Their functions as
                    keepers of the treasury were withdrawn from the urban quaestors by Augustus and
                    transferred to other magistrates, but the office itself continued to exist into
                    the 3d century, though as to the nature of the duties attached to it we have
                    little or no information.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">The Military</hi><hi rend="italic">Quaestors.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> These were instituted in 421 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.,</hi> when two new quaestors were added to the original two. They never
                    had a distinctive appellation like that of the urban quaestors, from whom,
                    however, they were clearly distinguished by the fact that, while the urban
                    quaestors did not stand in a special relation of subordination to any particular
                    magistrate, a non-urban quaestor was regularly assigned as an indispensable
                    assistant or adjutant to every general in command, whose name or title the
                    quaestor usually added to his own.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Thus Cicero speaks of the <hi rend="italic">provincia
                    consularis</hi> of the quaestor, and we find <hi rend="italic">quaestor</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Cn.</hi><hi rend="italic">Pompei,</hi> &amp;c.</p></note>
                    Originally they were the adjutants of the consuls only, afterwards of the
                    provincial praetors, and still later of the proconsuls and propraetors. The
                    dictator alone among military commanders had no quaestor, because a quaestor
                    would have been a limitation to his powers. The governor of Sicily had two
                    quaestors; all other governors and commanders had but one. Between the quaestor
                    and his superior a close personal relation, analogous to that between a son and
                    his father, existed, and was not severed when their official connexion ceased.
                    Not till the close of the republic do cases occur of a quaestor being sent to a
                    province invested with praetorial and even consular powers; in one case at least
                    the quaestor so sent had a second quaestor placed under him. The duties of the
                    military quaestor, like those of the treasury quaestor, were primarily
                    financial. Moneys due to a provincial governor from the state treasury were
                    often, perhaps regularly, received and disbursed by the quaestor; the magazines
                    seem to have been under his charge; he coined money, on which not unfrequently
                    his name appears alone. The booty taken in war was not necessarily under the
                    control of the quaestor, but was dealt with, especially iu later times, by
                    inferior officers called <hi rend="italic">praefecti</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >fabrum.</hi> But, though his duties were primarily financial, the quaestor was
                    after all the chief assistant or adjutant of his superior in command, and as
                    such he was invested with a certain degree of military power; under the republic
                    his military rank was superior to that of the legates, though under the empire
                    this relation was reversed. When the general left his province before the
                    arrival of his successor he usually committed it to the care of his quaestor,
                    and, if he died or was incapacitated from naming his successor, the quaestor
                    acted as his representative. Unlike the urban quaestor, the military quaestor
                    possessed not a criminal but a civil jurisdiction corresponding to that of the
                    aediles at Rome.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">The Italian</hi><hi rend="italic">Quaestors.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> The subjugation of Italy occasioned the institution (in 267
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> of four new quaestors, who appear to have been
                    called <hi rend="italic">quaestores classici</hi> because they were originally
                    intended to superintend the building of the fleet <hi rend="italic"
                    >(classis)</hi>; their functions, however, are very imperfectly known. Though no
                    doubt intended to assist the consuls, they were not subordinated (like the
                    military quaestors) to a special consul. They were stationed at Ostia, at Gales
                    in Campania, and in Gaul about the Padus (Po). The station of the fourth is not
                    mentioned; perhaps it was Lilybaeum in Sicily.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
