<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0193-0176-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">QUESNAY, François (9th edition, volume 20, page
                    176)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p161">Surgeons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k35mg3z">Socialism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ww7712k">Wealth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1123768">Socialization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1123637">Socialism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1062841">Physicians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n193/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">QUESNAY, <hi rend="smallcaps">François</hi></label>
                    (1694-1774), was one of the most eminent economists of the 18th century. He was
                    born at Mérey, near the village of Montfort ΓAmaury, about 28 miles from Paris,
                    on the 4th of June, 1694, a year memorable also for the birth of Voltaire. He
                    was the son of a worthy advocate, who had the reputation of ruining his own
                    practice by reconciling the parties who came to consult him about their suits.
                    The modest resources of the family were derived principally from the cultivation
                    of a small landed estate, Quesnay’s mother in particular busying herself much
                    with the details of its management, which she thoroughly understood. His boyish
                    years were thus spent amidst country scenes and the occupations of the farm, and
                    he retained to the end a strong predilection for rural life and a special
                    interest in the welfare of the agricultural population. Little attention was
                    given to his early literary instruction; it is said that he could not read till
                    he was eleven years of age, when he was taught partly by the family gardener,
                    who used as the text book the <hi rend="italic">Maison</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Rustique</hi> of Jean Liébault, a work “wherein” (to quote the words of its old
                    English translator, Richard Surflet, 1606) “is conteined whatever can be
                    required for the building or good ordering of a husbandman’s house or countrey
                    farme.” This book Quesnay is said to have studied with such assiduity as to have
                    almost known it by heart. He learned Greek and Latin and the elements of several
                    sciences with scarcely any aid from masters. He was possessed with an ardent and
                    untiring desire for knowledge, and we are told that more than once he walked to
                    Paris for a book, which he read on his way back the same day, thus travelling
                    twenty leagues on foot.</p>
                <p>At the age of sixteen he became apprentice to a surgeon in the neighbourhood of
                    Mérey, who was not able to teach him much, and he soon went to Paris to continue
                    his professional education. He there devoted himself with great ardour for five
                    or six years to the study of medicine and surgery, diligently attending the
                    hospitals, and following the courses of anatomy, chemistry, and botany; he also
                    learned drawing and engraving, in which he acquired considerable skill, and gave
                    some attention to metaphysics, to which he had been attracted by the reading of
                    Malebranche’s <hi rend="italic">Recherche</hi><hi rend="italic">de la
                    Vérité.</hi> About 1718 he established himself at Mantes, and soon obtained a
                    distinguished <hi rend="italic">clientèle.</hi> He became known to the Maréchal
                    de Noailles, who conceived a high esteem for him, and persuaded the queen,
                    whenever she came to Maintenon, which was not very far from Mantes, to consult
                    no physician but Quesnay. A celebrated practitioner of the time, named Silva,
                    having published a treatise on bleeding, which, though of little merit, was
                    loudly applauded by his friends, Quesnay wrote a refutation of it, founded on
                    the principles of hydrostatics, which brought his name much into notice. When La
                    Peyronnie had procured about 1730 the foundation of an academy of surgery with
                    the view of elevating that profession, he selected Quesnay for the post of
                    perpetual secretary. Coming to Paris to fill it, he obtained through La
                    Peyronnie’s influence the office of surgeon in ordinary to the king. He was the
                    author of the remarkable preface which was prefixed to the first volume of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> of the academy. He was for a long time much
                    occupied with the controversies between the faculty of medicine and the college
                    of surgery concerning the respective limits of the two professions, and wrote
                    most of the pieces in which the claims of the latter were asserted. Finding that
                    frequent attacks of the gout were rendering him incapable of performing manual
                    operations, he procured in 1744 the degree of doctor of medicine from the
                    university of Pont-à-Mousson; but, though thus changing the nature of his
                    practice, he continued to defend the rights of the surgical profession. He soon
                    after purchased the reversion to the office of physician in ordinary to the
                    king, and afterwards became his first consulting physician; in this capacity he
                    was installed in the palace of Versailles, occupying apartments near those of
                    Madame de Pompadour. Louis XV. esteemed Quesnay much, and used to call him his
                    thinker; when he ennobled him, he gave him for arms three flowers of the pansy
                    <hi rend="italic">{pensée),</hi> with the motto <hi rend="italic"
                    >Propter</hi><hi rend="italic">excogitationem</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >mentis.</hi></p>
                <p>He now devoted himself principally to economic studies, taking no part in the
                    court intrigues which were perpetually going on around him. About the year 1750
                    he became acquainted with Μ. de Gournay, who was also an earnest inquirer in the
                    economic field; and round these two distinguished men was gradually formed the
                    philosophic sect of the <hi rend="italic">Économistes,</hi> or, as for
                    distinction’s sake they were afterwards called, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Physiocrates.</hi> The most remarkable men in this group of disciples were the
                    elder Mirabeau (author of <hi rend="italic">L'Ami</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Hommes,</hi> 1756-60, and <hi rend="italic">Philosophie Rurale,</hi> 1763), the
                    Abbé Baudeau <hi rend="italic">{Introduction</hi><hi rend="italic">à la
                    Philosophie Économique,</hi> 1771), Le Trosne <hi rend="italic">{De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">l'Ordre Social,</hi> 1777), Morellet (best known by his
                    controversy with Galiani on the freedom of the corn trade), Mercier Lariviere,
                    and Dupont de Nemours. Of the writings of the last two, as well as of the
                    general doctrine of the physiocrats, some account has been given in the article
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Political Economy</hi> (see vol. xix. pp. 359 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.).</hi> The principal economic work of Quesnay himself was the
                    <hi rend="italic">Tableau</hi><hi rend="italic">Économique,</hi> which Laharpe
                    called <hi rend="italic">VAlcoran</hi><hi rend="italic">des Économistes.</hi> A
                    small <hi rend="italic">édition</hi><hi rend="italic">de luxe</hi> of this work,
                    with other pieces, was printed in 1758 in the palace of Versailles under the
                    king’s immediate supervision, some of the sheets, it is said, having been pulled
                    by the royal hand. Already in 1767 the book had disappeared from circulation,
                    and no copy of it is now procurable; but the substance of it is has been
                    preserved in the <hi rend="italic">Ami</hi><hi rend="italic">des Hommes</hi> of
                    Mirabeau, and the <hi rend="italic">Physiocratie</hi> of Dupont de Nemours. In
                    Quesnay’s <hi rend="italic">Maximes Générales du Gouvernement Économique d'un
                    Royaume Agricole,</hi> which was put forward as an <hi rend="italic">Ëxtrait des
                    Économies Royales de Sully,</hi> and was printed along with the <hi
                    rend="italic">Tableau</hi> in 1758, besides stating his economic doctrines, he
                    expresses his opinion in favour of a legal despotism as the best form of
                    government. “Let the sovereign authority be single, and superior to all the
                    individuals of society and all the unjust enterprises of private interest The
                    system of counter-forces in a government is a harmful one, which produces only
                    discord among the great and the oppression of the weak.” He had contributed to
                    the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie</hi> in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n194/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0194-0177"/></p>
                <p>1756 the articles “Fermiers” and “Grains,” which contained the earliest
                    announcement of his principles through the press; and he published a number of
                    minor pieces in the <hi rend="italic">Journal de l</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Agriculture, du Commerce,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">des Finances,</hi> and in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Éphémérides du Citoyen.</hi> His <hi rend="italic">Droit
                    Naturel,</hi> which was included in the <hi rend="italic">Plιysiocratie</hi> of
                    Dupont de Nemours, is especially noteworthy as showing the philosophic
                    foundation of his economic system in the theory of thej⅛z&lt;s' <hi
                    rend="italic">natures.</hi></p>
                <p>Interesting notices of Quesnay’s character and habits have been preserved to us
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> of Marmontel and those of Mme. duHausset,
                    <hi rend="italic">femme</hi><hi rend="italic">de chambre</hi> to Mme. de
                    Pompadour.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>These <hi
                    rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> were first printed by Quintin Craufurd in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Mélanges</hi><hi rend="italic">d’</hi><hi rend="italic">Histoire
                    et de Littérature,</hi> 1806, and again in 1817; they baye since been published
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi><hi rend="italic">des Mémoires relatifs
                    à la Révolution Française,</hi> 1824, and also in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bibliothèque des Mémoires relatifs à</hi><hi rend="italic">l’</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Histoire de France pendant le</hi><hi rend="italic">lS</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> me</hi><hi rend="italic">Siècle.</hi></p></note> His
                    probity and disinterested zeal for the public good did not suffer from the
                    atmosphere of the court; he never abused his credit with the sovereign or the
                    favourite for any selfish end. To raise the national agriculture from the decay
                    into which it had fallen and to improve the condition of the working population
                    were the great aims he kept steadily in view. His conversation was piquant,
                    humorous, and suggestive, often taking the form of moral and political
                    apologues. Some of his weighty sayings are quoted by contemporary writers. Here
                    is one of them. Having met in Madame de Pompadour’s salon an official person
                    who, in recommending violent measures for the purpose of terminating the
                    vexatious disputes between the clergy and the parliament, used the words, “C’est
                    la hallebarde qui mène un royaume,” Quesnay replied, “Et qu’est ce qui mène la
                    hallebarde?” adding, after a pause, “C’est l’opinion; c’est donc sur l’opinion
                    qu’il faut travailler.” Diderot, D’Alembert, Duclos, Helvetius, Buffon, Turgot,
                    Marmontel, used to meet in his rooms in the palace, and also several of the
                    physiocrats above named; and Madame de Pompadour, who affected the patronage of
                    philosophy and science, sometimes came to join them and converse with them.
                    Amongst them, when they were alone, subjects were sometimes discussed in a tone
                    which would not have pleased the royal ear. Thus, one day, Mirabeau having said,
                    “The nation is in a deplorable state,” Larivière replied in prophetic words, “It
                    can only be regenerated by a conquest like that of China, or by some great
                    internal convulsion; but woe to those who live to see that! The French people do
                    not do things by halves !” Adam Smith, during his stay on the Continent with the
                    young duke of Buccleuch in 1764—66, spent some time in Paris, where he made the
                    acquaintance of Quesnay and some of his followers; he paid a high tribute to
                    their scientific services in his <hi rend="italic">Wealth of Nations,</hi> and
                    would have dedicated that work to Quesnay, had the latter been alive at the time
                    of its publication.</p>
                <p>At the age of seventy Quesnay went back to the study of mathematics. He thought,
                    we are told, that he had discovered the quadrature of the circle, and was not
                    prevented by the remonstrances of his friends from printing his supposed
                    solution of the problem. He died in 1774, having lived long enough to see his
                    great pupil, Turgot, in office as minister of finance. Quesnay had married in
                    1718, and had a son and a daughter; his grandson by the former was a member of
                    the first Legislative Assembly.</p>
                <p>The economic writings of Quesnay are collected in the 2d vol. of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Principaux Économistes,</hi> published by Guillaumin, with preface
                    and notes by Eugène Daire. His writings on medicine and surgery have now only an
                    historic interest. They were as follows :— 1. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Observations</hi><hi rend="italic">sur les effets de la saignée,</hi> 1730 and
                    1750; 2. <hi rend="italic">Essai physique sur l’économie animale avec l'art de
                    guérir par la saignée,</hi> 1736 and 1747; 3. <hi rend="italic">Recherches
                    critiques et historiques sur l’origine,</hi><hi rend="italic">les divers états,
                    et les progrès de la chirurgie en France</hi> (said to have been the joint work
                    of Quesnay and Louis), 1744, and, with slightly altered title, 1749; 4. <hi
                    rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi rend="italic">de la suppuration,</hi> 1749; 5. <hi
                    rend="italic">Traité</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">la
                    gangrène,</hi> 1749; 6. <hi rend="italic">Traité des fièvres continues,</hi>
                    1753; 7. <hi rend="italic">Observations sur la conservation de la vie</hi> (said
                    to have been printed at Versailles along with the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tableau</hi><hi rend="italic">Économique'),</hi> 1758. His other writings were
                    the article “Évidence” in the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Recherches sur l’évidence des vérités géométriques,</hi> with a
                    <hi rend="italic">Projet de nouveaux éléments de géométrie,</hi> 1773. Quesnay’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Éloge</hi> was pronounced in the Academy of Sciences by
                    Grandjean de Fouchy (see the <hi rend="italic">Recueil</hi> of that Academy,
                    1774, p. 134). There is a good portrait of him, engraved by J. Ch. François,
                    which is reproduced in the <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire d’Économie</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Politique</hi> of Coquelin and Guillaumin. (J. K. I.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
