<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0807-0732-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAMBYSES (9th edition, volume 4, page 732)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>267 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9j752">Kafirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915906">Ethiopians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n807/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAMBYSES</label>, a Persian royal name, derived from the
                    Greek Ka/xßJcn/ç, in which form it appears in Herodotus and in the Greek writers
                    generally. In inscriptions from Egypt the name is given as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kaμβυσatς</hi> (Letronne, <hi rend="italic">Recueil</hi><hi rend="italic">d.
                    inscrip, grecq.,</hi> ii. pp. 350, 356, ∕.). In the old-Persian of the Behistun
                    inscription it stands in the form <hi rend="italic">Kabujiya</hi> (Rawlinson) or
                    <hi rend="italic">Kambujiya</hi> (Oppert, Spiegel). In Zend the name takes the
                    form <hi rend="italic">Kavaus,</hi> and in Arabic and modern Persian it is worn
                    down still further to <hi rend="italic">Kavus</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kaus.</hi> In Egyptian the name occurs under three forms of transcription,— <hi
                    rend="italic">Kanbuza, Kembatet</hi> (Lepsius, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kŏnigsbuch,</hi> taf. xlix.), or rather <hi rend="italic">Kambuzia,</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">Kambunsa</hi> (Lauth, <hi rend="italic">Ein netter</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Kambyses-text,</hi> p. 5). The etymology of the name is obscure,
                    and the attempts to explain it by Rawlinson <hi rend="italic">(Jour. As.
                    Soc.,</hi> xi. p. 97) and Benfey <hi rend="italic">(Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >persischen Keilinschriften,</hi> p. 77) cannot be regarded as successful. It
                    has been often remarked that the name, or one very similar, occurs more than
                    once in the East as an ethnical and geographical designation. Thus we find
                    Camboja a territory in India, Kamoj a tribe of the Kafirs in Cabul; and a
                    territory named Cambysene, situated in the north on the Kur, is known to Greek
                    geographers. In the same region there was a river called Cambyses, the modern
                    Jora. Perhaps with Spiegel <hi rend="italic">(Eranische Alterthurnskunde,</hi>
                    vol. ii. p. 294) we may regard the personal name Kambujiya as originally an
                    adjective, meaning belonging to Kambuja. In Egypt, also, Cambysu occurs in the
                    <hi rend="italic">Itinerarium</hi> as the name of a place in the Delta, but this
                    is probably derived from the Persian king about to be mentioned, by whom Egypt
                    was conquered</p>
                <p>The persons known by the name of Cambyses belong to the Achaemenian line of
                    Persian kings. It is thought that the great-grandfather of Cyrus the Great was
                    thus called. The evidence, however, for the existence of this Cambyses, though
                    strong, is constructive rather than direct (see Rawlinson’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Herodotus,</hi> vol. iv. p. 259). It is certain that the father of Cyrus was
                    named Cambyses. He is called by Herodotus (i. 107) “a Persian of good family,”
                    but by Xenophon <hi rend="italic">(Cyrop.,</hi> i. 11, 1) he is denominated
                    “king of the Persians.” The justness of this title is proved by an inscription
                    on a brick found at Senkereh, in which Cyrus calls himself “the son of Cambyses,
                    the powerful king,” as well as by the statement of Darius Hystaspis, in the
                    Behistun inscription (col. i. 4), that eight of his Achaemenian ancestors had
                    been kings. During the reign of this Cambyses the Persian nation was included in
                    the Median empire, and he is represented as the vassal of the Median king
                    Astyages. At the same time he is said to have married Mandane, the daughter of
                    Astyages, by whom he became the father of Cyrus. Such, at least, is the account
                    of Herodotus, Xenophon, Diodorus, and Trogus Pompeius. Ctesias and Nicolaus
                    Damascenus give a different representation.</p>
                <p>It is stated by Loftus <hi rend="italic">(Chaldoea and Susιαna,</hi> p. 224) that
                    he found at Warka “bricks inscribed in slightly <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n808/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0808-0733"/> relieved cuneiform characters of Cambyses, the
                    brother of Cyrus, a personage of whom we possess no historical notice
                    whatsoever.”</p>
                <p>The only other, and the best known, king of this name is the elder son and
                    successor of Cyrus, who reigned over the Persian empire, according to Herodotus,
                    for seven years and five months—from 529 to 521 B.c. Of his proceedings before
                    his famous invasion of Egypt little is known. 'To this period we must now, on
                    the authority of the Behistun inscription (i. 10), in opposition to Herodotus
                    (iii. 30), assign the secret murder of his brother, Bardiya (the Smerdis,
                    Merdis, Mardus, or Mergis of the Greeks,— called Tanyoxarces by Ctesias, and
                    Tanyoxares by Xenophon). Egypt at this time lay on the borders of the Persian
                    empire; its subjugation had long been an object of ambition to the great Asiatic
                    conquerors; it had recently provoked reprisals from Persia by sending help to
                    Lydia against Cyrus; and in resolving to attack that country Cambyses was both
                    carrying out the settled policy of his predecessors and accomplishing the
                    purpose of his own father. If therefore, as is not unlikely, there was such an
                    occasion given for the enterprise as that which Herodotus relates, it is not
                    necessary to suppose that this was more than a pretext. A year or two were spent
                    in collecting the forces of the empire, and the preparatory measures taken seem
                    to have been marked by prudence and skill. A fleet of Phoenician and Greek ships
                    was collected to operate against the vessels of the Egyptians; and the help of
                    an Arabian chief was secured to provide water for the army in crossing the
                    desert on the south and west of Palestine. The old king of Egypt, Amasis, under
                    whom the country had enjoyed a long period of peace and prosperity, died a few
                    months before the invasion, and was succeeded by his son Psammenitus, under whom
                    the measures of defence proved unsuccessful. An obstinately contested but
                    decisive victory was gained by the Persian arms near Pelusium, and this was
                    speedily followed up by the siege and capture of the capital, Memphis, and by
                    the subjugation of the whole country. The date of this conquest is commonly
                    regarded as 525 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> (see Rawlinson, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Anc. Mon.,</hi> vol. i. p. 385), though some find cause to place it one or even
                    two years earlier <hi rend="italic">(cf.</hi> v. Gumpach, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Zeitrechnung</hi><hi rend="italic">d. Ass. u. Bab.,</hi> pp. 165, <hi
                    rend="italic">f.</hi>; Lauth, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> pp. 13, <hi
                    rend="italic">f.</hi>; Brugsch, <hi rend="italic">Hist.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >d’Egypte,</hi> L p. 267; Duncker, <hi rend="italic">Gesell.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">d. Altei'tlιums,</hi> vol. ii. p. 792, n.; Lepsius, <hi
                    rend="italic">Königsbuck,</hi> p. 89).</p>
                <p>Henceforward the life and activity of Cambyses centred iu his new dominion. We
                    know from an important hieroglyphic inscription proceeding from a priest of
                    Neith at Sais, that he assumed the responsibilities and titles proper to a king
                    of Egypt, taking’ as his throne-name that of Ramesut. Moreover, it is evident
                    that for a time at least he cultivated the good-will of his new subjects. We
                    learn that he took Egyptians who had been officers of Psam-r.ιenitus into his
                    immediate service; that he sought instruction in regard to the rites of their
                    religion, and was initiated into certain of its mysteries; that he listened to
                    complaints in regard to the profanation of the temples by Persian and other
                    foreign soldiers, and gave orders for their removal from the sacred precincts;
                    that he secured the priests in the receipt of the temple*revenues, and arranged
                    for the due and continued celebration of the customary ceremonies and festivals.
                    A monument is still extant on which he is represented adoring, on bended knee,
                    the god Apis. (See De Rougé, <hi rend="italic">Mémoire sur la statue naopliore
                    du Vatican,</hi> passim; Brugsch, <hi rend="italic">op.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >dt.</hi>, vol. i. pp. 266,∕.; Lauth, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> pp.
                    17,∕.) One act, indeed, of a different complexion is reported by Herodotus (iii.
                    16), viz., his outraging and finally consuming by fire the embalmed body of
                    Amasis,—an act, the historian assures us, which shocked the feelings alike of
                    Egyptians and of Persians, and which strongly attests the same jealous and
                    resentful temper which prompted the murder of his brother.</p>
                <p>After having established himself in his new possession, Cambyses, Herodotus (iii.
                    17, ∕.) informs us, planned three expeditions. One was against Carthage, in
                    regard to which, however, he was thwarted by the refusal of his Phoenician
                    mariners, who formed the principal portion of his sea-forces, to operate against
                    their kindred. Another was directed against the Oasis and temple of Jupiter
                    Ammon in the desert west of Egypt (see Heeren, <hi rend="italic">D.
                    afrikan.</hi><hi rend="italic">Völker,</hi> i. p. 416), the issue of which was
                    that the whole of the force sent on this enterprise, numbering, it is said,
                    50,000 men, perished in the sand. The third was intended for the subjugation of
                    the Ethiopians on the south of Egypt (regarding whose locality see Heeren, <hi
                    rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> i. pp. 337, ∕.; Rawlinson, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Herod.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 421; Maspero, <hi rend="italic">Histoire
                    ancienne,</hi> pp. 533, ∕.), and of this Cambyses himself took the command. The
                    army, however, had marched less than a fifth of the distance when their
                    provisions failed, and they were reduced to the utmost straits,—even, it is
                    said, to cannibalism. Cambyses was thus forced to retrace his steps and to lead
                    back the remnant of his army to Egypt in disappointment and disgrace.</p>
                <p>Under the smart of this threefold discomfiture the conduct of Cambyses towards
                    the Egyptians assumed a new and much more stern and cruel aspect. The people of
                    Memphis were rejoicing on occasion of the discovery of a calf bearing the marks
                    of their god Apis, when he arrived there on his return from his unfortunate
                    expedition. Irritated by their apparent lack of sympathy, and misconstruing
                    their joy, he ordered some of the magistrates of the city to be put to death;
                    and what was still more fatal to his popularity, he commanded the newly-found
                    god to be led into his presence, and inflicted upon it with his dagger a mortal
                    wound. The epitaph of this unfortunate god “has been found by Μ. Mariette in the
                    Serapeum, and is now in the museum of the Louvre” (Lenormant, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Manual of Anc. Hist.,</hi> vol. ii. p. 99). We hear also of his violating the
                    sepulchres of the Egyptians, and of his penetrating into the sanctuaries of
                    their gods, and making sport of the more grotesque images. According to
                    Herodotus, it seemed to the Egyptians that he had gone mad; and it is certain
                    that they retained the most gloomy recollections of this period of their
                    history. In the inscription already mentioned, drawn up while the Persians were
                    still supreme in the country, and therefore with due reserve and caution,
                    reference is made to the procedure of Cambyses in such language as the following
                    :—“There happened a calamity in this district along with the very great calamity
                    which befell the whole land ;” “a frightful misfortune befell Egypt, the like of
                    which never occurred in this land” (Brugsch, <hi rend="italic">op. dt.,</hi> i.
                    p. 271; Lauth, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 19, <hi rend="italic"
                    >cf.</hi> p. 49). It is, in all probability, the sense of this “frightful
                    misfortune ”—the keenness of feeling excited by the outrageous deeds of Cambyses
                    towards their gods—which led the Egyptians to allege that he was smitten with
                    frenzy, and to put in circulation some at least of the many stories relating to
                    his cruelty towards his own countrymen and relatives which Herodotus and others
                    report.</p>
                <p>After an absence from Persia of several years, Cambyses, having appointed
                    Aryandes, a Persian, governor of Egypt, set out on his homeward march. He was
                    met, according to Herodotus (iii. 64), at a place in Syria called Agbatana,
                    supposed by some to be Batanaea, or Bashan, by others to be Hamath, by the
                    tidings of the Median revolution, the usurpation of the sovereignty by Gomates,
                    the Magian, and the impersonation by the usurper of his own brother whom, as has
                    been noticed, he had caused to be secretly murdered. Springing hastily upon his
                    horse, his sword fell from the sheath and wounded him mortally in the thigh.
                    According <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n809/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0809-0734"/> to Ctesias <hi rend="italic">(Exc. Pers.,</hi> §
                    12) he died at Babylon, of a wound accidentally inflicted while carving a piece
                    of wood for his amusement These accounts agree in representing his death as
                    accidental A somewhat different impression is conveyed by the statement of
                    Darius on the point in the Behistun inscription (i. 11), who says that “killing
                    himself he died’ <hi rend="italic">(Of.</hi> Oppert, <hi rend="italic">Les
                    inscriptions cles Aclièmé aides,</hi> p. 54.) It may be, as Spiegel believes <hi
                    rend="italic">(Erαn. Alterthum.,</hi> ii. p. 302), that the phrase expresses
                    nothing more than the Greek tradition reports. Rawlinson, however <hi
                    rend="italic">(Anc. Mon.,</hi> iv. p. 394), and Duncker <hi rend="italic">(op.
                    cit.,</hi> ii. p. 801) understand it as meaning that he committed suicide. The
                    character of this king is sufficiently obvious. It is evident that he was an
                    impulsive, self-willed, reckless, ambitious despot, of the peculiarly Oriental
                    type, possessed of considerable ability as a general, but with passions so
                    strong and uncontrolled as to render the powers he possessed worthless for good.
                    It was reported that from his childhood he was liable to epilepsy and also, what
                    is probably more trustworthy, that he came to be much given to wine. By the
                    Egyptians he made himself utterly abhorred. By the Persians also, while they
                    acknowledged his success in enlarging their empire, his memory was held in evil
                    repute. While they called Cyrus a father, they called his son a despot or
                    master; and while they said the one was “gentle, and procured them all manner of
                    goods,” they called the other “harsh and reckless” (see Herodotus, iii. 33, 34,
                    89). In the Hebrew Scriptures, Cambyses appears once under the name of
                    Ahasuerus, in Ezra iv. 6 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Artaxerxes).</hi> Some
                    suppose that he is the “cruel lord” and “fierce king,” to whose hands the
                    Egyptians were to be given over, according to Isa. xix. 4 His name occurs in
                    Babylonian contract-tablets found at Warka, with the title “Cambyses, king of
                    Babylon.” (See Loftus, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> p. 222; Bosanquet, <hi
                    rend="italic">Trans. Bib. Archaeology,</hi> i. pp. 210, ∕.) He is usually
                    regarded as the Lohrasp of Persian traditional history (Malcom, <hi
                    rend="italic">Hist, of Persia,</hi> i. p. 334); but another of the heroes of
                    that cycle of romance, Kaus, appears both from the name and from the exploits
                    ascribed to him to be the true representative of Cambyses. <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Of.</hi> Spiegel, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> vol.i. p. 594; Gobineau,
                    <hi rend="italic">Hist,</hi><hi rend="italic">des Perses,</hi> vol. i. p. 523.)
                    (w.τu.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
