<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0782-0707-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CALLAO (9th edition, volume 4, page 707)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>267 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205585">Panama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028641">Mud</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1132220">Steam</term>
                    <term ref="fast:927722">Flour</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058953">Peruvians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52fm3g">Ports</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0341g">Customs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j696">Steam</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26m93">Flour</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx4522p">Peruvian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n782/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CALLAO</label>, the chief port of Peru, lies 8½ miles from
                    Lima, the capital city, in 12° 4' S. lat., 77° 13' W. long It is built on a flat
                    point of land in the recess of a spacious and well-sheltered bay, which is
                    partly enclosed by the islands of San Lorenzo and Fronton, and affords the best
                    anchorage on the Peruvian coast. The modern town lies half a mile north of the
                    site of an older city, destroyed by an earthquake and invasion of the sea in
                    1746. It consists mainly of houses built of wicker-work and plastered with mud,
                    stronger buildings being dangerous from the frequency of earthquakes; but a
                    walled quadrangular fortress, built by the Spanish Government between 1770 and
                    1775, extends over about 15 acres, and is now used for the custom-house offices
                    and stores. There are also several forts mounting cannon, and among the public
                    buildings are the military and naval Government offices and barracks, three .
                    Catholic churches and a Protestant chapel, two clubs, a hospital, and four
                    banks. Several newspapers are published in the town. Callao is the headquarters
                    of the Pacific Steam Navigation Company in South America (incorporated in 1840),
                    and the works in connection with their large fleet of steam-vessels— foundries,
                    carpenters’ shops, flour-mills, bakeries, and gasworks—occupy a large area near
                    the custom-house. A large steam sugar-refinery is also in operation. Harbour
                    works, consisting of sea walls of concrete blocks, and docks, with <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n783/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0783-0708"/> berthing space for thirty large vessels, begun in
                    1871, were completed in February 1875, superseding the old and inconvenient pier
                    and boat harbour. These works comprise also eighteen steam-cranes for loading
                    goods, a triple line of railway along the dock walls, gas illumination, and
                    supplies of fresh water. A floating dock, 300 feet in length, capable of taking
                    up a vessel of 21 feet draught, and 5000 tons weight, was built in Glasgow and
                    sent out to Callao harbour in 1863. The phenomenon of the bubbling up of
                    sulphuretted hydrogen gas in the harbour, known as “Callao painter,” from its
                    action on the paint of ships, has generally been ascribed to volcanic action,
                    the belief having been that Callao is in the crater of an extinct volcano; but
                    the borings for the new works discovered the cause of this to be in strongly
                    impregnated springs forcing their way up through a stratum of clay and mud.
                    Callao communicates with Lima by carriage road, and by a railway, completed in
                    1852, which is now extended through the capital towards Oroya over the Maritime
                    Andes. The Pacific Company despatches or receives an ocean steamer almost every
                    week to or from Liverpool by Valparaiso, the Strait of Magellan, and Rio de
                    Janeiro; a separate bi-weekly steam line unites the port with Valparaiso, and
                    communication is maintained with Panama by steamers four times a month each way.
                    French and German steam lines have also headquarters at Callao. Trade is carried
                    on mainly with Britain, the United States, France, Italy, Germany, Norway, and
                    Central America, an average of nearly 2000 vessels entering the harbour
                    annually, and frequently clearing in ballast for the Guano Islands, although
                    exportation from the former main source of supply of guano — the Chincha
                    Islands—ceased in 1872. This substance continues to be the most valuable export;
                    after it come sugar, cotton, wool, hides, silver, and gold. Callao imports
                    timber and railway material, wheat, ice, cattle, coal, and mixed cargoes of
                    manufactures from foreign countries, and considerable quantities of flour from
                    Chili. The whole value of imports and exports exceeds £6,000,000 annually. Since
                    1850, with the exception of the years between 1856 and 1861, when the
                    immigration was prohibited by Congress, Chinese coolies have been imported in
                    considerable numbers through Callao from the Portuguese possession of Macao in
                    China. Perhaps 100,000 male Chinese have been introduced under contracts to
                    serve for eight years; the passages have too often been attended with great
                    hardships and frightful mortality, but the Chinese prove valuable workers on the
                    great railroads now constructing in Peru.</p>
                <p>Though the climate of Callao is good, having the pure breeze from the Pacific,
                    and a temperature rarely exceeding 77° or falling below 65° Fahr., yet, in the
                    absence of all hygiene, diseases, such as fevers and smallpox, are very
                    prevalent, and the rate of mortality is high. The population, in default of
                    recent exact enumeration, may be taken at from 15,000 to 18,000; the census of
                    1866, the latest, gave 14,800, a decrease of upwards of 2000 in seven years, and
                    the number was further reduced by the havoc made by yellow fever in 1868. The
                    traffic and business, and with these probably the population, of the port are,
                    however, increasing.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
