<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0730-0659-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CALDERON DE LA BARCA, Pedro (9th edition, volume 4,
                    page 659)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>267 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897468">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:966832">Idealism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897549">Dramatists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198490">Dreams</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1005551">Magicians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xg38">Dreams</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp2k">Cross</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62623">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639k505">Idealism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n730/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CALDERON DE LA BARCA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pedro</hi></label>
                    (1600-1681), the most eminent representative of the Spanish national drama, was
                    born in Madrid, January 17,1600. His prosperous life was undistinguished by
                    striking incidents. He received his education at Salamanca, and after having
                    been, as would seem, for some years a retainer or dependant of various noblemen,
                    in 1625 entered the army, where it is hinted that he did not distinguish
                    himself. He had begun to write for the stage in 1622, and in 1636 he was
                    summoned to court, and soon became habitually employed as a writer of court
                    spectacles by King Philip IV., a munificent patron of authors and artists. He
                    was also made a knight of Santiago, and saw some further military service in
                    Cata-Ionia<pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n731/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0731-0660"/>: but in 1651 he entered the church, and from that
                    period wrote nothing but spectacular plays for representation at court, and the
                    religious pieces known as <hi rend="italic">Autos Sacramentales.</hi> He
                    received various ecclesiastical preferments from Philip IV., and prolonged his
                    days in wealth and honour until his death on May 25,1681. Very few traits of his
                    personal character have been preserved, and little else can be extracted from
                    the sonorous eulogium of his friend and biographer Vera Tassis than that he was
                    held in esteem for gravity, urbanity, and modesty. A surer testimony to his
                    character is the spirit of his works, which are animated throughout by a lofty
                    ideal of honour and religion according to the conceptions of his age and
                    country, and are wholly free from the usual impurity of the stage. He must
                    evidently have been a highly accomplished man, possessed of a large stock of
                    erudition.</p>
                <p>The entire number of pieces comprised in Hartzenbusch’s edition of Calderon,
                    which does not include the <hi rend="italic">autos sαcrαmentαles,</hi> is 122.
                    There are 72 <hi rend="italic">autos.</hi> It is of course impossible to notice
                    here more than a fraction of this prodigious mass of dramatic poetry. We shall
                    briefly characterize the classes under which it admits of being distributed,
                    adducing a few of the more remarkable dramas as representatives of the whole,
                    and following in the main the admirable arrangement of Schack.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Religious Dramas.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Of these
                    Schack reckons sixteen, including <hi rend="italic">The Statue of
                    Prometheus</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Life is a Dream.</hi> This division
                    comprises some of Calderon’s most famous pieces, in particular <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Wonder-working Magician,</hi> in which the brilliancy of his poetical
                    imagination is displayed to the fullest extent, and by Shelley’s translation of
                    which he is hitherto best known in England. The subject—the voluntary surrender
                    of a human soul to the Evil One— offers striking analogies and equally strong
                    contrasts to Goethe’s <hi rend="italic">Faust.</hi> The comparison of the two
                    pieces is most instructive, and most forcibly attests the vast progress in depth
                    of thought and complexity of emotion of the modern over the mediaeval world. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Devotion of the Cross</hi> is another of the most remarkable
                    pieces of this class, rich in poetical beauties, and exhibiting Catholic
                    antinomianism in its most unmitigated form. There is a deeper vein of thought in
                    <hi rend="italic">Life is a Dream,</hi> in which the poet is comparatively free
                    from ecclesiastical influences, and which is also one of his most striking and
                    original productions. <hi rend="italic">The Constant Prince,</hi> founded on Don
                    Ferdinand of Portugal’s captivity, is the very flower of Spanish religion,
                    courtesy, and chivalry, and, like <hi rend="italic">Life is a Dream,</hi> is an
                    excellent acting play. <hi rend="italic">The Schism of England</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">The Dayspring in Copacavaηa,</hi> apart from their great poetical
                    merits, are interesting as indications of the national feeling with regard to
                    nearly contemporary events.</p>
                <p>2. Nineteen of Calderon’s dramas are classed as historical tragedies. These
                    generally exhibit his talent for effective theatrical situation in the most
                    advantageous light; but in psychological depth and truth he is far behind the
                    great dramatic masters of other countries. The most celebrated of these pieces
                    are founded on incidents in Spanish and Portuguese history, from the posthumous
                    coronation of Inez de Castro to the heart-rending story of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Gomez Arias’s Leman,</hi> and the powerful domestic tragedy of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Alcalde of Zalamea,</hi> which displays more individuality in the
                    delineation of personal character than is usual with him. Nowhere can a fuller
                    insight be obtained into the peculiarities of the Spanish character and the
                    national ideal while the nation was still a great Catholic and Crusading power.
                    Calderon’s treatment of historical fact, it need hardly be said, is frequently
                    as free as Shakspeare’s. The most remarkable of his historical plays, whose
                    plots are not derived from the history of his own country, are <hi rend="italic"
                    >No Monster like Jealousy,</hi> a most powerful tragedy on the story of Herod
                    and Mariamne; <hi rend="italic">The Locks of A bsalom,</hi> so greatly admired
                    by Shelley; and <hi rend="italic">Zenobia</hi><hi rend="italic">the
                    Great.</hi></p>
                <p>3. The subjects of twenty-four of Calderon’s pieces are derived from mythology,
                    chivalric romance, or novels. Most of these are merely spectacular, affording
                    little scope for strictly dramatic power, but dazzling from the opulence of the
                    poet’s invention, and the sweetness and variety of his versification. He has
                    here given his imagination the freest rein, and is nowhere more truly himself.
                    <hi rend="italic">No Magic like Love,</hi> a play on the story of Circe; <hi
                    rend="italic">Echo and Narcissus</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">The Bridge of Mantible</hi> may be cited as characteristic
                    examples.</p>
                <p>4. Sixteen romantic dramas, generally melodramas or tragi-comédies, form the
                    transition from Calderon’s tragic to his comic theatre. None of his plays are
                    more distinguished for ingenuity of conception and grace of style. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Loud Secret</hi> is perhaps the most celebrated, but the rest
                    are of hardly inferior merit.</p>
                <p>5. We now come to Calderon’s comedies of intrigue, the so-called “comedies of
                    cloak and sword,” his delineations of the manners of his day, and of the actual
                    human life around him. His range is an exceedingly limited one in comparison
                    with that of the English dramatists. It hardly transcends the sphere of ordinary
                    good society,—the valets and other representatives of the lower orders being for
                    the most part merely conventional types. The motive of his pieces, moreover,
                    seldom comprehends more than the two prime factors of love and jealousy. Within
                    these limits, however, his perception is commonly correct, and his characters
                    are depicted with more individuality and subtlety than in his more serious
                    pieces. Even his high-flown strain of chivalric sentiment and his punctilious
                    formality correspond to fact. They are artificial indeed, but not affected, for
                    they actually represent the ideal of the best contemporary society, and
                    represent the Spanish cavalier, if not precisely as he was, yet as he wished to
                    be esteemed. The capital merit of these pieces, however, is the prodigious
                    ingenuity of the plots, and the fertility of invention by which our attention is
                    kept continually on the stretch. Calderon’s expedients are inexhaustible; every
                    fresh incident surprises, and none appears capricious or unnatural. Twenty-five
                    plays are included under this head. <hi rend="italic">The Fairy Lady</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">’Tis ill keeping a House with Two Doors</hi> are perhaps the
                    most generally known; all however are nearly upon a level.</p>
                <p>6. <hi rend="italic">Autos Sacramentales.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> A volume
                    might be written upon this most peculiar of all the forms of the modern European
                    drama. We can only describe it here as a development of the mystery or miracle
                    play of the Middle Ages, designed like it for public representation on some
                    specified religious occasion, and falling like it into two classes, the strictly
                    Biblical play, of which Calderon’s <hi rend="italic">Brazen Serpent</hi> is an
                    instance, and the religious allegory. The latter is Calderon’s characteristic
                    department, and nothing can surpass the boldness and quaintness of his
                    personifications. Man, the World, Gαilt, the Morning Star, the Synagogue, and
                    Apostacy figure, for example, among his innumerable <hi rend="italic">dramatis
                    personoe.</hi> The riches of his invention and his diction are nowhere more
                    abundant; but the profoundness of his philosophy and theology have been greatly
                    over-estimated by writers of his own religious communion.</p>
                <p>7. <hi rend="italic">Minor Pieces.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> Calderon also
                    composed numerous farces, interludes, and other brief occasional pieces, the
                    greater part of which are lost.</p>
                <p>Calderon received the Spanish drama from his predecessors in a flourishing
                    condition, exhausted, in conjunction with his numerous gifted contemporaries,
                    every phase of which it allowed, and left it at his death in a condition of
                    total decay. His retirement from the theatre in middle <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n732/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0732-0661"/> life was probably occasioned by the conviction
                    that it admitted of no further development. In his relation to his predecessors
                    he appears as an innovator, chiefly in the simplification of metrical forms.
                    Though at least half of each of his plays is still in complete rhyme, he
                    nevertheless resorts to assonances more liberally than his forerunners. If, on
                    the one hand, this brings him nearer to the language of reality, it on the other
                    sometimes betrays him into verbosity. In his earlier pieces the exuberance of
                    his genius, and the example of the popular lyrical poets of the day, tempted him
                    into conceits and extravagances of diction which are less apparent in his later
                    works. He yet has more fire and colour than any other of the Spanish dramatists,
                    and may be described as the one among them in whom the Oriental element is most
                    largely developed. He shares with his rivals the reproach of repetition, of
                    calculated stage effect, and of stereotyped forms of expression, which become at
                    length mere convention and surplusage. The peculiarity of the form of
                    composition cultivated by Calderon renders it difficult to assign his relative
                    rank among poets of the first class. The Spanish drama is a creation <hi
                    rend="italic">sui generis,</hi> and all attempts at a comparison between it and
                    other theatrical forms must be futile for want of a common measure. The art of
                    Calderon attains its purpose not less completely than that of Shakespeare or
                    Sophocles; all that can be said in its disparagement is that this purpose is
                    less elevated. It falls below the art of Greece, inasmuch as it makes no
                    pretension to represent the ideal either of divinity or of manhood; and. below
                    the art of Shakespeare, inasmuch as, instead of offering a mirror to universal
                    nature, it is restricted to the representation or poetic expression of a
                    temporary and accidental phase of manners. It is the most perfect embodiment
                    conceivable of all the romantic and chivalrous elements of Spanish national
                    life; there is not, perhaps, such another example in literature of the wonderful
                    power of poetry to eliminate all baser matter, and present the innermost idea of
                    a society in untarnished brightness. Calderon is also the most perfect
                    representative of the state of feeling induced by unconditional allegiance to
                    the Catholic Church, at the critical moment when the scales of faith and
                    knowledge are yet in equilibrium. Great Catholic poets may yet arise, with even
                    more than Calderon’s depth of conviction, but none can again enjoy Calderon’s
                    serenity. There is no disturbing element in his world, either of innovation or
                    of resistance; he is everything which by theory a consummate Catholic poet ought
                    to be. It is therefore but logical that he should be set up as the rival of
                    Shakespeare by the partisans of the mediaeval revival, of whom Frederick
                    Schlegel is the most eminent literary representative. It would be a waste of
                    time to contrast the conventional uniformity of his pieces, reducible to five or
                    six types at most, with Shakespeare’s infinite variety; the faint
                    individualization of his characters with Shakespeare’s miraculous subtlety; his
                    class prejudices with Shakespeare’s universal sympathy; his stereotyped cast of
                    thought with Shakespeare’s comprehensive wisdom. It is enough to remark, that
                    greatly as he is admired and widely as he is read, he has not contributed a
                    single appreciable element to the literature of any country but his. own, while
                    Shakespeare has revolutionized the taste of Europe. His relation to his
                    contemporaries is also different from Shakespeare’s. Shakespeare is a sun among
                    stars; Calderon the brightest star of a group. We shall render him most justice,
                    not by instituting a vain parallel with Shakespeare, or even Goethe, but by
                    regarding those qualities which he necessarily has in common with all poetical
                    dramatists. In these respects it is impossible to praise him too highly Nothing
                    can surpass the fertility, ingenuity, and cousiste∣jcy of his constructive
                    faculty on the one hand, or the affluence of his imagery and melody of his
                    versification on the other. The poet and the playwright are happily combined in
                    him; the development of his plots holds the spectator in suspense from first to
                    last, and the diction, except in designedly comic passages, seldom lapses below
                    the pitch of dignified and exquisite poetry. Even the extravagance of his
                    hyperboles appears almost natural amid the general torrent of impassioned
                    feeling. The interminable length of many of his speeches is certainly a fault,
                    and is partly attributable to the fluency and facility of his metre. If we
                    regard him as a tragic poet, we must allow him power, restricted by the absence
                    of any philosophical view of human nature or destiny. As a comic poet he excels
                    in the <hi rend="italic">vis comica</hi> of situation; but his dialogue is more
                    remarkable for vivacity than humour. His proper and peculiar sphere is that of
                    the fancifully poetical. His inventiveness is here equal to any feat of
                    construction, and his imagination to any opulence of adornment. After
                    Shakespeare and Aristophanes, no dramatist has understood so well how to
                    transport his reader or spectator to an ideal world.</p>
                <p>Calderon’s metrical forms, although, as already stated, less rich and intricate
                    than those of the earlier Spanish dramatists, are nevertheless a great obstacle
                    to his being adequately translated. No language but the German, in fact, is
                    adapted to render him. Gries’s version in that language is very celebrated.
                    Schlegel and Schack have rendered some plays very well; and the <hi
                    rend="italic">autos</hi> have been translated by Lorinser. Shelley’s version of
                    some scenes of the <hi rend="italic">Wonder-working Magician</hi> is
                    incomparably the best English interpretation, and no reproduction in our
                    language will ever be perfectly successful that does not proceed upon his
                    principle of intermingling blank verse with irregular lyrical metres. Mr
                    Fitzgerald and Mr D. F. M <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> Carthy, two excellent
                    translators, have erred,—the former by resorting to blank verse entirely, the
                    latter by discarding it altogether. Mr Fitzgerald’s version is too English, and
                    Mr M'Carthy’s too Spanish; the peculiar delicacy of the assonant rhyme, which he
                    has endeavoured to preserve throughout, is entirely imperceptible in our
                    language. Mr Fitzgerald has rendered six plays, and Mr M <hi rend="superscript">
                    l</hi> Carthy eleven. There is perhaps no more congenial field for a writer of a
                    poetical temperament than the translation of Calderon.</p>
                <p>The chronology of Calderon’s pieces is unsettled, but much has been done to
                    adjust it. Many of them were printed during his life, but the first collective
                    edition was that published in 1685 by his friend Vera Tassis. It is not quite
                    complete, and some plays, including most of the author’s dramatic trifles, are
                    irremediably lost. The best edition is that by Hartzenbusch in Aribau’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Bibliotcca de Autores Españolcs</hi> (4 vols., Madrid, 1848-50).
                    It does not contain the <hi rend="italic">autos,</hi> which were published at
                    Madrid in 1717 and in 1759-60. There is also a good edition by Keil (Hamburg,
                    1827-30). Accounts of Calderon will be found in Bouterwek, Ticknor, and other
                    historians of Spanish literature; but the best and fullest is that by Schack in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der dramatischen Literatur und Kunst in
                    Spanien,</hi> vol. iii. (Berlin, 1846.) (R. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
