<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0697-0626-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CADIZ (9th edition, volume 4, page 626)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>267 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980379">Isthmuses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205805">Cuba</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n697/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CADIZ</label> (in Latin <hi rend="italic">Gades,</hi> and
                    formerly called Cales by the English), the capital of a province of the same
                    name in Spain, is built on the extremity of a tongue of land projecting about
                    five miles into the sea, in a direction N.W. from the Isla de Leon, in 36° 3Γ
                    N". lat., 6° 18' W. long., 94 miles by rail south of Seville, and 13 from Xeres.
                    The city, which is six or seven miles in circumference, is surrounded by a wall
                    with five gates, one of which communicates with the isthmus. Seen from a
                    distance off the coast, it presents a magnificent display of snow-white turrets
                    rising majestically from the sea: and for the uniformity and elegance of its
                    buildings, it must certainly be ranked asrine of the finest cities of Spain,
                    although, being hemmed in on all sides, its streets and squares are necessarily
                    contracted. Every house in the city annually receives a coating of whitewash,
                    which, when it is new, produces a disagreeable glare in the streets. The most
                    characteristic feature of Cadiz is the marine promenades, fringing the city all
                    round between the ramparts and the sea, especially that called the <hi
                    rend="italic">Alameda</hi> on the eastern side, commanding a view of the
                    shipping in the bay and the ports on the opposite shore. The principal square is
                    the Plaza de San Antonio, surrounded by handsome houses with elegant façades,
                    the centre pleasantly shaded with trees, and furnished with numerous seats of
                    marble. Communicating with it is the principal street (Calle ÌAncha), in which
                    are the exchange and houses of the nobility. The houses are generally lofty <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n698/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0698-0627"/> and well-built, with open central courts,
                    surmounted by turrets and flat roofs in the Moorish style. The principal public
                    buildings are the two cathedrals (one built in the 13th century, the other begun
                    in 1720, but not completed till 1840); the Hospicio or Casa de Misericordia,
                    adorned with a marble portico, and having an interior court with Doric
                    colonnades; the bull-ring, with room for 12,000 spectators; the two theatres,
                    the prison, the custom-house, and the lighthouse of San Sebastian on the western
                    side, rising 172 feet from the rock on which it stands. Besides the Hospicio
                    already mentioned, which sometimes contains 1000 inmates, there are numerous
                    other charitable institutions, such as the women’s hospital, the foundling
                    institution, the admirable Hospicio de San Juan de Dios for men, and the
                    lunatic., asylum. Gratuitous instruction is given to a large number of children,
                    and there are several mathematical and commercial academies, maintained by
                    different commercial corporations, a nautical school, a school of design, a
                    theological seminary, a flourishing medical school, an <hi rend="italic"
                    >Academia de Nobles</hi><hi rend="italic">Artes</hi> (founded in 1789,
                    principally by the exertions of Governor O’Reilly), an excellent ∙ observatory,
                    and a hydrographic depot. There are several public libraries attached to the
                    various educational establishments, but none of any note. The museum is filled
                    for the most part with wretched copies of ancient masterpieces, but in the
                    church of the Capuchinos, which was formerly a’ monastery, is an unfinished
                    picture of the marriage of St Catherine by Murillo, the last effort of his
                    pencil, as he met his death by falling from the scaffold on which he was
                    painting.</p>
                <p>Cadiz is the see of a bishop, who is suffragan to the archbishop of Seville, but
                    its chief conventual and monastic institutions have been suppressed. Its noble
                    bay, more than 30 miles in circuit and almost entirely land-locked by the
                    isthmus and the headlands which lie to the N.E., has principally contributed to
                    its commercial importance. The outer bay stretches from the promontory and town
                    of Rota to the mouth of the Guadalete; and the inner bay, protected by the forts
                    of Matagorda and Puntales, affords generally good anchorage, and contains a
                    harbour formed by a projecting mole, where vessels of small burden may
                    discharge. The entrance to the bays is rendered somewhat dangerous by the low
                    shelving rocks (Cochinos and Las Puercas), which encumber the passage, and by
                    the shifting banks of mud deposited by the Guadalete and the Rio Santi Petri. On
                    the mainland, at the mouth of the latter river, is the village of Caracca, which
                    contains about 6000 inhabitants, and possesses a naval arsenal and dockyard; and
                    on the isthmus are situated the well-frequented sea-bathing establishments.</p>
                <p>The commercial greatness of Cadiz is no longer what it was in the 17th and 18th
                    centuries. At one time it was the great focus of intercourse between Spain and
                    the Spanish colonies; and from 1720 to 1765 it enjoyed a monopoly of the traffic
                    with Spanish America, which had previously been in the hands of Seville. Its
                    prosperity began to decline when the trade of San Domingo, Cuba, Porto Rico, and
                    the other islands was opened up to the greater ports of Spain, and decayed
                    almost entirely in the beginning of the present century, when the colonies
                    achieved their independence. An attempt was made by the Spanish Government in
                    1828 to restore its former greatness, by making it a free warehousing port, but
                    this valuable privilege was withdrawn in 1832. Since the opening of the railway
                    to Seville and the improvements effected in the harbour, the commercial activity
                    has greatly increased; and in spite of the disturbing influences of political
                    revolutions, Cadiz is still one of the most important ports in Spain. It is the
                    European terminus of many of the principal mail-lines from the colonies both in
                    the east and west. Besides the Xeres wine, for which it received in 1872 no less
                    than £2,458,487 from Britain alone, it exports quicksilver, brandy, oil,
                    provisions, flour, and wool. The salt trade, which was formerly of considerable
                    extent, is almost extinct. The imports consist chiefly of sugar and coffee from
                    Havana and Porto Rico, English coal from Cardiff, cocoa, hemp, flax, linens,
                    dried fish, hides, cotton and woollen manufactures, rice, spices, indigo,
                    staves, and timber. The total number of vessels that entered in 1872 was 1140,
                    of which 494 were steamships; and the total tonnage was 287,850. Of the sailing
                    vessels 179 were British and 136 Italian, of the steamships 127 British and 281
                    Spanish. The manufactures of Cadiz are unimportant, though a considerable
                    stimulus to industry is given by the <hi rend="italic">Sociedad economica de
                    Amigos del Pais,</hi> which introduced the cochineal plant, and grants medals
                    for improvements in manufactures.</p>
                <p>Cadiz is strongly fortified with ramparts and bastions, and defended by the forts
                    of San Sebastian, Santa Catalina, Matagorda, and Puntales Castle. On the
                    neighbouring coast the isthmus is protected by an intrenchment called the
                    Cortadura, or Fort San Fernando.</p>
                <p>From its almost insular position it enjoys a mild and serene climate, the mean
                    annual temperature being about 64° Fahr., while the mean summer and winter
                    temperatures vary only about 10° above and below this point. From the same cause
                    it labours under a great deficiency of water, which must either be collected in
                    cisterns from the' tops of the houses or brought at great expense from Santa
                    Maria on the opposite coast. Population in 1845, 53,922, and in 1860,
                    71,521.</p>
                <p>Cadiz is identical with the ancient Agadir, Gadir, or Gaddir (in Greek <hi
                    rend="italic">Gαdeirα),</hi> which was a flourishing Phoenician colony long
                    before the beginning of classical history, and continued in the hands of the
                    Carthaginians, though somewhat disaffected to them, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n699/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0699-0628"/> till after the Punic wars, when Spain became a
                    Roman province. C. Julius Caesar conferred the <hi rend="italic">civitas</hi> of
                    Rome on all its citizens in 49 B.c.; and not long after L. Cornelius Balbus
                    Minor built what was called the “New City,” constructed the harbour which is now
                    known as Puerto Real, and erected the bridge across the strait of Santi Petri,
                    which unites the Isla de Leon with the mainland, and is now known as the Puente
                    de Zuazo, after Juan Sanchez de Zuazo, who restored it in the 15th century.
                    Under Augustus, when it was the residence of no fewer than 500 <hi rend="italic"
                    >equites,</hi> it was made a municipium with the name of Augusta Urbs Gaditana,
                    and its citizens ranked next to those of Rome. Some remains of the ancient city,
                    and particularly of the temple of Hercules, are said to be visible below the
                    sea. After the fall of Rome it was destroyed by the Goths, and remained in
                    obscurity under the Moors, from whom it was retaken by Alphonso the Wise in
                    1262, but it emerged again when the discovery of America made it valuable as a
                    market for colonial produce. In more recent contests Cadiz has been subjected to
                    several disasters. It was taken and pillaged in 1596 by the British fleet, under
                    Essex and Howard, in revenge for the Spanish Armada. It was attacked, but
                    without success, by Lord Wimbledon in 1626, and by the duke of Ormond and Sir
                    George Rooke in 1702. It was bombarded by Nelson in 1800. In 1808 the Spanish
                    patriots in Cadiz brought the French fleet, which lay in the bay blockaded by
                    Admiral Collingwood, to a surrender; and they were in turn subjected to a
                    protracted siege of two years by Marshal Victor, from which they were relieved
                    by the successes of Wellington in the Peninsula. It was once more reduced by the
                    Duke d’Angoulême in 1823, and remained in the hands of the French till 1828. In
                    1868 the city was the centre of the revolution which effected the dethronement
                    of Queen Isabella.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
