<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0883-0800-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CANCER, or Carcinoma (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    800)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>267 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mh3x">Organ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rq88">Growth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p161">Surgeons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1047771">Organisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047777">Organization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:948571">Growth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139336">Surgeons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n883/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CANCER, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Carcinoma</hi></label> (from
                    <hi rend="italic">cancer,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">καρκίνος,</hi> an eating
                    ulcer), is the name given to a class of morbid growths or tumours which occur in
                    man, and also in certain of the lower animals. The term is apt to be somewhat
                    loosely employed, partly owing to the fact that there are not a few forms of
                    diseased growth respecting which it is still a matter of debate whether they are
                    to be regarded as cancerous or not; and in some measure also to the difficulty
                    often experienced in recognizing true cancer particularly in its earlier
                    stages.</p>
                <p>The disease exists in various forms, which, although differing from each other in
                    many points, have yet certain common characters to which they owe their special
                    significance.</p>
                <p>1. In structure such growths are composed of nucleated cells and free nuclei
                    together with a milky fluid called <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n884/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0884-0801"/> cιaeor juice, ah contained within a more or less
                    dense fibrous stroma or framework.</p>
                <p>2. They have no well-defined limits, and they involve all textures in their
                    vicinity, while they also tend to spread by the lymphatics and veins, and to
                    cause similar growths in distant parts or organs called “secondary cancerous
                    growths.”</p>
                <p>3. They are undergoing constant increase, and their progress is usually
                    rapid.</p>
                <p>4. Pain is a frequent symptom. When present it is generally of a severe and
                    agonizing character, and together with the local effects of the disease and the
                    resulting condition of ill health or “cachexia,” hastens the fatal termination
                    to which all cancerous growths tend.</p>
                <p>5. When such growths are removed by the surgeon they are apt to return either at
                    the same or at some other part.</p>
                <p>The chief varieties of cancer are <hi rend="italic">Scirrhus</hi> or hard cancer,
                    <hi rend="italic">Encephaloid</hi> or soft cancer, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Epithelial cancer.</hi></p>
                <p>Scirrhus is remarkable for its hardness, which is due to the large amount of its
                    fibrous, and relatively small proportion of its cell elements. It is of
                    comparatively slow growth, but it tends to spread and to ulcerate. Its most
                    common seat by far is the female breast, though it sometimes affects internal
                    organs.</p>
                <p>Encephaloid is in structure the reverse of the last, its softness depending on
                    the preponderance of its cell over its fibrous elements. Its appearance and
                    consistence resemble brain substance (hence its name), and it is of such rapid
                    growth as to have given rise to its being occasionally termed <hi rend="italic"
                    >acute cancer.</hi> Its most frequent seats are internal organs or the limbs.
                    Ulceration and haemorrhage are common accompaniments of this form of cancer.</p>
                <p>Epithelial cancer is largely composed of cells resembling the natural epithelium
                    of the body. It occurs most frequently in those parts provided with epithelium,
                    such as the skin and mucous membranes, or where those adjoin, as in the lips.
                    This form of cancer does not spread so rapidly nor produce secondary growths in
                    other organs to the same extent as the two other varieties, but it tends equally
                    with them to involve the neighbouring lymphatic glands, and to recur after
                    removal.</p>
                <p>Various views are entertained, and much discussion has taken place respecting the
                    causation of cancer, but little has as yet been satisfactorily ascertained on
                    the point. By some the disease is held to be from the first an entirely local
                    affection, due to some alteration in the nutrition of the part, irrespective of
                    any condition of the system generally, but in course of time coming to assume a
                    malignant form, and to infect the system secondarily. Others, on the contrary,
                    maintain that a certain constitutional condition, either as regards the blood or
                    some of the tissues of the body, must exist prior to the development of the
                    disease to which it gives rise. A third view is that the concurrence of a
                    constitutional and a local cause is necessary for the production of cancer
                    Without entering into an examination of these opinions, it appears evident that
                    a constitutional element cannot be excluded in view of such well-known facts as
                    a hereditary liability to cancer, and also of its occasional appearance in
                    several parts of the body at one time.</p>
                <p>The hereditary tendency in some persons to* this disease has long been recognized
                    by medical men; but its extent was not accurately ascertained till Sir James
                    Paget affirmed, as the result of his observations, that in one out of every
                    three cases of cancer a family history of the malady could be traced, and
                    further, that even this probably does not represent the whole extent of the
                    hereditary predisposition to cancer.</p>
                <p>Cancer is essentially a disease of degeneracy, all statistics going to show its
                    relatively great frequency after middle life; and the mortality, according to Dr
                    Walshe, goes on increasing with each decade until the eightieth year. Cancer
                    may, nevertheless, attack persons of any age, and instances of its occurrence
                    are not unknown even among young children. It affects females to a much larger
                    extent than males,—this, however, being fully explained by the greater liability
                    of the female breast and of the uterus to the disease than any other organs of
                    the body; for, apart from this, cancer is quite as common among men. It occurs
                    equally among all ranks of life.</p>
                <p>The commencement of a cancerous growth is frequently attributed to some local
                    injury, as in the case of blows on the breast, or in the well-known instance of
                    cancer of the lip following the irritation produced by smoking a short clay
                    pipe. But it is only as exciting causes that the influence of such injuries can
                    be admitted; and there must still remain, as necessary to account for the
                    disease, some antecedent condition of the system which gives the particular
                    direction to the form of morbid action in the part.</p>
                <p>Cancer tends to advance steadily to a fatal termination, but its duration varies
                    in different cases according to the part affected, and according to the variety
                    of the disease. Soft cancer affecting important organs of the body often proves
                    fatal in a few months, while, on the other hand, cases of hard or epithelial
                    cancer may sometimes last for several years; but no precise limit can be
                    assigned for any form of the disease. In some exceptionally rare instances
                    cancerous growth may exist for a great length of time, and undergo a kind of
                    spontaneous cure, or at least prolonged arrestment.</p>
                <p>With respect to the treatment of cancer the only hope of success lies in the
                    entire removal of the disease. This can obviously be only accomplished where the
                    growth affects parts which are within reach of the surgeon. When in such cases
                    the tumour is of recent formation, is limited in its extent, does not largely
                    affect the neighbouring lymphatic glands, and has not as yet produced any marked
                    deterioration of the general health, the surgeon is warranted in operating.
                    Although it must be admitted that the results are generally disappointing from
                    the intense tendency of the disease to recur sooner or later, yet the relief to
                    suffering and the prolongation of life obtained are alone sufficient to justify
                    operative interference when otherwise admissible, not to mention the fact that
                    in some rare instances a cure has thus been achieved. Nor is the view of the
                    constitutional and hereditary nature of cancer necessarily inconsistent with the
                    adoption of such remedial measures,—since, from the analogy of other hereditary
                    diseases, it is probable that these influences are more potent at certain times
                    of life, and that by prompt treatment the period of special liability may be
                    tided over, although the inherent tendency cannot be eradicated. When from the
                    extent of the disease or its existence in internal organs no attempt at removal
                    can be made, all that can be hoped for is the relief of suffering, and it is
                    certain that even in such circumstances much may be done by appropriate medical
                    treatment. It is painful to think how many of the unfortunate sufferers from
                    this malady place themselves in the hands of ignorant persons who profess to be
                    able to cure cancers, but whose violent remedies, if they do not actually
                    destroy life, as has often been the case, only aggravate suffering and entail
                    disappointment.</p>
                <p>Cancer is known to occur in many of the lower animals, being probably most common
                    among the domestic tribes, but it presents no special peculiarities as a disease
                    beyond those already referred to. <hi rend="smallcaps">(j.</hi> o. A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
