<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0894-0811-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CANOE (9th edition, volume 4, page 811)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>267 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zd29">Joints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x62g">Rest</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn5g">Oak</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845879">Canoeists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1750261">Inch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1129434">Speed</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983905">Joints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205669">Jordan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n894/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CANOE</label>, a species of boat. In several Eastern
                    languages the word <hi rend="italic">lean</hi> means something hollow, with a
                    certain degree of strength. Pliny says some Indian reeds are long enough to form
                    a boat for three men between the joints. The French <hi rend="italic"
                    >cαnot,</hi> Spanish <hi rend="italic">canoa,</hi> Italian <hi rend="italic"
                    >canoe,</hi> are derived from the Latin <hi rend="italic">canna;</hi> but a
                    canoe is sometimes called in France <hi rend="italic">bateau, bôt, pirogue,
                    caique,</hi><hi rend="italic">chaloupe, navire,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >nacelle,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">périssoir,</hi> and the paddle <hi
                    rend="italic">pagaye,</hi> and the canoeist <hi rend="italic">pagayeur.</hi> The
                    English word “canoe” may be defined as a boat propelled by one or more paddles
                    used without a fixed fulcrum on the boat, and therefore invariably with the
                    sitter facing towards the bow. Tho Venetian gondola and the Maltese boats, and
                    many others, are rowed by men who face the bows, but they always have a fixed
                    rest for the rowlock. Canoes are made of various substances. Those of the
                    Esquimaux are of sealskin stretched over whalebone, and are propelled by the
                    double-bladed paddle, 7 feet long and 6 inches broad, used by one man, whose
                    dress is united with the deck covering, so as to be watertight.</p>
                <p>The North American “dug-out” canoe is made from a tree hollowed by fire, while
                    the bark canoes are formed by birch bark sewn together, according to the size
                    required, until the craft will hold as many as seventy men. Paper canoes have
                    been used in the United States. Cork leather <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n895/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0895-0812"/> would probably be a very good material. Canoes of
                    tin and of india-rubber have been used in England, but practically all the best
                    canoes now built in England, America, and France for general travelling are of
                    oak, cedar, or pitch pine. The canoe was popular in England more than twenty
                    years ago at Oxford and Cambridge, but only for short river practice, until in
                    1865 one was specially designed for a long journey by water in seas, lakes, and
                    rivers, and by carriage on land in railways or carts or on horseback, or by
                    being dragged over rough ground or borne on men’s shoulders through woods and
                    over hills.</p>
                <p>The general type of this “Rob Roy” canoe is built of oak with a cedar deck. The
                    length is from 12 to 15 feet, and the beam from 26 to 30 inches, the depth 10 to
                    16 inches. The paddle is 7 feet long with 6 indies of breadth in the blade, and
                    is either double-bladed, or, if it is used with a single blade, a rudder is
                    worked by the foot to counteract the lateral swerving. A backboard swinging with
                    the paddler’s motion enables the canoeist to sit in a comfortable position for
                    many hours at a time, and a mast with some light sails completes his equipment,
                    so that a favourable wind eases the muscular exertion. An ordinary travelling
                    canoe when complete weighs about 70 lb. It will float with its paddle and 10
                    ft&gt; of luggage in 5 inches of water. In the Indian canoes of America the
                    single paddle is usually employed, and the men kneel to the work. The canoeists
                    in the Straits of Magellan paddle standing. The peculiar advantages of a canoe
                    may be summed up thus :—</p>
                <p>1. The canoeist faces forwards in the direction of his progress, and therefore he
                    can readily steer without turning his head round.</p>
                <p>2. His centre of gravity is five or six inches below what would be necessary in a
                    row-boat, and therefore the canoe is more steady, and is very suitable for
                    shooting from. When the action of the paddle stops the canoeist is at once in
                    comfortable rest. In descending a rapid where rocks or snags are numerous, the
                    canoeist has much power of seeing and avoiding danger, while he can also get out
                    readily, and can sit on the deck in places where the feet, being in the water,
                    are of service in warding off collisions.</p>
                <p>3. The knees of the canoeist press outwards against the sides of the “well” or
                    opening in the deck, so that in high seas there is ample ‘ ‘ purchase” for
                    counteracting an upset, while the canoeist can use great power with his paddle
                    at a critical moment for lifting the craft over a wave. The alternate action of
                    the arms opens the chest, and the legs are continually exercised by pressure
                    against the stretcher, while the sway of the whole body at each stroke of rowing
                    is dispensed with.</p>
                <p>4. He can instantly hoist sail without leaving his place or shifting ballast, and
                    he can fish or shoot conveniently without changing his seat. He can sleep in the
                    canoe when it is properly prepared.</p>
                <p>5. The canoe being impelled without rowlocks, by pressure through the legs to the
                    feet resting on the stretcher, and by only one implement (the paddle), the
                    joints of the planks and the nails and fastenings, are not loosened, as in other
                    boats, by the jerky leverage of rowlocks.</p>
                <p>6. The deck covering (not feasible in a row-boat) protects the paddler and his
                    luggage from wind, rain, and sea, and adds to the “stiffness” of his craft, so
                    that it can be dragged on rough ground without injury. A canoe should have a
                    very flat floor °and small keel; this secures stability, while it diminishes
                    speed to a very small extent.</p>
                <p>7. Ladies and young children can conveniently use the canoe because of its safety
                    and the simplicity of its mode of propulsion. Many double canoes are used in
                    England, and some with four paddlers together.</p>
                <p>For actual speed over a short and straight course the ordinary sculling skiff is
                    superior to the canoe, but for long journeys of more than a week’s duration, and
                    in strange rivers, or with frequent portage, rough usage, intricate navigation,
                    or unexpected difficulties, the canoe is found to be much more convenient than
                    the rowing boat. Forty miles a day in lakes can be kept up for weeks together in
                    a travelling canoe, unless against a contrary wind. Fast racing canoes are 20
                    feet long and 18 inches broad, and attain a speed of 8 miles an hour. Canoes for
                    “upset races” (where the canoeist has to jump out, tow his boat while swimming,
                    and then get in) and for the race “over land and water” are specially built for
                    their purpose. Other canoes are built chiefly for sailing, and these carry “drop
                    keels,” “rockers,” and heavy ballast.</p>
                <p>In 1866 the Royal Canoe Club was formed in England, and the Prince of Wales
                    became commodore, while about 500 members have been elected in various parts of
                    the world. After the English canoes were seen in Paris at the Exhibition of
                    1867, others like them were built in France. Branches and clubs were formed also
                    at the English universities, and in Liverpool, Hull, Edinburgh, Glasgow, and New
                    York. A publication called <hi rend="italic">The Canoeist</hi> records the more
                    important cruises in canoes in almost every country on the globe. One member of
                    the club crossed the English Channel from Dover to Boulogne in his canoe,
                    another from Boulogne to Dover, and a third crossed the Irish Channel from
                    Scotland to Ireland. Many old and new rivers have been explored for the first
                    time in canoes, among which the most interesting were the hitherto inaccessible
                    parts of the Jordan, the Kish on, and the Abana and the Pharpar at Damascus, as
                    well as the Lake Menzaleh in the Delta of the Nile, and. the Lake of Galilee and
                    Waters of Merom in Syria. So far as has been ascertained, not one of the members
                    of the Royal Canoe Club has been drowned in any of the numerous long cruises
                    performed.</p>
                <p>See Macgregor’s <hi rend="italic">A Thousand Miles in the Rob Roy Canoe, The Rob
                    Roy on the Baltic,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Rob Roy on the Jordan, Red
                    Sea, Nile, and Gennesareth, Ac.; Canoe Travelling,</hi> by W. Baden Powell; <hi
                    rend="italic">Cruise in a Cockle Shell,</hi> by A. H. Reed; <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Canoeist</hi> (Royal Canoe Club). (J. MO.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
