<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0993-0953-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0mz9r">Pain</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0wq2m">Temperance</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jr84">Tempering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hv6n">Defectives</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1050382">Pain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1147289">Temper</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1147375">Tempering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1147309">Temperance</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1741509">Defection</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=993" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">XENOCRATES</label>, a celebrated ancient Grecian philosopher,
                    was born at Chalcedon in the ninety-fifth Olympiad. At first he attached himself
                    to AEschines, but afterwards became a disciple of Plato, who took much pains in
                    cultivating his genius, which was naturally heavy. His temper was gloomy, his
                    aspect severe, and his manners little tinctured with urbanity. These material
                    defects his master took great pains to correct, frequently advising him to
                    sacrifice to the Graces; and the pupil was patient of instruction, and knew how
                    to value the kindness of his preceptor. As long as Plato lived, Xenocrates was
                    one of his most esteemed disciples; after his death he closely adhered to his
                    doctrine; and in the second year of the 110th Olympiad, he took the chair in the
                    academy, as the successor of Speusippus. Xenocrates was celebrated among the
                    Athenians, not only for his wisdom, but likewise for his virtues. So eminent was
                    his reputation for integrity, that when he was called upon to give evidence in a
                    judicial transaction, in which an oath was usually required, the judges
                    unanimously agreed that his simple asseveration should be taken, as a public
                    testimony to his merit. Even Philip of Macedon found it impossible to corrupt
                    him. So abstemious was he with respect to food, that his provision was
                    frequently spoiled before it was consumed. His chastity was invincible. Phryne,
                    a celebrated Athenian courtezan, attempted without success to seduce him. Of his
                    humanity the following pathetic incident is a sufficient proof. A sparrow, which
                    was pursued by a hawk, flew into his bosom; he afforded it protection till its
                    enemy was out of sight, and then let it go, saying that he would never betray a
                    suppliant. He was fond of retirement, and was seldom seen in the city. He was
                    discreet in the use of his time, and carefully allotted a certain portion of
                    each day to its proper business. One of these he employed in silent meditation.
                    He was an admirer of the mathematical sciences; and was so fully convinced of
                    their utility, that when a young man, who was unacquainted with geometry and
                    astronomy, desired admission into the academy, he refused his request, saying
                    that he was not yet possessed of the handles of philosophy. In fine, Xenocrates
                    was eminent both for the purity of his <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=994" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0994-0954"
                    />morals and for his acquaintance with science, and supported the credit of the
                    Platonic school by his lectures, his writings, and his conduct. He lived to the
                    first year of the 116th Olympiad, or the eighty-second of his age, when he lost
                    his life by accidentally falling, in the dark, into a reservoir of water.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
