<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?> <?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0994-0954-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title/>
                <author/>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>TEI-page files converted by Python to TEI-entry file</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z31nv0r">Lips</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4959c77k">Cooperation</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:999431">Lips</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176240">Wisdom</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=994" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">XENOPHON</label>, an illustrious philosopher, commander, and
                    historian, was the son of Gryllus, an Athenian, and is supposed to have been
                    born in the fourth year of the eighty-third Olympiad, 445 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >b. c.</hi> When he was a youth, Socrates, struck with his personal
                    appearance, determined to admit him into the number of his pupils. Meeting him
                    by accident in a narrow passage, the philosopher put his staff across the path,
                    and stopping him, asked w here those things were to be purchased which are
                    necessary to human life? Xenophon appearing at a loss for a reply to this
                    unexpected salutation, Socrates proceeded to ask him where honest and good men
                    were to be found? Xenophon still hesitating, Socrates said to him, “Follow me,
                    and learn.” From that time Xenophon became a disciple of Socrates, and made a
                    rapid progress in that moral wisdom for which his master was so eminent.
                    Xenophon accompanied Socrates in the Peloponnesian war, and fought courageously
                    in defence of his country. He afterwards entered into the army of Cyrus as a
                    volunteer in his expedition against his brother. This enterprise proving
                    unfortunate, Xenophon, after the death of Cyrus, advised his fellow-soldiers to
                    attempt a retreat into Greece. They listened to his advice; and having had many
                    proofs of his wisdom as well as courage, they gave him the command of the army,
                    after the death of their generals. In this command he acquired great glory by
                    the prudence and firmness with which he conducted them back, through the midst
                    of innumerable dangers, into their own country. The particulars of this
                    memorable service are related by Xenophon himself in his Anabasis, frequently
                    called the Retreat of the ten Thousand. After his return into Greece, he joined
                    Agesilaus, king of Sparta, and fought with him against the Thebans in the
                    celebrated battle of Chaeronea. The Athenians, displeased at this alliance,
                    brought a public accusation against him for his former conduct in engaging in
                    the service of Cyrus, and condemned him to exile. The Spartans upon this took
                    Xenophon, as an injured man, under their protection, and provided him a
                    comfortable retreat at Scillus. Here, with his wife and two children, he
                    remained several years, and passed his time in the society of his friends, and
                    in writing those historical works which have rendered his name immortal. A war
                    at length arose between the Spartans and Eleans; and Xenophon was obliged to
                    retire to Lepreum, where his sons had taken refuge. He afterwards removed, with
                    his whole family, to Corinth, where he is supposed to have died, about the age
                    of ninety; but the chronology of his life is involved in obscurities from which
                    it cannot easily be extricated.</p>
                <p>Of the works of Xenophon there are many editions. The <hi rend="italic">editio
                        princeps</hi> was printed by Junta, Florent. 1516, fol. An edition more
                    correct, and containing some works omitted in the first, issued from the press
                    of Aldus, Venet. 1525, fol. After several intervening impressions appeared that
                    of H. Stephanus, 156), fol. Another important edition, several times reprinted,
                    was that of Leunclavius, Basil. 1569, fol. After a long interval, this was
                    followed by the edition of Wells, Oxon. 1703, 5 tom. 8vo. The editor, who is not
                    commended for his fidelity, has added Dodwell’s <hi rend="italic">Chronologia
                        Xenophontea.</hi> This edition of Dr Wells was republished with considerable
                    improvements by Thieme, Lipsiae, 1763-4, 4 tom. 8vo. A valuable edition with a
                    commentary was afterwards published by Weiske, Lips. 1798-1804, 6 tom. 8vo. We
                    shall only mention another edition, that of J. G. Schneider, Lips. 1815, 6 tom.
                    8vo. A very useful accompaniment of any edition must not be overlooked, namely
                    Sturz’s <hi rend="italic">Lexicon Xenophonteum.</hi> Lips. 1801-4, 4 tom. 8vo.
                    The materials had partly been collected by Thieme. Of several works of Xenophon
                    there are many separate editions, some of them very elaborate. Several of them
                    have likewise been translated into many different languages. Gail published
                    “OEuvres complètes de Xénophon, traduites en Français, accompagnées du texte, de
                    la version Latine, et de notes critiques.” Paris, 1797- 1804, 6 tom. 4to. A
                    supplementary volume, in three parts, containing various appendages, was
                    subsequently published. The French version is not entirely new. The translations
                    of the Cyropaedia, Anabasis, and Memorabilia, by Dacier, Larcher, and Levêque,
                    have been adopted with some slight modifications. Some of his works have been
                    repeatedly translated into English; but we shall only specify the version of the
                    Cyropaedia by the Hon. Maurice Ashley Cooper, of the Anabasis by Edward Spelman,
                    of the Memorabilia by Sarah Fielding, of the Symposium by Dr Wellwood, and of
                    the History by Dr Smith, dean of Chester.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Χενορηον,</hi> a native of Ephesus, is supposed to have
                    written towards the close of the second century. His romance, “De Anthia et
                    Habrocome Ephesiacorum libri v.” was first edited by Cocchi, Lond. 1726, 4to. An
                    Italian translation had previously been published by Salvini, Lond. 1723, 8vo.
                    The original work appears in the collection of Mitscherlich, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Scriptores Erotici Gravi.</hi> Biponti, 1792-4, 3 tom. 8vo. It was about
                    the same time edited by Polyzoes, Viennae Aust. 1793, 8vo. A much better edition
                    was soon afterwards published by Baron Locella, Vien. Aust. 1796, 4to. Another
                    edition, regarded as the best, was published by Peerlkamp, Harlemi, 1818, 4to.
                    This romance of Xenophon the Ephesian has repeatedly been translated into French
                    and German, as well as Italian; and an English version was published by Rooke,
                    Lond. 1727, 8vo.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
