<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0829-0794-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DAMIRI (9th edition, volume 6, page 794)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n829/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DAMIRI</label> (1341-1405), sometimes spelt <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">DomaIrI,</hi> or, with the Arabic article, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Ad-DamIri,</hi> is really an adjective of relation applied to a person or thing
                    belonging to one of the two contiguous towns of North and South Damirah, near
                    Damietta, in Egypt. Under this name is usually understood a well-known Arabian
                    writer on canon law, who is at the same time the author of a treatise on natural
                    history, which in the East has attained considerable celebrity. His full name
                    and title is Kemal ud-den Abu’l BagH Muhammed Ben Musa Ben Isa ad-Damiri
                    Ash-Skafei. He was born in Cairo in the year 742 of the Hegira (1341 A.D.), and
                    died there in the year 808 (1405). Damiri’s reputation, so far as the Western
                    nations are concerned, is not based upon his work as a jurist, but wholly upon
                    his natural history, which is entitled <hi rend="italic">The Life of
                    Animals</hi> (Hayat’ul Haiwan). In this treatise the author gives the names of
                    931 beasts, birds, fishes, and insects with which he was (probably rarely by
                    personal knowledge) acquainted, arranging these alphabetically, and giving a
                    longer or shorter account of their nature and peculiarities, according as the
                    data, actual or fabulous, in his possession would allow him. As might have been
                    anticipated, he is more especially copious and minute when he comes to treat of
                    animals like the lion and the camel; but in all cases he defines the orthography
                    and vocalization of the name, gives the forms of the plurals and feminines, and
                    supplies the local or vernacular titles by which the animals were known. It is
                    unnecessary to say that Damiri does not treat natural <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n830/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0830-0795"/> history in the exact and systematic manner of the
                    modern zoologist Not only would that have been impossible at the time at which
                    he lived, but he himself did not profess to be a scientific observer, and he was
                    induced to prepare his work on natural history in consequence of the gross
                    ignorance of this subject which was exhibited by many of the theologians of the
                    period. His exposition of the natural history of his country is essentially the
                    result of his interest in theological and legal matters, and his wide
                    acquaintance with the learned culture of the Arabic language, and therefore is
                    from a scientific point of view a mere compilation; and at the same time his
                    literary knowledge induced him to interrupt the scientific continuity of his
                    narrative by disquisitions of a totally irrelevant character. Thus, in the
                    middle of his article on the Goose, he inserts a consecutive sketch of the
                    history of the Caliphate, from the death of Ali to the accession of
                    Al-Muktafi-—a period of nearly 800 years—at the end of which historical
                    interlude he resumes his article, as if it had not been interrupted. In spite,
                    however, of its deficiencies, the <hi rend="italic">Life of Animals</hi> has an
                    interest of its own and a permanent value to scholars. All references in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Sunna</hi> to any particular animal are mentioned, anecdotes
                    relating to it are introduced, its uses in supplying articles of the materia
                    medica are pointed out, the means to counteract its noxious qualities are
                    indicated, the lawfulness of using its flesh as food is discussed, the proverbs
                    which allude to it are recounted, and citations from the poets who have noticed
                    it are quoted. The amount of discursive reading shown in the work is very great,
                    as it contains quotations from 560 prose authors, and from the divâns, or
                    collected editions, of 199 poets. Upon the whole, therefore, the literary value
                    of the treatise to scholars is by no means small, as it exhibits the natural
                    history of his age and country surrounded by the associations with which the
                    experience and literature of the Arabs had invested it.</p>
                <p>After finishing his work on natural history, Damîrî reproduced it in a
                    compendious form, and it has thus come down to us in a large and a smaller
                    recension. Others, moreover, (such as Al-Usyûti) formed abridgments of it.
                    Manuscript copies of the work exist in many public libraries, and the larger
                    edition has been printed, in the original language, at Cairo, in 2 vols. folio,
                    in 1278 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.</hi> (1861 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi> The
                    European scholar who made the first and amplest use of this work was S. Bochart,
                    in his <hi rend="italic">Hierozoicon,</hi> which first appeared in 1663.</p>
                <p>The other works of Damîrî have not obtained, even in the East, the popularity
                    accorded to his <hi rend="italic">Life of Animals.</hi> His most prominent work
                    on legal subjects is a commentary in four volumes on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Minh</hi><hi rend="italic">â</hi><hi rend="italic">j</hi> of An-Nawawi.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Haji Chalfa,</hi> ed. Fluegel, vol. iii. p. 122; Nicoll, <hi
                    rend="italic">Biblioth. Bodlei. MSS. Orient. Cat.</hi>; Fluegel’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Arabische Hdss, der K. K. Bibliothek zu Wien;</hi> Wuestenfeld’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Arabische Aerzte und Naturforscher,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
