<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0819-0784-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DALTON, John (9th edition, volume 6, page 784)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:939255">Gays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084913">Quakers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839010">Briquets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1090626">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:820653">Atomizers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:820644">Atomism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:820649">Atomization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:820656">Atoms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62f7n">Reading</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x51x">Atoms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42805584">Atomism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gf8v">Quakers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47w67561">Visions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n819/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DALTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1766-1844),
                    the celebrated physicist, and founder of the atomic theory of chemistry, was
                    born September 5, 1766, at Eaglesfield, 2¾ miles south-west of Cockermouth, in
                    Cumberland. His grandfather, Jonathan Dalton, was a member of the Society of
                    Friends, and Dalton as well as his parents belonged to that body. His father,
                    Joseph Dalton, who in 1755 married Deborah Greenup, had three
                    children,—Jonathan, John, the subject of this sketch, and Mary. The occupation
                    in which he was engaged, namely, that of weaving woollens, was not a lucrative
                    one, and Mrs Dalton assisted in the support of the family by the sale of
                    stationery. John received his early education from his father and from a Mr
                    Fletcher, the teacher of the Quakers’ school at Eaglesfield. At the age of
                    twelve he himself began the work of school-teaching, in which he continued for
                    two years; then, for a year or more, he worked occasionally on his father’s
                    farm. His principal study was mathematics, in which he received aid from a
                    distant relative, a gentleman of the name of Robinson, living in the vicinity of
                    Eaglesfield. In 1781 Dalton left his native village to become assistant to his
                    cousin George Bewley, the master of a school for boys and girls at Kendal; and
                    there he spent the next twelve years of his life in teaching, and in studying
                    Latin, Greek, mathematics, and natural philosophy. During that period he became
                    acquainted with the blind philosopher, Mr Gough, to whose influence and help his
                    progress in scientific knowledge was in no small measure due. In 1785 Dalton
                    became, through the retirement of his cousin, joint-manager with his brother of
                    the school at Kendal, and in addition to his ordinary teaching he, in 1787 and
                    1791, gave courses of lectures in natural philosophy. The school was not
                    generally popular, for its young masters were uncouth in manners, and kept aloof
                    from society. Discipline was strict, and the elder brother Jonathan is said to
                    have been stern and severe; John being milder and gentler, and continually
                    preoccupied with mathematics, allowed faults to escape his notice, and was
                    consequently preferred by the scholars. About the year 1790 Dalton appears to
                    have been desirous to secure a larger sphere for his abilities by entering on
                    the profession of law or of physic; but his projects meeting with no
                    encouragement from his relations, he continued to live at Kendal, till in the
                    spring of 1793 he obtained, mainly through Mr Gough, the appointment of teacher
                    of mathematics and natural philosophy in the New College, Moseley Street,
                    Manchester. That position he retained up to the time of the removal of the
                    College to York in 1799, when he became a private tutor. In 1794 the number of
                    his pupils at the College, in mathematics, mechanics, algebra, geometry,
                    book-keeping, natural philosophy, and chemistry, was 24. It was in 1792 that he
                    first visited London, which he described as “a surprising place, and well worth
                    one’s while to see once; but the most disagreeable place on earth for one of a
                    contemplative turn to reside in constantly.”</p>
                <p>During his residence at Kendal Dalton had contributed solutions of problems and
                    questions on various topics to the <hi rend="italic">Gentlemarts</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Ladies' Diaries;</hi> but his first separate publication was his
                    <hi rend="italic">Meteorological Observations and Essays,</hi> published
                    September 1793, a result of the study of natural phenomena during upwards of
                    seven years previously. The book contained much original matter, but met
                    nevertheless with only a limited sale, for, having been printed exclusively for
                    the author, it never found its way in any large numbers into the hands of
                    publishers. Another work by Dalton, entitled <hi rend="italic">Elements of
                    English Grammar,</hi> was published in 1801. On October 3, 1794, Dalton became a
                    member of the Manchester Literary and Philosophical Society, before which, on
                    the 31st, he read a communication entitled “Extraordinary Facts relating to the
                    Vision of Colours.” In this paper he gives the earliest account of that ocular
                    peculiarity known as dyschromatopsis, chromato-pseudopsis (false vision of
                    colours), Daltonism, parachromatism, or colour-blindness, and sums up its
                    characteristics as observed in himself and others.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The subject is fully treated of in Dr G.
                    Wilson’s <hi rend="italic">Researches on Colour-Blindness,</hi> 1855.</p></note>
                    When a boy, being present at a review of troops, and hearing those around him
                    expatiating on the gorgeous effect of the military costume, he asked in what the
                    colour of a soldier’s coat differed from that of the grass on which he trod; and
                    it was the derisive laugh and the exclamations of his companions which this
                    question called forth that first made him aware of the defectiveness of his
                    eye-sight. Besides the blue and purple of the spectrum he was able to recognize
                    but one colour, yellow; or, as he states in his paper, “That part of the image
                    which others call red appears to me little more than a shade or defect of light;
                    after that the orange, yellow, and green seem one colour, which descends pretty
                    uniformly from an intense to a rare <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n820/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0820-0785"/> yellow, making what I should call different
                    shades of yellow.”</p>
                <p>On March 1, 1799, Dalton read to the Manchester Society a paper on rain and dew,
                    and the origin of springs, which was subsequently followed by various
                    disquisitions—on heat, the colour of the sky, steam, the auxiliary verbs and
                    participles of the English language, and the reflectibility and refrangibility
                    of light. In May 1800 he was elected to the secretaryship of the society, an
                    office which he held until 1808, when he became vice-president in the place of
                    Dr Roget. In 1817 he became president, and remained so till the time of his
                    death. On July 31, 1801, was read the first of four important essays by Dalton,
                    “On the Constitution of Mixed Gases /’ “On the Force of Steam or Vapour from
                    Water and other Liquids in different Temperatures, both in a Torricellian Vacuum
                    and in Air:” “On Evaporation/’ and “On the Expansion of Gases by Heat.” In the
                    second of these he makes the striking remark,—“There can scarcely be a doubt
                    entertained respecting the reducibility of all elastic fluids, of whatever kind,
                    into liquids; and we ought not to despair of effecting it in low temperatures,
                    and by strong pressures exerted upon the unmixed gases ;” further, he describes
                    experiments to ascertain the tension of aqueous vapour at different points
                    between 32° and 212° Fahr., and concludes, from observations on the behaviour of
                    the vapour of six different fluids, “that the variation of the force of vapour
                    from all liquids is the same for the same variation of temperature, reckoning
                    from vapour of any given force.” In the fourth essay he observes—“I see no
                    sufficient reason why we may not conclude that all elastic fluids under the same
                    pressure expand equally by heat, and that for any given expansion of mercury,
                    the corresponding expansion of air is proportionally something less, the higher
                    the temperature It seems, therefore, that general laws respecting the absolute
                    quantity and the nature of heat are more likely to be derived from elastic
                    fluids than from other substances.” Dalton thus both enunciated the law of the
                    expansion of gases, stated six months later by Gay-Lussac, and indicated the
                    future employment of the air-thermometer.</p>
                <p>But the most important of Dalton’s numerous investigations are those concerned
                    with the atomic theory of chemistry. The subject of chemisty seems to have first
                    occupied his attention about the year 1796. In 1802 he had already arrived at
                    some conception of the law of the multiple combining proportions of the
                    elements, which was afterwards developed by him. Thus, in a paper “On the
                    Proportion of the Several Gases or Elastic Fluids constituting the Atmosphere,”
                    read on the 29 th of October in that year, he says—though, as it happened, his
                    conclusions were based upon the incorrect supposition that the size of the
                    vessels he employed affected the nature of the chemical union of the gases they
                    contained—“The elements of oxygen may combine with a certain portion of nitrous
                    gas, or with twice that portion, but with no intermediate quantity. In the
                    former case <hi rend="italic">nitric</hi> acid is the result, in the latter <hi
                    rend="italic">nitrous</hi> acid.”</p>
                <p>Dr Thomson states <hi rend="italic">{History of Chemistry,</hi> vol. ii.)— “Mr
                    Dalton informed me that the atomic theory first occurred to him during his
                    investigations of olefiant gas and carburetted hydrogen gas.” In 1850, however,
                    in a notice of Wollaston, read before the Glasgow Philosophical Society, he
                    remarks,—“Mr Dalton founded his theory on the analysis of two gases, namely,
                    protoxide and deutoxide of azote The first of these he considered as a com pound
                    of one atom of azote with one atom of oxygen, and the second of one atom of
                    azote united with two atoms of oxygen.” Inasmuch as from the recognition of the
                    law of definite and multiple combining proportions of the elements originated
                    the establishment of that of their relative, Dalton may be said to have received
                    assistance in the foundation of his atomic theory from the researches here
                    alluded to by Thomson; but the latter part of the statement is manifestly
                    erroneous, for the two gases referred to were invariably represented by Dalton
                    as compounds respectively of two atoms and one atom of azote (nitrogen) with a
                    single atom of oxygen. It is doubtless the earlier of Thomson’s observations
                    that is to be regarded as correct, more especially as Dalton himself says, in
                    1810, in his <hi rend="italic">New System of Chemical Philosophy,</hi> with
                    respect to carburetted hydrogen,— “No correct notion of the constitution of the
                    gas about to be described seems to have been formed till the atomic theory was
                    introduced and applied in the investigation. It was in the summer of 1804 that I
                    collected, at various times and in various places, the inflammable gas obtained
                    from ponds.” As a matter of fact, the first germs .of the atomic theory were
                    Dalton’s views of the separate existence of aqueous vapour in the atmosphere,
                    which necessitated the assumption that gases were constituted of independent
                    atoms; indeed they are represented as such, each atom having its distinguishing
                    symbol, in the plate accompanying the paper “On the Constitution of Mixed
                    Gases.” Dalton appears already in 1803 to have pictured to himself the form of
                    atoms, for in a paper “On the Absorption of Gases by Water” we read—“A particle
                    of gas pressing on the surface of water is analogous to a single shot pressing
                    on a square pile of them ;” and five years later, he writes in his <hi
                    rend="italic">New System,—“Whatever,</hi> therefore, may be the shape or figure
                    of the solid atom abstractedly, when surrounded by such an atmosphere [of heat]
                    it must be globular; but as all the globules in any small given volume are
                    subject to the same pressure, they must be equal in bulk, and will, therefore,
                    be arranged in horizontal strata like a pile of shot.” At the end of the paper
                    on “Absorption” just alluded to, Dalton gives the following first table of the
                    relative weights of the ultimate particles of gaseous and other bodies, which
                    was constructed, he tells us, in order to test whether the solubility of gases
                    in water was dependent upon the weight of their particles:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Hydrogen 1</p><p>Azot 4 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Nitrous oxide<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>The figures for nitrous gas (nitric oxide) and nitrousoxi.de Bhould
                            have been 9’7 and 13’9, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> 5’5 + 4’2 and 5 5 +
                            4 2x2.</p></note> 13'7</p><p>Sulphur 144</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Carbone 4'3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Nitric acid 15 2</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ammonia 5'2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sulphuretted hydrogen.. 15 4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Oxygen 5'5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Carbonic acid 15’3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Water 6'5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Alcohol 154</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Phosphorus 7’2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sulphureous acid 19 9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Phosphuretted hydrogen. 8’2</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Sulphuric acid 25’4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Nitrousgas <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> 9’3</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Carburetted hydrogen</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Ether 9'6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>from stagnant water... 6’3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Gaseous oxide of carbone. 9 ’8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Olefiant gas 5’3</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>As this table contains the results of the analyses of olefiant gas and
                    carburetted hydrogen made in the summer of 1804, it must have been completed
                    after that date, and possibly was not added to the paper containing it till
                    shortly before the printing of the latter in November 1805. It was in 1803, as
                    we are informed in the preface to the <hi rend="italic">New System,</hi> that
                    Dalton “was gradually led to those primary Jaws which seem to obtain in regard
                    to heat and to chemical combination;” and in a letter to his brother in that
                    year he writes that he has been fully engaged in all his leisure hours in the
                    pursuit of chemical and philosophical inquiries, “having got into a track that
                    has not been much trod in before.” Dr Bryan Higgins, in a little pamphlet
                    composed about the year <hi rend="italic">It 75,</hi> had treated of “atoms”
                    which united with one another; but the fixity of the constitution of chemical
                    substances had apparently formed no part of his ideas. “The matter of fire,”
                    according to him, “limits the quantity in which aeriform fluids, and bodies
                    containing it, can combine chemically, ’ and it <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n821/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0821-0786"/> is his belief that the forces of atoms measure
                    the attraction of matter, yet he ventures on no deduction as to the comparative
                    numbers of the attracting atoms. Upon these views we find an advance in the
                    writings of William Higgins, who not only held that atoms combined to form
                    molecules of compound bodies, but reasoned that they must unite singly or by
                    twos and threes, there being no intermediate division of atoms; nowhere,
                    however, does he attempt to elevate his conclusions into a general law. Next
                    Richter, and after him Fischer, showed the existence of definite quantitative
                    relations between the constituents of bodies, but for these relations they
                    assigned no cause; and it was reserved for Dalton to give to the world a theory
                    which linked together and reduced to order and simplicity the previously
                    disconnected and unexplained phenomena of chemical combination. Till 1811
                    Dalton, who drew his deductions from his own rough expermental work, was
                    unacquainted with the observations of William Higgins; and although Richter’s
                    determinations may have aided him in the proving of his laws, still, as Dr R. A.
                    Smith has remarked, “they could never have given him fundamental ideas.” Dalton
                    makes the following clear distinction between his own researches with respect to
                    the ultimate constitution of matter and those of other chemists <hi
                    rend="italic">(New System,</hi> pt. i. p. 213, 1808):—</p>
                <p>“In all chemical investigations, it has justly been considered an important
                    object to ascertain the relative <hi rend="italic">weights</hi> of the simples
                    which constitute a compound. But unfortunately the inquiry has terminated here;
                    whereas from the relative weights in the mass, the relative weights of the
                    ultimate particles or atoms of the bodies might have been inferred, from which
                    their number and weight in various other compounds would appear, in order to
                    assist and to guide future investigations, and to correct their results. Now, it
                    is one great object of this work to show the importance and advantage of
                    ascertaining <hi rend="italic">the relatioe weights of the ultimate particles,
                    both of simple and compound bodies, the number of simple elementary particles
                    which constitute one compound particle, and the number of less compound
                    particles which enter into the formation of one more compound particle.</hi></p>
                <p>If there are two bodies, A and B, which are disposed to combine, the following is
                    the order in which the combinations may take place, beginning with the most
                    simple, namely:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1 atom</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>of A +1 atom</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>of B = 1 atom of C binary.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1 atom</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>of A + 2 atoms of B = 1 atom of D temarv.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>2 atoms of A +1 atom</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>of B = 1 atom of E ternary.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1 atom</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>of A + 3 atoms of B = 1 atom of F quaternary’.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell cols="2"><p>3 atoms of A +1 atom</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>of B = 1 atom of G quaternary, &amp;e., &amp;c.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In 1810 appeared the second part of volume i. of the <hi rend="italic">New
                    System,</hi> in which the chemical elements are described. The first part of
                    volume ii. was not published till 1827J it by no means represents the advanced
                    state of chemidal science at that time, and the appendix, giving Dalton’s latest
                    views, is the only portion of it that is of any special interest. A history of
                    the development of the atomic theory since its first promulgation will be found
                    under <hi rend="smallcaps">Chemistry,</hi> vol. v. p. 465. By Dr Thomson, its
                    first advocate, by Wollaston, and by Dr Henry, it was ably supported, and the
                    analyses of Berzelius placed it on a stable footing. “The theory of multiple
                    proportions,” wrote Berzelius, “is a mystery without the atomic hypothesis.”
                    Strange to say, the conclusions of Gay-Lussac with regard to the combining
                    volumes of gases, which afforded the strongest evidence in favour of the atomic
                    theory, were distrusted, and perhaps never fully accepted by Dalton. The
                    tenacity with which he clung to opinions once formed is further exemplified by
                    his unwillingness to recognize chlorine as a chemical element, and his
                    persistent use of the atomic weights first adopted by him, in spite of the later
                    and more trustworthy determinations of other chemists. The memoirs of Dalton
                    read before the Manchester Literary and Philosophical Society were in all 116.
                    In one of these, read in 1814, he lays down the principles of the volumetric
                    method of analysis, af which he is undoubtedly to be regarded as the originator,
                    although its wide practical application is the result of the labours of numerous
                    after-chemists. The earlier of Dalton’s papers are the most important and
                    complete; one of his latest, however, “On a New and Easy Method of Analyzing
                    Sugar,” describes a discovery of much interest, viz., that the volumes of highly
                    hydrated salts when dissolved are equal to those of their volumes of water, the
                    volume of the salt itself disappearing. Before Dalton had become known as the
                    propounder of the atomic theory, he had already attained a considerable
                    reputation by his scientific labours, and in 1804 he was chosen to give a course
                    of lectures on natural philosophy at the Royal Institution in London. Subsequent
                    discourses were delivered by him at the same place in the winter of 1809-10. He
                    was, it would seem, deficient in many of those qualities that go to form an
                    attractive public lecturer. His voice is said to have been harsh, indistinct,
                    and unemphatic, and his manner of dealing with his subject ineffective; he is
                    described, moreover, as an indifferent experimenter, and as “singularly wanting
                    in the language and power of illustration.” An imaginative or brilliant style of
                    diction, it is to be supposed, can scarcely have been at the command of one
                    whose hours of leisure from the routine of tuition were unceasingly devoted to
                    laboratory work, and who eschewed, and even to some extent discouraged, literary
                    pursuits. His library, he was once heard to declare, he could carry on his back,
                    and yet he had not read half the books which constituted it. In the autumn of
                    1805 Dalton went to live in George Street, Manchester, with his friend the Rev.
                    W. J ohns, and with him and his family he continued to reside, in the greatest
                    harmony, for the next twenty-six years. Engaged in his favourite studies, he
                    passed a quiet and almost uneventful life, interrupted only by occasional visits
                    to London and other cities, and by annual excursions to the Lake country. Into
                    society he rarely went, and amusement he had none, with the exception of a game
                    at bowls on Thursday afternoons. In 1810 he was asked by Davy to offer himself
                    as a candidate for the fellowship of the Royal Society, but he declined,
                    possibly from pecuniary considerations. In 1822 he was proposed without his
                    knowledge, was elected, and paid the usual fee. Four years later he received the
                    king’s medal of the society, “for the development of the chemical theory of
                    Definite Proportions usually called the Atomic Theory, and for his labours and
                    discoveries in physical and chemical science.”</p>
                <p>In the summer of 1822, in company with Mr Benjamin Dockray and Mr W. D. Crewdson,
                    Dalton spent a short time at Paris, where he met Ampere, Arago, Berthollet,
                    Biot, Briquet, Cuvier, Fourier, Gay-Lussac, Laplace, Thenard, Vauquelin, and
                    other distinguished men of science. Six years previously he had been made a
                    corresponding member of the Academy of Sciences; and in 1830 he was elected by
                    that body to fill the place of Davy as one of its eight foreign associates.
                    Dalton was present at the first meeting of the British Association, held at York
                    in 1831. On the occasion of the second meeting, at Oxford in 1832, the honorary
                    degree of D.C.L. was conferred upon him. The scarlet hue of his doctor’s gown
                    was to him, he said, “that of nature,” the colour of “green leaves.”</p>
                <p>In June 1833, Lord Grey’s Government conferred upon Dalton an annual pension of
                    £150, which in 1836 was raised to £300. In the former year a subscription list
                    was opened in Manchester to obtain funds for providing that city with a lasting
                    memorial of its great chemist; and the sum of £2000 having been raised, Chantrey
                    was intrusted with the execution of a bust, which was eventually placed in the
                    entrance hall of the Manchester Royal Institution. During his stay in London,
                    whither he had gone in 1834 to sit to the sculptor, Dalton was presented at
                    court, and in the autumn he received from the university of Edinburgh <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n822/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0822-0787"/> the degree of LL.D, lie officiated as
                    vice-president of the chemical section of the British Association at Dublin in
                    1835, and at Bristol in 1836. On the 18th April 1837, he was seized with an
                    attack of paralysis, a disease of which his brother had died in December 1834.
                    In the following year, on the 15th February, he had a second attack, after
                    which, though still able to make experiments, he was manifestly much enfeebled,
                    both physically and mentally, and required constant medical attendance. On May
                    20,1844, he suffered from another fit. On the 26 th of July 1844, he recorded,
                    with trembling hand, his last meteorological observation, and on the morning of
                    the 27th he fell from his bed, and was found lifeless by his attendant. He was
                    publicly buried on the 12th of August at Ard wick cemetery, about a mile and a
                    half from Manchester.</p>
                <p>In person Dalton was robust and muscular, and his countenance was open, and
                    expressive of the earnestness, simplicity, and truth of his character. His
                    height was about 5 feet 7 inches; he stooped slightly; and his gait was stiff
                    and awkward, but rapid. In dress he adhered to, the mode of the Quakers. His
                    manners were singularly free from pedantry and ostentation, and he had a grave,
                    quiet demeanour. Generally he enjoyed excellent health. His medical attendant,
                    finding him once greatly recovered from an attack of catarrh, attributed the
                    improvement to a dose of James’s powder prescribed on the previous day. “I do
                    not well see how that can be,” said Dalton, “as I kept the powder until I could
                    have an opportunity of analyzing it.” Dalton was somewhat silent in general
                    company, but with his familiar friends he would often indulge in active
                    conversation. His letters to his acquaintances evince no small power of
                    observation. On religious topics he appears to have been peculiarly reserved,
                    and his friends found it difficult to gain an idea of his doctrinal views. He
                    “never had time” to get married, he said; but his correspondence, and the
                    testimony of those who knew him, show that he delighted in the society of women
                    of education and refinement; his pinched circumstances in early life were
                    perhaps the chief cause why he remained single. He liked tobacco, and remarked
                    of Davy, “the principal failing in his character as a philosopher is that he
                    does not smoke.” Dalton was careful, though not parsimonious, in his
                    expenditure, and left at his death a small fortune; when occasion required he
                    could show himself remarkably open-handed. Davy wrote of Dalton in 1829:—“He was
                    a very coarse experimenter, and almost always found the results he required,
                    trusting to his head rather than to his hands. Memory and observation were
                    subordinate qualities in his mind; he followed with ardour analogies and
                    inductions; and however his claims to originality may admit of question, I have
                    no doubt that he was one of the most original philosophers of his time, and one
                    of the most ingenious.” Superadded to his natural talents, and “his almost
                    intuitive skill in tracing the relations of material phenomena,” there was in
                    Dalton, to use the words of Professor Sedgwick, “a beautiful moral simplicity
                    and singleness of heart, which made him go on steadily in the way he saw before
                    him, without turning to the right hand or to the left, and taught him to do
                    homage to no authority before that of truth.”</p>
                <p>Henry, <hi rend="italic">Life of Dalton,</hi> Cavendish Society, 1854; Robert
                    Augus Smith, <hi rend="italic">Memoir of John Dalton and History of the Atomic
                    Theory,</hi> 1856. A list of Dalton’s papers and other publications is given on
                    pp. 253-63 of the latter work. See also Roscoe, “On Dalton’s First Table of
                    Atomic Weights,” in <hi rend="italic">Nature,</hi> Nov. 19, 1874. (F.H.B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
