<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0860-0825-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DARIUS I (9th edition, volume 6, page 825)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109953">Scythians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1938968">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:818281">Aryanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qb9vd72">Scythians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k50h">Zoroastrianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n860/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DARIUS I</label>., the son of Hystaspes, was the true
                    consolidator of the Persian empire. His administrative ability founded a new
                    type of government, and organized the crude mass of conquered states bequeathed
                    him by his predecessors. His military talents, though considerable, have been
                    thrown into the shade by his legislative and financial ones. The originator of
                    imperial centralization and unity, the inventor of a well-regulated system of
                    taxation, and the introducer of an alphabetic system of writing, he found a
                    half-dissolved amalgamation of discordant populations on his accession, and left
                    a firmly-welded empire at his death.</p>
                <p>In the great inscription on the rock of Behistun, where he has recorded his
                    struggles and victories, Darius traces his descent from Achaemenes, through four
                    ancestors all kings like himself. He seems to have stood next to the line of
                    Cyrus in succession to the throne; and Cyrus, when setting out on his campaign
                    against the Massagetae, already suspected him of aiming at the crown. He
                    accompanied Cambyses to Egypt, but was recalled by his father to the capital at
                    the time the conspiracy was being formed against the Magian usurper Gomates, who
                    professed to be Bardes (Smerdis in Herodotus), the brother of Cambyses. With six
                    other Persian nobles Darius succeeded in overthrowing the Magian usurpation, and
                    pursued the pseudo-Smerdis to Sikhyuvatis, a fortress in Nisaea, where he was
                    put to death, April 2, 521 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> The friends of Gomates
                    were massacred, the yearly festival of the Magophonia instituted, and the
                    religion of Zoroaster, which had been suppressed in favour of the idolatrous
                    worship of the Turanian (as opposed to the Aryan) Medes, was solemnly restored.
                    Darius, now twenty-eight years old, was proclaimed king.</p>
                <p>The first six years of his reign were occupied in suppressing the revolts which
                    broke out throughout the empire, occasioned partly, perhaps, by the zeal with
                    which the new monarch maintained the Zoroastrian faith, and which led him to
                    look with special favour on the monotheistic Jews. Pretender after pretender
                    appeared—Atrines and afterwards Martes, in Susiania; Nidintabel, who called
                    himself Nebuchadrezzar son of Nabonidus, in Babylonia; Phraortes, who claimed to
                    be Xathrites son of Cyaxares, in Media and Parthia; Tritantachmes, in Sagartia;
                    Phraates, in Margiana; (Eosdates, a second pseudo-Smerdis, in Persia itself; and
                    an Armenian, Aracus, in Babylon; but they were all successively crushed by
                    Darius or his generals. The most serious of these revolts were those in Media
                    and Babylonia, and it was probably during the first Babylonian revolt that the
                    long siege of Babylon mentioned by Herodotus took place, resulting in the
                    attempted plunder of the image of Bel (518 B.c.) This siege may have introduced
                    the otherwise unknown “Darius the Mede” into the book of Daniel (see article on
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Daniel).</hi> The Median Phraortes, who probably belonged
                    to the Turanian part of the population, proved more than a match for three
                    generals of Darius, and the king had to leave Babylon, which he had just
                    succeeded in capturing, and take the field in person, before the war was
                    finished by the seizure and crucifixion of Phraortes at Ecbatana. The second
                    capture of Babylon was followed by the execution of the Behistun inscription,
                    515 B.C., in which Darius declares that he had translated “the Ancient Book,”
                    “the Text of the Divine Law <hi rend="italic">(Avesta)</hi> and a Commentary of
                    the Divine Law and the Prayer (ZencZ)” from Bactrian into the old Persian, and
                    had restored it to the nations of the empire (see Oppert’s translation of the
                    Median version of the Behistun inscription in <hi rend="italic">Records of the
                    Past,</hi> vol. vii.) It must have been for the sake of this translation that
                    the Assyrian cuneiform syllabary was simplified into an alphabet of forty
                    characters. A revolt of Iskunka, a chief of the Sacae, was suppressed shortly
                    after the inscription was engraved. Before this, Oroetes, governor of Sardis,
                    who had murdered Polycrates of Samos, and aimed at making himself independent,
                    had been put to death, as well as Aryandes, satrap of Egypt, who had issued a
                    silver coinage of his own.</p>
                <p>Darius now set about consolidating and organizing hie empire. An elaborate
                    bureaucratic system was instituted, and the empire divided into a varying number
                    of provinces, each under a governor or satrap <hi rend="italic"
                    >(khshatrapdva),</hi> appointed by the king for au indefinite time, and
                    responsible for a fixed tribute. The power of the satrap was checked by “royal
                    clerks,” who sent annual reports of the satrap and his actions to the king, by
                    retaining the old chiefs or kings of the province by the side of the satrap
                    wherever possible, and by sending members of the royal family to the satrapies.
                    Except in the border satrapies, the military power was intrusted to a separate
                    officer, and it was only in the border provinces, accordingly, that a revolt was
                    to be feared. It is said that the chief fortresses had each an independent
                    commander, while in Persia proper “royal judges” went on circuit. The satrap
                    represented the king, and had the power of life and death. The money tribute,
                    raised probably by a land-tax, amounted, according to Mr Grote’s calculation, to
                    £4,254,000,—7740 talents (£2,964,000) being paid in silver, and the rest in
                    gold. The Indian satrapy contributed by far the most, and Persia proper paid
                    nothing. Part of tho tribute was paid in kind, Babylonia and Assyria furnishing
                    one-third. There were, besides, water-rates, and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n861/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0861-0826"/> taxes for the use of such crown property as
                    fisheries and the like, but the amount to be paid to the imperial treasury was
                    in all cases fixed. It was otherwise, however, with the exactions the satraps
                    were allowed to make on their own account, and which must have pressed heavily
                    on the people. The tribute enabled Darius to issue a coinage of extreme purity,
                    and his gold darics were worth about 22s. of our money. An incised bar was the
                    imperial stamp. The satrapies were connected with one another by highroads and
                    posting-stations, at which relays of horses were kept for the royal
                    messengers.</p>
                <p>After building a palace at Susa, the new capital of the empire, and founding the
                    <hi rend="italic">Cheld Minar</hi> at Persepolis, Darius overran the Punjaub,
                    and had the Indus navigated by a naval expedition under Scylax of Caryanda.
                    Under the guidance of Democedes, a physician of Crotona, the Greek seas were
                    also explored as far as Magna Graecia, and the northern frontier was
                    strengthened by a campaign against the Scythians. Ariamnes of Cappadocia first
                    examined the northern shores of the Black Sea, after which Darius, with 600
                    ships and the aid of the Asiatic Greeks, crossed the Bosphorus by a bridge
                    constructed by the Greek Mandrocles, conquered the Getae, and threw a bridge of
                    boats across the Danube. Leaving the defence of the bridge to the Greeks, he
                    pursued the Scythians as far as the 50th parallel, burning Gelonus (perhaps the
                    modern Voronej), and recrossed the bridge in safety, thanks to the fidelity of
                    Histiaeus of Miletus. Megabazus, or Megabyzus, next reduced Thrace and made
                    Amyntas of Macedon tributary (506). In the following year Otanes subjugated
                    Byzantium, Chalcedon, Antandros, Lemnos, and Imbros.</p>
                <p>In 500 B.c. the Ionic revolt broke out. The allies of the Ionians from Athens and
                    Eretria landed in Asia Minor and burnt Sardis, an event which led the Greeks of
                    the Hellespont, as well as the Carians and the Cyprians, to join the
                    insurrection. The revolt was crushed in 495 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> by
                    the battle of Lade and the sack of Miletus; aud a terrible punishment was taken
                    upon the Greek cities on the coasts and islands of the Aegean. Miltiades, the
                    tyrant of the Chersonese, escaped with difficulty to Athens, while Darius
                    prepared to avenge the burning of Sardis. His son-in-law, Mardonius, was
                    accordingly sent against Athens and Eretria with a powerful force. But after
                    establishing democracies in the place of tyrants in various Greek cities, and
                    capturing Thasos and its gold mines, Mardonius lost 300 ships and more thau
                    20,000 men in a storm off Mount Athos, and, being further surprized by the
                    Thracian Bryges, returned to Asia Minor. Two years afterwards (490 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> Darius sent another expedition under Datis, which
                    destroyed Eretria, but was ingloriously defeated at Marathon by the Athenians
                    under Miltiades. Darius now made preparations for an attack upon a scale which
                    the Greeks would have found it hardly possible to withstand while an able prince
                    like Darius was at the head of the empire; but in the fourth year of the
                    preparations (487 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.),</hi> just before everything was
                    ready, Egypt broke out into revolt. Before the revolt could be put down Darius
                    died, 486 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> in the sixty-third year of his age
                    according to Herodotus, or the seventy-second according to Ctesias, who,
                    however, curtails his reign by three years. Darius had already nominated Xerxes,
                    his son by Atossa, the daughter of Cyrus, as his successor,—his eldest son,
                    Artobazanes, whose mother was a daughter of Gobryas, being set aside as born
                    before his father was king.</p>
                <p>Long before his death Darius had excavated a richlyornamented tomb with four
                    pillars and other sculptures out of the rocks of Naksh-i-Rustam, about four
                    miles from Persepolis. In an inscription on the facade of the tomb he enumerates
                    28 different countries or satrapies, including India and “the Scythians beyond
                    the sea,” over which he bore sway. His name D&amp;ryavush is rendered</p>
                <p>“worker” or “organizer,” by Herodotus; but the true meaning of the word is rather
                    “the maintainer,” from <hi rend="italic">darj</hi> (Sanskrit, <hi rend="italic"
                    >dhri,</hi> “conservare ”). <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. h. s.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
