<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-9149-0276-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANUBIS (7th edition, volume 3, page 276)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk07518">Face</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m32nc36">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26c70">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="fast:919522">Face</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925173">Fire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:954023">Heating</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193099149?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANUBIS</label>, a symbolical deity of the Egyptians, was
                    regarded as the faithful companion of Osiris and of Isis. Temples and priests
                    were consecrated to him, and lus image was borne in all religious ceremonies.
                    Cynopohs&gt; <pb break="no" facs="nls:193099162?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0703-9162-0277"/> situated in the Lower Thebais, was built in
                    honour of 'Anubis. The temple in which he was worshipped no longer exists. The
                    priests celebrated his festivals there with great pomp, and consecrated the dog
                    to him as his living representation. “Anubis,” says Strabo, “is the city of
                    dogs, the capital of the Cynopolitan prefecture. These animals are fed there on
                    sacred aliments, and religion has decreed them a worship.” An event, however,
                    related by Plutarch, brought them into considerable discredit with the people.
                    Cambyses having slain the god Apis, and thrown his body into a field, all
                    animals respected it except the dogs, which alone ate of his flesh. This impiety
                    diminished the popular veneration for them.</p>
                <p>Cynopolis was not the only city which burned incense on the altars of Anubis. He
                    had chapels in almost all the temples. On solemnities, his image always
                    accompanied those of Isis and Osiris. Rome having adopted the ceremonies of
                    Egypt, the emperor Commodus, to celebrate the Isiac feasts, shaved his head, and
                    himself carried the god Anubis. The statue of this god was either of massive
                    gold or gilt, as well as the attributes that accompanied him. Anubis signifies
                    <hi rend="italic">gilded.</hi> The denomination was mysterious; and the Egyptian
                    priests, it would seem, had not given it without reason.</p>
                <p>The signification of this emblematical deity is thus explained by Plutarch: “The
                    circle which touchesand separates the two hemispheres, and which is the cause of
                    this division, receiving the name of <hi rend="italic">horizon,</hi> is called
                    <hi rend="italic">Anubis.</hi> He is represented under the form of a dog,
                    because that animal watches day and night.” St Clemens of Alexandria, who was
                    well informed in the mystic theology of the Egyptians, favours this explication.
                    The two dogs, says he (the two Anubis), are the symbols of two hemispheres which
                    environ the terrestrial globe. He adds in another place,—others pretend that
                    these animals, the faithful guardians of men, indicate the tropics, which guard
                    the sun on the south and on the north like porters.</p>
                <p>According to the former of these interpretations the priests, regarding Anubis as
                    the horizon, gilded his statue, to mark that this circle, receiving the first
                    rays of the sun, appears sparkling with brightness on his rising, and that at
                    his setting he reflects his last rays upon the earth. They said, in their sacred
                    fables, that Anubis was the son of Osiris, but illegitimate. In fact, he only
                    gives to the earth a borrowed light, and cannot be esteemed, like Horus, as the
                    father of the day, or as the legitimate offspring of Osiris. It may be added,
                    that the visible horizon, turning with the sun, is his inseparable
                    companion.</p>
                <p>In the latter of these explications, where Anubis represents the tropics, he is
                    also the faithful guardian of Isis and Osiris. In fact, the course of the sun
                    and of the moon is contained between the circles wherein the solstices are
                    performed. They neither deviate to the right nor left. These limits, assigned by
                    the Author of nature, might, therefore, in hieroglyphic language, be represented
                    by a divinity with the head of a dog, who seemed to oppose the passage on the
                    side of the two poles. The other opinion, notwithstanding, seems more natural,
                    and to be more analogous to the ideas of the priests.</p>
                <p>Upon the whole, it is reasonable to imagine that Anubis at first was only a
                    symbolical image, invented by astronomers to give a sensible expression of their
                    discoveries; that afterwards the people, accustomed to see it in their temples,
                    which were the depositories of science, adored it as a deity; and that the
                    priests favoured their ignorance by connecting it with their religion. The
                    worship of Anubis being introduced, that of the dog became his emblem. . Almost
                    all the gods of· the Gentiles have originated i∏ this manner. <hi
                    rend="subscript"> l</hi><hi rend="italic">ΑN</hi> ∖ IL, in smithery, and other
                    manufactures of the malleable metals, is an instrument on vvhich substances are
                    laid for the purpose of being hammered.</p>
                <p>For some purposes anvils are made of cast iron; but when the face of the anvil is
                    required to possess great hardness, or a bright surface, it is made of wrought
                    iron and faced with steel. The core or body of wrought iron anvils is prepared
                    at the forge, where malleable iron is first formed into bars, or into masses for
                    any particular purpose. The body of the anvil is formed by welding a number ot
                    smaller masses together under the forge-hammer. These are rude blocks of
                    different sizes, according to the size of the anvil. Smaller masses are also
                    furnished in this way, which the anvil-maker occasionally welds to the large
                    blocks, for giving to the anvil any particular form.</p>
                <p>The fire-place or hearth of the anvil-maker’s forge is similar to the common
                    smith’s forge. His bellows are not double, like the latter. His fuel is cork,
                    which produces a great heat without much flame. Adjacent to the hearth is a
                    crane, which, turning upon a pivot, brings the heated masses of iron from the
                    fire to the anvil. The latter is a large mass of cast metal, about 18 inches
                    square on the face, and about a foot from the ground. When the core of the anvil
                    to be formed is heated, the first thing is to make three square holes, one in
                    the bottom, and one at each end of the anvil. These holes are about 11- inch
                    long, 1 inch broad, and about 2 inches deep. They are for the purpose of
                    receiving a bar of iron, which is connected with the crane by which the anvil is
                    held in the fire, and by which it is turned and guided while forming with the
                    hammers.</p>
                <p>The common smith’s anvil is generally made of seven pieces, namely, the core or
                    body; the four corners, for the purpose of enlarging its base; the projecting
                    end, which contains a square hole, for the reception of a set, or chisel, to cut
                    oft’ pieces of iron; and the seventh piece is the beak, or conical end, used for
                    turning pieces of iron into a circular form, welding hoops, &amp;c. These pieces
                    are each separately welded to the core, and hammered so as to form a regular
                    -surface with the whole. When large pieces are required to be welded to the
                    core, one fire is not sufficient to heat both at the same time. In this case two
                    hearthš are employed. The core and the piece are both raised to a welding heat.
                    The piece being put into its place, is hammered by a quick succession of blows
                    till it adheres. The whole is again heated and hammered till the due form is
                    obtained. The hammering is performed by a number of men at the same time, each
                    using a large swing-hammer. The blows follow each other in regular succession,
                    great experience and care being required to prevent the hammers from coming in
                    contact with each other.</p>
                <p>When the anvil has received its due form, it now requires to be faced with steel.
                    This is performed by first preparing the steel face to the size of the anvil.
                    The anvil is then heated to a strong welding heat in one fire, while the steel
                    facing is heated in another, but not. so hot as the iron. The anvil is now
                    brought out and placed in a proper position, and the facing is brought to it.
                    The surfaces which are to be brought together are brushed, and the facing is
                    then laid on and hammered as rapidly as possible, till it is closely united. The
                    whole is finished by repeated heating-and hammering.</p>
                <p>The next process iş that of hardening the anvil. This consists in heating the
                    face, in particular, to a full red heat, and quenching it in cold water. When a
                    stream of water can be employed it is better. Where this cannot be had, the mass
                    of water should be great, and the anvil moved about as quick as possible. The
                    facing should be laid on as thin as it can be firmly welded; when it is too
                    thick it is apt to crack in the hardening. τ <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193099175?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-9175-0278"/> After
                    hardening, the face is ground till it is perfectly even, and the edges made
                    sharp or round, as may be required. When the anvil is required for planishing
                    metals, it is polished with emery, and afterwards with crocus.</p>
                <p>The smith’s anvil is generally placed loose upon a wooden block, the root-end of
                    an oak-tree being preferred. The anvils used in cutlery and for files are
                    fastened into a large block of stone, which is doubtless better than having the
                    anvil loose upon a small block. The more firmly the anvil is connected with the
                    earth and the substance it stands upon, the greater will be the effect of the
                    blow of the hammer.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
