<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-1827-0482-10" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARGYLESHIRE or Argyllshire (7th edition, volume 3, page
                    482)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j67915v">Handicraft</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950959">Handicraft</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039481">Norwegians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193101827?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARGYLESHIRE or <hi rend="smallcaps">Argyllshire</hi></label>,
                    an extensive county in the west of Scotland, is usually described under two
                    great divisions,—the mainland, and" such of the Western Islands as-are
                    politically attached to it. It is of the former only that we propose to give
                    some account at present, referring to the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Hebrides</hi> for the islands noted below,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>ose of the first rate are Islay, Mull, and Jura; of the
                    second, Gigha and Cara, Colonsay, Lismore, Tyree, Coll, Ulva and . + <hi
                    rend="superscript"> m</hi> θ <hi rend="superscript"> l</hi> L Kerreray Luing,
                    Seil or Saoil; and of the third, Scarba, Lunga, Shuna, Ičolmkill or Iona,
                    Kisdale, Inch Kenneth, Staflä, Monk, Rum, and Cannay. <hi rend="superscript">
                    b</hi></p></note> which form a part of this comity.</p>
                <p>The mainland of Argyleshire, situate between 55° 21' and 57° north latitude, and
                    between l <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi> 22' and 3° 25' of longitude west from
                    Edinburgh, is bounded on the north by Inverness-shire, on the east by the
                    counties of Perth and Dumbarton, on the south by the Irish Sea, and on the west
                    by the Atlantic Ocean; the Frith of Clyde, which separates it from the shire of
                    Renfrew, forming its boundary on the south-east. Its greatest length, from the
                    Mull of Kintyre on the south to the point of Ardnamur-chan on the north, is. 115
                    miles; its breadth above 68; and from the windings of the numerous bays and
                    creeks with which the land is everywhere, indented, it is supposed<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193101840?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-1840-0483"/> to have more
                    than 600 miles of sea-coast. The mainland of Argyleshire is divided into 35
                    parishes, nine of which are united, reducing the number to 26: two in part
                    belong to Inverness-shire, and only one is altogether inland. The extent of this
                    part of the county is equal to about one thirteenth part of the whole of
                    Scotland, the land comprehending 2200 square miles, and the lakes 60.</p>
                <p>The general features of the country are varied and striking in a high degree,
                    consisting of lofty mountains, deep glens, and inlets of the sea entering far
                    into the land. Towards the northern parts it assumes the wild and savage
                    grandeur so peculiarly eharaeteristie of the Highlands of Scotland. Mountains
                    piled on mountains in magnificent disorder present a sublime, but, in an
                    agricultural point of view, a very unpromising prospect; yet in the most barren
                    districts the hills supply pasture for sheep in considerable numbers; and on the
                    valleys and low grounds are raised oats, bere or big, and potatoes, part of
                    which latter produce is exported. Some qf the mountains are among the loftiest
                    in Scotland, particularly Ben Cruachan, which rises 3390 feet above the level of
                    the sea; and on the borders towards the counties of Perth and Dumbarton, the
                    mountains contiguous to Ben Lomond are little inferior to it in height. The
                    inlets of the sea are very numerous. Amongst others are Loeh Fine, Loeh Etive,
                    Loch Welford, Loeh Linnhe, Loch Leven, &amp;c. The district of Kintyre enters
                    into the north channel, and is almost divided from the mainland at the narrow
                    isthmus of Tarbat. The district of Cowal is also nearly peninsulated by Loch
                    Long on the one side and Loch Fine on the other. The interior parts of the
                    county are interspersed with a great number of small fresh-water lakes. A
                    barrenness of soil and scanty vegetation prevail chiefly on the summits of the
                    higher mountains, which exhibit great masses of stratified rocks or groups in a
                    columnar form. Some of the glens are covered with large fragments of these which
                    have been precipitated from the impending cliffs, and consequently afford but
                    scanty pasturage; however, the greater part of them yield good grass. Others of
                    them exhibit miles of fertility, verdure, and cultivation, particularly
                    Glendarual, the most prolific valley of the county. Formerly Argyleshire was
                    interspersed with numerous woods, which, uniting with the lofty mountains,
                    formed the most romantic scenery. But these have been almost all cut down or
                    destroyed to make way for the introduction of sheep; and planting has not,
                    except in a few instances, been carried to any considerable extent. The late
                    duke of Argyle planted very extensively in the neighbourhood of 1nverary, and
                    several other gentlemen have followed his example; nevertheless, one of the most
                    striking features in the aspect of the county is its want of wood. Remains of
                    ancient forests are still very extensive in various places; and these consist
                    chiefly of oaks, ashes, pines, and birches. The level of the country towards the
                    southern parts descends the nearest to an equality with that of the sea. The
                    elevation of the country is highest towards the interior parts of the counties
                    of Perth and Inverness.</p>
                <p>ſhe fallow-deer, which formerly abounded in the woods and on the mountains, are
                    now only to be seen in the preserves of a few gentlemen; but forest deer are
                    still found in considerable numbers in Glenetive and in Mull. Roes are pretty
                    numerous in the northern parts of the county, and moor game are also found in
                    abundance. The blackcattle, which in former times ran wild on the mountains, are
                    now entirely confined to the low grounds, where their young arc fed in winter by
                    the proprietors. Fish are not at all so abundant as is generally supposed; for
                    although white fish are taken in considerable numbers, particularly in the
                    neighbourhood of Campbeltown, still the quantity is small compared with what is
                    taken on other parts of the Seotish eoast; and Loeh Fine is the only inlet of
                    the sea distinguished for its herring-fishery. There are valuable metals to be
                    found in this county, sueh as copper, lead, and iron; and also some minerals,
                    particularly strontian.</p>
                <p>The only crops cultivated to any extent in the mainland of Argyleshire are bere
                    or big, oats, and potatoes. Wheat is raised near Campbeltown, and in other parts
                    of Kintyre; but the quantity is very small, the climate being too wet and
                    variable for its successful cultivation. But the management of potatoes in this
                    district is equal to that of any other part of Scotland, and great quantities
                    are annually exported from it. Turnips and sown grasses are pretty common in the
                    southern, and, among the larger farmers, in the northern districts. Clovers are
                    also frequent; but notwithstanding that these and other green crops are better
                    adapted to the elimate than grain, they have not yet come into extensive
                    culture. The principal object in the culture of big is the supply of the
                    distilleries. The great body of the inhabitants live almost exclusively on
                    oatmeal and potatoes, of the former of which they have been in the practice of
                    importing about 20,000 bolls (of 140 lbs.) annually. The progress of agriculture
                    in this county has been greatly retarded, both by the nature of the land and the
                    political condition of the people. .Out of 1,408,000 aeres, only 125,000 are
                    arable; and these are scattered unconnected over a broad and broken surface, on
                    the sides of bills, or in valleys between rocky eminences, particularly in the
                    northern districts. Another obstacle to improvement will be found in the remains
                    of the feudal system. This county is peopled with a few great proprietors, and a
                    numerous small tenantry, servile in their habits to their superiors, ignorant
                    and indolent in their character, and in their domestic economy presenting all
                    the repulsive features of poverty. Of the valued rent, taken in 1751, of the
                    mainland, with four small islands, amounting to L.9924. 8s. Id., almost a fourth
                    belongs to two proprietors. This valuation was considered to be equal to the
                    half of the real rent at that period, after deducting all public burdens; but in
                    1798, when the agricultural survey of the county was published, the gross rental
                    had risen to L.89,000, collected from upwards of 2700 tenants; and in 1811 the
                    rent of the whole county, of which the islands might produce about a fifth,
                    amounted to L.192,073. 14s. 2d. for the lands, and for the houses to L.5208.
                    18s. 10d. But the most important obstacles to agricultural improvement arc
                    inefficient draining, the want of leases, the high rack-rents that are generally
                    exacted, and the system of letting farms to small tenants, who possess the grass
                    in common, and have “rig about” of the arable land, which they exchange with
                    each other every second year. But Kintyre must be an exception from the remarks
                    upon the county in general. In that district agriculture is more encouraged, and
                    consequently more prosperous. Indeed it cannot be denied that the county
                    throughout has been considerably improved, but certainly not to the extent of
                    its resources; and it is to be hoped that the frequent transference of landed
                    property which has taken place within the last fifty years, and the example and
                    encouragement of the late duke of Argyle, the greatest landholder in it, cannot
                    fail to extend a more beneficial system of rural economy. It may be remarked,
                    that of late years considerable numbers of the inhabitants, and those not of the
                    poorest class, have emigrated to America.</p>
                <p>Cattle were long the principal source of the revenue C of the landholders and
                    tenantry of Argyleshire; and the si native breed, which has been improved of
                    late by more careful, treatment, is well known to be equal, if not supe <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193101853?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-1853-0484"/>
                    rior, to any other race of cattle in the kingdom. Their number in 1798 was
                    computed at upwards of 50,000, and they are understood to have increased
                    considerably since; for though they are now excluded from the more elevated
                    tracts, which are better occupied by sheep, the improved management of the lower
                    grounds, small as it is compared with what it might be, has, upon the whole,
                    enlarged the means of their subsistence. These cattle are sent from the country
                    in a store condition, commonly when about three years old, and fatted on the
                    pastures of the south, the greater number for the consumption of England. Dairy
                    husbandry is practised to some extent in the southern parts of Kintyre, where
                    there is a large proportion of arable land; but it cannot be extended to the
                    inland and more mountainous districts of the county.</p>
                <p>Until the middle of last century, the only sheep in Argyleshire were of the small
                    native race, and their number was inconsiderable; but these have entirely
                    disappeared, and we do not know that there is a single animal of the breed to be
                    found, except in the most distant islands of the Hebrides. The black-faced is
                    the species that is now almost universally reared. About the period above
                    referred to, coarse-woolled heath sheep were introduced into the higher and more
                    barren districts; and as it was soon discovered that the scanty herbage of these
                    gloomy mountains could be converted into a much greater quantity of mutton than
                    of beef, besides yielding a valuable article of manufacture, these hardy animals
                    soon spread over extensive regions, upon which cattle could barely subsist in
                    the summer months; and the income of the landed proprietors and of the public
                    was accordingly augmented in proportion. At present probably two fifths of the
                    whole rent of land paid in the county arises from the produce of the sheep-farm.
                    Notwithstanding the outcry of ignorance, and the more mischievous speculations
                    of mistaken philanthropy, the introduction of this species of live stock, now
                    increased to about 300,000, has not had the effect of diminishing the population
                    of Argyleshire.</p>
                <p>In this division of the county there is a considerable extent of natural
                    coppice-wood, probably near 40,000 acres, which are cut periodically, commonly
                    every 19 or 20 years, and at one time the returns were at the rate of about 20s.
                    per acre annually; but the value of this article has of late greatly diminished.
                    Very extensive plantations have been formed by the duke of Argyle and other
                    proprietors. Those of his Grace are reckoned to contain 2,000,000 of trees,
                    worth 4s. each, amounting to the enormous sum of L.400,000.</p>
                <p>The great extent of sea-coast which Argyleshire possesses, and the nature of the
                    county, penetrated as it is in almost every direction by arms of the sea, and
                    traversed by extensive lakes, afford ample facilities for the prosecution of
                    fisheries; but, either from the unproductiveness of the waters, or the want of
                    vigour and perseverance in the fishermen, with the exception of those of Loch
                    Fine, the fisheries have neither been extensive nor lucrative. The white-fishing
                    especially has been neglected. Enterprising fishermen might certainly greatly
                    increase, the produce in this branch, which would be of essential benefit to the
                    inhabitants of so ungenial a territory. In Loch Fine alone, in the years 1794
                    and 1795, the herrings caught were computed to be worth more than L.89,000
                    (Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Sur-</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> ve</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">lh</hi> 1798); but the fisheries there have of late years greatly
                    fallen off.</p>
                <p>The mainland of Argyleshĩre is principally composed of primitive rocks, which in
                    some quarters are skirted and intermixed with those of the transition class,
                    while floetz rocks occur very sparingly. No volcanic rocks have hitherto been
                    met with in the mainland of Argyleshire, but those of an alluvial nature abound
                    everywhere. The primitive and transition rocks are stratified, and the general
                    direction of the strata is from north-east to south-west. The primitive rocks
                    are granite, gneiss, mica slate, clay slate, limestone, porphyry, sienite, trap,
                    and quartz rocķ. The transition rocks are greywacke, greywacke slate, clay
                    slate, trap, and quartz; and the floetz rocks are red sandstone, conglomerate,
                    and rocks of the coal formation. The islands off the coast of Argyleshire afford
                    highly· interesting examples of rocks of the different classes: Isla and Jura,
                    of the primitive and transition rocks; Mul], of floetz and primitive rocks;
                    Staffa, Rum, and Canny, of floetz rocks; and Coll, Tyree, and Iona, of primitive
                    rocks.</p>
                <p>Coal has been wrought for many years near Campbelltown in Kintyre, and lead at
                    Strontian in Sunart; and besides the slate quarries of Easđale, an island
                    belonging to this county, others have been opened at Ballachelish in Appin, and
                    on the islands of Belnahua, Luing, Seil, and Kerrara.</p>
                <p>Manufactures have made little progress in this district, and no attempts to
                    establish them upon a large scale have yet been successful. Mr Dale endeavoured
                    to extend to it some branches of the cotton manufacture, which failed, it is
                    said, from want of water-carriage; but a number of weavers in Campbeltown and
                    its neighbourhood have been employed for some time in working cottons from
                    Glasgow. The late duke of Argyle established a woollen manufactory near
                    Inverary, which languished for some time, and was finally abandoned many years
                    ago. There is a bleachfield in Kintyrc, a tannery at Campbeltown, and another at
                    Oban, which, however, has not been wrought for several years; and there are
                    iron-works in Upper Lorn, belonging to an English company, who bring the ore
                    thither chiefly for the sake of the charcoal which the woods afford. The
                    manufacture of kelp from sea-weed, to the extent of 800 tons annually, is none
                    of the least profitable branches of industry; and that of their scanty crops of
                    grain into ardent spirits, certainly the most pernicious.</p>
                <p>The commerce of Argyleshire is also very limited, its &lt; exports consisting
                    chiefly of raw produce: sheep, cattle, and fish, format least two thirds of the
                    whole; and slates, oak bark, and kelp, constitute nearly the remainder. The
                    imports are almost confined to the supply of necessaries, principally oatmeal
                    and flour, and such articles of luxury as habit has rendered scarcely less
                    indispensable.</p>
                <p>Thus, notwithstanding its natural advantages, this county is far from being
                    characteristic either of wealth or industry. It was expected that the Crinan
                    Canal, which was cut across the peninsula of Kintyre, at an expense of
                    L.140,000, shortening the voyage from the West Highland and Hebridean ports to
                    the river Clyde about 200 miles, would cause an influx of wealth to the county;
                    but neither it nor the Caledonian Canal, which gives access from the county to
                    the German Ocean, has answered the expectations of the projectors, or
                    contributed in any eminent degree to the prosperity of Argyleshire. Indeed, but
                    for steam navigation, both would have been nearly useless; and even with that
                    accessory, there is no adequate return for the vast sums expended on them.</p>
                <p>This county still contains many ancient monuments,! which display the warlike
                    spirit of its former inhabitants. In the course of the eighth and ninth
                    centuries it was conquered, along with the neighbouring isles, by the Danes and
                    Norwegians. For five or six centuries it continued under the dominion of Norway,
                    and during that period was under the direct administration of feudal chieftains,
                    generally of Norwegian extraction, who each maintained an almost independent
                    government. Along with the Hebridean isles, all the western parts óf Argyle
                    became the conquest of the Scotish monarchs in the 14th century. Some time
                    after, Macdonald, the representative of <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193101866?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-1866-0485"/> this region,
                    obtained leave from the Scotish crown to hold his possessions as a feudatory to
                    that kingdom; but, from his turbulent spirit, he and his family were engaged in
                    perpetual rebellions, which were at last punished by the forfeiture of their
                    estates, which, along with their titles, were bestowed on the Campbells; and
                    these have ever since retained them in peace and loyalty, beloved and honoured
                    by their country. The county of Argyle gives the title of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Duke</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Earl</hi> to the chief of this family, who
                    likewise enjoys several other important posts under the crown. His vassals are
                    so numerous, that in former times he could on occasion bring 3000 or 4000
                    fighting men into the field. This clan is numerous in Argyleshire, and there are
                    a great number of castles and seats belonging to gentlemen who hold of the duke,
                    and boast themselves descended from his family.</p>
                <p>- The county sends one member to parliament; it is also the seat of a provincial
                    synod. It contains two royal boroughs and 49 parishes.</p>
                <p>The population of the whole county, as taken under the last population acts of
                    1811 and 1821, will be seen from the following tables.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="10" role="data" rows="1"><p>1811.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>DISTRICTS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>OCCUPATIONS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>PERSONS.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Inhabited.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>By how many Families
                            occupied.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Building and Uninhabited.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in
                            Agriculture.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in Trade,
                            Manufactures, or Handicraft.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>All other Families not comprised in
                            the two preceding classes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Argyle .</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2702</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3720</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>76</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1568</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>545</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1607</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7729</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7908</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15637</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cowal</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1212</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1276</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>44</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>789</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>329</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>158</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3318</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3569</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6887</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Islay</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2636</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2687</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1162</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1284</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>615</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>788</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6814</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7348</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>14162</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Kintyre</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2959</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3733</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>62</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1074</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>994</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1735</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8404</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9882</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>18286</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Lorn</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2721</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2845</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>353</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1064</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>752</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1029</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>6462</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7317</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>13779</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mull</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3010</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3107</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>24</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2642</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>254</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>211</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7948</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8886</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16834</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15240</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>17368</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1721</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8421 </p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3419</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5528</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40675</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>44910</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>85585</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="10" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>DISTRICTS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>HOUSES.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>OCCUPATIONS.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>PERSONS.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Inhabited.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>By how many Families
                            occupied.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Building and uninhabited.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Families chiefly employed in
                            Agriculture.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>F <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                            amilies chiefly employed in Trade, Manufactures, or
                            Handicraft.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>All other Families not comprised in
                            the two preceding classes.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Males.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Females.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total of Persons.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Argyle</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2966</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3343</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>43</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1887</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>504</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>952</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8648</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8802</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>17450</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cowal</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1327</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1402</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>40</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>501</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>372</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>529</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3874</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3858</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7732</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Islay</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2892</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3122</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>48</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2246</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>447</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>429</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8476</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8517</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16993</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Kintyre</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2823</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>4014</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>57</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>869</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>895</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2250</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9584</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>10814</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20668</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Lorn</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2827</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3091</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>141</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1246</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>826</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1019</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7584</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7686</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15270</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mull</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3224</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3337</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1040</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>2240</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>424</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>673</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9339</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9864</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>19203</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16059</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>18309</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1369</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8989</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3468</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5852 .'</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>47505</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>49541</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>97316</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
