<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-0722-0397-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ARCHBISHOP (7th edition, volume 3, page 397)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1939192">Metropolitans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018897">Metropolitanates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs0f">Archbishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193100722?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ARCHBISHOP</label>, the name of a church dignitary of the
                    first class. Archbishops were not known in the East till about the year 320; and
                    though there were some soon after this who had the title, yet that was only a
                    personal honour, by which the bishops of considerable cities were distinguished.
                    It was not till of late that archbishops became metropolitans, and had
                    suffragans under them. Athanasius appears to be the first who used the title <hi
                    rend="italic">Archbishop,</hi> which he gave occasionally to his predecessor;
                    Gregory Nazianzen, in like manner, gave it to Athanasius; not that either of
                    them was entitled to any jurisdiction, or even any precedence, in virtue of it.
                    Among the Latins, Isidore Hispalensis is The first that speaks of archbishops.
                    He distinguishes four orders or degrees in the ecclesiastical hierarchy, viz.
                    patriarchs, archbishops, metropolitans, and bishops.</p>
                <p>The archbishop, beside the inspection of the bishops and inferior clergy in the
                    province over which he presides, exercises episcopal jurisdiction in his own
                    diocese. He is guardian of the spiritualities of any vacant see in his province,
                    as the king is of the temporalities, and exercises ecclesiastical jurisdiction
                    in it. He is entitled to present by lapse to all the ecclesiastical livings in
                    the disposal of his diocesan bishop, if not filled within six months. He has
                    likewise a customary prerogative, upon consecrating a bishop, to name a clerk or
                    chaplain, to be provided for by such bishop; in lieu of which it is now usual to
                    accept an option. He is said to be enthroned when vested m the archbishopric,
                    whereas bishops are said to be installed.</p>
                <p>Ιhe ecclesiastical government of England is divided into two provinces, viz.
                    Canterbury and York. Canterbury has the following suffragan bishoprics
                    appertaining <hi rend="superscript"> t0</hi> it: St Asaph, Bangor, Bath and
                    Wells, Bristol, Chichester, Lichfield and Coventry, St Davids, Ely, Exeter,
                    Gloucester, Hereford, Llandaflf, Lincoln, London, Norwich,</p>
                <p>Oxford, Peterborough, Rochester, Salisbury, Winchester, and Worcester. To York
                    appertain the bishoprics of Carlisle, Chester, and Durham; to which may be added
                    the bishopric of Sodor and Man, whose bishop is not a lord of parliament.</p>
                <p>The archbishop of Canterbury had anciently, viz. till the year 1152, jurisdiction
                    over Ireland as well as England, and was styled a <hi rend="italic"
                    >patriarch,</hi> and sometimes <hi rend="italic">alterius orbis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">papa,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">orbis Britannici pontifex.</hi>
                    Matters were done and recorded in his name thus,— <hi rend="italic">Anno</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">pontificatus nostri</hi><hi rend="italic">primo,</hi> &amp;c. The
                    first archbishop of Canterbury was Austin, appointed by King Ethelbert on his
                    conversion to Christianity, about the year 598. He was also <hi rend="italic"
                    >legatus natus.</hi> He even enjoyed some special marks of royalty; as to be
                    patron of a bishopric, which he was of Rochester; and to make knights, coin
                    moneys, &amp;c. The archbishop is still the first peer of England, and the next
                    to the royal family, having precedence of all dukes and all great officers of
                    the crown. It is his privilege, by custom, to crown the kings and queens of this
                    kingdom. He may retain and qualify eight chaplains, whereas a duke is allowed by
                    statute only six. He has, by common law, the power of probate of wills and
                    testaments, and granting letters of administration. He has also a power to grant
                    licences and dispensations in all cases formerly sued for in the court of Rome,
                    and not repugnant to the law of God. He accord-ly issues special licences to
                    marry, to hold two livings, &amp;c. and he exercises thę right of conferring
                    degrees. He also holds several courts of judicature; as court of arches, court
                    of audience, prerogative court, and court of peculiars.</p>
                <p>The archbishop of York has the like rights in his province as the archbishop of
                    Canterbury. He has precedence of all dukes not of the royal blood, and of all
                    officers of state, except the lord high chancellor. He has also the rights of a
                    count palatine over Hexhamshire. The first archbishop of York was Paulinus,
                    appointed by Pope Gregory about the year 622. He had formerly jurisdiction over
                    all the bishops of Scotland; but in the year 1470 Pope Sextus IV. created the
                    bishop of St Andrews archbishop and metropolitan of all Scotland.</p>
                <p>Scotland, whilst episcopacy prevailed in that country, had two archbishops, of St
                    Andrews and Glasgow, the former of which was accounted the metropolitan, and,
                    even before it arrived at the dignity of an archbishopric, resisted with great
                    spirit all the attempts of the archbishops of York in England to become the
                    metropolitans of Scotland. The sees of Argyll, Galloway, and the Isles, were
                    suffragans to Glasgow; all the others in the kingdom to St Andrews.</p>
                <p>Ireland has four archbishops—of Armagh, Dublin, Cashel, and Tuam; the first of
                    which is primate of all Ireland.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
