<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-9292-0287-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">APOLLONIUS (7th edition, volume 3, page 287)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j678z7h">Cone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45h7bt4s">Manuscripts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w64d">Barrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1765196">Space</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874609">Cone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193099292?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">APOLLONIUS</label> of Perga, in Pamphylia, is one of the most
                    illustrious of the ancient Greek geometricians. The date of his birth has not
                    been precisely ascertained; but as he flourished under Ptolemy Philopater, who
                    died in the year 205 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> after a reign of 16 years,
                    it is conjectured that he was born about the middle of the third century before
                    our era, and that he was about 40 years posterior to Archimedes. He studied at
                    Alexandria under the successors of Euclid, and is pre-eminently distinguished
                    among the disciples of that illustrious school, in which the mathematical
                    sciences were at all times held in the highest estimation.</p>
                <p>Few of the numerous compositions of Apollonius have escaped the ravages of time;
                    but the description which has been given of them by Pappus, in the preface to
                    the seventh book of the <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Collections,</hi>
                    explains their nature and value, and gives the admirers of the ancient analysis
                    great reason to regret the loss of those which have perished. The most
                    celebrated of his productions was the treatise on the <hi rend="italic">Conic
                    Sections</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> a work∙which, according to the testimony
                    of Geminius Rhodius, was regarded with so much admiration by the contemporaries
                    oi <pb break="no" facs="nls:193099305?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0703-9305-0288"/> .its author, that they bestowed on him the title
                    of the <hi rend="italic superscript"> z</hi><hi rend="italic">Great
                    Geometrician.</hi> This title is justified by the excellence of the work, which
                    is unquestionably far superior to any treatise on the subject which we know to
                    have existed among the ancients, and which has not indeed, in some respects,
                    been surpassed in modern times. But while we bestow this praise on the treatise
                    of Apollonius, we are not to suppose that he was the inventor of all, or even
                    the greater part, of the properties which are demonstrated in it. Several
                    treatises on the conic sections are known to have existed previously, in which
                    the theory or these curves seems to have been prosecuted to a very considerable
                    length. Pappus mentions, in particular, in terms of the highest eulogy, the five
                    books on Solid Loci, or the conic sections, which were composed by Aristaeus <hi
                    rend="italic">the ancient,</hi> who lived about 350 years <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.</hi> c.; and the construction given by Menechmus, of the problem to find two
                    mean proportionals between two given straight lines, which leads to the
                    duplication of the cube, shows that the disciples of Plato had advanced far in
                    the same department of geometry. In fact, as it was the object of Apollonius to
                    give a complete treatise of the conic sections, he did not scruple to avail
                    himself of the discoveries of his predecessors, and, accordingly, embodied in
                    his own work what had previously been done by Aristaeus, Kudoxus of Cnidus,
                    Mcnechmus, Euclid, Conon, Thrasidaeus, Nicoteles, and others. It is now
                    impossible to distinguish the propositions which were borrowed from his
                    predecessors from those which were invented by himself; but it is certain that
                    he both made great additions to the theory of the conic sections, and
                    improvements in the manner of treating it. Eutocius informs us that Apollonius
                    was the first who showed that all the three sections may be cut from the same
                    cone, by varying the position of the intersecting plane; for previous authors
                    had always supposed the plane of the section perpendicular to the side of the
                    cone,—an hypothesis which requires that the three sections be cut from three
                    cones of different species, namely, the parabola from a right-angled cone, the
                    ellipse from an obtuse, and the hyperbola from an acute. It has, however, been
                    established by Guido Ubaldus, in his commentary on the second book of the <hi
                    rend="italic">AEquiponderantes</hi> of Archimedes, that the Syracusan geometer
                    was acquainted with the fact, that the three sections may be derived from the
                    same cone. The generalization is indeed so very obvious, that we can scarcely
                    persuade ourselves that it was not previously made by the more ancient writers;
                    and it is probable, that if they usually assumed the cutting plane to have a
                    particular position with reference to the cone, it was only on account of some
                    facilities which that hypothesis afforded them in establishing the fundamental
                    properties of the sections. Pappus ascribes to Apollonius the names by which the
                    three sections are now distinguished and characterized: the term <hi
                    rend="italic">Parabola,</hi> however, occurs in the writings of Archimedes.</p>
                <p>Of the eight books which Apollonius composed on the conic sections, the first
                    four only have reached us in the original Greek. Three more have been preserved
                    through the medium of an Arabic version; the last is unfortunately lost. A Latin
                    translation of the first four was published by Memmius, at Venice, in 1537; and
                    another, much more accurate, by Commandine, in 1568, with the addition of the
                    commentary of Eutocius, and the lemmas of Pappus to all the eight books.
                    Hitherto the last four books had not been discovered; but as the nature of their
                    contents was sufficiently known from the indications of Pappus, several attempts
                    were made to supply their loss by a restoration. Maurolycus, a Sicilian geometer
                    of the 16th century, successfully commenced the theory of the fifth and sixth
                    books; and Vivianĩ, the last and favourite disciple of the illustrious Galileo,
                    was employed on the, same subject, when two different manuscript versions' of
                    the work of Apollonius were accidentally brought to light. Among a number of
                    Arabic manuscripts brought from the East by Golius, one was found which
                    contained seven books of the conics. Golius was sufficiently i∏. structed in
                    geometry to be aware of the value of his discovery; he hastened to communicate
                    it to the mathematicians of that time, and proposed to publish a translation of
                    the work. This project, however, failed from some cause which has not been
                    explained; and, notwithstanding the intimation which had been given, the last
                    four books still continued to be regarded as lost, till the year 1658, when
                    Alρhonso Borelli, the celebrated author of the treatise <hi rend="italic"
                    >De</hi><hi rend="italic">Motu Animalium,</hi> happened to discover, in the
                    library of the Medici at Florence, an Arabic manuscript with the following
                    inscription: <hi rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergoei</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Conicorum Libri</hi><hi rend="italic">Octo.</hi> Borelli obtained
                    permission to carry this manuscript to Rome, where, with the assistance of
                    Abraham Ecchellensis, he translated the fifth, sixth, and seventh books.
                    Notwithstanding the inscription, the eighth book was wanting; and as this was
                    also the case with regard to the manuscript of Golius, it seems probable that it
                    had not been translated into Arabic.</p>
                <p>The last four books of the conics of Apollonius formed a considerable part of
                    what may be termed the transcendental geometry of the ancients; and they exhibit
                    some of the most elegant and successful applications of the geometrical
                    analysis. The fifth book, for example, which treats of the greatest and least
                    lines that can be drawn from given points to the peripheries of the curves,
                    contains nearly all the properties of normals and radii of curvature which are
                    now generally investigated by the aid of the differential calculus, and almost
                    anticipates the admirable theory of involutes and evolutes which confers so
                    brilliant a lustre on the name of Huygens. The seventh book also contains some
                    theorems which, although they have now passed into the elements, are
                    sufficiently difficult and remote to afford scope for the exercise of address
                    and ingenuity, even when their investigation is attempted by the modern
                    analysis. Dr Halley, guided by the description of Pappus, divined the contents
                    of the eighth book, and published a magnificent edition of the whole at Oxford
                    in 1710.</p>
                <p>The other treatises of Apollonius which are mentioned by Pappus are the following
                    :—Is/, The Section of Ratio, or Proportional Sections; <hi rend="italic"
                    >2d,</hi> the Section of Space; <hi rend="italic">3d,</hi> the Determinate
                    Sections; <hi rend="italic">⅛th,</hi> the Tangencies; 5⅛ the Inclinations; <hi
                    rend="italic">6th,</hi> the Plane Loci. Each of these was divided into two
                    books, and, with the <hi rend="italic">data</hi> of Euclid and the <hi
                    rend="italic">porisms,</hi> they formed the eight treatises which, according tø
                    Pappus, constituted the body of the ancient analysis. Of the above treatises of
                    Apollonius, the first only has reached us through an Arabic translation. It was
                    discovered in Arabic among the Selden manuscripts in the Bodleian Library at
                    Oxford, by Dr Edward Bernard, who commenced a translation of it, from which,
                    however, he was deterred by the difficulties occasioned by the extreme
                    inaccuracy of the manuscript before he had finished a tenth part. This small
                    portion of the translation was revised by Dr David Gregory; the rest was
                    translated, or more properly speaking, divined, by Dr Halley, who published it
                    in 1706, together with the analogous treatise on the <hi rend="italic">Section
                    of Space,</hi> which he had restored after the indication of its contents given
                    by Pappus. The general problem resolved in the first treatise, although it is
                    branched out into a great variety of cases, may be comprehended in the following
                    enunciation: “Two straight lines being given by position, together with a point
                    in each, it is required to draw through a third given point a straight <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193099318?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0703-9318-0289"/>
                    line intersecting the two former straight lines, so that the 'segments
                    intercepted between the given points and the points of intersection with the
                    third line may be to each other in a given ratio.” The problem which forms the
                    subject of the second treatise differs from the above only jn requiring that the
                    intercepted segments on the two straight lines given by position shall contain a
                    given rectangle.</p>
                <p>The object of the treatise on the <hi rend="italic">Determinate Sections</hi>.was
                    “to find a point in a straight line given by position, the rectangles or squares
                    of whose distances from given points in the given straight line shall have a
                    given ratio.” A restoration of this and the two preceding treatises was
                    attempted by Snellius; but although he certainly resolved the problems which had
                    been proposed by Apollonius, hiş solutions were far inferior in point of
                    elegance to those of the Greek geometer. The discovery of the treatise on the
                    Section of Ratio enabled a comparison to be made of the restored with the
                    original work. Some cases of the <hi rend="italic">Determinate Section</hi> were
                    also resolved by Alexander Anderson of Aberdeen, in his supplement to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Apollonius</hi><hi rend="italic">Redivivus,</hi> published at
                    Paris in 1612. But by far the most complete and <hi rend="superscript">;</hi>
                    elegant restoration of the problem was given by Dr Simson of Glasgow, with two
                    additional books on the same subject. It has been published among his posthumous
                    works.</p>
                <p>. The treatise on <hi rend="italic">Inclinations,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi>
                    the object of which was to insert a straight line of a given length, and tending
                    to a given point, between two lines (straight lines or circles) given by
                    position,—was first investigated by Marinus Ghetaldus, a patrician of Ragusa,
                    afterwards by Hugo de Omerique in his ingenious treatise on the <hi
                    rend="italic">Geometrical Analysis,</hi> published at Cadiz in 1698. The
                    different cases ,of the problem have been resolved in a very elegant manner by
                    Dr Horsley, who published his restoration in</p>
                <p>• 1770.</p>
                <p>The treatise <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Tactionibus,</hi> which
                    relates to the contact of circles and straight lines, has afforded exercise for
                    the ingenuity of many modern mathematicians. The general problem which it
                    embraces may be enunciated as follows: Three things (points, straight lines, or
                    circles) being given by position, it is required to describe a circle which may
                    pass through the given points and touch the given straight lines and circles.
                    The most difficult case of the problem is that in which the three things given
                    are circles; the question' being then to determine the centre and radius of a
                    circle, which shall touch these circles given in magnitude and position. This
                    problem, which is now considered as quite elementary, possesses an historical
                    interest on account of the great names connected with its solution. It was
                    proposed by Vieta, the most skilful geometrician of the 16th century, to
                    Adrianus Romanus, who, in constructing it, employed the very obvious
                    consideration of the intersection of two hyperbolas. Such a • solution of a
                    plane problem,.which ought to be constructed by means of straight lines and
                    circles only, was very far from being satisfactory to Vieta: he therefore
                    himself proposed a more geometrical construction, and restored the whole
                    treatise of Apollonius, in a small work which he published at Paris in 1660
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">Apollonius Gallus.</hi> The∙treatise of
                    Vieta is entitled to the praise of great ingenuity, but it falls far short of
                    the geometrical elegance of the known productions of Apollonius; and simpler
                    solutions have since been found of the more dif- ∙∙ficult cases of the general
                    problem. An algebraic solution oí the same question was attempted by Descartes;
                    -but the equations at which he arrived were so exceedingly complicated, that he
                    himself ingenuously confessed that he should not be able to construct one of
                    them in a shorter time than three months. The Princess Elizabeth of Bohemia, who
                    carried on an epistolary correspondence with Descartes, gave a solution of the
                    same kind. Newton himself, in his <hi rend="italic">Universal Arithmetic,</hi>
                    condescended to consider this problem; but he succeeded little better than
                    Vieta, whose method he followed. In the 16th lemma of the first book of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Principia,</hi> he has, however, given a different and simpler
                    investigation, and reduced with great skill the two hyperbolic loci of Adrianus
                    Romanus to the intersection of two straight lines. Simple geometrical solutions,
                    since that of Dr Simson was published, are to be found in every elementary work.
                    In speaking of this problem, Montucla observes, that it is one of those to which
                    the algebraic analysis applies with difficulty. His opinion, however, would have
                    been different had he lived to see the extremely simple and elegant algebraic
                    investigation given by Gergonne in the <hi rend="italic">Annales</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">des Mathématiques,</hi> not only of this, but of the analogous
                    problem in space which was proposed by Descartes to Fermat, viz. to describe a
                    sphere touching four spheres given by position. In fact, it would be difficult
                    to select a problem in elementary geometry better calculated to display the
                    resources and pliability of the algebraic calculus, than this very one which had
                    been considered as belonging so exclusively to the analysis of the ancients. A
                    very full and interesting historical account of this problem is given in the
                    preface to a little work of Camerer, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergaei quae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >supersunt,</hi><hi rend="italic">ac</hi><hi rend="italic">maxime</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Lemmata</hi><hi rend="italic">Pappi</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >in</hi><hi rend="italic">hos libros,</hi><hi rend="italic">cum</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Observationibus,</hi> &amp;c. Gothae, 1795, 8vo∙</p>
                <p>The last of the treatises mentioned by Pappus,— <hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Locis Planis,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> is only a collection of
                    properties of the straight line and circle, and corresponds to the construction
                    of equations of the first and second degree. It has been restored in the true
                    spirit of the ancient geometry by Dr Simson, whose treatise well deserves the
                    attention of the student.</p>
                <p>Besides the works which we have now enumerated, we are informed, by the fragment
                    of the second book of Pappus, published among the works of Dr Wallis, that
                    Apollonius occupied himself with arithmetical researches, and composed a
                    treatise on the multiplication of large numbers. Astronomy is also indebted to
                    him for the discovery, or at least for the demonstration, of the method of
                    representing, by means of epicycles and deferents, the phenomena of the stations
                    and retrogradations of the planets. He appears also to have been the inventor of
                    the method of projections, and has the distinguished meritof having been the
                    first who attempted to found astronomy on the principles of geometry, and
                    establish an alliance between these two sciences which has been productive of
                    the greatest benefit to both.</p>
                <p>Of the personal character of this most assiduous and inventive geometrician,
                    nothing is known excepting what may be gathered from a few unfavourable hints
                    thrown out by Pappus. Pappus describes him as vain, arrogant, envious of the
                    reputation of others,, and inclined to depreciate their merit; and contrasts him
                    with the amiable and disinterested Euclid, who was always ready to allow to
                    every one his just share of praise, and who manifested on every occasion the
                    most benevolent feelings towards all men, especially towards those who laboured
                    to improve or extend the science of geometry. The charge of (appropriating to
                    himself the discoveries of Archimedes, which was brought against-Apollonius by
                    Heraclius, had probably no other foundation than the boastful manner in which he
                    spoke of his own discoveries, and affected to despise those of other
                    mathematicians; for, as has been well remarked, pretensions pushed too far
                    excite in the rest of mankind a sort of re-action of self-love, which leads them
                    to contest the most legitimate titles. But whatever may have been the case with
                    regard to the per <pb break="no" facs="nls:193099331?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0703-9331-0290"/> sonal qualities of Apollonius, the powers of his
                    mind and his unwearied industry command universal admiration. The great value
                    attached to his productions by the ancients is manifest from the number and
                    celebrity of the commentators who undertook to explain them. Among these we find
                    the names of Pappus, the learned and unfortunate Hypatia, Serenus, Eutocius,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The remarkable editions of the works of Apollonius are the following :—1. <hi
                    rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergaei</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Conicorum libri</hi><hi rend="italic">quatuor,</hi><hi rend="italic">ex
                    versione Erederici Commandini.</hi> Bononiae, 1566, fol. 2. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergaei</hi><hi rend="italic">Conicorum
                    libri</hi> v. vi. vii. <hi rend="italic">Paraphraste Abalphato Asphanensi nunc
                    primum editi: Additus in calce Archimedis Assumtorum liber, ex Codicibus
                    Arabicis Manuscr.: Abrahamus Ecchellensis Latinos reddidit: J. Alfonsus Borellus
                    curam in Geometricis Ver-sioni contulit, et Notas uberiores in universum opus
                    adjecit.</hi> Florentiae, 1661, fol. 3. <hi rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Pergaei</hi><hi rend="italic">Conicorum libri octo, et Sereni
                    Antissensis de Sectione Cylindri et Coni libri</hi><hi rend="italic">duo.</hi>
                    Oxoniae, 1710, fol. (This is the splendid edition of Dr Halley.) 4. The edition
                    of the first four books of the Conics given in 1675 by Barrow. 5. <hi
                    rend="italic">Apollonii</hi><hi rend="italic">Pergaei de</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sectione Rationis libri</hi><hi rend="italic">duo</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >:</hi><hi rend="italic">Accedιrnt</hi><hi rend="italic">ejusdem</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Sectione Spatii libri duo
                    Restituti:</hi><hi rend="italic">Praemittitur,</hi> &amp;c. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Opera et Studio</hi><hi rend="italic">Edmuηdi Halley.</hi> Oxoniae, 1706,
                    4to.</p>
                <p>See Bayle’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> Bossut, <hi
                    rend="italic">Essai sur</hi><hi rend="italic">l'Hist. Gem</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >des</hi><hi rend="italic">Math.,</hi> tome i.; Montucla, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hist,</hi><hi rend="italic">des Math.,</hi> tome i.; Vossius <hi rend="italic"
                    >de Scient. Math.;</hi> Simson’s <hi rend="italic">Sectiones</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Conicae,</hi> preface; and Hutton’s <hi rend="italic">Mathematical
                    Dictionary.</hi> (s.)</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Apollonius,</hi> the author of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Argonautics,</hi> and surnamed the Rhodian, from the place of his residence, is
                    supposed to have been a native of Alexandria, where he is said to have recited
                    some portion of his poem while he was yet a youth. Finding it ill received by
                    his countrymen, he retired to Rhodes, where he is conjectured to have polished
                    and completed his work, supporting himself by the profession of rhetoric, and
                    receiving from the Rhodians the freedom of their city. He at length returned
                    with considerable honour to the place of his birth, succeeding Eratosthenes in
                    the care of the Alexandrian library in the reign of Ptolemy Euergetes, who
                    ascended the throne of Egypt in the year before Christ 246. That prince had been
                    educated by the famous Aristarchus, and rivalled the preceding sovereigns of his
                    liberal family in the munificent encouragement of learning. Apollonius was a
                    disciple of the poet Callimachus; but their connection ended in the most violent
                    enmity, which was probably owing to some degree of contempt expressed by
                    Apollonius for the light compositions of his master. The learned have vainly
                    endeavoured to discover the particulars of their quarrel. The only work of
                    Apollonius which has descended to modern times is his poem above mentioned, in
                    four books, on the Argonautic expedition. Both Longinus and Quintilian have
                    assigned to this work the mortifying character of mediocrity. It was published
                    for the first time at Florence in 1496, with the ancient Greek Scholia, in a 4to
                    volume, now exceedingly rare. There is an excellent edition by Brunck, published
                    in 1780, and another by Beck, published in 1797; but the best is that of
                    Professor Schafer, printed at Leipsic in 2 vols. 8vo, in 1810-13.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Apollonius,</hi> a Pythagorean philosopher, born at Tyana in
                    Cappadocia about the beginning of the first century. At 16 years of age he
                    became a strict observer of Pythagoras’s rules, renouncing wine and all sorts of
                    flesh; not wearing shoes, letting his hair grow, and wearing nothing but linen.
                    He soon after set up for a reformer of mankind, and chose his habitation in a
                    temple of AEsculapius, where he is said to have performed many wonderful cures.
                    Philostratus has written the life of Apollonius, in which there are numberless
                    fabulous stories recounted of him. We are told that he went five years without
                    speaking, and yet during that time stopped many seditions in Cilicia and
                    Pamphylia; that he travelled, and set up for a legislator; that he gave out he
                    understood all languages without having ever learned them; and that he could
                    tell the thoughts of men and understood the oracles which birds gave by their
                    singing. The heathens were fond of opposing the pretended miracles of this man
                    to those of our Saviour; and by a treatise which Eusebius wrote against one
                    Hierocles, we find that the object of the latter, in the treatise which Eusebius
                    refutes, seems to have been to draw a parallel between Jesus Christ and
                    Apollonius, in which he gives the preference to this philosopher. Μ. Dupin wrote
                    a confutation of Philostratus’s life of Apollonius.</p>
                <p>Apollonius wrote four books of Judicial Astrology; a Treatise upon the
                    Sacrifices, showing what was proper to be offered to each deity; and a great
                    number of Letters; all of which are now lost.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
