<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0703-9097-0272-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANTONINUS’S Wall (7th edition, volume 3, page
                    272)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f63">Chains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4280520x">Discoverers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qk72">Fonts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46m33654">Dikes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851789">Chains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:930451">Fonts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193099097?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ANTONINUS’S <hi rend="smallcaps">Wall</hi></label>, the name
                    of the third rampart or defence that had been built or repaired by the Romans
                    against the incursions of the North Britons. It is called by the people in the
                    neighbourhood <hi rend="italic">Graham's Dike,</hi> from the notion that one
                    Graham, or Grimus, first made a breach in it after the retreat of the Romans out
                    of Britain. The first barrier erected by the Romans was the chain of forts made
                    by Agricola from the frith of Forth to that of Clyde, in the year 81, to protect
                    his conquest from the inroads of the Caledonians. The second was the vallum or
                    dike thrown up by Adrian in the year 121. It terminated on the western side of
                    the kingdom at <hi rend="italic">Axelοdunum</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Prugh,</hi> on the Solway sands, and was supposed to have reached no farther
                    than <hi rend="italic">Pons El</hi> ∖ <hi rend="italic">i</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Newcastle</hi> on the eastern; but from an inscription lately
                    discovered, it appears to have extended as far as the wall of Severus. This
                    rampart of Adrian’s was situated much farther south than Agricola’s chain; the
                    country to the north having been either, according to some authors, recovered by
                    the native Britons after the departure of Agricola, or, according to others,
                    voluntarily slighted by Adrian. However, this work of Adrian’s did not long
                    continue to be the extreme boundary of the Roman territories to the north in
                    Britain; for Antoninus Pius, the adopted son and immediate successor of Adrian,
                    having, by his lieutenant Lollius Urbicus, recovered the country once conquered
                    by Agricola, commanded another rampart to be erected between the friths of Forth
                    and Clyde, in the track where Agricola had formerly built his chain of forts.
                    The great number of inscriptions which have been found in or near the ruins of
                    this wall or rampart, to the honour of Antoninus Pius, leave us no room to doubt
                    its having been built by his direction and command. If the fragment of a Roman
                    pillar with an inscription, now in the college library of Edinburgh, belonged to
                    this work, as is generally supposed, it fixes the date of its execution to the
                    third consulship of Antoninus, which was <hi rend="smallcaps">a.</hi> D. 140,
                    only twenty years after that of Adrian, of which this seems to have been an
                    imitation. This wall or rampart, as some imagine, reached from Caer-ridden on
                    the frith of Forth to Old Kirkpatrick on the Clyde; or, as others think, from
                    Kinniel on the east to Dunglass on the west. These different suppositions hardly
                    make a mile of difference in the length of this work, which, from several actual
                    mensurations, appears to have been 37 English or 40 Roman miles. Capitolinus, in
                    his life of Antoninus Pius, directly affirms that the wall which that emperor
                    built in Britain was of turf. This in the main' is unquestionably true, though
                    it is evident (from the vestiges of it still remaining, which not very many
                    years ago were dug up and examined for near a mile together) that the foundation
                    was'of stone. Mr Camden also tells us that the principal rampart was faced with
                    square stone, to prevent the earth from falling into the ditch. The chief parts
                    of this work were as follows: 1. A broad and deepn ditch, whose dimensions
                    cannot now be discovered with certainty and exactness, though Mr Pont says it
                    was 12 feet wide. 2. The principal wall or rampart was abou? 12 feet thick at
                    the foundation, but its original height cannot now be determined. This wall was
                    situated on the south brink of the ditch. 3. A military way on the south side of
                    the principal wall, well paved, and raised a little above the level of the
                    ground. This work, as well as that of Adrian, was defended by garrisons placed
                    in forts and stations along the line of it. The number of these forts or
                    stations, whose vestiges were visible in Mr Font’s time, was 18, situated at
                    about the distance of two miles from each other. In the intervals between the
                    forts there were turrets or watch-towers; but the number of these, and their
                    distance from each other, cannot now be discovered.</p>
                <p>It is not a little surprising, that though it is now more than 1600 years since
                    this work was finished, and more than 1300 since it was slighted, we can yet
                    discover, from authentic monuments which are still remaining, by what particular
                    bodies of Roman troops almost every part of it was executed. ^ This discovery is
                    made from inscriptions upon stones, which were originally built into the face of
                    the wall, and have been found in or near its ruins. From these inscriptions it
                    appears in general, that this great work was executed by the second legion, the
                    vexillations of the sixth legion and of the twentieth legion, and one cohort of
                    auxiliaries. Some of these inscriptions have suffered greatly by the injuries of
                    time and other accidents; so that we cannot discover from them with absolute
                    certainty how many paces of this work were executed by each of these bodies of
                    troops. The sum of the certain and probable information contained in these
                    inscriptions, as it is collected by Mr Horsley, stands thus:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Paces.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The second legion built</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11603</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The vexillation of the sixth
                            legion</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7411</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The vexillation of the twentieth
                            legion</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7801</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>All certain</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>26815</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>The vexillation of the twentieth
                            legion, the monument certain, and the number probable</p><p>The same
                            vexillation on a plain monument, no</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3411</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>number visible, supposed</p><p>The
                            sixth legion, a monument, but no number,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3500</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>supposed</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Cohors prima Cugernorum</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3000</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>39726</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>or 39 miles 726 paces, nearly the whole length of the wall. It would be both
                    useful and agreeable to know how long these troops were employed in the
                    execution of this great work. But of this we have no information. Neither do we
                    know what particular bodies of troops were in garrison in the several forts and
                    stations along the line of this wall, because these garrisons were withdrawn
                    before the <hi rend="italic">Nοtitiα Imperii</hi> was written.</p>
                <p>Though we cannot discover exactly how many years this wall of the emperor
                    Antoninus continued to be the boundary of the Roman territories in Britain, yet
                    we. know with certainty that it was not very long. For we are told by an author
                    of undoubted credit (Dion Cassius, lib. lxxii.), that, in the reign of Commodus,
                    A. n. 180, “he had wars with several foreign nations, but none so dangerous as
                    that of Britain; for the people of the island, having passed the wall, which
                    divided them from the Ro-. mans, attacked them, and cut them to pieces.’·’</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
