<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0125-0112-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PURCELL, Henry (9th edition, volume 20, page
                    112)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49s1kn07">Priests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4930p22j">Organists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:893060">Didos</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n125/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PURCELL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry</hi></label> (1658-1695),
                    English musical composer, was born in 1658 in St Ann’s Lane, Old Pye Street,
                    Westminster. His father, Henry Purcell, was a gentleman of the chapel-royal, and
                    in that capacity sang at the coronation of Charles II. After his father’s death
                    in 1664 the boy was placed under the guardianship of his uncle, Thomas Purcell,
                    a man of extraordinary probity and kindness. Through the interest of this
                    affectionate guardian, who was himself a gentleman of His Majesty’s chapel,
                    Henry was admitted to the chapel-royal as a chorister, and studied first under
                    Captain Henry Cooke, “master of the children,” and afterwards under Pelham
                    Humfrey. He is said to have composed well at nine years old; but the earliest
                    work that can be certainly identified as his is an ode for the king’s birthday,
                    written in 1670. After Humfrey’s early death in 1674 he continued his studies
                    under Dr Blow. In 1676 he was appointed copyist at Westminster Abbey—not
                    organist, as has sometimes been erroneously stated—and in the same year he
                    composed the music to Dryden’s <hi rend="italic">Aurenge-Zebe,</hi> and
                    Shadwell’s <hi rend="italic">Epsom Wells</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Libertine.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">The, Libertine</hi> was suggested by Tirso
                    de Molina’s tale, <hi rend="italic">El Bur-ladar de Sevilla,</hi> afterwards
                    dramatically treated by Molière and chosen by Da Ponte as the foundation of
                    Mozart’s <hi rend="italic">Don Giovanni.</hi></p></note> These were followed in
                    1677 by the music to Mrs Behn’s tragedy, <hi rend="italic">Abdelazor,</hi> and
                    in 1678 by an overture and masque for Shadwell’s new version of Shakespeare’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Timon</hi><hi rend="italic">of Athens.</hi> The excellence of
                    these compositions is proved by the fact that they contain songs and choruses
                    which never fail to please, even at the present day. The masque in <hi
                    rend="italic">Timon</hi><hi rend="italic">of Athens</hi> is a masterpiece, and
                    the chorus “In these delightful pleasant groves” in <hi rend="italic">The
                    Libertine</hi> is constantly sung with applause by English choral societies. In
                    1679 he wrote some songs for Playford’s <hi rend="italic">Choice Ayres, Songs,
                    and Dialogues,</hi> and also an anthem, the name of which is not known, for the
                    chapel-royal. From a letter written by Thomas Purcell, and still extant, we
                    learn that this anthem was composed for the exceptionally fine voice of the Rev.
                    John Gostling, then at Canterbury, but afterwards<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n126/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0126-0113"/> a gentleman of His Majesty’s chapel. Purcell
                    wrote several anthems at different times for this extraordinary voice, a <hi
                    rend="italic">basso profundo,</hi> the compass of which is known to have
                    comprised at least two full octaves, from D below the stave to D above it. The
                    dates of very few of these sacred compositions are known; but one, “They that go
                    down to the sea in ships,” though certainly not written until some time after
                    this period, will be best mentioned here. In thankfulness for a providential
                    escape of the king from shipwreck Gostling, who had been of the royal party, put
                    together some verses from the Psalms in the form of an anthem, and requested
                    Purcell to set them to music. The work is ‘a very fine one but very difficult,
                    and contains a passage which traverses the full extent of Gostling’s voice,
                    beginning on the upper D and descending two octaves to the lower.</p>
                <p>In 1680 Dr Blow, who had been appointed organist of Westminster Abbey in 1669,
                    resigned his office in favour of his pupil; and Purcell, at the age of
                    twenty-two, was placed in one of the most honourable positions an English artist
                    could occupy. He now devoted himself almost entirely to the composition of
                    sacred music, and for six years entirely severed his connexion with the theatre.
                    But during the early part of the year, and in all probability before entering
                    upon the duties of his new office, he had produced two important works for the
                    stage, the music for Lee’s <hi rend="italic">Theodosius</hi> and D’Urfey’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Virtuous Wife.</hi> There is also strong evidence that it was in
                    1680—not, as has been generally represented, in 1675—that he composed his opera
                    <hi rend="italic">Dido and</hi><hi rend="italic">Aeneas,</hi> a work of far
                    greater significance in the development of art than has generally been supposed,
                    since it forms a very important landmark in the history of English dramatic
                    music. It was written, to a libretto furnished by Nahum Tate, at the request of
                    Josiah Priest, a professor of dancing, who also kept a boarding-school for young
                    gentlewomen, first in Leicester Fields and afterwards at Chelsea. At the time of
                    its production<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    difficulty in fixing the exact date of its composition arises from a doubt as to
                    whether or not it was performed in Leicester Fields before it was played in the
                    new boarding-school at Chelsea.</p></note> the condition of dramatic music in
                    England was very rudimentary indeed,—so much so that the opera, properly so
                    called, cannot fairly be said to have existed even in embryo, though it had long
                    flourished brilliantly in Italy, and was beginning to take firm root in France.
                    No English composer had as yet soared above the songs and choruses introduced
                    into the masques, the comedies, and the tragedies of the period, for the purpose
                    of enlivening the performance,—music always of a purely incidental character,
                    and always quite unconnected with the progressive action of the piece. Very
                    different was the mixed form of entertainment thus produced from the true
                    musical drama, the invention of which in Italy dated as far back as the closing
                    years of the 16th century. At that period a number of literary and artistic
                    savants—among them Vincenzo Galilei, the father of the astronomer, Jacopo Peri,
                    Giulio Carcini, and the poet Rinuccini—were accustomed to meet in Florence for
                    purposes of discussion at the house of Giovanni Bardi, count of Vernio. Deeply
                    imbued with the principles of the Renaissance, these heated enthusiasts were
                    determined to carry them from the domain of literature into that of music; and
                    their first dream was the revival of the method of recitation practised by the
                    early Greeks in the tragedies of Aeschylus and Sophocles. This, however, was, if
                    only for technical reasons, absolutely impossible. The art was lost for ever;
                    but in seeking to resuscitate it they invented something much more
                    precious—dramatic recitative. With this at command the construction of the
                    veritable “dramma per la musica” was no difficult matter; and in fact Peri
                    actually pro duced a true opera, <hi rend="italic">Euridice,</hi> which in 1600
                    was performed at Florence in honour of the marriage of Maria de’ Medici with
                    Henry IV. of France. Purcell, who had never been in Italy, confesses himself, in
                    the preface to his sonatas, “unskilful in the Italian language,” and could never
                    by any chance have heard an Italian opera; but he knew very well what Italian
                    music was, and had not neglected to study it deeply. Yet it is doubtful whether
                    all Italy could at that moment have produced a work so full of inborn genius as
                    <hi rend="italic">Dido and</hi><hi rend="italic">Aeneas</hi><note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Alessandro Scarlatti was one
                    year younger than Purcell, and produced his first opera, <hi rend="italic"
                    >L'Onestà.</hi><hi rend="italic">nell'</hi><hi rend="italic">amore,</hi> in
                    1680.</p></note><hi rend="italic">?</hi> It is a musical drama in the strictest
                    sense of the term, a genuine opera, in which the action is entirely carried on
                    in recitative, without a word of spoken dialogue from beginning to end; and the
                    music is of the most genial character—a veritable inspiration, overflowing with
                    spontaneous melody, and in every respect immensely in advance of its age. It
                    never found its way to the theatre, though it appears to have been very popular
                    among private circles. It is believed to have been extensively copied, but one
                    song only was printed by Purcell’s widow in <hi rend="italic">Orpheus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Britannicus,</hi> and the complete work remained in manuscript
                    until 1840, when it was printed by the Musical Antiquarian Society, under the
                    editorship of Sir George Macfarren. There is a tradition that the part of Anna
                    (erroneously called Belinda), written for an alto voice, was sung by the
                    composer himself. Should this story be verified, it will tell strongly in favour
                    of the opinion that Purcell really did compose <hi rend="italic">Dido
                    and</hi><hi rend="italic">Aeneas</hi> at the age of seventeen, <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> in 1675; for it is certain that at the coronation of .James II. he
                    sang bass.</p>
                <p>In 1682 Purcell was appointed organist of the chapelroyal, <hi rend="italic"
                    >vice</hi> Edmund Lowe deceased, an office which he was able to hold conjointly
                    with his appointment at Westminster Abbey. For some years after this his pen was
                    busily employed in the production of sacred music, odes addressed to the king
                    and royal family, and other similar works. In 1685 he wrote two of his finest
                    anthems, “I was glad” and “My heart is inditing,” for the coronation of James
                    II. In 1687 he resumed his connexion with the theatre by furnishing the music
                    for Dryden’s tragedy <hi rend="italic">Tyrannic Love.</hi> It is probable that
                    the public were not at this time prepared for works of so advanced a character
                    as <hi rend="italic">Dido and</hi><hi rend="italic">Aeneas</hi>; for, though the
                    young composer’s pen was constantly employed in the production of incidental
                    music, overtures, and act tunes for pieces of the period, we find him attempting
                    no more operas based upon the true principles so cordially accepted on the
                    Continent. In this year also Purcell composed a march and quick-step, which
                    became so popular that Lord Wharton adapted the latter to the fatal verses of
                    <hi rend="italic">Lillibulero</hi>; and in January 1688 he composed his anthem
                    “Blessed are they that fear the Lord,” by express command of the king. A few
                    months later he wrote the music for D’Urfey’s play, <hi rend="italic">The Fool’s
                    Preferment.</hi> In 1690 he wrote the songs for Dryden’s version of
                    Shakespeare’s <hi rend="italic">Tempest,</hi> including “Full fathom five” and
                    “Come unto these yellow sands,” and the music for Betterton’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Prophetess</hi> (afterwards called <hi rend="italic">Dioclesian)</hi> and
                    Dryden’s <hi rend="italic">Amphitryon</hi>; and in 1691 he produced his dramatic
                    masterpiece, <hi rend="italic">King Arthur,</hi> also written by Dryden, and
                    first published by the Musical Antiquarian Society in 1843.</p>
                <p>But Purcell’s greatest work is undoubtedly his Te Deum and Jubilate, written for
                    St Cecilia’s Day, 1694, the first English Te Deum ever composed with orchestral
                    accompaniments. In this he pressed forward so far in advance of the age that the
                    work was annually performed at St Paul’s Cathedral till 1712, after which it was
                    performed alternately with Handel’s Utrecht Te Deum and Jubilate until 1743,
                    when it finally gave place to Handel’s <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n127/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0127-0114"/> Dettingen Te Deum. Purcell did not long survive
                    the production of this great work. He died at his house in Dean’s Yard,
                    Westminster, on 21st November 1695, leaving a widow and three children, the
                    former of whom soon afterwards published a number of his works, including the
                    now famous collection called <hi rend="italic">Orpheus</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Britannicus.</hi></p>
                <p>Besides the operas we have already mentioned, he wrote <hi rend="italic">Don
                    Quixote, Bonduca, The Indian Queen, The Fairy Queen,</hi> and others, a vast
                    quantity of sacred music, and numerous odes, cantatas, and other miscellaneous
                    pieces. (W. S. R. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
