<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0115-0102-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PUGIN, Augustus Welby Northmore (9th edition, volume
                    20, page 102)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891345">Designers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891253">Design</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109343">Screens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn3j">Screens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn40316">Ornament</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dr26">Sketching</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zz3k">Design</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n115/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PUGIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Augustus Welby
                    Northmore</hi></label> (1812-1852), architect, was the son of Augustus Pugin, a
                    native of France, who practised as an architect in London. He was born in Store
                    Street, Bedford Square, on 1st March 1812. After completing the ordinary course
                    of education at Christ’s Hospital (blue-coat school), he entered his father’s
                    office, where he displayed a remarkable talent for drawing. When he had mastered
                    the elements of his profession he devoted a large portion of his time to the
                    sketching of public buildings; he also accompanied his father on several
                    professional tours in France. While still very young he was employed by his
                    father to design furniture in the mediaeval style for Windsor Castle, and in
                    1831 he designed the scenery for the new opera of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kenilworth</hi> at Her Majesty’s Theatre. Shortly afterwards he involved
                    himself deeply in money difficulties by an attempt to establish a manufactory of
                    stained glass, metal work, and furniture at Hart Street, Covent Garden. From the
                    time, however, that he devoted himself steadily to his profession as an
                    architect he never failed to find full employment. Shortly after his secession
                    from the Church of England to that of Rome he published <hi rend="italic"
                    >Contrasts; or a Parallel between the Architecture of the 15th and 19th
                    Centuries</hi> (1836), in which he severely criticized the architecture of
                    Protestantism. His other principal works are <hi rend="italic">True Principles
                    of Christian Architecture</hi> (1841), a <hi rend="italic">Glossary of
                    Ecclesiastical Ornament</hi> (1844), and a <hi rend="italic">Treatise on Chancel
                    Screens and Rood Lofts</hi> (1851). Pugin was the designer of a large number of
                    important Roman Catholic buildings, and also assisted Sir Charles Barry in the
                    preparation of the designs for the new Houses of Parliament, Westminster. Early
                    in 1852 he was attacked by insanity, which caused his death on 14th September of
                    the same year.</p>
                <p>Future historians who may write the architectural history of the 19th century
                    will probably describe as its leading characteristic that enthusiastic revival
                    of the Gothic style which took place in the second quarter of the century and
                    continued with unabated vigour for more than thirty years. Among the many able
                    architects who during this period contributed to cover England with churches and
                    other buildings, designed in a style which for three centuries had been rejected
                    as barbarous, the name of Pugin deserves to be the most conspicuous. No man so
                    thoroughly mastered the true principles of the Gothic style in its various
                    stages, both in its leading lines and in the minutest details of its mouldings
                    and carved enrichments, and that too at a time when illustrated works on Gothic
                    architecture, such as have since been produced in enormous quantities,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>These numerous illustrated
                    works, with every detail shown to a workable scale, by doing away with the
                    necessity for studying the <pb corresp="kp-eb0920-0116-0103" xml:id="pbn9103"/>
                    buildings themselves, and being used simply like “cribs” to an unknown language,
                    are partly accountable for numberless recent buildings, which, while they are
                    Gothic in form, are utterly devoid of the refinement, fitness, and true taste
                    displayed in the buildings of the Middle Ages.</p></note> had scarcely begun to
                    exist; thus young Pugin had <pb corresp="pbn9103"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n116/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0116-0103"/> to learn the alphabet of his chosen style by
                    careful and laborious study of the glorious examples of Gothic, both
                    ecclesiastical and domestic, in ¼mich England was then (far more than now) so
                    extraordinarily rich. His father was for many years engaged in preparing a large
                    series of works on the Gothic buildings of England, almost, if not quite, the
                    first which were illustrated with accurate drawings of mediaeval buildings; the
                    early youth of A. W. Pugin was mostly occupied in making minute measured
                    drawings for his father’s books, and in this way his enthusiasm for Gothic art
                    was first aroused. All through his life, both in England and during many visits
                    to Germany and France, he continued to make, for his own instruction and
                    pleasure, great numbers of drawings and sketches, especially in pen and ink, and
                    with sepia monochrome. These are perhaps the most beautiful architectural
                    sketches that have ever been produced, perfect in their delicacy and precision
                    of touch, and masterpieces of skilful treatment of light and shade. They are
                    mostly minute in scale, some almost microscopic in detail. Many of the
                    Continental street scenes and interiors of cathedrals are of especial beauty
                    from their contrasts of brilliant light and transparent shadow,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Three volumes of photographs
                    of these sketches have been published in a square octavo form, but have suffered
                    from reduction in size.</p></note> treated with Rembrandt-like vigour. At a very
                    early age his wonderful mastery of Gothic detail was shown by the valuable aid
                    he rendered to Sir Charles Barry in the construction of the new Houses of
                    Parliament in 1836 and 1837.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>A comparison of the decorations of the Houses of Parliament
                    with other contemporary and even later Gothic buildings shows in a very striking
                    way the remarkable talent and industry displayed by Pugin in the
                    work.</p></note> For some time he worked as a paid clerk to Barry, and to Pugin
                    is mainly due the very remarkable excellence of all the details in this great
                    building, executed, it must be remembered, at a time when hitherto all examples
                    of the revived Gothic were of the most ignorant and tasteless description. Pugin
                    not only designed and even modelled a great part of the sculpture and other
                    decorations of the building, but had actually to train a school of masons and
                    carvers to carry out his designs with spirit and accuracy.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>A few years ago very ill-judged attempts were
                    made to claim for Pugin the main credit of Barry’s design—claims which he
                    himself would have been the last to raise.</p></note></p>
                <p>While still young Pugin became a Roman Catholic, and this, if possible, increased
                    his intense zeal and enthusiasm for Gothic, or, as he preferred to call it,
                    Christian architecture. His profession became to him a sort of religion, and his
                    study of mediaeval buildings was closely associated with his love for the mystic
                    symbolism and the highly aesthetic outward form of the old faith. The result of
                    this was that he was almost wholly employed by adherents of the Catholic
                    religion. In one way this was a fortunate circumstance, for it saved him from
                    the temptation of assisting in that great wave of falsification and
                    vulgarization which, under the name of “restoration,” has devastated the
                    principal mediaeval buildings of Great Britain and Ireland. In another way it
                    was unfortunate, for his Catholic employers were mostly much pinched for money,
                    and at the same time so devoid of all sympathy for the principles of which he
                    was the chief exponent, that they almost always insisted on the greatest
                    possible amount of display being made in the cheapest possible manner. On
                    account of this it is unfair to judge of Pugin’s genius from a critical
                    examination of his executed works. In almost every case his design was seriously
                    injured, both by cutting down its carefully considered proportions and by
                    introducing shams (above all things hateful to Pugin), such as plaster groining
                    and even cast-iron carving. The cathedral of St George at Southwark, and even
                    the church of the Jesuits in Farm Street, Berkeley Square, London, are
                    melancholy instances of this. Thus his life was one series of disappointments;
                    no pecuniary success compensated him for the destruction of his best designs, as
                    in him the man of business was thoroughly subordinate to the artist. He himself
                    used to say that the only church he had ever executed with unalloyed
                    satisfaction was the one at Ramsgate, which he not only designed but paid for.
                    Pugin was very broad in his love for the mediaeval styles, but on the whole
                    preferred what is really the most suited to modern requirements, namely, the
                    Perpendicular of the 15th century, and this he employed in its simpler domestic
                    form with much success both in his own house at Ramsgate and in the stately
                    Adare Hall in Ireland, built for Lord Dunraven. The cathedral of Killarney and
                    the chapel of the Benedictine monastery of Douai were perhaps the ecclesiastic
                    buildings which were carried out with least deviation from Pugin’s original
                    conception.</p>
                <p>He was a skilful etcher and produced a number of works illustrated in this way by
                    his own hand, and written with much elo quence, antiquarian knowledge, and even
                    brilliant humour. This last gift is exemplified in a series of etched plates in
                    his <hi rend="italic">Contrasts:</hi> on one side is some noble structure of the
                    Middle Ages, and on the other an example of the same building as erected in the
                    19th century.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Pugin’s
                    sense of humour was keener than is altogether convenient for a man of business;
                    on one occasion when a certain Catholic bishop wrote asking him to design a
                    handsome church, which was to cost an absurdly small sum of money, he replied,
                    “My lord, say thirty shillings more and have a tower and spire.”</p></note> His
                    works on <hi rend="italic">Chancel Screens</hi> and on <hi rend="italic">The
                    True Principles of Christian Architecture</hi> are very ably written and
                    exquisitely illustrated.</p>
                <p>Pugin’s melancholy and premature end was to a great extent caused by the
                    embittering influence of the constant frustration of his noblest artistic
                    struggles and conceptions.</p>
                <p>See Ben. Ferrey, <hi rend="italic">Recollections of A. Welby Pugin and his
                    Father,</hi> London, 1861.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
