<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0118-0105-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PUNCHINELLO (9th edition, volume 20, page 105)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn01649">Creation</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t1d">Popularity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m03z186">Gallicisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882407">Creationism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937852">Gardening</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n118/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PUNCHINELLO</label> (It. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Polidnella,</hi><hi rend="italic">Pulcinella),</hi> the most popular of the
                    puppets, is of Italian origin, though its history is by no means free from
                    obscurity. The earlier etymologists sought to trace the name to various mythical
                    individuals, by whom, it was alleged, the type was first furnished. Galiani
                    adopts the theory which derives it from the name of Puccio d’Aniello, a vintager
                    of Acerra near Naples, who, having by his wit and grotesque appearance
                    vanquished some strolling comedians in their own sphere, was induced to join the
                    troop, and whose place, by reason of his popularity, was supplied after his
                    death by a masked actor who imitated his dress and manner. The claims of other
                    individuals—Paolo Cinella, Polliceno, and Pulcinella, a Neapolitan dealer in
                    fowls—-have also found supporters, and the derivation of the name and character
                    from some old mystery representing Pontius (O.E. <hi rend="italic">Pownce∙,</hi>
                    Fr. <hi rend="italic">Ponce)</hi> Pilate and Judas, or the Jews, was formerly
                    popular. It has even been suggested that the title is a modification of πολύ
                    κιv∈ω as expressive of the restlessness which is characteristic of the puppet;
                    and the assumption that the character was invariably of diminutive size has
                    given rise to its reference to the word <hi rend="italic">pollice,</hi> the
                    thumb (cf. <hi rend="italic">Däumling,</hi> Tom Thumb). The most plausible
                    theory, however, regards the name in its Italian form as a diminutive of <hi
                    rend="italic">puldno,</hi> fem. <hi rend="italic">pnddna,</hi> a chicken. It is
                    sometimes stated that, in consequence of the habit of using the word “chicken”
                    as a term of endearment, it came to mean “a little child,” and hence “a puppet”
                    (Skeat). But this again involves the assumption that the application of the name
                    to the character was in some measure determined by the size of the puppets,
                    whereas it would appear to have been transferred from the comic stage to the
                    puppet show, and the Pulcinella of the stage was not necessarily a dwarf. The
                    choice, therefore, seems to lie between the theory of Quadrio, that it was
                    applied on account of the resemblance of the hooked nose to a beak, and that of
                    Baretti, which ascribes its employment to the nasal squeak and timorous
                    impotence of the original character. With respect to the development of the
                    modern type, it has been assumed that the whole family of Italian <hi
                    rend="italic">maschere</hi> (Arlecchino, Brighetta, and the like) are modified
                    survivals of the principal Oscan characters of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Atellanx,</hi> and that Punchinello is the representative of Maccus, the fool
                    or clown. In proof of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n119/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0119-0106"/> this it is urged that Acerra, the supposed
                    residence of Puccio d’Aniello and the traditional source of the character, is in
                    the neighbourhood of Aversa, the old Atelia; and reference is also made to a
                    bronze statue of Maccus, discovered at Rome in 1727, an engraving of which has
                    been preserved in Ficoroni’s <hi rend="italic">Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Maschere
                    Sceniche e</hi><hi rend="italic">le</hi><hi rend="italic">Figure</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Corniche</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Antichi
                    Romani.</hi> But the resemblance of the statue to the puppet is scarcely to be
                    termed a striking one, and the large nose and deformed figure are somewhat
                    hazardous ground on which to base a theory,— especially in view of the fact that
                    such points of likeness as there are in it to the northern Punch-are not to be
                    found in the Neapolitan Pulcinella. It is possible that some relic of the old
                    <hi rend="italic">Ludi Osci,</hi> transmitted through the Vice of the mystery
                    plays, is to be found in the character; but any direct descent from the Maccus
                    of the Atellanae seems precluded by the fact that, while there are traces of the
                    gradual development of the northern Punch from the Neapolitan Pulcinella, the
                    latter with its grey hat, white smock and trousers, masked face, and undistorted
                    body is widely different from its alleged prototype. It seems necessary,
                    therefore, to regard the Pulcinella as in large part a distinct creation of
                    comparatively modern date. Prior to the 17th century there is no indication in
                    the Italian burlesque poets of the existence of Pulcinella, though Riccoboni
                    places the creation of the part before 1600.</p>
                <p>Andrea Perrucci (1699) and Gimma assert with some show of authority that Silvio
                    Fiorillo, a comedian named after his principal part Captain Matamoros (the
                    Italian <hi rend="italic">Miles</hi><hi rend="italic">Gloriosus),</hi> invented
                    the Neapolitan Pulcinella. It was afterwards improved by Andrea Calcese,
                    surnamed Ciuccio, who died of the plague in 1656, and who, according to Gimma,
                    imitated in the character the peasants of Acerra. This would place the origin of
                    the Italian Pulcinella somewhere about the commencement of the 17th century, the
                    original character appearing to have been that of a country clown, hook-nosed,
                    shrill-voiced, cowardly, boastful, and often stupid, yet given at.times to
                    knavish tricks and shrewd sayings. In thorough accordance with this date, we
                    find that the earliest known appearance of Polichinelle in France is at the
                    commencement of the reign of Louis XIV., in the show of the puppet-playing
                    dentist Jean Brioché. It might have been expected that the shrewder and wittier
                    side of the character would most commend itself to the French mind, and there is
                    good reason to believe that the Polichinelle of Brioché was neither a blunderer
                    nor a fool. The puppet was almost immediately seized upon as the medium of
                    political satire of the kind exemplified in the <hi rend="italic">Letter
                    of</hi><hi rend="italic">Polichinelle</hi><hi rend="italic">to Cardinal
                    Mazarin</hi> (1649), and it is described in the <hi rend="italic">Combat de
                    Cyrano de Bergerac</hi> as a “petit Ésope de bois, remuant, tournant, virant,
                    dansant, riant, parlant, petant” and as “cet hétéroclite marmouset, disons
                    mieux, ce drolifique bossu.” In this there appear signs of transformation,
                    whether the importation to France took place before or after the alleged
                    improvements of Calcese. The hunchback had been long associated in France with
                    wit and laughter, and there are, therefore, some grounds for Magnin’s theory
                    that the northern Punch is of French origin, a Gallic type under an Italian
                    name, though there does not seem to be sufficient reason for adopting his
                    suggestion that Polichinelle was a burlesque portrait of Béarnais. The date of
                    its introduction into England has been disputed, Payne Collier being of opinion
                    that Punch and King William came together, a second theory suggesting an earlier
                    origin with the Huguenot refugees. In view of its popularity in France prior to
                    the Restoration, however, it would be strange if its migration had been so long
                    delayed, and it is more than probable that it crossed the Channel in the wake of
                    the Royalists. Apart from the general references by Pepys (1662) and by Evelyn
                    (1667) to an Italian puppet-show at Covent Garden, the former makes mention
                    (1669) of some poor people who called their fat child Punch, “that word being
                    become a word of common use for all that is thick and short.” An allusion to
                    “Punchinellos” is also to be found in Butler’s satire on English imitation of
                    the French, and Aubrey speaks of “a Punchinello holding a dial” as one of the
                    ornaments of Sir Samuel Lely’s house at Whitehall. But, though the puppet did
                    not travel in the train of William of Orange, allusions to it become far more
                    frequent after the Revolution of 1688, and the skill of the Dutch in their
                    treatment of puppet mechanism may have enhanced its attractiveness. In 1703 it
                    was introduced at Bartholomew Fair into a puppet play of the creation of the
                    world; in 1709 <hi rend="italic">{Tatler,</hi> No. 16) it was to be found in a
                    representation of the Deluge, though in a different part from that of the Momus
                    Polichinelle of Piron’s <hi rend="italic">ArlequinΛ)eucalion</hi> (1722); and in
                    1710 <hi rend="italic">{Spectator,</hi> No. 14) it is mentioned as a leading
                    figure in Powell’s puppet-show at Covent Garden. The alleged satire on Robert
                    Walpole, entitled <hi rend="italic">A Second Tale of a Tub, or the History of
                    Robert Powel, the Puppet-Showman</hi> (1715), furnishes some details of Punch
                    performances, and has an interesting frontispiece representing Powell with Punch
                    and his wife. The Judy (or Joan, as she appears to have been sometimes called)
                    is not of a specially grotesque order, but the Punch is easily recognizable in
                    all but the features, which are of the normal puppet type. Other allusions are
                    to be found in Gay’s <hi rend="italic">Shepherds Week— Saturday</hi> (1714) and
                    Swift’s <hi rend="italic">Dialogue between Mad Mulli-nix and Timothy</hi>
                    (1728). The older Punchinello was far less restricted in his actions and
                    circumstances than his modern successor. He fought with allegorical figures
                    representing want and weariness as well as with his wife and with the police,
                    was on intimate terms with the patriarchs and the seven champions of
                    Christendom, sat on the lap of the queen of Sheba, had kings and dukes for his
                    companions, and cheated the Inquisition as well as the common hangman. Powell
                    seems to have introduced a trained pig which danced a minuet with Punch, and the
                    French have occasionally employed a cat in place of the dog Toby, whose origin
                    is somewhat uncertain. A typical version of the modern play, with illustrations,
                    was published by Payne Collier and Cruikshank in 1828. <hi rend="smallcaps">(r.
                    μ. w.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
