<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0131-0118-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PUY, Le, or more precisely Le (9th edition, volume 20,
                    page 118)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4154dq9v">Cloisters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838413">Breccia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n131/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PUY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Le</hi>, or more precisely <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Le</hi></label><hi rend="smallcaps">Puy</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">en</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Velay,</hi> chief town of the
                    department of Haute-Loire, France, 352 miles from Paris by rail and 270 in a
                    direct line, rises in the form of an amphitheatre at a height of 2050 feet above
                    sea-level upon Mont Anis, the hill that divides the left bank of the Dolézon
                    from the right bank of the Borne (a rapid stream which joins the Loire 3 miles
                    below). From the new town, which lies east and west in the valley of the
                    Dolézon, the traveller ascends the old feudal and ecclesiastical town through
                    narrow steep streets, paved with slippery pebbles of lava, to the cathedral
                    commanded by the fantastic pinnacle of Mont Corneille. Mont Corneille, which is
                    433 feet above the Place de Breuil (in the lower town), is a steep rock of
                    volcanic breccia, surmounted by a colossal iron statue of the Virgin (53 feet
                    high, standing on a pedestal 23 feet high), cast after a model by Bonassieux out
                    of 213 guns taken at Sebastopol. The monument is composed of eighty parts fitted
                    together and weighs 98∣ tons. Another statue, that of a bishop of Puy, also
                    sculptured by Bonassieux, faces that of the Virgin. From the platform of Mont
                    Corneille a magnificent panoramic view is obtained of the town, and of the
                    volcanic mountains, which make this region one of the most interesting parts of
                    France. The Romanesque cathedral (Notre Dame), dating from the 6th to the 12th
                    century, has a particoloured façade of white sandstone and black volcanic
                    breccia, which is reached by a flight of sixty steps, and consists of three
                    tiers, the lowest composed of three high arcades opening into the porch beneath
                    the nave of the church; above are three windows lighting the nave; and these in
                    turn are surmounted by three gables, two of which, those to the right and the
                    left, are of open work. Two side porches lead to the cathedral by the transept
                    The bell-tower (184 feet), which rises behind the choir in seven stories, is one
                    of the most beautiful examples of the Romanesque transition period. The bays of
                    the nave are covered in by octagonal cupolas; the central cupola forms a
                    lantern. The choir and transepts are barrel-vaulted. The cathedral has mural
                    paintings of the 12th and 13th centuries, an open-work Romanesque screen
                    surrounding the sanctuary, and a manuscript Bible belonging to the 9th century.
                    The cloister, to the north of the choir, is striking <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n132/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0132-0119"/> owing to its variously-coloured materials and
                    elegant shafts; Viollet le Duc considers one of its galleries to belong to the
                    oldest known type of cathedral cloister (8th and 9th centuries). Connected with
                    the cloister are remains of fortifications of the 13th century, by which it was
                    separated from the rest of the city. Near the cathedral the baptistery of St
                    John (4th century), built on the foundations of a Roman building, is surrounded
                    by walls and numerous remains of the period, partly uncovered by recent
                    excavations. The church of St Lawrence (14th century) contains the remains of Du
                    Guesclin. Le Puy possesses fragmentary remains of its old line of
                    fortifications, among them a machicolated tower, which has been restored, and a
                    few curious old houses dating from the 12th to the 17th century. Of the modern
                    monuments the statue of La Fayette and a fountain in the Place de Breuil,
                    executed in marble, bronze, and syenite, may be specially mentioned. The museum,
                    named after Crozatier, a native metal-worker to whose munificence it principally
                    owes its existence, contains antiquities, engravings, a collection of lace, and
                    ethnographical and natural history collections. Among the curiosities of Puy
                    should be noted the church of St Michel d’Aiguille, beside the gate of the town,
                    perched on an isolated rock like Mont Corneille, the top of which is reached by
                    a staircase of 271 steps. The church dates from the end of the 10th century and
                    its chancel is still older. The steeple is of the same type as that of the
                    cathedral. Three miles from Puy are the ruins of the Château de Polignac, one of
                    the most important feudal strongholds of France. The population of Puy in 1881
                    was 18,567. The trade is chiefly in cattle, woollens, grains, and vegetables.
                    The principal manufacture is that of laces and blondes (in woollen, linen,
                    cotton, silk, gold, and silver threads), which is carried on by 130,000
                    workwomen in the neighbourhood, the yearly turnover being £1,000,000. The town
                    is connected by rail with St Étienne and Lyons, and also with Brioude on the
                    line from Clermont-Ferrand to Nîmes.</p>
                <p>It is not known whether Le Puy existed previously to the Roman invasion. Towards
                    the end of the 4th or beginning of the 5th century it became the capital of the
                    country of the Vellavi, at which period the bishopric, originally at Revession,
                    now St Paulien, was transferred hither. Gregory of Tours speaks of it by the
                    name of Anicium, because a chapel “ad Deum” had been built on the mountain,
                    whence the name of Mont Adidon or Ani, which it still retains. In the 10th
                    century it was called Podium Sanctae Mariae, whence Le Puy. In the Middle Ages
                    there was a double enclosure, one for the cloister, the other for the town. The
                    sanctuary of Notre Dame was much frequented by pilgrims, and the city grew
                    famous and populous. Rivalries between the bishops (who held directly of the see
                    of Rome) and the lords of Polignac, revolts of the town against the royal
                    authority, and the encroachments of the feudal superiors on municipal
                    prerogatives often disturbed the quiet of the town. The Saracens in the 8th
                    century, the Routiers in the 12th, the English in the 14th, the Burgundians in
                    the 15th, successively ravaged the neighbourhood. Le Puy sent the flower of its
                    chivalry to the crusades in 1096, and Raymond d’Aiguille, called d’Agiles, one
                    of its sons, was their historian. Many councils and various assemblies of the
                    states of Languedoc met within its walls; popes and sovereigns, among the latter
                    Charlemagne and Francis I., visited its sanctuary. Pestilence and the religious
                    wars put an end to its prosperity. Long occupied by the Leaguers, it did not
                    submit to Henry J V. until many years after his accession.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
