<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0920-0033-0020-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PRUSSIA, Rhenish (9th edition, volume 20, page
                    20)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn40532">Walloons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1097054">Rhinelanders</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210278">Belgium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n33/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PRUSSIA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Rhenish</hi></label> (German,
                    <hi rend="italic">Rhewpreussen,</hi><hi rend="italic">Rhein</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">provinz,</hi><hi rend="italic">Rheinland),</hi> the most westerly
                    province of the kingdom of Prussia, is bounded on the N. by Holland, on the E.
                    by Westphalia, Hesse-Nassau, and Hesse-Darmstadt, on the S.E. by the Rhenish
                    Palatinate, on the S. and S.W. by Lorraine, and on the W. by Luxemburg, Belgium,
                    and Holland. The small district of Wetzlar in the midst of the province of Hesse
                    also belongs to Rhenish Prussia, which, on the other hand, surrounds the
                    Oldenburg principality of Birkenfeld. The extent of the province is 10,420
                    square miles, or nearly twice that of the kingdom of Saxony; its extreme length,
                    from north to south, is nearly 200 miles and its greatest breadth is just under
                    90. It includes about 200 miles of the course of the Rhine, which forms the
                    eastern frontier of the province from Bingen to Coblentz and then flows through
                    it in a north-westerly direction.</p>
                <p>The southern and larger half of Rhenish Prussia, belonging geologically to the
                    Devonian formations of the lower Rhine, is hilly. On the left bank are the
                    elevated plateaus of the Hundsrück and the Eifel, separated from each other by
                    the deep valley of the Moselle, while on the right bank are the spurs of the
                    Westerwald and the Sauerland, the former reaching the river in the picturesque
                    group known as the Seven Mountains. The highest hill in the province is the
                    Walderbeskopf (2670 feet) in the Hochwald, and there are several other summits
                    above 2000 feet on the left bank, while on the right there are few which attain
                    a height of 1600 feet. Most of the hills are covered with trees, but the Eifel
                    is a barren and bleak plateau, with numerous traces of volcanic agency, and is
                    continued towards the north-west by the moorlands of the Hohe Venn. To the north
                    of a line drawn from Aix-la-Chapelle to Bonn the province is flat, and marshy
                    districts occur near the Dutch frontier. The climate varies considerably with
                    the configuration of the surface. That of the northern lowlands and of the
                    sheltered valleys is the mildest and most equable in Prussia, with a mean annual
                    temperature of 50° Fahr,, while on the hills of the Eifel the mean does not
                    exceed 44°. The annual rainfall varies in the different districts from 18 to 32
                    inches. Almost the whole province belongs to the basin of the Rhine, but a small
                    district in the north-west is drained by affluents of the Meuse. Of the numerous
                    tributaries which join the Rhine within the province, the most important are the
                    Nahe, the Moselle, and the Ahr on the left bank, and the Sieg, the Wupper, the
                    Ruhr, and the Lippe on the right. The only lake of any size is the Laacher See,
                    the largest of the “maare” or extinct crater lakes of the Eifel.</p>
                <p>Of the total area of the Rhenish province about 46 ’ 5 per cent, is occupied by
                    arable land, 17 per cent, by meadows and pastures, and 31 per cent, by forests.
                    Little except oats and potatoes can be raised on the high-lying plateaus in the
                    south of the province, but the river-valleys and the northern lowlands are
                    extremely fertile. The great bulk of the soil is in the hands of small
                    proprietors, and this is alleged to have had the effect of somewhat retarding
                    the progress of scientific agriculture. The usual cereal crops are, however, all
                    grown with success, and tobacco, hops, flax, rape, hemp, and beetroot (for
                    sugar) are cultivated for commercial purposes. Large quantities of fruit are
                    also produced. The vine-culture occupies a space of 30,000 acres, about half of
                    which are in the valley of the Moselle, a third in that of the Rhine itself, and
                    the rest mainly on the Nahe and the Ahr. The choicest varieties of Rhine wine,
                    however, such as Johannisberger and Steinberger, are produced higher up the
                    river, beyond the limits of the Rhenish province. In the hilly districts more
                    than half the surface is sometimes occupied by forests, and large plantations of
                    oak are formed for the use of the bark in tanning. Considerable herds of cattle
                    are reared on the rich pastures of the lower Rhine, but the number of sheep in
                    the province is comparatively small, and is, indeed, not greatly in excess of
                    that of the goats. The wooded hills are well stocked with deer, and a stray wolf
                    occasionally finds its way from the forests of the Ardennes into those of the
                    Hundsrück. The salmon fishery of the Rhine is very productive and trout abound
                    in the mountain streams. (Compare the agricultural tables under <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Prussia,</hi> p. 14 <hi rend="italic">supra.)</hi></p>
                <p>The great mineral wealth of the Rhenish province probably furnishes its most
                    substantial claim to the title of the “richest jewel in the crown of Prussia.”
                    Besides parts of the Carboniferous measures of the Saar and the Ruhr, it also
                    contains important deposits of coal near Aix-la-Chapelle. Iron occurs abundantly
                    near Coblentz, the Bleiberg in the Eifel possesses an apparently
                    inex-häustible<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit20newyrich/page/n34/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0920-0034-0021"/> supply of lead, and zinc is found near Cologne
                    and Aix-la-Chapelle. The mineral products of the district also include lignite,
                    copper, manganese, vitriol, lime, gypsum, volcanic stones (used for
                    mill-stones), and slates. In 1882 the total value of the minerals raised in the
                    province was £5,460,000, or nearly one-third of the produce of Prussia; by far
                    the most important item is coal, the output of which was upwards of 15,000,000
                    tons, valued at &lt;£4,400,000. Of the numerous mineral springs the best known
                    are those of Aix-la-Chapelle and Kreuznach.</p>
                <p>The mineral resources of Rhenish Prussia, coupled with its favourable situation
                    and the facilities of transit afforded by its great waterway, have made it the
                    most important manufacturing district in Germany. The industry is mainly
                    concentrated round two chief centres, Aix-la-Chapelle and Düsseldorf (with the
                    valley of the Wupper), while there are naturally few manufactures in the hilly
                    districts of the south or the marshy flats of the north. In the forefront stand
                    the metallic industries, the total produce of which was valued in 1882 at
                    &lt;£5,200,000. The foundries produced upwards of a million tons of iron,
                    besides zinc, lead, copper, and other metals. The largest iron and steel works
                    are at Essen (including Krupp’s cannon-foundry), Oberhausen, Duisburg,
                    Düsseldorf, and Cologne, while cutlery and other small metallic wares are
                    extensively made at Solingen, Remscheid, and Aix-la-Chapelle. The cloth of
                    Aix-la-Chapelle and the silk of Crefeld form important articles of export. The
                    chief industries of Elberfeld-Barmen and the valley of the Wupper are
                    cottonweaving, calico-printing, and the manufacture of turkey red and other
                    dyes. Linen is largely made at Gladbach, leather at Malmedy, glass in the Saar
                    district, and beetroot sugar near Cologne. Though the Rhineland is <hi
                    rend="italic">par excellence</hi> the country of the vine, no less than
                    52,000,000 gallons of beer were brewed in the province in 1882-83, equivalent to
                    an annual consumption of fifty-one quarts per head of population; distilleries
                    are also numerous, and large quantities of sparkling Moselle are made at
                    Coblentz, chiefly for exportation to England. Commerce is greatly aided by the
                    navigable rivers, a very extensive network of railways, and the excellent roads
                    constructed during the French régime. The imports consist mainly of raw material
                    for working up in the factories of the district, while the principal exports are
                    coal, fruit, wine, dyes, cloth, silk, and other manufactured articles of various
                    descriptions.</p>
                <p>The population of Rhenish Prussia in 1880 was 4,074,000, including 2,944,186
                    Roman Catholics, 1,077,173 Protestants, and 43,694 Jews. The Roman Catholics
                    muster strongest on the left bank, while on the right bank about half the
                    population is Protestant. The distribution of the confessions is, however,
                    somewhat sporadic, owing to the varied histories of the constituent parts of the
                    province. The great bulk of the population is of Teutonic stock, and about a
                    quarter of a million are of Flemish blood. On the north-west frontier reside
                    about 12,000 Walloons, who speak French or Walloon as their native tongue. The
                    Rhine province is the most thickly populated part of Prussia, the general
                    average being 390 persons per square mile, while in the government district of
                    Düsseldorf the proportion rises to 754. The province contains a greater number
                    of large towns than any other province in Prussia, and 62 <hi rend="superscript"
                    > ,</hi> 5 of the population is returned as urban. Upwards of half the
                    population are supported by industrial and commercial pursuits, and barely a
                    quarter by agriculture. There is a university of good standing at Bonn, and the
                    success of the elementary education is borne witness to by the fact that in 1883
                    only 0'19 per cent, of the Rhenish recruits were unable to read and write. For
                    purposes of administration the province is divided into the five districts of
                    Coblentz, Düsseldorf, Cologne, Aix-la-Chapelle, and Treves; Coblentz is the
                    official capital, though Cologne is the largest and most important town. In the
                    greater part of the province the Code Napoléon, introduced under the French
                    régime, is still in force. Being a frontier province the Rhineland is strongly
                    garrisoned, and the Rhine is guarded by the four strong fortresses of Cologne
                    with Deutz, Coblentz with Ehrenbreitstein, Wesel, and Saarlouis. In the Prussian
                    parliament the province of the Rhine is represented by twenty-seven members in
                    the upper house and eighty-two in the lower.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History. —</hi> The present province of Rhenish Prussia was
                    formed in 1815 out of the duchies of Cleves, Berg, Upper Guelders, and Jülich,
                    the ecclesiastical principalities of Treves and Cologne, the free cities of
                    Aix-la-Chapelle and Cologne, and nearly a hundred small independent lordships,
                    knightships, and abbeys. It is therefore manifestly impracticable to give more
                    than a broad general sketch of the historical development of a region of which
                    the component parts have had so little of their past in common. At the earliest
                    historical period we find the territories between the Ardennes and the Rhine
                    occupied by the Treviri, Eburones, and other Celtic tribes, who, however, were
                    all more or less modified and influenced by their Teutonic neighbours. On the
                    right bank of the Rhine, between the Main and the Lahn, were the settlements of
                    the Mattiaci, a branch of the Germanic Chatti, while farther to the north were
                    the Usipetes and Tencteri. Julius Caesar conquered the tribes on the left bank
                    and Augustus established numerous fortified posts on the Rhine, but the Romans
                    never succeeded in gaining a firm footing on the right bank. Under the Romans
                    the districts to the west of the Rhine, forming parts of the provinces of
                    Belgica Prima, Germania Superior, and Germania Inferior, enjoyed great
                    prosperity and reached a high degree of civilization. Several Roman emperors
                    resided and issued their edicts at Treves, the capital of Belgica Prima, and the
                    important Roman remains in this city as well as in other parts of the province
                    give an idea of the material benefits the territory derived from their dominion.
                    As the power of the Roman empire declined the Franks pushed forward along both
                    banks of the Rhine, and by the end of the 5th century had regained all the lands
                    that had formerly been under Teutonic influence. The German conquerors of the
                    Rhenish districts were singularly little affected by the culture of the
                    provincials they subdued, and all traces of Roman civilization were submerged in
                    a new flood of paganism. By the 8th century the Frankish dominion was firmly
                    established in central Germany and northern Gaul; and under the Carlovingiau
                    monarchs the Rhineland, and especially Aix-la-Chapelle, plays a rôle of
                    considerable prominence. On the division of the Carlovingian realm the part of
                    the Rhenish province to the east of the river fell to the share of Germany,
                    while that to the west remained with the evanescent middle kingdom of
                    Lotharingia. By the time of Otho I. (936-973) both banks of the Rhine had become
                    German, and the Rhenish territory was divided between the duchies of Upper and
                    Lower Lorraine, the one on the Moselle and the other on the Meuse. Subsequently,
                    as the central power of the German sovereign became weakened, the Rhineland
                    followed the general tendency and split up into numerous small independent
                    principalities, each with its separate vicissitudes and special chronicles. The
                    old Lotharingian divisions passed wholly out of use, and the name of Lorraine
                    became restricted to the district that still bears it. In spite of its
                    dismembered condition, and the sufferings it underwent at the hands of its
                    French neighbours in various periods of warfare, the Rhenish territory prospered
                    greatly and stood in the foremost rank of German culture and progress.
                    Aix-la-Chapelle was fixed upon as the place of coronation of the German
                    emperors, and the ecclesiastical principalities of the Rhine bulk largely in
                    German history. Prussia first set foot on the Rhine in 1609, when it acquired
                    the duchy of Cleves; and about a century later Upper Guelders and Mors also
                    became Prussian. At the peace of Basel in 1795 the whole of the left bank of the
                    Rhine was resigned to France, and in 1806 the Rhenish princes all joined the
                    Confederation of the Rhine. The congress of Vienna assigned the whole of the
                    lower Rhenish districts to Prussia, which had the tact to leave them in
                    undisturbed possession of the liberal institutions they had become accustomed to
                    under the republican rule of the French. (Compare <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Rhine.)</hi> (J. F. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
