<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-3879-0368-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HIMALEH, or Himalaya (7th edition, volume 11, page
                    368)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1121907">Snow</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851789">Chains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996970">Levellers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996964">Leveling</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rn70">Snow</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f63">Chains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61762">Leveling</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193643879?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HIMALEH, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Himalaya</hi></label>
                    (literally the <hi rend="italic">Seat of Snow),</hi> sometimes <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Himachal</hi><hi rend="italic">(Snowy Mountains),</hi> are the
                    names given to a vast range of lofty mountains which separates India from the
                    two Thibets, and forms the highest part of that extended chain which was known
                    to the ancient writers of Europe by the names of <hi rend="italic">Imaus</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">Emodus,</hi> which is, in all probability, a corruption of the
                    Sanscrit name; as <hi rend="italic">“</hi><hi rend="italic">Imaus,"</hi> says
                    Pliny, “in the language of the natives, signifies <hi rend="italic"
                    >snowy!</hi></p>
                <p>If we consider the Himalaya as extending from the defile near Cashmere through
                    which the Setlij or Sutledge flows, to that through which the Brahmapootra
                    passes, the length will be, from north-west to south-east, nearly 1000 British
                    miles; the western extremity being about the latitude 32°, and longitude 77°;
                    the eastern about the latitude 24°, and longitude 95°. Throughout the whole of
                    this extent their snow-capt summits present a succession of peaks of great but
                    unequal elevation, some of which, in the fine pure atmosphere of Hindustan, are
                    visible at an almost incredible distance. “The southernmost ridge of the Bootan
                    Mountains,” says Major Rennell, “rises near a mile and a half perpendicular
                    above the plains of Bengal, in a horizontal distance of only fifteen miles; and,
                    from the summit, the astonished traveller looks back on the plains, as on an
                    extensive ocean beneath him.” Beyond is a chain of peaks still higher, which, he
                    adds, “are visible from the plains of Bengal, at the distance of 150 miles, and
                    are commonly covered with snow.” From these expressions, and from his conclusion
                    of their being “in point of elevation equal to any of the mountains of the old
                    hemisphere,” it is quite clear that this celebrated geographer had no adequate
                    idea of their real height.</p>
                <p>On the northern termination of the plains of Hindustan is a narrow belt of a
                    thickly wooded, swampy country, called Terreeana, between which and the base of
                    the great Himalaya chain lies a broad tract of a rugged, mountainous region,
                    from sixty to a hundred miles in width, full of fertile and well-peopled
                    valleys, and once divided into a number of petty states, which are now mostly
                    absorbed by the British or the Chinese empires; the latter at least laying claim
                    to some of the hilly countries to the south of the Himalaya, as tributary
                    states, to which our recent conquests have brought us into immediate contact.
                    Beginning at the westward, the principal of these states were Serinagur, Almora,
                    Kemaoon, Gorkah, Nepaul, and Bootan: all of these are parts of the mountainous
                    belt, and their towns and fortresses occupy the summits of hills rising to the
                    height of from 4000 to 6000 feet; and many of the shoulders or abutments which
                    connect these hills with the lofty range of Himalaya are from 8000 to 14,000
                    feet high. The great extent of these mountain masses produces a greater degree
                    of cold in winter than would probably be found in the same degree of latitude in
                    Europe at an equal elevation; and, as will presently appear, a greater degree of
                    heat also. In the middle of winter the snow covers the summits of those inferior
                    hills, and falls sometimes even in the interjacent valleys; but the climate, in
                    every part of this mountainous region, is delightfully fine, and almost all the
                    species of European vegetables are found in a native state, and growing in the
                    greatest luxuriance. In fact, since we have had free access to the base of the
                    Himalaya range, it has been discovered that the general character of the
                    vegetation corresponds very nearly with that of the middle and southern parts of
                    Europe, and that a very large portion of the trees and shrubs of the latter are
                    indigenous in the former; such as pines of various species,oaks,
                    chestnuts,horse-chestnuts, walnuts,birch, the hazel, the raspberry, gooseberry,
                    bilberry, barberry, and strawberries. Many of the flowering shrubs, and the
                    humbler plants, as the polyanthus, anemone, and ranunculus, the common and lemon
                    thyme, mint, sweet basil and a great variety of other aromatic plants, clothe
                    the sides of the hills, and shed their fragrant odours around. Moorcroft
                    mentions the furze <hi rend="italic">(Ulex European,</hi> which was supposed not
                    to be met with out of Europe. These hills may be considered as the roots and
                    branches of the great stem, all of them connected more or less remotely with it,
                    and appearing at a distance, when seen from the plains of Hindustan, as a
                    succession of inferior ranges; but, on entering the country, “the whole,” says
                    Mr Fraser, “becomes a confused and chaotic assemblage of most rugged mountains,
                    huddled into masses and peaks, and running into ridges which defy
                    arrangement.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Journal of a Tour through part of the Snowy Range of the Himalaya
                    Mountains,</hi> 4to, Lonđ. 1820.</p></note></p>
                <p>The highest peaks of the Himalaya Mountains had long been noticed before it was
                    known or even conjectured what their absolute height might be above the level of
                    the sea. All the information respecting them that could be obtained was derived
                    from Hindu pilgrims, who annually flocked to pay their devotions at the shrine
                    of some deity presiding over the various wild and awful features of these
                    elevated regions. To a people gifted, like the Hindus, with strong imaginative
                    faculties, the snow-capt summits of the Himalaya Mountains, and the numerous
                    torrents issuing from their bosom, which, when united into one grand stream,
                    carried fertility over their extensive plains, could not fail to become so many
                    varied objects of their veneration. From the accounts of these people, the main
                    branch of the Ganges was represented to issue from a chasm or cavern in the side
                    of the mountains, to which, from its supposed resemblance to the mouth of an
                    animal sacred in the ritual of their faith, was given the name of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Cow's Mouth.</hi> This cavern was supposed to perforate the great
                    chain of mountains, and the source of the Ganges to be in a lake on the other
                    side, considerably to the eastward of the Cow’s Mouth. This lake was named
                    Manasarovara, and was held sacred; and, under the impression of the relation of
                    pilgrims being correct, the source and passage of the Ganges were laid down in
                    the most improved maps of Hindustan.</p>
                <p>The authority, however, on which this hypothesis rested not being deemed
                    satisfactory, it was determined by the Bengal government that an expedition
                    should be undertaken to ascertain how the fact stood; and Captains Raper and
                    Hearsay, accompanied by Captain Webb, assistantsurveyor, set out in the spring
                    of the year 1808, in order to clear up this point; and from their observations,
                    and those of more recent travellers, it has now been ascertained, that the main
                    sources of the Ganges are all on the southern side of the great Himalaya chain;
                    and that, reckoning from the westward, they consist of, 1. the Jumna (whose two
                    great branches are the Girree and the Touse); 2. the Bhagiruttee, whose source
                    is near the celebrated spot called Gangoutri, where the Cow’s Mouth is supposed
                    to be situated; and, 3. the Alkananda, with its numerous tributary streams, the
                    last of which rivers is now acknowledged as the main branch of the Ganges.</p>
                <p>The object of Captains Raper and Hearsay was to penetrate as far as possible to
                    the sources of the two great branches, the Bhagiruttee and the Alkananda∙ With
                    great difficulty and fatigue they approached near enough to Ga∏- goutri to
                    enable them to conclude, from the contraction of the stream, and the stupendous
                    height and unbroken sides of the Himalaya Mountains, that “there can be no doubt
                    but the source of that branch is situated <hi rend="italic">in</hi> the snowy
                    range;” and that “any other hypothesis can scarcely be reconciled to
                    hydrostatical principles.” Not quite satisfied, however, with this conclusion,
                    they dispatched one of those <pb break="no" facs="nls:193643892?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-3892-0369"/> fanatics of India, known by the name of Fakirs,
                    who deem a pilgrimage to Gangoutri to have the effect of redeeming the person
                    performing it from all the troubles of this life, and of ensuring him a happy
                    passage through all the stages of transmigration which he is destined to undergo
                    in another, to push his inquiries farther into the mountains. This man reported,
                    on his return, that, a few miles beyond Gangoutri, the river was lost under vast
                    beds of snow, and that a rock in the midst of the rushing stream resembled the
                    body and head of a cow; and here the valley was terminated by the steep and
                    wall-sided mountain.</p>
                <p>The party next set out in order to trace the other great stream of the Ganges,
                    the Alkananda, and succeeded in reaching a spot four or five miles beyond the
                    temple of Bhadrinath, where the stream was narrowed to eighteen or twenty feet,
                    and where “the north faces of the mountains were completely covered with snow
                    from the summit to the base.” A little way beyond this place was a cascade named
                    Barsiè d’Hara, where the Alkananda (or, as sometimes called, the Vishnuganga)
                    was entirely concealed under immense heaps of snow, beyond which no traveller
                    has been known to pass. Yet this place was estimated to be still distant about
                    twenty miles from the southern front of the Himalaya chain. In these lofty
                    regions, beyond Bhadrinath, stands the populous town <hi rend="italic">of</hi>
                    Manah, consisting of two hundred houses; the inhabitants of a different race
                    from the generality of the mountaineers; and, from their broad faces, small
                    eyes, and olive-coloured complexions, evidently of a Tartar origin. Seven
                    hundred villages are said to be attached to the temple of Bhadrinath, whose
                    sanctity may be estimated by the fact of no less than 40,000 pilgrims, chiefly
                    fakirs, having visited it that year.</p>
                <p>Not less holy in the estimation of the Hindus, though less frequented from the
                    difficulty of access, is the source of the main stream of the Alkananda, named
                    the Cali-gunga, near which is situated the temple of Kedar-nath, at an elevation
                    of 12,000 feet nearly above the level of the sea. This place was not visited by
                    Messrs Raper and Hearsay, but its height was ascertained barometrically by
                    Captain Webb.</p>
                <p>Though this expedition threw considerable light on the nature of the country
                    between the plains of Hindustan and the southern base of the Himalaya Mountains,
                    and succeeded in tracing two of the most considerable branches of the Ganges
                    nearly to their sources, still the great chain of the Himalaya itself had not
                    yet been approached, and the altitude of its various peaks above the level of
                    the sea remained undecided. The account however given by Captain Raper <hi
                    rend="italic">(Asiatic Researches,</hi> vol. xii.) is full of interesting and
                    important details.</p>
                <p>The task of penetrating this vast chain was left to the exertions of a more
                    daring traveller. Mr Moorcroft, accompanied by Captain Hearsay, the same who had
                    been on the former expedition, and by a Hindu pundit of the name of Harkh Deo,
                    set out with the hope of finding a passage across these mountains into the
                    regions of Tartary, in order to purchase horses and the shawl-goat, and, at the
                    same time, to collect such geographical information respecting these unknown
                    regions as might fall within their reach. With the latter view, the learned
                    pundit was engaged for the express purpose of <hi rend="italic">striding</hi>
                    over these mountainous regions, along the whole route, in regular paces of four
                    feet each; a task which, it seems, he performed with exemplary patience and
                    perseverance, across rocks, and rivers, and the most rugged precipices, without
                    failing or faultering, except on one single occasion, where a piece of rock had
                    slipped out of a narrow ledge on the very verge of a tremendous declivity, and
                    left a gap just wide enough to show an abyss below, of a depth sufficient to
                    appal the stoutest heart.</p>
                <p>Beginning their operations at the point where the Dauli river falls into the
                    Alkananda, they followed up the former to the very base of the Himalaya, and,
                    after eighteen days of excessive fatigue, reached a gorge in the mountains,
                    named the Nitee Ghati, or Pass of Nitee. At some distance below it was a small
                    village of the same name, the great height of which was inferred by the hill,
                    terminating the valley on which it stood, being tipped with snow on the 5th of
                    June, and also by a quick breathing with which Mr Moorcroft was seized, and
                    which obliged him to stop every four or five steps; he complained also of a
                    sense of fulness in the head, accompanied by giddiness. In ascending the Ghaut,
                    the difficulty of breathing increased, with great oppression about the heart;
                    and, when on the point of falling asleep, a sense of suffocation was felt, and
                    sighing became frequent and distressing. The same symptoms of oppression and
                    debility were experienced by Μ. Saussure on the Alps, which he ascribed rather
                    to the presence of carbonic acid gas, than to the tenuity of the atmosphere. We
                    conceive, however, that the great height alone is sufficient to account for
                    these symptoms.</p>
                <p>At Nitee the travellers were informed that the passage of the mountains was never
                    attempted before <hi rend="italic">Sancrant,</hi> or the entrance of the sun
                    into Cancer; they waited, therefore, till the 24th of June. For the last twenty
                    days the thermometer at sun-rise was generally about 46°, at noon 72°, and from
                    that to 80°; the nights were clear and serene; the birch trees and rose bushes
                    were just then bursting into leaf, the furze coming into blossom, and the grain
                    appearing above the ground.</p>
                <p>The length of the Nitee Pass is about two miles; it leads to an elevated plain,
                    to which there is little or no descent, called by the natives Undes or Ondes,
                    which signifies “the country of wood.” The name of Thibet was not known to them,
                    and Captain Webb thinks it may have been derived from <hi rend="italic"
                    >Teiba,</hi> which signifies, in the Gorkah language, “high-peaked mountains.”
                    The mountains crossing this plain, or rising in detached masses out of its
                    surface, were covered with snow. - The first, and indeed the only continued
                    ridge seen by Moorcroft, was at the distance of about forty miles from the
                    Himalaya, and nearly parallel to it, closing, however, gradually upon it to the
                    eastward; but, at the distance of above eighty miles, they united, not far from
                    the two lakes of Rawan-hrad and Manasarovara, which were separated from each
                    other by a slip of land about four or five miles in width. The ridge thus
                    uniting with the Himalaya is named Caillas, which is rather a generic term for
                    any high mountain, than peculiar to a single one, and is among the Hindus what
                    Olympus was among the Greeks.</p>
                <p>The intermediate plain consists of a rugged stony surface, bristled in some
                    places with rude shapeless rocks, and in others scooped out into broad and deep
                    ravines, presenting on every side an extended dreary waste, without a tree or
                    shrub to enliven the prospect, the only vegetation being confined to some low
                    furze bushes, a woolly plant like everlasting, tufts of silky grass, and a
                    species of moss, exhibiting a sickly green, among patches of snow and splashes
                    of snow water. The only enlivening objects that appeared to Mr Moorcroft and his
                    party were “two very beautiful poplar trees, in which were many goldfinches.”
                    These were on the banks of a considerable stream, flowing to the westward, down
                    the middle of the plain, in the bed of which was a species of tamarisk, then in
                    blossom, and reaching to the height of eight feet.</p>
                <p>This river was then conjectured, and has since been ascertained, to be the
                    Sutledge or Satudra. It rises in the lake Rawan-hrad, to the eastward of any of
                    the sources of the Ganges, and, having collected in its western course the
                    various streams from the northern face of the Hima <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193643905?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-3905-0370"/> laya, and the
                    southern face of the Caillas, finds a passage through the former chain, near
                    Mount Kantel, on the eastern side of Cashmere; and, on entering the plain of
                    Hindustan, becomes the easternmost of the Punjab, or Five Rivers, the boundary
                    of our Indian possessions to the westward; and, in its course to the southward,
                    joins the Indus. This source and direction of the Sutledge can now be no longer
                    doubted, as its course, which was ascertained by Mr Baillie Fraser to lie
                    through the great range of mountains, has been traced back through the ravine of
                    the Himalaya, and for a considerable distance to the eastward. On this elevated
                    plain is situated the town of Deba.</p>
                <p>Mr Moorcroft and his party having passed the first tableland, crossed the Caillas
                    range, on the other side of which the rugged plain extended beyond the reach of
                    sight. The numerous streams from the northern face of Caillas, uniting in the
                    vale of Ghertope, form a river of considerable magnitude, which, from
                    information, pursues a northwesterly course for some hundred miles, passes by
                    Latak, and then crossing the Hindu Coosh, which may be considered as a
                    prolongation of the Himalaya, to the westward of Cashmere, assumes the name of
                    Indus or Scinde; of which great river it may be considered as one of the main
                    branches, the other coming from the northward out of the mountains called the
                    Moos-tag.</p>
                <p>Mr Moorcroft did not ascertain what river or rivers flowed <hi rend="italic"
                    >out</hi> of the lake Manasarovara, and seems to think that it has no outlet.
                    This is very improbable, as its water was fresh, and there seems to be little
                    doubt but the Sanpoo, or the main branch of the Brahmapootra, issues from its
                    eastern extremity. In that case, this lake may be considered as about the
                    highest part of the general level of the great plateau of Tartary.</p>
                <p>Thus, by the exertions of intelligent travellers, the geography of the great
                    mountainous buttress which supports the elevated regions of Thibet and Tartary
                    has been pretty well ascertained; but all is still conjecture as far as regards
                    an extensive range of country to the north, the north-west, and north-east of
                    the Caillas range of mountains.</p>
                <p>Neither the ancients, to whom the Himalaya Mountains were well known, nor the
                    Hindus, to whom they have always been the cherished objects of veneration, nor
                    our countrymen, who, from the plains of Bengal, had so often gazed at their
                    snow-capped summits from a distance of 150 miles, ventured to form a conjecture
                    even of their absolute height above the level of those plains. Mr Colebrooke, jn
                    his Note to Captain Raper’s <hi rend="italic">Narrative,</hi> observes that,
                    “without supposing the Himalaya to exceed the Andes, there is still room to
                    argue, that an extensive range of mountains, which rears high above the line of
                    perpetual snow, in an almost tropical latitude, an uninterrupted chain of lofty
                    peaks, is neither surpassed nor rivalled by any other chain of mountains <hi
                    rend="italic">but</hi> the Cordilleras of the Andes.” Shortly after this,
                    however, he thinks the observations of Captain Webb “authorize the opinion, that
                    the Himalaya is the loftiest range of alpine mountains which has yet been
                    noticed, its most elevated peaks <hi rend="italic">exceeding</hi> the highest of
                    the Andes.”</p>
                <p>The highest part of the Himalaya is about the centre of the chain, or between the
                    source of the Bhagiruttee and the valley of Nepaul. From an observation taken by
                    Colonel Crawford (when at Cathmandu, in Nepaul, in 1802) of very small angles at
                    the extremities of a short measured base, it is concluded that one peak, called
                    Ðhaibun, rose to an elevation of 20,140 feet above the spot where the
                    observation was made; which being itself 4500 feet above the level of the sea,
                    would make the height of this peak 24,640 feet. By similar observations, the
                    height of another peak was proved to be 22,319 feet, of another 24,525, another
                    22,952 feet, and of a fifth 23,162 feet, above the level of the sea.</p>
                <p>But the peak which was found to possess the most extraordinary elevation was that
                    called <hi rend="italic">Dhaτvala-giri,</hi> or the White Mountain. By a mean of
                    three observations, taken from the following computed distances, and seen under
                    their respective angles·, namely,</p>
                <p>At station A, distance 89∙j⅞ <hi rend="superscript"> 5</hi><hi rend="subscript">
                    ττ</hi> miles. Ang. 2° 48'</p>
                <p>B, 102 <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 8</hi> ∕θ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ° l <hi rend="superscript"> θ</hi> ' C, l36 <hi
                    rend="subscript"> τ</hi> ¾⅛ 1° 22/ and, by allowing for refraction, the height
                    of this moun tain is calculated at 27,677 feet above the plains of Go-rak’hpur;
                    which plains being 400 feet above the mouth of the Ganges, it follows that the
                    whole height of Dhawala-giri must be taken at more than 28,000 feet above the
                    level of the sea. By a subsequent calculation, however, the height of this peak
                    was reduced to 26,862 feet. Of this and six other peaks, the following are the
                    results of Mr Colebrooke’s calculations, made from the observations of Captain
                    Webb:</p>
                <p>Feet.</p>
                <p>Dhawala-giri, “on the lowest computation”...26,862 Jamunawatari, or Jamautri
                    25,500</p>
                <p>A mountain supposed to be Dhaibun 24,740</p>
                <p>A nameless mountain 22,768</p>
                <p>Another nameless mountain 24,625</p>
                <p>Another, near the last 23,262</p>
                <p>A third, in its vicinity 23,052</p>
                <p>These heights are probably exaggerated; it appears, indeed, that subsequent
                    observations, made by Captain Webb, with an excellent instrument, from the
                    extremities of a well-determined and sufficient base, have decided them to be
                    so. They make, for instance, the height of the first “nameless mountain” in the
                    above table only 21,000 feet above the plains of Rohilkhunđ, or 21,500 above the
                    level of the sea, being a deduction from Mr Colebrooke’s calculation, for the
                    same mountain, of 1268 feet.</p>
                <p>The following table exhibits the results of Captain Webb’s corrected
                    observations, of no less than twentyseven different peaks of the Himalaya range,
                    as taken in the progress of his survey of Kumaon, but for the accuracy of which
                    he candidly admits it would be impossible to vouch, in all the circumstances
                    under which the observations were taken. They are, however, in all probability,
                    not far from the truth:</p>
                <p>No. of Peak. Altitude. No. of Peak. Altitude.</p>
                <p>1 22,345 15 22,419</p>
                <p>2 22,058 16 17,994</p>
                <p>3 22,840 17 19,153</p>
                <p>4 21,611 18 21,439</p>
                <p>5 19,106 ] 9 22,635</p>
                <p>6 22,498 20 20,407</p>
                <p>7 22,578 21 19,099</p>
                <p>8 23,164 22 19,497</p>
                <p>9 21,311 23 22,727</p>
                <p>10 15,733 24 22,238</p>
                <p>11 20,68 1 25 22,277</p>
                <p>12 23,263 26 21,045</p>
                <p>13 22,313 27 20,923</p>
                <p>14 25,669</p>
                <p>After these trigonometrical deductions had been made, Captain Webb had the good
                    fortune to succeed in making several barometrical observations in the Nitee
                    Pass, through which Moorcroft had reached the plateau of Tartary. In his way
                    thither he reached nearly the base of those lofty peaks of the Himalaya which
                    tower above the temple of Kedar-nath, and the altitudes of which are amongst
                    those previously determined by triangulation, at a great distance, and seen
                    under very small angles. He had, however, at this place, the advantage of
                    observing one of these peaks under an angle of 2b <hi rend="superscript"> o</hi>
                    15' 15''; and <pb break="no" facs="nls:193643918?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-3918-0371"/> this, he says, gave him a result that agreed as
                    well as could be expected with the position and altitude he had formerly
                    assigned to it. The temple itself, by the mean of five barometers, was found to
                    be 11,897 feet above the level of Calcutta, or about 12,000 above that of the
                    sea, vet no snow lay near it in the beginning of July.</p>
                <p>Captain Webb next proceeded to Josimuth, near the commencement of the defile
                    leading to the Nitee Pass, where hc met with one of the civil servants of the
                    East India Company proceeding on a mission to the frontier, with a view of
                    opening a commercial intercourse with the Tartars. These subjects of China,
                    however, declined all connection with us, and pushed forward picquets of cavalry
                    to guard the pass. This untoward circumstance did not deter Captain Webb from
                    proceeding. On approaching the pass he experienced the same difficulty of
                    breathing which occurred to Moorcroft, and from the influence of which, he says,
                    neither horses nor yaks are exempt. The natives call it <hi rend="italic"
                    >Eis-Kee-huiva,</hi> or the poisonous atmosphere; and conceive it to be owing to
                    the effluvia of certain flowers.</p>
                <p>He found in the pass a troop of Tartar cavalry, who, with some inhabitants of
                    Deba, received him kindly, and consented to let him remain until an answer
                    should be received from Ghertope respecting his farther progress, which, at the
                    end <hi rend="italic">of</hi> fifteen days, was <hi rend="italic">a</hi>
                    negative, or, which amounted to the same thing, a reference to the viceroy of
                    Lassa. He had been permitted, however, to proceed to the crest or highest ridge
                    <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the Nitee Ghaut, which is at or near its farthest
                    extremity, and to make his observations, which are exceedingly interesting and
                    important. On the 21st of August, at three p. <hi rend="smallcaps">μ.,</hi> by
                    the mean of four barometers, the mercury stood at 16,27 inches, and the
                    thermometer at 47°; and on the same day and hour, and the two preceding and
                    following days, the state <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the barometer and
                    thermometer at Dumdum, about fifty feet above the sea, by a journal of the
                    weather kept by Colonel Hardwicke, was as follows:</p>
                <p>Aug. 19, barometer 29,46 inches. Ther∙ 88°</p>
                <p>20 29,46 84</p>
                <p>21 29,48 85</p>
                <p>22 29,48 84</p>
                <p>23 29,65 81</p>
                <p>Mean 29,51 84∙4</p>
                <p>From which the Nitee Ghaut above Dumdum must be 16,764 feet, and above the sea
                    16,814 feet. Yet, at this extraordinary elevation, not a vestige of snow
                    appeared in the Ghaut, nor on the shoulder of the ridge on the left of the pass,
                    which rose to the height of 300 feet above it; and hence it would appear that
                    the lower point of congelation, on the northern or Tartarian side of the
                    Himalaya, is <hi rend="italic">not less than seventeen thousand feet.</hi></p>
                <p>From the crest of the Ghaut Captain Webb was able to perceive the line of the
                    Sutledge winding through the plain to the westward, and to take the angle of
                    depression, from which, and Moorcroft’s distance (generally found to be
                    correct), he determined the elevation of this lowest part of the table-land of
                    Thibet to be 15,924 feet. The angle of đepresssion was 1° 28' 10", and the
                    distance 15^ British miles. Notwithstanding this enormous elevation of 15,000
                    feet, the banks of the Sutledge afford the finest pastures for myriads of
                    quadrupeds; and crops of a species of barley called <hi rend="italic">ooa,</hi>
                    from which the natives make their bread, are annually produced. Nay more; on the
                    cheeks of the Nitee Pass plants were found that ripened their seed at the height
                    of 17,000 feet. These singular anomalies, so utterly at variance with the
                    theories of Humboldt, Leslie, Kirwan, and all European writers on the subject,
                    can only be explained with reference to the great radiation of heat from that
                    vast extent of elevated land that rises out of Central Asia like the boss of a
                    shield, creating as it were a new atmosphere of its own. “As the heat,” says the
                    Baron de Humboldt, “of high regions of the atmosphere depends on the radiation
                    of the plains, it is conceived that, under the same geographical parallel, çne
                    may not find in the system of transatlantic climates the isothermal lines of the
                    same elevation above the level of the sea, as in the system of European
                    climates.” For the same reason, the system will apply still less to the climates
                    of Central Asia. The same philosopher has observed, that the Cordilleras of the
                    Andes, though they extend from north to south 120 degrees of latitude, are,
                    generally speaking, not more than from two to three, and very rarely from four
                    to five degrees in breadth; but the vast surface of table-land, supported by the
                    great Himalaya buttress, stretching from Daouria on the east, to Belur-tagh on
                    the west, through 47 degrees of longitude, and from the Altai on the north, to
                    the Himalaya on the south, through a mean breadth of 20 degrees of latitude,
                    presents a <hi rend="italic">plateau,</hi> more or less elevated, equal to above
                    three millions of square miles.</p>
                <p>In confirmation of the great influence of radiated heat from extensive elevated
                    plains, some strong facts are exhibited both in America and Asia. Thus, on the
                    mountains which rise out of the elevated plain <hi rend="italic">of</hi> Mexico,
                    Humboldt observed the lower line of perpetual congelation, in lat. 19°-20°, at
                    15,090 feet above the sea, which, by the table of Professor Leslie, ought to
                    have been at 13,560, making a difference between fact and theory of 1530 feet.
                    The lower point on the side of Chimboraço, nearly under the equator, was 15,746
                    feet, being only 656 feet higher than on the mountains of Mexico; whereas, by
                    Leslie’s table, the difference ought to be 1729 feet. Compare, again, the height
                    of this lower limit of perpetual congelation on the side of Chimboraço with the
                    observations of Captain Webb in the Nitee Pass, and we have the extraordinary
                    anomaly of a place in Asia, in 30° of latitude, having that limit higher by 1253
                    feet than another place in America immediately under the equinoctial line, and
                    at 5500 feet, or more than a mile, higher than it ought to be in that parallel
                    of latitude, according to the theory on which Professor Leslie constructed his
                    table.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See the article
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Climate.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>It is right to observe, however, that the same anomaly exists, though in a less
                    degree, on the southern face and abutments of the Himalaya range. Thus the
                    elevation of Kedar-nath, at 12,000 feet, is below the verge of perpetual snow,
                    which in Europe, on the same parallel of latitude, would be at 700 feet lower.
                    Thus, also, the village and temple of Milem, in lat. 30° 25', were not only
                    without snow at the height of 11,790 feet, but extensive fields of buckwheat and
                    Tartaric barley were growing at that elevation. In the same degree of latitude
                    the same height in Europe would be some hundred feet within the limits of
                    perpetual snow. At the same height, on the 21st of June, Captain Webb’s
                    encampment was surrounded with flourishing woods of oaks, of the long-leafed
                    pine, and the arborescent rhododendron, and the surface was clothed with a rank
                    vegetation. On the following day he determined the elevation of
                    Pilgointi-Churhai Pass to be more than 12,700 feet above the sea; yet even here
                    no snow was visible, but the black soil was dad with creeping plants; and the
                    shoulder of a mountain rising still higher was without a vestige of snow, and
                    appeared, as far as could be seen through the mist, enamelled with flowers. The
                    reflected heat from the perpendicular face of the immense mass of naked rock, on
                    which snow cannot rest, exposed to the <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193643931?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-3931-0372"/> rays of a
                    south-western sun, will probably be deemed sufficient to explain the anomaly
                    which is found to exist on the southern side of the chain.</p>
                <p>Of the geological strata of these mountains we have notas yet full information.
                    Mr Baillie Fraser, who penetrated to the very base of the great chain, at the
                    head of the Jumna and the Bhagiruttee branches, describes the first and inferior
                    hills of sandstone, more or less destructible, of indurated clay, with beds of
                    rounded pebbles and gravel. The second ridge of hills, rising to the height of
                    1500 to 5000 feet, are sharp, rough, and run into numerous ridges, divided by
                    deep shaggy dells; and the crests of the ridges are frequently so sharp that two
                    persons can hardly stand abreast upon them. Beyond these are a mass of hills
                    entirely composed of limestone, of a round, lumpish, rugged character, whose
                    highest points may be from 5000 to 7000 feet. Next to these commences the
                    schistus, or slate, which continues to the very roots of the Snowy Mountains.
                    All above appeared to be striated hard grey gneiss, and a compact granite,
                    which, Mr Fraser supposes, is the material which constitutes the highest ridges
                    and crests of this great mountain range; but schistus is the rock that mostly
                    predominates. Hot springs are found on both sides of the Himalaya; and copper,
                    lead, and iron, are commonly met with. Gold is also found in the beds of the
                    rivers. Captain Webb obtained the petrified bones of an animal of the deer kind,
                    which were dug out of a bed of gravel, on the side of the Caillas Mountain, at
                    least 16,000 feet above the level of the sea, a height at which, it may safely
                    be asserted, no other organic remains have hitherto been discovered.</p>
                <p>For some further statements of the height of the highest peaks of the Andes, as
                    compared with those of the Himalaya chain, see the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Asia.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
