<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-0629-0118-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HALLER, Albert Van</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 11, page 118</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1164079">Vans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:828168">Basil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1078723">Progress</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w744">Progress</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193640629" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HALLER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Albert Van</hi></label>, an
                    eminent physician, was born at Berne, on the 16th of October 1708. He was the
                    son of an advocate of considerable eminence in his profession. His father had a
                    numerous family, and Albert was the youngest of five sons. From the first period
                    of his education he showed a great genius for almost every kind of literature.
                    To forward the progress of his studies, his father took into his family a
                    private tutor, named Abraham Billodz; and such was the discipline exerted by
                    this pedagogue, that the accidental sight of him at any future period of life
                    excited in Haller great uneasiness, and renewed all his former terrors.
                    According to the accounts which are given us, the progress of Haller’s studies,
                    at the earliest periods of life, was rapid almost beyond belief. When other
                    children were beginning only to read, he was studying Bayle and Moreri; and at
                    nine years of age he was able to translate Greek, and beginning the study of
                    Hebrew. Not long after this, however, the course of his education was somewhat
                    interrupted by the death of his father, an event which happened when he was in
                    the thirteenth year of his age. After this he was sent to the public school at
                    Berne, where he exhibited many specimens of early and uncommon genius. He was
                    distinguished for his knowledge of the Greek and Latin languages; but he was
                    chiefly remarkable for his poetical genius; and his essays in verse, published
                    in the German language, were read and admired throughout the whole empire. In
                    the sixteenth y <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> ear of his age he began the study
                    of medicine at Tubingen, under Duvemoy and Camerarius; and continued there for
                    the space of two years, when the great reputation of Boerhaave attracted him to
                    Leyden. Nor was this distinguished teacher the only man by whose superior
                    abilities he had there an opportunity of profiting. Ruysch was still alive, and
                    Albinus was rising into fame. Animated by such examples, he spent all the day,
                    and the greater part of the night, in the most intense study; and the
                    proficiency which he made gained him universal esteem both amongst his teachers
                    and his fellow students. From Holland he, in the year 1727, proceeded to
                    England, where, however, his stay was but short; and, in fact, it was rather his
                    intention to visit the illustrious men of that period, than to prosecute his
                    studies in London. But he formed connections with some of the most eminent
                    persons of the time. He was honoured with the friendship .of Douglas and
                    Cheselden; and he met with a reception proportioned to his merit from Sir Hans
                    Sloane, president of the Royal Society. After his visit to Britain he proceeded
                    to France, and there, under Winslow and Le Dran, with the latter of whom he
                    resided during his stay in Paris, he had opportunities of prosecuting anatomy,
                    which he had not before enjoyed. But the zeal of the young anatomist was greater
                    than the prejudices of the people at that period, even in the enlightened city
                    of Paris, could tolerate. An information being lodged against him to the police
                    for dissecting dead bodies, he was obliged to cut short his anatomical
                    investigations, and effect a precipitate retreat. Still, however, intent on the
                    further prosecution of his studies, he went to Basil, where he became a pupil of
                    the celebrated Bernoulli.</p>
                <p>Thus improved and instructed by the lectures of the most distinguished teachers
                    of that period, by uncommon natural abilities, and by unremitting industry, he
                    returned to the place of his nativity in the twenty-sixth year of his age. Not
                    long after this he offered himself as a candidate, first for the office of
                    physician to an hospital, and afterwards for a professorship. But neither the
                    character which he possessed before he left his native country, nor the fame
                    which he had acquired and supported whilst abroad, were sufficient to combat the
                    interest opposed to him. He was disappointed in both; and it was even with
                    difficulty that he obtained, in the following year, the appointment of keeper of
                    a public library at Berne. The exercise of this office was indeed by no means
                    suited to his great abilities; but it was agreeable to him, as it afforded him
                    an opportunity for indulging that extensive reading by <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193640642" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0642-0119"/>which he has been so justly
                    distinguished. The neglect of his merit which marked his first outset, neither
                    diminished his ardour for medical pursuits, nor detracted from his reputation
                    either at home or abroad. Soon afterwards he was nominated by King George II. a
                    professor in the university of Göttingen. The duties of this important office he
                    discharged with no less honour to himself than advantage to the public, for the
                    space of seventeen years, and it afforded him an ample field for the exertion of
                    those great talents which he possessed. Extensively acquainted with the
                    sentiments of others respecting the economy of the human body, struck with the
                    diversity of opinions which they held, and sensible that the only means of
                    investigating truth was by careful and candid experiment, he undertook the
                    arduous task of exploring the phenomena of human nature from the original
                    source, viz. life. In these pursuits he was no less industrious than successful,
                    and there was hardly any function of the body on which his experiments did not
                    reflect either a new or a stronger light. Nor was it long necessary for him, in
                    this arduous undertaking, to labour alone. The example of the preceptor inspired
                    his pupils with the same spirit of industrious exertion. Zinn, Zimmerman,
                    Caldani, and many others, animated by a generous emulation, laboured with
                    indefatigable industry to prosecute and to perfect the discoveries of their
                    master. The mutual exertion of the teacher and his students not only tended to
                    forward the progress of medical science, but placed the philosophy of the human
                    body upon a surer and almost entirely new basis. But the labours of Dr Haller,
                    during his residence at Göttingen, were by no means confined to any one
                    department of science. He was not more anxious to be an improver himself, than
                    to instigate others to similar pursuits. To him the anatomicaI theatre, the
                    school of midwifery, the chirurgical society, and the royal academy of sciences
                    at Göttingen, owe their origin. Such distinguished merit could not fail to meet
                    with a suitable reward from the sovereign under whose protection he then taught.
                    The king of Great Britain not only honoured him with every mark of attention
                    which he himself could bestow, but also procured him letters of nobility from
                    the emperor. On the death of Dillenius, he had an offer of the professorship of
                    botany at Oxford; the states of Holland invited him to fill the chair of the
                    younger Albinus; and the king of Prussia was anxious that he should become the
                    successor of Maupertuis at Berlin. Marshal Keith wrote to him in the name of his
                    sovereign, offering him the chancellorship of the university of Halle, vacant by
                    the death of the celebrated Wolff. Count Orloff invited him to Russia, in the
                    name of his mistress the empress, offering him a distinguished place at St
                    Petersburg. The king of Sweden conferred on him an unsolicited honour, by
                    raising him to the rank of knight of the order of the polar star; and the
                    emperor of Germany did him the honour of a personal visit, during which he
                    passed some time with him in the most familiar conversation.</p>
                <p>Thus honoured by sovereigns, revered by men of learning, and esteemed by all
                    Europe, he had it in his power to have held the highest rank in the republic of
                    letters. Yet, declining all the tempting offers which were made to him, he
                    continued at Göttingen, anxiously endeavouring to extend the rising fame of that
                    medical school. But after seventeen years residence in that university, an ill
                    state of health having rendered him less fit for the duties of the important
                    office which he held, he solicited and obtained permission from the regency of
                    Hanover to return to his native city of Berne. His fellow-citizens, who might at
                    first have fixed him amongst themselves, with no less honour than advantage to
                    their city, were now as sensible as others of his superior merit. A pension was
                    settled upon him for life, and he was nominated at different times to fill the
                    most important offices in the state. These occupations, however, did not
                    diminish his ardour for useful improvements. He was the first president, as well
                    as the greatest promoter, of the Economical Society at Berne; and he may be
                    considered as the father and founder of the orphan hospital of that city.
                    Declining health, however, restrained his exertions in the more active scenes of
                    life, and for many years he was confined entirely to his own house. Even this,
                    however, could not put a period to his utility; for, with indefatigable
                    industry, he continued his favourite employment of writing till within a few
                    days of his death, which happened on the 12th of December 1777, in the
                    seventieth year of his age. The works of Haller are, 1. Opuscula Botanica,
                    Göttingen, 1749, in 4to; 2. Historia Stirpium Helvetiae indigenarum incoata,
                    Berne, 1768, in three vols. folio; 3. Opera Minora, Lausanne, 1762-1768, in
                    three vols. 4to; 4. Elementa Physiologiae, Lausanne, 1757-1766, in eight vols.
                    4to; 5. Four <hi rend="italic">Bibliothecae,</hi> containing chronological lists
                    of every book of every age, country, and language, which had come to his
                    knowledge, respecting medicine, with brief analyses and opinions subjoined. Of
                    these he published the Bibliotheca Botanica, Zurich, 1771; Bibliotheca
                    Chirurgica, Berne, 1774; Bibliotheca Anatomica, Zurich, 1774 and 1777, each in
                    two vols. 4to; and the Bibliotheca Medicinae Practicae, Bale, 1776, in three
                    vols. 4to. One of his earliest, and, in his opinion, one of his best works, was
                    his <hi rend="italic">Icones Anatomicae,</hi> which he began to publish in 1743,
                    in fasciculi or numbers, and which principally related to the blood-vessels <hi
                    rend="italic">in situ</hi><hi rend="italic">naturali.</hi> But the reputation of
                    Haller rests chiefly on his <hi rend="italic">Elementa Physiologice</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> a workwhich astonished the learned world by the excellence
                    of its arrangement, the precision of the style, the immense detail into which
                    the author enters on the structure of the parts, the profound discussion of all
                    the opinions previously delivered as to their functions and uses, the exact and
                    prodigiously numerous references to all those passages in authors where allusion
                    was made to the smallest matters connected with the science, and the revolution
                    it almost instantaneously effected in physiology, owing to the substitution of
                    induction for hypothesis. The principle which pervades the work, and which is
                    also the great discovery of the author, is that of irritability, considered as a
                    force peculiar to the fleshy fibre, independently of sensibility properly so
                    called, and distributed in a manner altogether different.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
