<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-9105-0770-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HYDERABAD (7th edition, volume 11, page 770)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cg69">Mahrattas</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f766g40">Sovereigns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193649105?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HYDERABAD</label>, an extensive province of Hindustan, in the
                    Deccan, which is situated principally between the 16th and 19th degrees of north
                    latitude. The name is now-applied generally to all the territories of the nizam,
                    so that it is exceedingly difficult to ascertain its exact limits. This
                    territory composed a considerable portion of the ancient Se-lingana. The country
                    is hilly, but not mountainous, being for the most part an elevated table-land,
                    in consequence of which the climate is colder than might be expected from the
                    latitude. During three months of the year the thermometer at the city of
                    Hyderabad, and in the country to the north, is often as low as45°, 40°, and even
                    35° of Fahrenheit. The country is fertile, and, under proper management, would
                    yield abundantly. But the whole territory is principally rented to powerful
                    zemindars, or is granted in jaghires to the officers of government. This
                    distribution of the landed property, which, with the exception of some portions
                    set aside for charitable purposes, and the estates of the nizam and the
                    different branches ot his family, is in the hands of a few individuals, is
                    supposed to be injurious to agriculture, and of course to the interests of the
                    revenue. The cultivators are wretchedly poor, and are much oppressed by their
                    superiors the holders, who are subject to little or no restraint from their
                    nominal sovereign. Where they ąre properly cultivated, the fields yield
                    excellent crops of wheat, which is transported by the inland carriers to the
                    sea-coast, whence <pb break="no" facs="nls:193649118?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-9118-0771"/> salt is brought in return. The districts acquired
                    by the nizam are particularly rich and fertile. But as agriculture is
                    discouraged by the oppression of the cultivators, commerce is obstructed by
                    heavy and injudicious internal taxes. In 1801 the custom-duties on importation
                    amounted to 15 per cent., which formed the principal revenue of the state; and
                    when the British remonstrated against the impolicy of these internal duties, the
                    nizam evinced the most decided aversion to reduce them, and still more to
                    abolish them, which was the counsel of the British government. It was at length
                    agreed that the tax should be reduced to two and a half per cent. But even the
                    levying of this duty was attended with such oppressions and vexation, that it
                    greatly impeded commerce. At present, the principal trade carried on between the
                    nizam’s dominions and those under the British government, consists in the
                    exportation of cotton to Berar and to the Northern Circars, and also to the
                    markets at Vellore, Arnee, and the vicinity. They bring back salt and salted
                    fish, cloths manufactured in the Northern Cirears, Arnee muslins, and European
                    manufactures; the latter principally for the supply of the British forces
                    subsidised by tlιe nizam, and for clothing his army. The chief towns of this
                    kingdom are Hyderabad, Golcondah, Warangole, Aurungabad, Beder, and Ellichpore.
                    The majority of the people are Hindus; but having been long the seat of a
                    Mahommedan government, a considerable portion of the inhabitants are of that
                    religion.</p>
                <p>This country was formerly subject to the rajahs of Telingana and Bijanagur; but
                    being afterwards conquered by the Mahommedans, was formed into a separate
                    kingdom in the year 1512, under the name of Golcondah, by Mahommed Kooly,
                    originally a Turkish adventurer. In 1687, it was brought under the dominion of
                    Aurungzebe, and was converted into one of the provinces of the Mogul empire,
                    and, with the other five southern provinces, was formed into a viceroyalty,
                    under an officer appointed by the court of Delhi, called the soobahdar of the
                    Deccan. In 1719, a Mogul officer, Cheen Khilij Khan, being appointed to this
                    government, with the title of Nizam al Moolk, or superintendent of the kingdom,
                    collected a large army, and ’got possession of all the strongholds of the
                    Deccan; and setting up for independence, he overawed the emperor Mahommed Shah
                    and his ministers. After the invasion of Nadir Shah in 1739, he left to the
                    Mogul nothing but the name of sovereign; and having made Aurungabad his capital,
                    he died at Boorhanpore in the year 1748, aged 104 years. He was succeeded by his
                    second son, who was assassinated in 1750, and succeeded by his nephew Muzuffer
                    Jung, who was assassinated the following year, and succeeded by his cousin
                    Salabut Jung. He had been confined for ten years by his brother Nizam Ali, who
                    for nearly twenty years was engaged in wars with Hyder Ali, the British, and the
                    Mahrattas, during which his territories were greatly contracted. On the 12th of
                    October 1800, he concluded a treaty offensive and defensive, by which he became
                    a dependent and ally of the British. He agreed to receive into his territories a
                    British force of 8000 infantry and 1000 cavalry; to relinquish to the British
                    the management of all his foreign relations; and, for the regular payment of the
                    troops stationed in his country, to cede certain portions of territory to the
                    British. By a commercial treaty concluded in 1802 with the British, it was
                    agreed, in lieu of all local duties, that a duty of five per cent, should be
                    levied on all articles respectively imported into the territories of each. In
                    1804, after the conclusion of the war with Scindia and the rajah of Nagpoor, the
                    nizam acquired a large accession of territory. At present the nizam’s dominions
                    comprehend the greater part of Berar, the whole of Hyderabad, Nandere, and
                    Beeder, and part of Aurungabad and Bejapoor.</p>
                <p>Towards the Nagpoor territories their limits are marked by the course of the
                    Wurda river, and on the one side of the British by the Krishna and Toombuddra.
                    This territory may be estimated in length at 420 by 220 miles, and contains
                    8,000,000 of inhabitants.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Hyderabad,</hi> the capital of the above-mentioned province
                    of Hyderabad, and of the nizam’s dominions. It is situated on the south side of
                    the Musa river, which runs rapidly during the rains, but in the dry season has
                    scarcely two feet of water. It is said to have been founded about the year 1586
                    by Sultan Mahommed Kootub Shah, who, thinking the air of Golcondah did not agree
                    with his constitution, gave orders for building a new city, which continued to
                    be the residence of the Kootub Shah dynasty till the year 1687, when it was
                    taken by Aurungzebe. The late Nizam Ali was the first of the nizams who made it
                    his residence, and he spent considerable sums in improving it. It is now a large
                    and populous place, about seven miles in circumference, and is surrounded by a
                    stone wall, with towers at the angles and gates, which, though incapable of
                    defence against artillery, is a good protection against the incursions of
                    cavalry. It contains two palaces and some elegant mosques, this having long been
                    the seat of Mahommedanism in the Deccan; and between it and Golcondah there are
                    some handsome tombs. This city possesses large magazines, in which arc deposited
                    the presents received at various times from the different native and European
                    powers, consisting of bales of woollen, casés of glass, glass-ware, China-ware,
                    clocks, watches, &amp;c. of European manufacture. These presents have
                    accumulated during a course of seventy or eighty years, having been received by
                    the father and grandfather of the present nizam as far back as the time of
                    Dupleix and Bussy. Since the late Nizam Ali transferred his residence to
                    Hyderabad, it has experienced no disturbance; and being the residence of the
                    court, has rapidly increased in wealth and population. At present it is
                    estimated to contain 120,000 inhabitants, including the suburbs. The travelling
                    distance from Calcutta by the Northern Circars is 902 miles, by Nagpoor 1043
                    miles, from Madras 352, from Bombay 480, from Delhi 923, from Poonah 387, from
                    Seringapatam 406. Long. 78. 42. E. Lat. 17. 15. N. .</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Hyderabad,</hi> a city of Hindustan, in the province of
                    Sinde, of which it is the capital. The fortress of Hyderabad, which is
                    appropriated solely to the residence of the princes and their families, is
                    situated on a rock the foot of which is washed by a branch of the river Indus,
                    here named the Fulalee. It is of an irregular pentagonal figure, suited to the
                    natural form of the rock, and is defended by round towers, and a high brick wall
                    perforated with loop-holes. The situation is remarkably strong; the sides of the
                    hill being in many places so steep as to render the ascent to the fortress
                    difficult, even though a breach were made in the walls. The weakest point is
                    towards the south-east, opposite a break in the rock from the Fulalee. A dry
                    ditch twelve feet broad protects the northern side. The position is good, and
                    the fortifications adequate to resist any attack of native tooops, though it
                    would not stand a siege of three days against Europeans. There is a good bazar
                    and several handsome mosques within the fort; and although little encouragement
                    is given to industry, the artisans are numerous and skilful. The Ameers, as
                    mentioned by Dr Burnes, who went on a mission to Hyderabad in 1828, pride
                    themselves greatly in the brilliant collection which they possess of jewels and
                    armour. A great part of their treasure consists in rubies, diamonds, pearls, and
                    emeralds, with which their daggers, swords, and matchlocks are adorned, and many
                    of which they wear as rings and clasps oņ different parts of their dresses. The
                    arts connected with this pursuit are encouraged by <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193649131?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-9131-0772"/> them. One or
                    two Persian goldsmiths are engaged at court, where they work in enamel, and
                    contrive expedients to display the jewellery of their masters. They have brought
                    to great perfection the art of inlaying letters of gold on steel. They
                    acknowledge the superiority of the English in the manufacture of gun-locks; and
                    the dress of their princes and nobles consists partly of English cloths.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi rend="italic">Viát to
                    the Court of</hi><hi rend="italic">Sinde,</hi> by J. Burnes, p. 92.</p></note>
                    Hyderabad is situated 130 miles from the sea, on the eastern side of the main
                    stream of the Indus, with which it is connected by the Fulalee at the distance
                    of three miles. The country around Hyderabad rises into hills, although it is
                    level till within a few miles of that city. The Indus is a perpetual source of
                    fertility, affording an inexhaustible supply of water for the irrigation of the
                    fields. The flat country of Sinde is intersected by branches from the main
                    stream, and by canals; and the transition from the parched deserts of Cutch to
                    such a scene of fertility is described by Dr Burnes as affording a very striking
                    contrast. The Fulalee in the month of August is from two and a half to three
                    fathoms deep at Hyderabad, and is covered with boats laden with heavy goods. The
                    population is 20,000. Long. 68. 41. E. Lat. 25. 22. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
