<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-3840-0365-10" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">HIGHMORE, Joseph (7th edition, volume 11, page
                    365)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w922">Writers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cm39">Lawyers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw0c">Pine</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hf8s">Pamphlets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:994346">Lawyers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1064206">Pine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193643840?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">HIGHMORE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph</hi></label>, a painter
                    and writer of some eminence in his day, was born in the parish of St James’s,
                    Garlickhithe, London, on the 13th of June 1692, being the third son of Mr Edward
                    Highmore, a coal-merchant in Thames Street. Having such an early and strong
                    inclination to painting that he could think with pleasure of nothing else, his
                    father endeavoured to gratify him by making a proposal to his uncle, who was
                    serjeant-painter to King William, and with whom Mr, afterwards Sir James
                    Thornhill, had served his apprenticeship. This however was subsequently for good
                    reasons declined, and he was articled as clerk to an attorney in 1707, but so
                    much against his own declared inclination, that in about three years he began to
                    form resolutions of indulging his natural disposition for his favourite art,
                    having continually employed his leisure hours in designing, and in the study of
                    geometry, perspective, architecture, and anatomy, but without any instructors in
                    these branches except books. He had afterwards an opportunity of improving
                    himself in anatomy, by attending the lectures of Mr Cheselden; besides entering
                    himself at the painters’ academy in Great Queen Street, where he remained ten
                    years, and had the honour to be particularly noticed by Sir Godfrey Kneller, who
                    distinguished him by the name of the Young Lawyer. In 1714 his clerkship
                    expired; and in 1715 he began painting as a profession, and settled in the city.
                    In the same year Dr Brook Taylor published his Linear Perspective. On this
                    complete and universal theory our artist grounded his subsequent practice; and
                    it has been generally allowed, that few if any of the profession at that time
                    were so thorough masters of Taylor’s excellent but intricate system. In 1716 he
                    married Susanna, daughter and heiress of Mr Anthony Hiller of Effingham, in
                    Surrey; a young lady in every respect worthy of his choice. As his reputation
                    and business increased, he took a more conspicuous station, by removing to a
                    house in Lincoln’s-Inn-Fields; and an opportunity soon offered of introducing
                    him advantageously to the nobility, by his being desired, by Mr Pine the
                    engraver, to make drawings for his prints of the knights of the bath, upon the
                    revival of that order in 1725. The publication of Pamela in 1744 gave rise to a
                    set of paintings by Highmore, which were engraved by two French engravers, and
                    published by subscription in 1745. In the same year he painted the only original
                    of General Wolfe, who was then about eighteen years of age. FIis Pamela
                    introduced him to the acquaintance and friendship of the excellent author of
                    that work, whose picture he drew, and for whom he painted the only original of
                    Dr Young. In 1750 he had the misfortune to lose his wife. On the first
                    institution of the Academy of Painting and Sculpture, in 1753, he was elected
                    one of the professors; an honour which, on aecount of many avocations, he was
                    induced to decline. In 1754 he published a critieal examination of two paintings
                    by Rubens on the ceiling of the banqueting-house at Whitehall, in which
                    architecture <pb break="no" facs="nls:193643853?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0711-3853-0366"/> is introduced,as far as relates to perspective;
                    together with the discussion of a question which has been the subject of debate
                    amongst painters; printed in 4to∙ Of the numerous portraits which Mr Highmore
                    painted, in an extensive practice of forty-six years, it is impossible and
                    useless to discuss the merits. . Some of the best in the historical branch may,
                    however, be mentioned, viz. Hagar and Ishmael; the Good Samaritan; the Finding
                    of Moses; the Harlowe Family, as described in Clarissa; Clarissa, the portrait
                    mentioned in that work; the Graces Unveiling Nature; the Clementina of
                    Grandison; and the Queen Mother of Edward IV. with her younger son, in
                    Westminster Abbey.</p>
                <p>His principal literary work was his Practice of Perspective, on the principles of
                    Dr Brook Taylor, written many years before, but not published till 1763. In 1765
                    he published Observations on a Pamphlet entitled Christianity not founded on
                    Argument; and in the same year two small volumes of Essays, moral, religious,
                    and miscellaneous, with a translation in prose of Mr Brown’s Latin poem on the
                    immortality of the soul. A strong constitution, and constant attention to his
                    health, prolonged his life and preserved his faculties until his eighty-eighth
                    year, when he gradually ceased to breathe, and, as it were, fell asleep, on the
                    3d of March 1780.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
