<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0574-0555-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TRIAL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 555</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s347">Trials</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1012869">Mayors</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1156290">Trials</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1169489">Wagers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n574/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TRIAL</label>, in law, is the examination of a cause before a
                    court of justice. It is the stage in the cause next after <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Pleading</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.).</hi> Advance in legal development is
                    generally marked by difference in the mode of trial. This was especially the
                    case in the history of Roman law, and it has been the same in England (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Action).</hi> Many forms of trial, notably those by <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Ordeal</hi> (<hi rend="italic">q.v.</hi>), by wager of battle
                    or of law (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Wager),</hi> and by grand assize, have
                    become obsolete, and new forms have been created by legislation in order to meet
                    altered circumstances of society. Up to a very recent date the tendency of the
                    Roman and English systems was in opposite directions. In the former and in
                    systems founded on it, such as the Scotch, trial by the judge became the rule,
                    in the latter trial by judge and jury. But the Judicature and Summary
                    Jurisdiction Acts have recently made considerable innovations upon the old
                    common-law right to trial by <hi rend="smallcaps">Jury</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(q.vf or per pais,</hi> as it was also called. The modes of trial in England
                    are very numerous, as to a certain extent each <hi rend="smallcaps">Court</hi>
                    (<hi rend="italic">q.v.</hi>) has its own procedure. Certain broad rules of
                    justice are observed by all courts, such as that both sides are to be heard, or
                    to have an opportunity of being heard, before decision, and that (unless in very
                    exceptional cases) the trial is to be in public.</p>
                <p>For purposes of convenience rather than as a scientific division trials may be
                    divided into civil and criminal. An ordinary trial in a civil case may be either
                    in a court of appellate jurisdiction (in which case it is perhaps more properly
                    called a hearing), in the High Court of Justice before a judge or referee, or in
                    an inferior court. Where the trial is in a court of first instance, it may be
                    either with or without a jury. In Chancery and Admiralty proceedings a jury is
                    not used, and the right to a jury in the Queen’s Bench Division has been
                    considerably restricted by the Rules of the Supreme Court, 1883, Order xxxvi.
                    Before these rules either party had an absolute right to have issues of fact in
                    an action in that division tried by jury. Now, unless in certain actions, mainly
                    of tort, in which a jury is as of right, a jury can only be obtained by
                    application of a party to the action, subject to the power of the court to
                    direct trial without a jury of any issue requiring prolonged examination of
                    documents or accounts or scientific or local investigation. The question of <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Venue</hi> (<hi rend="italic">q.v.)</hi> in civil actions has
                    ceased to be of importance since the Judicature Acts. Most courts are entitled
                    in proper cases to the assistance of assessors. Trial with assessors is in
                    frequent use in the Admiralty Division. A trial whether by jury or not may be by
                    affidavit or on <hi rend="italic">νiνα voce</hi> evidence. The latter is the
                    rule where the trial is by jury. In a county court a jury of five is allowed in
                    certain cases on application. In other inferior courts of local jurisdiction a
                    jury is sometimes the rule, as in the (London) Lord Mayor’s Court, sometimes
                    not, as in the Chancellor’s Court at Oxford or Cambridge. In criminal cases the
                    trial is by jury, except where a court of <hi rend="smallcaps">Summary
                    Jurisdiction (</hi><hi rend="italic">q.v.)</hi> is empowered to try offences of
                    a comparatively unimportant nature. The right to trial by due process of law
                    before condemnation is secured to the subject by sec. 29 of Magna Charta. A new
                    trial may be ordered in civil actions and in misdemeanours (in the latter case
                    only after conviction of the defendant) on various grounds, the most usual of
                    which are misdirection by the judge, improper admission or rejection of
                    evidence, and the finding of a verdict against the weight of evidence. In
                    actions in the High Court new trials are less liberally granted than was the
                    case before the Judicature Acts, Order xxxix. considerably restricting the
                    right. An application for a new trial of an action is no longer made by <hi
                    rend="italic">ex parte</hi> motion in the first instance, as was the course
                    before 1883, but upon notice of motion. Besides the ordinary modes of trial,
                    there are others of an exceptional nature or of rare occurrence. In a trial by
                    arbitration, the tribunal is chosen by the parties themselves, and they are not
                    entitled to object to the trial as conducted by the arbitrator as long as it
                    conforms to rules of ordinary justice. Peers are tried for treason or felony
                    before the House of Lords, or the court of the Lord High Steward if the trial
                    takes place during the recess of parliament. A trial at bar—a survival of the
                    universal mode of trial before the writ of <hi rend="smallcaps">Nisi Prius</hi>
                    (<hi rend="italic">q.v.</hi>) was given by the Statute of Westminster the
                    Second—takes place before three or four judges of the Queen’s Bench Division,
                    and is in use as of right where the crown is interested in the litigation, or at
                    the discretion of the court in other cases where questions of unusual importance
                    or difficulty are raised. The trial of a petition of right (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Petition,</hi> vol. xviii. p. 705) is now assimilated to that
                    in civil actions. Trials by record, by certificate, and by inspection, though
                    not expressly abolished, appear to have become obsolete. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Impeachment</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> is still a right of the House of
                    Commons, but has not recently been exercised. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Court-Martial</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.</hi>) is the mode of trial for
                    offences committed by persons in the naval or military service of the crown.</p>
                <p>In Scotland and the United States trials are either with or without a jury. The
                    most usual trials in Scotland are those before a judge of the Court of Session
                    or the High Court of Justiciary or in a sheriff court. In the United States
                    trials are either in a United States or a State court; in the latter case they
                    are regulated by State legislation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
