<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0606-0585-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TROLLOPE, Anthony</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 585</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pt4b">Novels</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t32v">Lion</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dz7j">Clerks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:987598">Kindness</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1039784">Novelle</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n606/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TROLLOPE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Anthony</hi></label>
                    (1815-1882), English novelist, was born in Keppel Street, Russell Square,
                    London, according to most authorities, on 24th April 1815; in his own <hi
                    rend="italic">Autobiography</hi> he merely gives the year. His father, a
                    barrister, who had been fellow of New College, Oxford, brought himself and his
                    family into the sorest straits by unbusiness-like habits, by quarrelling with
                    his profession, or at least with the attorneys, and by injudicious speculations,
                    especially in farming. Trollope’s mother, Frances Milton, according to her son,
                    was nearly thirty when she married in 1809. By her husband’s wish she made a
                    strange journey to America in 1827, for the purpose of setting up a kind of
                    fancy shop in Cincinnati, which failed utterly. Her visit, however, furnished
                    her with the means of writing <hi rend="italic">The Domestic Manners of the
                    Americans.</hi> This at once brought her in a considerable sum, and
                    thenceforward she continued to be the mainstay of her family. Her husband being
                    obliged at last actually to fly the country from his creditors, his wife
                    maintained him by her pen, at Bruges, till his death there in 1835. For some
                    time Mrs Trollope wrote chiefly travels; but she soon became known as a
                    novelist, and was very industrious. Her novels, the best of which are probably
                    <hi rend="italic">The Vicar of Wrex-hill</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Widow
                    Barnaby,</hi> are now rarely read, and indeed were never at their best above
                    good circulating library level: they are written with cleverness indeed, and a
                    certain amount of observation, but with many faults of taste, and with an almost
                    total want of artistic completeness and form. Her late beginning, her
                    industrious career (for she wrote steadily for more than thirty years, till her
                    death in October 1863, at Florence), and the entire absence in her of any
                    blue-stocking or <hi rend="italic">femme-savante</hi> weakness would have made
                    her remarkable, even if she had not transmitted, as she undoubtedly did
                    transmit, her talent, much increased, to her children.</p>
                <p>Anthony Trollope was the third son. By his own account few English men of letters
                    have had an unhappier childhood and youth. He puts down his own misfortunes, at
                    Harrow, at Winchester, at Harrow again, and elsewhere, to his father’s pecuniary
                    circumstances, which made his own appearance dirty and shabby, and subjected him
                    to various humiliations. But it is permissible to suspect that this was not
                    quite the truth, and that some peculiarities of temper, of which in after life
                    he had many, contributed to his unpopularity. At any rate he seems to have
                    reached the verge of manhood as ignorant as if he had had no education at all.
                    While living abroad he tried ushership; but at the age of nineteen he was
                    pitchforked by favour (for he could not pass even the ridiculous examination
                    then usual) into the post-office. Even then his troubles were not over. He got
                    into debt; he got into ridiculous entanglements of love affairs, which he has
                    very candidly avowed; he was in constant hot water with the authorities; and he
                    seems to have kept some very queer company, which long afterwards stood him in
                    stead as models for some of his novel pictures. At last in August 1841 he
                    obtained the appointment of clerk to one of the post-office surveyors in a
                    remote part of Ireland, with a very small nominal salary. This salary, however,
                    was practically quadrupled by allowances; living was cheap; and the life suited
                    Trollope exactly, being not office work, which he always hated, but a kind of
                    travelling inspectorship. And here he not only began that habit of hunting which
                    (after a manner hardly possible in the stricter conditions of official work
                    nowadays) he kept up for many years even in England, but within three years of
                    his appointment engaged himself to Miss Rose Heseltine, whom he had met in
                    Ireland but who was of English birth. They were married in June 1844. His
                    headquarters had previously been at Banagher; he was now transferred to
                    Clonmel.</p>
                <p>Trollope had always dreamt of novel-writing, and his Irish experiences seemed to
                    supply him with promising subjects. With some assistance from his mother he got
                    his first two books, <hi rend="italic">The Macdermοts of Ballycloran</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">The Kellys and the O'Kellys,</hi> published, the one in 1847,
                    the other the next year. But neither was in the least a success, though the
                    second perhaps deserved to be; and a third, <hi rend="italic">La Vendee,</hi>
                    which followed in 1850, besides being a much worse book than either, was an
                    equal failure. Trollope made various other literary attempts, but for a time ill
                    fortune attended all of them. Meanwhile he was set on a new kind of post-office
                    work, which suited him even better than his former employment—a sort of roving
                    commission to inspect rural post deliveries and devise their extension, first in
                    Ireland, then throughout the west of England and South Wales. That he did good
                    work is undeniable; but his curious conception of official duty (on his
                    discharge of which he prided himself immensely) is exhibited by his confessions
                    that he “got his hunting out of it,” and that he felt “the necessity of
                    travelling miles enough [he was paid by mileage] to keep his horses.” It was
                    during this work that he struck the vein which gave him fortune and fame—which
                    might perhaps have given him more fame and not much less fortune if he had not
                    worked it so hard—by conceiving <hi rend="italic">The Warden.</hi> This was
                    published in 1855. It brought him little immediate profit, nor was even <hi
                    rend="italic">Barchester Towers,</hi> which followed, very profitable, though it
                    contains his freshest, his most original, and, with the exception of <hi
                    rend="italic">The Last Chronicle of Barset,</hi> his best work. The two made him
                    a reputation, however, and in 1858 he was able for the first time to sell a
                    novel, <hi rend="italic">The Three Clerks,</hi> for a substantial sum, £250. A
                    journey on post-office business to the West Indies gave him material for a book
                    of travel, <hi rend="italic">The West Indies and the Spanish Main,</hi> which he
                    frankly and quite truly acknowledges to be much better than some subsequent work
                    of his in the same kind. From this time his production (mainly of novels) was
                    incessant, and the sums which he received were very large, amounting in one case
                    to as much as £3525 for a single book, and to nearly £70,000 in the twenty years
                    between 1859 and 1879. All these particulars are given with great minuteness by
                    himself, and are characteristic. The full high tide of his fortunes began when
                    the <hi rend="italic">Cornhill Magazine</hi> was established in the autumn of
                    1859. He was asked at short notice to write a novel, and wrote <hi rend="italic"
                    >Framley Parsonage,</hi> which was extremely popular; two novels immediately
                    preceding it, <hi rend="italic">The Bertrams</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Castle
                    Richmond,</hi> had been much less successful.</p>
                <p>As it will be possible to notice few of his subsequent works in detail, the list
                    of them, a sufficiently astonishing one, may be given here :— <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tales of All Countries</hi> (3 series, 1861-1870); <hi rend="italic">Orley
                    Farm, North America</hi> (1862); <hi rend="italic">Rachael Ray</hi> (1863); <hi
                    rend="italic">The Small House at Allington, Can You Forgive Her?</hi> (1864);
                    <hi rend="italic">Miss Mackenzie</hi> (1865); <hi rend="italic">The Claverings,
                    Nina Balatka, The Last Chronicle of Barset</hi> (1867); <hi rend="italic">Linda
                    Tressel</hi> (1868); <hi rend="italic">Ρhineas Finn, He Knew He Was Right</hi>
                    (1869); <hi rend="italic">Brown, Jones, and Robinson, The Vicar of Bullhampton,
                    An Editor's Tales, Caesar</hi> (1870); <hi rend="italic">Sir Harry Hotspur of
                    Humblethwaite, Ralph the Heir</hi> (1871); <hi rend="italic">The Golden Lion of
                    Granpere</hi> (1872); <hi rend="italic">The Eustace Diamonds, Australia and New
                    Zealand (1873); Phineas Redux, Harry Heathcote of Gangoil, Lady Anna</hi>
                    (1874); <hi rend="italic">The Way We Live Nour</hi> (1875); <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Prime Minister</hi> (1876); <hi rend="italic">The American Senator</hi>
                    (1877); <hi rend="italic">Is He Popenjoy? South Africa</hi> (1878); <hi
                    rend="italic">John Caldigate, An Eye for</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n607/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0607-0586"/><hi rend="italic">an Bye, Cousin Henry, Thackeray
                    (1879); The Duke's Children, Cicero (1880); Ayala's Angel, Dr Wortle's School
                    (1881); Frau Frohmann, Lord Palmerston, The Fixed Period, Kept in the Dark,
                    Marion Fay (1882); Mr Scarborough's Family, The Land Leaguers</hi> (1883);
                    and</p>
                <p>(1884).</p>
                <p>How this enormous total was achieved in spite of official work (of which, lightly
                    as he took it, he did a good deal, and which he did not give up for many years),
                    of hunting three times a week in the season, of whist-playing, of not a little
                    going into general society, he has explained with his usual curious minuteness.
                    He reduced novel-writing to the conditions of regular mechanical work—so much so
                    that latterly he turned out so many words in a quarter of an hour, and wrote at
                    this rate so many hours a day. He divided every book beforehand into so many
                    days’ work and checked off the tallies as he wrote.</p>
                <p>A life thus spent could not be very eventful, and its events may be summed up
                    rapidly. In 1858 he went to Egypt also on post-office business, and at the end
                    of 1859 he got himself transferred from Ireland to the eastern district of
                    England. Here he took a house at Waltham. He took an active part in the
                    establishment of <hi rend="italic">The Fortnightly Review</hi> in 1865; he was
                    editor of <hi rend="italic">St Paul’s</hi> for some time after 1867; and at the
                    end of that year he resigned his position in the post-office. He stood for
                    Beverley and was defeated; he received from his old department special missions
                    to America and elsewhere (he had already gone to America in the midst of the
                    Civil War). He went to Australia in 1871, and before going broke up his
                    household at Waltham. When he returned he established himself in London, and
                    lived there till 1880, when he removed to Harting on the confines of Sussex and
                    Hampshire. He had visited South Africa in 1877 and travelled elsewhere. On 3rd
                    November 1882 he was seized with paralysis, and died on 6th December.</p>
                <p>Of Trollope’s personal character it is not necessary to say much. Strange as his
                    conception of official duty may seem, it was evidently quite honest and sincere,
                    and, though he is said to have been as an official popular neither with
                    superiors nor inferiors, he no doubt did much good work. Privately he was much
                    liked and much disliked,—a great deal of real kindness being accompanied by a
                    blustering and overbearing manner, and an egotism, not perhaps more deep than
                    other men’s, but more vociferous. His literary work needs more notice. Nothing
                    of it but the novels is remarkable for merit. His <hi rend="italic">Caesar</hi>
                    and the <hi rend="italic">Cicero</hi> are curious examples of a man’s
                    undertaking work for which he was not in the least fitted. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thackeray</hi> exhibits (though Trollope appears to have both admired Thackeray
                    as an artist and liked him as a man) grave faults of taste and judgment and a
                    complete lack of real criticism. The books of travel are not good, and of a kind
                    not good. <hi rend="italic">Nina Balatka</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Linda
                    Tressel,</hi> published anonymously and as experiments in the romantic style,
                    have been better thought of by the author and by some competent judges than by
                    the public or the publishers. <hi rend="italic">Brown, Jones, and Robinson</hi>
                    was still more disliked, and is certainly very bad as a whole, but has touches
                    of curious originality in parts. The rest of the novels have been judged very
                    differently by different persons. There is no doubt that their enormous volume
                    prejudiced readers against them even long before the author let the public into
                    the secret of their manufacture, which has made the prejudice deeper. There is
                    also no doubt that Trollope seldom or never creates a character of the first
                    merit (Mr Crawley in the <hi rend="italic">Last Chronicle of Barset</hi> is the
                    one possible exception), and that not one of his books can be called a work of
                    genius. At the same time no one probably has produced anything like such a
                    volume of anything like such merit. He claims for himself that his characters
                    are always more or less alive, and they are. After his first failures he never
                    produced anything that was not a faithful and sometimes a veιy amusing
                    transcript of the sayings and doings of possible men and women. His characters
                    are never marionettes, much less sticks. He has some irritating mannerisms,
                    notably a trick of repetition of the same form of words. He is sometimes
                    absolutely vulgar,— that is to say, he does not deal with low life, but shows,
                    though always robust and pure in morality, a certain coarseness of taste. He is
                    constantly rather trivial, and perhaps nowhere out of the Barset series (which,
                    however, is of itself no inconsiderable work) has he produced books that will
                    live. The very faithfulness of his representation of a certain phase of thought,
                    of cultivation, of society, uninformed as it is by any higher spirit, in the
                    long run damaged, as it had first helped, the popularity of his work. But,
                    allowing for all this, it may and must still be said that he held up his mirror
                    steadily to nature, and that the mirror itself was fashioned with no
                    inconsiderable art. (G. SA. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
