<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0319-0302-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THIERS (9th edition, volume 23, page 302)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043068">Occasionalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n319/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THIERS</label>, Louis <hi rend="smallcaps">Adolphe</hi>
                    (1797-1877), “liberator of the territory,” as even the short-lived gratitude of
                    France continues to call him, was born at Marseilles on April 16, 1797. His
                    family are somewhat grandiloquently spoken of as “cloth merchants ruined by the
                    Revolution,” but it seems that at the actual time of his birth his father was a
                    locksmith. His mother belonged to the family of the Chéniers, and he was well
                    educated, first at the Lycée of Marseilles, and then in the faculty of law at
                    Aix. Here he began his life-long friendship with Mignet, and was <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n320/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0320-0303"/> called to the bar at the age of 23. He had,
                    however, little taste for law and much for literature; and he obtained (it is
                    said by an ingenious trick, and in spite of unfair and prejudiced attempts to
                    deprive him of it) an academic prize at Aix—for a discourse on Vauvenargues. In
                    the early autumn of 1821 Thiers went to Paris, and was quickly introduced as a
                    contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Constitutionnel,</hi> at first on literary
                    and then on general and especially political subjects, as well as art and the
                    drama. In each of the years immediately following his arrival in Paris he
                    collected and published a volume of his <hi rend="italic">Constitutionnel</hi>
                    articles, the first on the salon of 1822, the second on a tour in the Pyrenees.
                    He was put out of all need of money by the singular benefaction of Cotta, the
                    well-known Stuttgart publisher, who was part-proprietor of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Constitutionnel,</hi> and made over to Thiers his dividends, or part of
                    them. Meanwhile he became very well known in Liberal society, especially in the
                    house of Laffitte, and he had begun and was rapidly compiling (at first with the
                    assistance of M. Felix Bodin and afterwards alone) the celebrated <hi
                        rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Revolution</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Française,</hi> which founded his literary and helped his
                    political fame. The first two volumes appeared in 1823, the last two (of ten) in
                    1827. The book brought him little profit at first, but became immensely popular.
                    The well-known sentence of Carlyle, that it is “as far as possible from meriting
                    its high reputation,” is in strictness justified, not merely in regard to this,
                    but in regard to all Thiers’s historical work, which is only too frequently
                    marked by extreme inaccuracy, by prejudice which passes the limits of accidental
                    unfairness and sometimes seems to approach those of positive dishonesty, and by
                    an almost complete indifference to the merits as compared with the successes of
                    his heroes. But Carlyle himself admits that Thiers is “a brisk man in his way,
                    and will tell you much if you know nothing.” In other words, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Revolution</hi> (again
                    like its author’s other work) possesses in a very high degree the gifts of
                    clearness, liveliness, and intelligible handling which so often distinguish
                    French writing. Coming as it did just when the reaction against the Revolution
                    was about to turn into another reaction in its favour, it was assured of
                    success.</p>
                <p>For a moment it seemed as if the author had definitely chosen the lot of a
                    literary man, even of a literary hack. He planned an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">Generale,</hi> and was about to survey
                    mankind from China to Peru on the deck of a French man-of-war as a preliminary
                    process. But the accession to power of the Polignac ministry in August 1829
                    changed his projects, and at the beginning of the next year Thiers, with Armand
                    Carrel, Mignet, and others, started the <hi rend="italic">National,</hi> a new
                    opposition newspaper, which openly attacked the older Bourbon line and was
                    foremost in provoking the famous and fatal Ordonnances of July. Thiers himself
                    was the soul (or at least one of the souls) of the actual revolution. What share
                    he had in the process sometimes attributed to him of “overcoming the scruples of
                    Louis Philippe” is no doubt a debateable question, with the problem <hi
                        rend="italic">in limine</hi> of the debate whether Louis Philippe had any
                    scruples to overcome. At any rate Thiers had his reward. He ranked, if not at
                    once, yet very soon, as one of the radical though not republican supporters of
                    the new dynasty, in opposition to the party of which his rival Guizot was the
                    chief literary man, and Guizot’s patron the duke of Broglie the main pillar
                    among the nobility, and which might be called by comparison Conservative. At
                    first Thiers, though elected deputy for Aix, obtained only subordinate places in
                    the ministry of finance. After the overthrow of his patron Laffitte, he seemed
                    to change his politics and became much less radical, and, after the troubles of
                    June 1832, this tendency was strengthened or rewarded by his appointment to the
                    ministry of the interior. He repeatedly changed his portfolio, but remained in
                    office for four years, became president of the council and in effect prime
                    minister, and began the series of quarrels and jealousies with Guizot which make
                    one of the chief and not the most creditable features of the politics of the
                    reign. At the time of his resignation in 1836 he was foreign minister, and, as
                    usual, wished for a spirited policy in Spain, which he could not carry out. He
                    travelled in Italy for some time, and it was not till 1838 that he began a
                    regular campaign of parliamentary opposition, which in March 1840 made him
                    president of the council and foreign minister for the second time. But he held
                    the position barely six months, and, being unable to force on the king an
                    anti-English and anti-Turkish policy, resigned on October 29, after having, as
                    was generally thought, with the direct purpose of stirring up Anglophobia,
                    begged the body of Napoleon from England. This was made the occasion of the
                    ceremony immortally ridiculed by Thackeray, and, it is said, condemned by Thiers
                    himself as unworthy of the occasion. He now had little to do with politics for
                    some years, and spent his time on the preparation, on a much larger scale than
                    his first work, of his <hi rend="italic">Histoire du Consulat et de</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">l'Empire,</hi> the first volume of which appeared in 1845, and
                    which continued to occupy him for more than twenty years of composition and
                    nearly twenty of publication. During the interval, though he was still a member
                    of the chamber, he spoke rarely, but after the beginning of 1846 his appearances
                    were more frequent, and he was evidently bidding once more for power on the
                    liberal and reforming side. Immediately before the revolution of February he
                    went to all but the greatest lengths, and when it broke out he and Odillon
                    Barrot were summoned by the king, but it was too late. Thiers was unable to
                    govern the forces he had helped to gather, and he resigned.</p>
                <p>Under the republic he took up the position of conservative republican, which he
                    ever afterwards maintained (his acceptance of the republic being not much more
                    heartfelt than his subsequent acceptance, after an interval, of the empire), and
                    he never took office. But the consistency of his conduct, especially in voting
                    for Prince Louis Napoleon as president, was often and sharply criticized, one of
                    the criticisms leading to a duel with a fellow deputy, Bixio. On the whole, his
                    conduct during these years, and still more during the last years of Louis
                    Philippe, may be said to have been not wholly creditable. He was arrested at the
                        <hi rend="italic">coup Tétat</hi> (when some malicious and apparently false
                    stories were spread as to his cowardice), was sent to Mazas, and then escorted
                    out of France. But in the following summer he was allowed to return. For the
                    next decade his history was almost a blank, his time being occupied for the most
                    part on <hi rend="italic">The Consulate and the Empire.</hi> It was not till
                    1863 that he re-entered political life, being elected by a Parisian constituency
                    in opposition to the Government candidate. For the seven years following he was
                    the chief speaker among the small band of anti-Imperialists in the French
                    chamber, and was regarded generally as the most formidable enemy of the empire,—
                    all the more formidable because he never gave occasion for taking any violent
                    steps against him. It has been pointed out that, while nominally protesting
                    against the foreign enterprises of the empire, he perpetually harped on French
                    loss of prestige, and so contributed more than any one else to stir up the fatal
                    spirit which brought on the war of 1870, and that, while constantly criticizing
                    and weakening the Government of his country, he gave it no help nor even offered
                    any. Even when the Liberal-Imperialist Ollivier ministry was formed, he
                    maintained at first an anything but benevolent neutrality, and then <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n321/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0321-0304"/> an open opposition, and it would be pleasant
                    to feel more certain than we can feel that his vigorous denunciation of the war
                    with Prussia was the result of honest conviction, and not merely of the fact
                    that it was not <hi rend="italic">his</hi> war. At any rate, it brought him
                    great unpopularity for the moment, with a corresponding reaction of gratitude
                    when the crash came. Again it is impossible to be sure whether mere “canniness,”
                    or something better, kept him from joining the Government of the National
                    Defence, of which he was in a manner the author.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless the collapse of the empire was a great opportunity for Thiers, and
                    it was worthily accepted. He undertook in the latter part of September and the
                    first three weeks of October a circular tour to the different courts of Europe,
                    in the hope (which he probably knew to be a vain one, though the knowledge
                    neither daunted his spirit nor relaxed his efforts) of obtaining some
                    intervention, or at least some good offices. The mission was unsuccessful; but
                    the negotiator was on its conclusion immediately charged with another—that of
                    obtaining, if possible, an armistice directly from Prince Bismarck. For a time
                    this also failed, as the Provisional Government would not accept the German
                    conditions; but at last France was forced to yield. The armistice having been
                    arranged, and the opportunity having been thus obtained of electing a National
                    Assembly, Thiers was chosen deputy by more than twenty constituencies (of which
                    he preferred Paris), and was at once elected by the Assembly itself practically
                    president, nominally “chef du pouvoir exécutif.” He lost no time in choosing a
                    coalition cabinet, and then personally took up the negotiation of peace.
                    Probably no statesman has ever had a more disgusting task; and the fact that he
                    discharged it to the satisfaction of a vast majority, even in a nation popularly
                    reputed the vainest, the least ballasted with common sense, and the most
                    ungrateful to public servants who are unsuccessful, is the strongest testimony
                    to Thiers’s merits. After contesting the matter, on the one side with the
                    determination of Germany to have the pound of flesh, on the other with the
                    reluctance of the Assembly to submit to the knife, he succeeded in convincing
                    the deputies that the peace was necessary, and it was (March 1, 1871) voted by
                    more than five to one.</p>
                <p>Thiers held office for more than two years after this event,—a length of tenure
                    which, in the circumstances and considering the French temper, is very
                    surprising, and shows the strength of the general conviction that he alone could
                    be trusted. He had at first to meet and crush at once the mad enterprise of the
                    Paris commune; and the severity which was undoubtedly shown in doing this is
                    more than justified by two considerations,—first, that failure to suppress it
                    would have meant anarchy throughout France; and, secondly, that the Germans
                    would almost to a certainty have made it a pretext for further demands. Soon
                    after this was accomplished, Thiers became (August 30) in name as well as in
                    fact president of the republic, and he set himself with vigour and success to
                    the tasks of rearranging the army, the finances (including the paying off of the
                    war indemnity), and the civil service, and of procuring the withdrawal of the
                    German army of occupation.</p>
                <p>The strong personal will and inflexible opinions of the president had much to do
                    with the resurrection of France; but the very same facts made it inevitable that
                    he should excite violent opposition. It seems to be generally acknowledged that
                    to him personally were due the establishment and retention of the republican
                    rather than the monarchical form of government, to which latter the Assembly as
                    first elected was notoriously disposed. He was a confirmed protectionist, and
                    free-trade ideas had made great way in France under the empire; he was an
                    advocate of long military service, and the devotees of <hi rend="italic">la
                        revanche</hi> were all for the introduction of general and compulsory but
                    short service. Both his talents and his temper made him utterly indisposed to
                    maintain the distant, Olympian, apparently inactive, attitude which is supposed
                    to be incumbent on a republican president; and (for his tongue was never a
                    carefully governed one) he sometimes let drop expressions scarcely consistent
                    with constitutional theories of the relation of the chief of the state, whether
                    president or king, to parliament. In January 1872 he formally tendered his
                    resignation; but the country was then in too manifestly disorganized a condition
                    to allow even his enemies to accept it. His position, however, was clearly one
                    not tenable for long in such a country as France. The Right (and not merely the
                    Extreme Right) hated him for his opposition to the restoration of the monarchy,
                    and with some justice reminded him of former declarations and opinions on the
                    subject; the Extreme Left could not forgive the suppression of the commune,
                    while some radical leaders, who may have had little sympathy with the commune
                    itself, saw in his great reputation and imperious personality a bar to their own
                    accession to power. His chief supporters—men like Rémusat, Barthélemy
                    Saint-Hilaire, and Jules Simon—were men rather of the past than of the present;
                    and he had few younger adherents.</p>
                <p>The year 1873 was, as a parliamentary year in France, occupied to a great extent
                    with attacks on Thiers. In the early spring regulations were proposed, and on
                    April 13 were carried, which were intended to restrict the executive and
                    especially the parliamentary powers of the president. On the 27th of the same
                    month a contested election in Paris, resulting in the return of the opposition
                    candidate, M. Barodet, was regarded as a grave disaster for the Thiers
                    Government, and that Government was not much strengthened by a dissolution and
                    reconstitution of the cabinet on May 19. Immediately afterwards the question was
                    brought to a head by an interpellation moved by the duke of Broglie. The
                    president declared that he should take this as a vote of want of confidence; and
                    in the debates which followed a vote of this character (though on a different
                    formal issue, and proposed by M. Ernoul) was carried by 16 votes in a house of
                    704. Thiers at once resigned (May 24).</p>
                <p>He survived his fall four years, continuing to sit in the Assembly, and, after
                    the dissolution of 1876, in the Chamber of Deputies, and sometimes, though
                    rarely, speaking. He was also, on the occasion of this dissolution, elected
                    senator for Belfort, which his exertions had saved for France; but he preferred
                    the lower house, where he sat as of old for Paris. On May 16, 1877, he was one
                    of the “363” who voted want of confidence in the Broglie ministry (thus paying
                    his debts), and he took considerable part in organizing the subsequent electoral
                    campaign. But he was not destined to see its success, being fatally struck with
                    apoplexy at St Germain-en-Laye on September 3. Thiers had long been married, and
                    his wife and sister-in-law, Mlle. Dosne, were his constant companions; but he
                    left no children, and had had only one—a daughter,—who long predeceased him. He
                    had been a member of the Academy since 1834. His personal appearance was
                    remarkable, and not imposing, for he was very short, with plain features,
                    ungainly gestures and manners, very near-sighted, and of disagreeable voice; yet
                    he became (after wisely giving up an attempt at the ornate style of oratory) a
                    very effective speaker in a kind of conversational manner, and in the epigram of
                    debate he had no superior among the statesmen of his time except Lord
                    Beaconsfield.</p>
                <p>Thiers is by far the most gifted and interesting of the group of literary
                    statesmen—not statesmen who have had a <hi rend="italic">penchant for</hi><pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n322/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0322-0305"/> literature, but men of letters whose literary
                    distinction has made them politicians—which forms a unique feature in the French
                    political history of this century. Numerous as these are, there are only two who
                    are at all comparable to him—Guizot and Lamartine; and as a statesman he stands
                    far above both. Nor is this eminence merely due to his great opportunity in
                    1870; for Guizot might under Louis Philippe have almost made himself a French
                    Walpole, at least a French Palmerston, and Lamartine’s opportunities after 1848
                    were, for a man of political genius, illimitable. But both failed, —Lamartine
                    almost ludicrously,—while Thiers in hard conditions made a striking if not a
                    brilliant success. A devil’s advocate may indeed urge that his egotist and
                    almost gasconading temperament stood him in stead in the trying circumstances of
                    his negotiations with the powers and with Prince Bismarck,—but this is not
                    really to his discredit. No less masterful methods than his would have sufficed
                    to bring France into order from the chaos succeeding the fall of the empire and
                    the invasion of the Germans. But Thiers only showed well when he was practically
                    supreme. Even as the minister of a constitutional monarch his intolerance of
                    interference or joint authority, his temper at once imperious and intriguing,
                    his inveterate inclination towards <hi rend="italic">brigue,</hi> that is to
                    say, underhand rivalry and caballing for power and place, showed themselves
                    unfavourably; and his constant tendency to inflame the aggressive and chauvinist
                    spirit of his country, though it may fairly claim to have been a kind of
                    patriotism, neglected fact, was not based on any just estimate of the relative
                    power and interests of France, and led his country more than once to the
                    verge—once, though he affected to warn her off, over the verge—of a great
                    calamity. In opposition, both under Louis Philippe and under the empire, and
                    even to some extent in the last four years of his life, his worse qualities were
                    always manifested. But with all these drawbacks he conquered and will retain a
                    place in what is perhaps the highest, as it is certainly the smallest, class of
                    statesmen—the class of those to whom their country has had recourse in a great
                    disaster, who have shown in bringing her through that disaster the utmost
                    constancy, courage, devotion, and skill, and who have been rewarded by as much
                    success as the occasion permitted.</p>
                <p>As a man of letters Thiers is very much smaller. He has not only the fault of
                    diffuseness, which is common to so many of the best-known histories of this
                    century, but others as serious or more so. The charge of dishonesty is one never
                    to be lightly made against men of such distinction as his, especially when their
                    evident confidence in their own infallibility, their faculty of ingenious
                    casuistry, and the strength of will which makes them (unconsciously, no doubt)
                    close and keep closed the eyes of their mind to all inconvenient facts and
                    inferences supply a more charitable explanation. But it is certain that from
                    Thiers’s dealings with the men of the first Revolution to his dealings with the
                    battle of Waterloo, constant, angry, and well-supported protests against his
                    unfairness were not lacking. Although his search among documents was undoubtedly
                    wide, its results are by no means always accurate, and his admirers themselves
                    admit great inequalities of style in him. These characteristics reappear
                    (accompanied, however, by frequent touches of the epigrammatic power above
                    mentioned, which seems to have come to Thiers more readily as an orator or a
                    journalist than as an historian) in his speeches, which have, since his death,
                    been collected in many volumes by his widow. Sainte-Beuve, whose notices of
                    Thiers are generally kindly, says of him, “Μ. Thiers sait tout, tranche tout,
                    parle de tout,” and this omniscience and “cocksureness” (to use the word of a
                    prime minister of England contemporary with this prime minister of France) are
                    perhaps the chief pervading features both of the statesman and the man of
                    letters.</p>
                <p>His histories, in many different editions, and his speeches, as above, are easily
                    accessible; his minor works and newspaper articles have not, we believe, been
                    collected in any form, works on him, by Μ. Laya, Μ. de Mazade, his colleague and
                    friend Μ. Jules Simon, and others, are numerous. But a thorough biographical
                    study of him has not yet been made; and, though monuments enough have been
                    raised in his own country, it is even there often complained that the incessant
                    and futile political struggles of the last ten years have too much obscured the
                    reputation and weakened the memory of the last great statesman of France. (G.
                    SA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
