<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0611-0590-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TROYES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 590</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1002458">Looms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:919892">Fairs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:844604">Calvinists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c72h">Gauls</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n611/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TROYES</label>, a town of France, formerly the capital of
                    Champagne, and now chef-lieu of the department of Aube, and an episcopal see, is
                    104 miles south-east of Paris by the railway to Belfort, at the junction of the
                    line from Orleans to Chalons. Several arms of the Seine and also the Haute-Seine
                    Canal run through the town. The cathedral of St Peter and St Paul, the building
                    of which lasted from 1206 till the 16th century, still wants the south tower.
                    The choir, the end chapels, and the sacristry were restored in 1849-1866. The
                    16th-century façade, with mutilated bas-reliefs and statues, is surmounted by
                    the tower of St Peter (230 feet). The choir, one of the most beautiful in
                    France, belongs to the 13th century, as does also its remarkable glass. The
                    treasury contains gospels of the 11th and 12th centuries, precious stones
                    brought from the East at the time of the crusades, and ancient and beautiful
                    lace. The unfinished church of St Urban, begun in 1262 at the expense of Urban
                    IV., is a charming specimen of the best period of Gothic architecture, the side
                    portals being remarkably light and delicate. The church of St Madeleine, built
                    at the beginning of the 12th century, enlarged in the 16th, and recently
                    restored, contains a rich rood-screen by Jean de Gualde (1508). In 1420 the
                    treaty of Troyes was signed in the church of St John, where Henry V. of England
                    and Catherine of France were subsequently married. The church of St Remy, with a
                    Romanesque tower, the churches of St Nizier and St Nicholas, both of the 16th
                    century, and that of St Pantaléon, of the 16th and 17th, should also be noticed.
                    There are some curious fireplaces in the town hall (17th century), and the
                    municipal archives contain the correspondence of the dukes of Lorraine and
                    Guise. The old abbey of St Loup is occupied by the library (80,000 volumes and
                    2720 manuscripts) and a museum containing numerous collections; that relating to
                    natural history is rich in ornithology and entomology, and has many aerolites.
                    Most of the old houses of Troyes are of wood, but some of stone of the 16th
                    century are remarkable for their beautiful and original architecture. The chief
                    industry of Troyes and the surrounding district is the manufacture of cotton and
                    woollen hosiery, which is woven almost entirely by hand, and is exported to
                    America and Switzerland. One-fourth of the population live by subsidiary
                    industries. There are 14 cotton mills with 10,000 spindles, bleaching, dressing,
                    and dye works, workshops for making looms, needle factories, iron and copper
                    foundries, 8 flour mills, and nursery and market gardens. A trade is carried on
                    in pork and cheese. A few miles from the town stands the curious church of St
                    Andrew (16th century), with a remarkable portal. The population in 1886 was
                    46,972 (46,067 in 1881).</p>
                <p>At the beginning of the Roman period Troyes <hi rend="italic">(Augustobona)</hi>
                    was the principal settlement of the Tricassi. It was christianized in the 3rd
                    century, and its bishop St Loup (426-479) founded renowned schools, and averted
                    the fury of Attila. In 484 Troyes passed into the hands of Clovis, and belonged
                    sometimes to Neustria, sometimes to Austrasia, till all Gaul was united under
                    Charles Martel. In 878 Pope John VIII. presided at a council in Troyes. The town
                    was fired and sacked by the Saracens in 720, and by the Normans in 889 and 905.
                    In 1229 Theobald IV., besieged in his capital, was delivered by king Louis IX.,
                    and in 1230 he granted the inhabitants a municipal charter. From this time the
                    fairs of Troyes became celebrated. During the captivity of King John in England,
                    Troyes resisted all attacks, and after Agincourt took the part of the
                    Burgundians. In 1417 the rule of Queen Isabeau of Bavaria was established in
                    Troyes, where in 1418 the parlement of Paris met; and on 21st May 1420 Henry V.
                    of England, Charles VI. of France, Isabeau, and Philip of Burgundy signed the
                    famous treaty of Troyes. On 9th July 1429 the town capitulated to Joan of Arc.
                    In the 16th century Protestantism made rapid progress, but in 1562 the Huguenots
                    were forced to retire to Bar-sur-Seine; after the massacre of St Bartholomew in
                    Paris, the Calvinists in the prisons of Troyes met the same fate. In 1577 the
                    inhabitants joined the League, and only opened their gates to Henry IV. in 1594.
                    In 1787 the parlement of Paris again met here. In 1814 both the allied and the
                    imperial armies occupied Troyes; and in 1870 the town was occupied by the
                    Germans.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
