<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0441-0422-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TOAD (9th edition, volume 23, page 422)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:840477">Bufo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151755">Toads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:810925">Anura</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120047">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1145710">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834062">Bladder</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807900">Amphibians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62661">Amphibia</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf7q">Toads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41s56">Batrachia</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xg19">Bladder</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n441/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TOAD</label>. This animal belongs to the Anurous division of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Amphibia,</hi> and toads and frogs are the only
                    representatives of the <hi rend="italic">Anura</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >Batrachia</hi> indigenous to Britain. To an ordinary observer the toad is
                    proved to be an amphibian by its moist soft skin, an anuran or tailless
                    amphibian by the want of a separate tail. The toad differs from the frog in the
                    following points :—It has no teeth on either of its jaws or on the roof of its
                    mouth, while the frog has a series of fine teeth on the upper jaw and also teeth
                    on the palate; the tongue in both animals is attached in front and free behind,
                    but that of the frog is forked at its free extremity, that of the toad is not;
                    the skin of the toad is rough with large protuberant warts, while that of the
                    frog is smooth; the body of the toad is more globular and puffy than that of the
                    frog; the hind legs in the toad are shorter, and the posterior digits not so
                    completely webbed, the animal being more terrestrial in its habits than the
                    frog. In the toad, as in the frog, there are four digits anteriorly, five
                    posteriorly. The warts of the toad’s skin contain large cutaneous glands, which
                    secrete a thick yellowish fluid with acrid properties, capable of irritating and
                    producing slight inflammation on the human skin. The use of this secretion is
                    probably to protect the toad from being devoured by carnivorous animals. Like
                    other <hi rend="italic">Amphibia,</hi> it has a large membranous bladder
                    communicating with the terminal part of the intestine—the allantoic bladder,—in
                    which fluid accumulates, probably from the kidneys, though the ureters do not
                    open directly into the bladder. The toad, when handled or alarmed in any way,
                    ejects the contents of its bladder. Owing to these peculiarities and its
                    appearance, the animal is commonly regarded with loathing, and credited with far
                    more poisonous properties than it possesses. In its breeding habits the toad
                    resembles the frog: its eggs are fertilized externally at the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n442/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0442-0423"/> moment of extrusion, as in the frog, the
                    parents resorting to the water for the purpose of reproduction. The ova are laid
                    in spring, and are arranged, not in shapeless masses, but in a string containing
                    a double series of eggs adhering by their gelatinous envelopes; the string
                    extends to a length of three or four feet. The tadpoles are similar to those of
                    the frog, but blacker; their metamorphosis takes place in the same manner, the
                    three pairs of external gills being first absorbed and replaced for a time by
                    internal gills, which are in their turn lost, the branchial slits being closed
                    by the coalescence of the opercular membrane with the skin. The metamorphosis is
                    complete in autumn. The toad is carnivorous, feeding on flies and other insects
                    and worms. It hibernates in winter, passing its period of torpidity in holes or
                    burrows in the earth. The finding of toads in a state of hibernation has given
                    rise to stories of their being found in the centre of trunks of trees or
                    imbedded in solid rock. The myth of the jewel in the head (Shakespeare) is
                    probably founded on the brightness of the eyes, in which the iris is
                    flame-coloured.</p>
                <p>There are two kinds of toad in Britain,—the Common Toad, which is almost black in
                    colour, and the Natter jack Toad, which is lighter, smaller, and has a bright
                    yellow line along the middle of the back. The length of the common toad is 3∣
                    inches, of the natter-jack 2f inches. The male natter jack possesses a bladder
                    or vocal sack beneath the throat communicating with the mouth, which acts as a
                    resonator to its voice; its cry is “gluck-gluck.” The vocal sack is absent in
                    the common toad, and only incompletely developed in the Green Toad of the
                    Continent.</p>
                <p>In zoological classification the toad belongs to the genus <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bufo,</hi> first constituted by Laurenti in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Synopsis</hi><hi rend="italic">Reptilium,</hi> of which the following
                    diagnosis is given in the <hi rend="italic">Brit.</hi><hi rend="italic">Mus.
                        Ccd.</hi><hi rend="italic">Batr. Sal.,</hi> 1882:—</p>
                <p>Pupil horizontal. Tongue elliptical or pyriform, entire and free behind. Vomerine
                    and maxillary teeth none. Tympanum distinct or hidden, seldom absent. Fingers
                    free; toes more or less webbed; the tips simple or dilated into small disks.
                    Outer metatarsals united. Omosternum generally missing; if present
                    cartilaginous; sternum a cartilaginous plate, sometimes more or less ossified
                    along the median line. Diapophyses of sacral vertebrae more or less dilated.
                    Terminal phalanges obtuse or triangular. Distribution cosmopolitan, except
                    Australia.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bufo vulgaris,</hi> Laurenti, the Common Toad, is thus
                    distinguished. Crown without bony ridges. First finger as long as or longer than
                    the second. Parotids distinct. Tympanum smaller than the eye. Toes half webbed;
                    no tarsal fold; subarticular tubercles of toes double. The species is widely
                    distributed, occurring throughout Europe, Asia, and north-west Africa.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bufo calamita,</hi> Laurenti, the Natter-jack Toad, shows the
                    following differences from <hi rend="italic">B. vulgaris</hi>:—toes not half
                    webbed; tympanum rather indistinct; a tarsal fold. It is distributed throughout
                    Europe.</p>
                <p>According to Boulenger there are 77 species of <hi rend="italic">Bufo</hi> known,
                    of which 35 are confined to the Old World, the rest to the American continent.
                    No species is common to the two great continents. The only other species
                    occurring in Europe besides the two which are found in Britain is <hi
                        rend="italic">Bufo</hi><hi rend="italic">viridis,</hi> Laurenti, which
                    ranges throughout Europe, Asia, and North Africa.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
