<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0453-0434-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TOLAND, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 434</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1085685">Questioning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n453/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TOLAND, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1670-1722),
                    or Janus Junius, as his sponsors are said to have named him, usually described
                    as a chief leader of the English deists, -was born November 30, 1670 or 1671, in
                    the north of Ireland, near Londonderry. He was the son, perhaps illegitimate, of
                    Catholic parents, and was brought up in their faith. But in his fifteenth year
                    he became a zealous Protestant, and in 1687 he passed from the school at
                    Redcastle to Glasgow university, recommended by the magistrates of Redcastle
                    “for his affection to the Protestant religion.” Thus early in life he became
                    “accustomed to examination and inquiry, and was taught not to captivate his
                    understanding to any man or society.” After three years at Glasgow he entered
                    the university of Edinburgh, taking his M.A. degree there June 30, 1690. He then
                    spent a short time in some Protestant families in England, and with their
                    assistance went to Leyden university, to qualify him for entering the Dissenting
                    ministry. He spent about two years in Leyden, studying ecclesiastical history
                    especially under the famous scholar Frederick Spanheim. At the expiration of
                    that time he took up his abode, January 7, 1694, at Oxford, having good
                    introductions to Creech, Mill, and others. Here he made large use of the
                    Bodleian Library, and soon acquired the reputation of being “a man of fine
                    parts, of great learning, and of little religion,” though there is no evidence
                    to show that the last distinction was justly his due. His letters show that he
                    then claimed to be a decided Christian, and that he was too orthodox to be
                    classed with the Arians or the Socinians. At the same time the characteristic
                    freedom and originality of his mind were displayed by his anticipation of
                    subsequent doubts of the integrity of the book of Job, and the separation of the
                    historical prologue and the speeches of Elihu from the original poem. While at
                    Oxford he commenced the book which called him into notoriety, and became one of
                    the standard “deistical writings ”—his <hi rend="italic">Christianity not
                    Mysterious.</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The
                    first edition, London, 1696, was anonymous; the second, published the same year,
                    bore on the title-page his name, and received a preface and some slight
                    alterations; and the third appeared in 1702 with an appended <hi rend="italic"
                    >Apology for Mr Toland.</hi></p></note> The book gave great offence, and several
                    replies to it were immediately published. The author was prosecuted by the grand
                    jury of Middlesex the year of its publication; and, when he attempted to settle
                    in Dublin at the beginning of 1697, he was greeted with dangerous denunciations
                    from the pulpits and elsewhere. He was soon prosecuted before the court of
                    King’s Bench, and on September 9th his book was condemned by the Irish
                    parliament to be burned and its author to be arrested. He escaped the latter
                    part of the sentence by flight to England. The title and the philosophical
                    principles of Toland’s book were singularly akin to those of Locke’s famous
                    work, <hi rend="italic">The Reasonableness of Christianity,</hi> published the
                    year before; and Locke’s opponents seized the opportunity of fathering upon the
                    philosopher the doctrines of his more heterodox and less guarded disciple. Thus
                    Toland’s work became the occasion of the celebrated controversy between
                    Stillingfleet and Locke, in which Locke takes pains to show the difference
                    between his position and Toland’s. Toland’s next work of importance was his <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of Milton</hi> (1698), in which, in connexion with his
                    exposure of the fictitious authorship of the <hi rend="italic">Eikon
                    Basilike,</hi> he found occasion to make reflexions on “the numerous
                    supposititious pieces under the name of Christ and His apostles and other great
                    persons.” This provoked the charge that he had called in question the
                    genuineness of the New Testament writings, and he replied in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Amyntor,</hi><hi rend="italic">or a Defence of Milton</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">s Life</hi> (1699), to which
                    he added a remarkable list of what are now called apocryphal New Testament
                    writings. In his remarks he really opened up the great question of the history
                    of the canon, towards the examination of which Stephen Nye, Jeremiah Jones, and
                    Nathanael Lardner made in reply to him the first valuable contributions. The
                    next year his <hi rend="italic">Amyntor</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Christianity
                    not Mysterious</hi> were under discussion in both Houses of Convocation, and the
                    Upper House declined to proceed against the author. In 1701 Toland spent a few
                    weeks at Hanover as secretary to the embassy of the earl of Macclesfield, and
                    was received with favour by the electress Sophia in acknowledgment of his book
                    <hi rend="italic">Anglia Libera,</hi> a defence of the Hanoverian succession. On
                    his return from the Continent he published a defence of himself, and of the
                    bishops for not prosecuting him, <hi rend="italic">Vindicius Liberius</hi>
                    (1702), and several political pamphlets. The next year he visited Hanover and
                    Berlin, and was again graciously received by the electress and her daughter
                    Sophia Charlotte, queen of Prussia. On his return to England (1704) he published
                    <hi rend="italic">Letters to Serena,</hi> and afterwards acknowledged that the
                    queen of Prussia was intended by the pseudonym. In these letters he anticipated
                    some of the speculations of modern materialism. The next year appeared his <hi
                    rend="italic">Account of Prussia and Hanover,</hi> of which Carlyle has made use
                    in his <hi rend="italic">Life of Frederick the Great.</hi> From 1707 to 1710 he
                    is again on the Continent,—at Berlin, Hanover, Düsseldorf, Vienna, Prague, and
                    The Hague, with very varying fortunes, but generally of an adverse character. In
                    1709 he published <hi rend="italic">Adeisidaemon</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Origines</hi><hi rend="italic">Judaicae</hi> (The Hague), in which, amongst
                    other things, he maintained that the Jews were originally Egyptians, and that
                    the true Mosaic institutions perished with Moses. This work provoked a number of
                    replies from Continental theologians. In 1710 he returned to England, living
                    chiefly in London and latterly at Putney, loving the country and his books, and
                    subsisting precariously upon the earnings of his pen and the benevolence of his
                    patrons. His literary projects were numerous (see the incomplete list in
                    Mosheim); and the nobler traits of his warm Irish nature appear in his projected
                    history of the ancient Celtic religion and his chivalrous advocacy of the
                    naturalization of the Jews. The last of his theological works were <hi
                    rend="italic">Nazarenus,</hi><hi rend="italic">or Jewish, Gentile, and Mahometan
                    Christianity</hi> (1718), and <hi rend="italic">Tetra-dymus</hi> (1720), a
                    collection of essays on various subjects, in the first of which, “Hodegus,” he
                    set the example subsequently followed by Reimarus and the rationalistic school
                    in Germany, of interpreting the Old Testament miracles by the naturalistic
                    method, maintaining, for instance, that the pillar of cloud and of fire of
                    Exodus was a transported signal-fire. His last and most offensive book was his
                    <hi rend="italic">Pantheisticon</hi> (Cosmopoli, 1720). He died May 11, 1722, as
                    he had lived, in great poverty, in the midst of his books, with his pen in his
                    hand, and left behind him a characteristic Latin epitaph, in which he could
                    justly claim to have been “veritatis propugnator, libertatis assertor.”</p>
                <p>Toland is generally classed with the deists, but at the time when he wrote his
                    first book, <hi rend="italic">Christianity not Mysterious,</hi> he was decidedly
                    opposed to deism, nor does Leland deal with that work as an exposition of
                    deistical views. The design of the work was to show, by an appeal mainly to the
                    tribunal of Scripture, that there are no facts or doctrines of the “gospel,” or
                    “the Scriptures,” or “Christian revelation” which, when revealed, are not
                    perfectly <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n454/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0454-0435"/> plain, intelligible, and reasonable, being
                    neither contrary to reason nor incomprehensible to it. The work undoubtedly
                    aimed a blow at some of the dogmas of later Christian times, but it claimed to
                    be “a vindication of God’s revealed will against the most unjust imputations”
                    which occasioned “so many deists and atheists.” Toland’s line of argument is to
                    show that the supposition of the doctrines of the gospel being repugnant to
                    clear and distinct ideas and common notions leads into absurdities and
                    inevitable scepticism; that the proof of the Divinity of Scripture is its
                    selfevidencing power; that, though men are dependent on Divine revelation for
                    the knowledge of the most important truths, the truths must themselves be plain
                    and intelligible when revealed; that all the doctrines, precepts, and miracles
                    of the New Testament are perfectly intelligible and plain; that, though reason
                    is disordered in the case of many men, the disorder is not in the faculty itself
                    but in the use made of it; that in the New Testament “mystery” never means
                    anything inconceivable in itself, but things naturally intelligible enough,
                    which are either so veiled by figurative words or rites, or so lodged in God’s
                    sole knowledge and decree, that they could not be discerned without special
                    revelation; that no miracle of the gospel is contrary to reason, for they were
                    all produced according to the laws of nature, though above its ordinary
                    operations, which were therefore supernaturally assisted; that mysteries were
                    first introduced into Christianity by the early admission into the church of
                    Levitical ceremonies and heathen rites and mysteries, and especially by mixing
                    up heathen philosophy with the simple religion of Christ. The work was intended
                    to be the first of three discourses, in the second of which he was to attempt a
                    particular and rational explanation of the reputed mysteries of the gospel, and
                    in the third a demonstration of the verity of Divine revelation against atheists
                    and all enemies of revealed religion. But, like so many other of his numerous
                    projects, this failed of execution. After his <hi rend="italic">Christianity not
                    Mysterious</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Amyntor,</hi> Toland’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Nazarenus</hi> was of chief importance, as vailing attention to
                    the right of the Ebionites to a place in the early church, though it altogether
                    failed to establish his main argument or to put the question in the true light.
                    His <hi rend="italic">Pantheisticon, sive Formula celebrandae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Sodalitatis</hi><hi rend="italic">Socraticae,</hi> of which he
                    printed a few copies for private circulation only, gave great offence as a sort
                    of liturgie service made up of passages from heathen authors, in imitation of
                    the Church of England liturgy. The title also was in those days alarming, and
                    still more so the mystery which the author threw round the question how far such
                    societies of pantheists actually existed. Poor Toland had been outlawed by the
                    churches of his day, and took a most imprudent delight in alarming and
                    mystifying his persecutors. This and all his later works must be read from the
                    point of view first suggested by Herder: “Who can refuse to see in Toland the
                    man of wide reading and of clear intellect, and the earnest inquirer, although,
                    as embittered by persecutions, with every fresh book he dipped his pen in a more
                    biting acid?”</p>
                <p>See Mosheim’s <hi rend="italic">Vindici</hi><hi rend="italic">ae Antiquae</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Christianorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Disciplinae,</hi> 1st ed.,
                    1720, 2d ed., 1722 (the life of Toland prefixed to the 2d edition of this essay
                    gives still the best and most learned account we have of his life and writings);
                    “Memoirs of the Life and writings of Mr John Toland,” by Des Maizeaux, prefixed
                    to <hi rend="italic">The Miscellaneous Works of Mr John Toland,</hi> in 2 vols.,
                    London, 1747; Leland’s <hi rend="italic">View of the Principal Deistical
                    Writers;</hi> Herder's <hi rend="italic">Adrastea;</hi> Lechler ’ s <hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >englischen Deismus</hi>; Isaac Disraeli’s <hi rend="italic">Calamities of
                    Authors; Theological Review,</hi> November 1864; Hunt's article in <hi
                    rend="italic">Contemporary Review,</hi> vol. viii., and his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Religious Thought in England;</hi> Leslie Stephen’s <hi rend="italic">History
                    of English Thought in Eighteenth Century</hi>; Cairns’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cunningham Lectures for 1880.</hi> 0η Toland's relation to the subsequent
                    Tübingen school, as presented in his <hi rend="italic">Nazarenus,</hi> see <hi
                    rend="italic">Theological Review,</hi> Get., 1877; and on his relation to
                    materialism, F. A. Lange's <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Materialismus.</hi>
                    (J. F. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
