<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0625-0604-08" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TULA (9th edition, volume 23, page 604)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gh2d">Pyrethrum</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669847">Slavs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4697039w">Lithuanians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sp8d">Tatars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:999306">Linum</term>
                    <term ref="fast:861701">Cirsium</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1093204">Regionalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n625/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TULA</label>, a government of central Russia, bounded by
                    Moscow on the N., Ryazan on the E., Tamboff and Orel on the S., and Kaluga on
                    the W., has an area of 11,950 square miles. It is intersected from south-west to
                    northeast by a gently undulating plateau, from 950 to 1020 feet in height, which
                    separates the drainage area of the Oka from that of the Don. The average
                    elevation of Tula is about 800 feet, and its surface is an undulating plain; but
                    the rivers flow in valleys so deeply cut and so scored with ravines that in
                    their neighbourhood the country assumes the aspect of a hilly region. Devonian
                    limestones, dolomites, and sandstones appear chiefly in the south-west; Lower
                    and Middle Carboniferous limestones and clays occupy the remainder of the area.
                    The former contain deposits of coal, which are now worked (chiefly at Malevka
                    and Novoselsk) to the extent of nearly one and a half million cwts. annually.
                    Jurassic clays are found in patches here and there. Glacial boulder clay covers
                    most of the region, while Lacustrine deposits are widely spread in the valleys
                    and depressions. Iron-ore is found all over the government; limestone,
                    fire-clay, and pottery clay are also obtained. The soil is black earth in the
                    south and east and clay or sandy clay in the north-west. Tula is watered chiefly
                    by the Oka and its tributaries (Upa, Zusha, Osetr, and Pronya). The Don rises in
                    Lake Ivan-Ozero (which feeds also a tributary of the Oka), and has a course of
                    35 miles within Tula. It is not navigable, and Peter I.’s attempt to connect it
                    with the Oka by means of a canal was never carried out. Lakes and marshes
                    (chiefly in the north-west) are few. Forests (8 per cent. of the area) are
                    rapidly disappearing. The climate is less rigorous than that of Moscow, the
                    average yearly temperature being 40°∙2 Fahr. (January, 13°·8; July, 67°∙5).</p>
                <p>The flora of Tula deserves some attention as marking the transition from that of
                    the south-east steppes to that of north-west Russia. A line drawn on the
                    northern slope of the water-parting already mentioned (a few miles to the south
                    of the city of Tula) divides the province into two parts, of which the southern
                    is a black earth region and the other is chiefly covered with boulder clay. The
                    boundary is marked by a series of crown forests— formerly a means of defence
                    against the nomad tribes, whence their name Zasyeka—which at the same time
                    constitute a line that is not passed by several species characteristic of the
                    steppe region, such as the <hi rend="italic">Lilia</hi> of the steppes, <hi
                        rend="italic">Lilium Martagon, Linum flavum, Lathyrus pisiformis, Geranium
                        sanguineum, Pyrethrum corymbosum,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Serratula
                        heterophylla.</hi> On the other hand, several northern species, which are
                    quite common in the marshes of Moscow, do not penetrate into Tula, and several
                    others, such as <hi rend="italic">Linnaea borealis, Viola palustris, Cirsium
                        palustre, Pedicularis palustris,</hi> do not cross the Zasyeka. The same
                    forests shelter several northern species which do not appear either in northern
                    or southern Tula, as also several southern herbaceous plants which are now only
                    occasionally met with in the black earth steppes of south Russia. Several
                    West-European plants (<hi rend="italic">Sanicula europaea, Carex remota,</hi><pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n626/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0626-0605"/><hi rend="italic">Cephalanthera ensifolia,
                        Allium ursinum)</hi> find their eastern limits in Tula. Another interesting
                    feature is the extension down the valley of the Oka, not only of pine-forests,
                    which are not found elsewhere within the province, but also of many herbaceous
                    plants originally from the south or south-west. The steppe flora of Tula is
                    being rapidly impoverished in consequence of the spread of agriculture: many
                    steppe plants are now found only in their last retreats on the dry uncultivated
                    limestone crags.</p>
                <p>The population of the government (750,000 in 1777) in 1883 was 1,360,000, of whom
                    115,770 were urban. They are all Great Russians, and either Orthodox Greeks or
                    Raskolniks. Their chief occupation is agriculture, 70 per cent. of the area
                    being arable. Nearly one-half of the soil belongs to landlords and merchants,
                    and the other half to the peasant communities (53 per cent. of the area, and 58
                    per cent. of the land under culture). The crops for 1883-85 averaged 7,574,200
                    quarters of grain and 10,172,000 bushels of potatoes, largely used for
                    distilleries. Beet-root culture is increasing (8520 acres in 1885, yielding
                    59,800 cwts. of sugar). The growth of tobacco is also spreading ( 10,000 cwts.
                    in 1885). There were in 1883 380,620 horses, 203,500 cattle, and 786,000 sheep.
                    Manufactures are rapidly developing; their aggregate production was valued at
                    £1,649,720 in 1883 (distilleries £293,956, sugar-works £601,827, tanneries
                    £148,356, iron works, brass works, &amp;c., about £150,000). Petty trades,
                    especially the manufacture of tea-urns, small brass ware, and harmoniums, and
                    also weaving, are extensively carried on and support a lively export trade;
                    timber, raw metals, and various manufactured wares are imported. The government
                    is traversed by the Moscow and Sebastopol and the Ryazhsk and Vyazemsk Railways,
                    as well as by the Oka. The government is divided into twelve districts, the
                    chief towns of which, with their population in 1882, are <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Tula</hi> (see below), Alexin (4960), Bogoroditsk (8030), Byeleff (9300),
                    Epifañ (3820), Efremoff (7770), Kashira (4610), Krapivna (1560), Novosil (4660),
                    Odoeff(5140), and Tcherñ (2675). Byeleff, Alexin, and Kashira are important
                    loading places on the Oka. The villages Malevka (coal-mines) and Niki-tino have
                    more than 5000 inhabitants each.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> Before the Slavonic immigration, the territory
                    of Tula was inhabited by the Mordves on the north and the Mestchers in the
                    south. The Slavs who occupied the Oka belonged to the branch of the Vyatichis,
                    who were soon compelled to pay a tribute to the Khazars. Subsequently the
                    territory on the Oka belonged to the principality of Tchernigoff, thus
                    maintaining its connexion with south-west Russia. In the 14th century part of it
                    fell under the rule of Ryazan and Moscow, while the remainder was under
                    Lithuanian dominion till the 15th century. Several of the towns of Tula were
                    founded in the 12th century, but the colonization of this fertile region went on
                    slowly on account of the raids of the Tatars.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
