<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0269-0252-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THEOCRITUS (9th edition, volume 23, page 252)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5wf0f">Matches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dr26">Sketching</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m29x">Dorians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w53k">Erosion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45v4z">Hymns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896967">Dorians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1921429">Sicilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848005">Carthaginians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115813">Shepherds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1011667">Matches</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n269/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THEOCRITUS</label>, of Syracuse, the foremost Greek pastoral
                    poet, lived a life of which nothing is known except from allusions in his own
                    works. The epigram appended to his poems makes him say, “I am a Syracusan, a man
                    of the people, a son of Praxagoras and Philinna.” He must have been born early
                    in the 3d century, among a Dorian people, whose Dorian speech survives in his
                    rural idyls. These “little pictures” chiefly represent the life of shepherds,
                    neat-herds, and fishermen in the woods and on the shores of Sicily. They are
                    doubtless inspired by the popular poetry of his time, and have much in common
                    with the Romaic chants of the modern Greek shepherds. The first idyl is a song
                    on Daphnis, the ideal <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n270/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0270-0253"/> herdsman, sung by the shepherd Thyrsis to a
                    goatherd. The second is the magical chant which Simaetha pours forth to the
                    magic moon, in the hope of recovering her lover. In the third a goatherd sings
                    to his love, Amaryllis. The fourth is an interchange of rude banter between two
                    country fellows; and the fifth is of the same kind. The scenes are in southern
                    Italy. The sixth is a Sicilian singing match between two ideal herdsmen,—not
                    contemporary rustics, but poets of nobler themes. The scene of the seventh is in
                    Cos, where the poet introduces himself at a singing match. He may have been
                    attached to the Asclepian medical school in Cos; his friend Nicias was a
                    physician. Sicily and rival minstrels occupy the ninth idyl. The tenth contains
                    probably some real popular ditties, chanted by the reapers. The eleventh,
                    addressed to Nicias, is a piece of artificial mythological <hi rend="italic"
                        >genre,</hi> “The Cyclops in Love.” The twelfth is a lyric, almost of
                    passionate affection. The thirteenth is another idyl on a mythical topic, the
                    adventures of Hercules and Hylas. The fourteenth and fifteenth are sketches of
                    military and urban life, the mercenary soldier in love, and the gathering at the
                    Adonis feast in Alexandria. Theocritus had wandered to the court of Ptolemy, and
                    joined the literary society of his court. The sixteenth is a patriotic piece:
                    the poet urges Hiero to assail the Carthaginians in Sicily. The seventeenth is a
                    conventional hymn to Ptolemy Philadelphus on his marriage with his sister. The
                    eighteenth is an epithalamium; the nineteenth a tiny picture of Eros stung by a
                    bee; the twentieth is the complaint of a herdsman rejected by a girl of the
                    town; the twenty-first an idyl of fisher life: two poor old fishermen recount
                    their dreams. The twenty-second idyl is a piece of heroic myth, the adventures
                    of Castor and Polydeuces; and the twenty-fourth is a tiny epic on the infancy of
                    Hercules. The twenty-third is an amorous complaint. The twenty-fifth describes
                    the slaughter by Hercules of the Nemean lion. The twentysixth justifies, in the
                    interests of the ritual of Dionysus, the murder of the curious Pentheus. The
                    twenty-seventh is the “Wooing of Daphnis,” or “Oaristys,” an amorous discourse
                    between a girl and a swain. The twenty-eighth is a graceful piece of <hi
                        rend="italic">vers de société,</hi> sent to a lady with the gift of an ivory
                    distaff. The twenty-ninth is amorous; and there remain an imperfect and a
                    spurious piece, and a set of twenty-three epigrams.</p>
                <p>On a general view, Theocritus’s surviving poems turn out to be—(1) rural idyls,
                    the patterns of Virgil’s eclogues, and of all later pastoral poetry; (2) minute
                    epics, or cabinet pictures from mythology; (3) sketches of contemporary 1ife in
                    verse; (4) courtly compositions; and (5) expressions of personal kindliness and
                    attachment. The first category and the third are those on which the fame of
                    Theocritus depends. His verse has a wonderful Doric melody; his shepherds are
                    natural Southern people: it is not his fault that what he wrote truly of them
                    has become a false commonplace in the pastoral poetry of the North.</p>
                <p>Of Theocritus’s own life we only know what has been recorded, that he lived in
                    Syracuse, Cos, and Alexandria, and that he was acquainted with Nicias, with
                    Aratus, the astronomical writer, and with Philinus, head of a school or sect of
                    physicians. The rest is silence or conjecture. Suidas says that, in addition to
                    the surviving poems, the <hi rend="italic">Praetidae,</hi> the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hopes, Hymns,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Heroines, Dirges, Elegies,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Iambics</hi> were attributed to him.</p>
                <p>The charm of Theocritus can only be tasted in his original Doric, but the best
                    English version is by Mr C. S. Calverley. Μ. Couat’s book on the Alexandrine
                    school of poetry may be recommended. J. Hauler, <hi rend="italic">De Theοc.
                        Vita</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Carminibus</hi>
                    (Freiburg, 1855), Hempel, <hi rend="italic">Quaest. Theοc.</hi> (Kiel, 1881),
                    and Rannow, <hi rend="italic">Studia</hi><hi rend="italic">Theοcritea</hi>
                    (Berlin, 1886), may also be found useful. The best English edition of the poems
                    is that of Bishop Wordsworth. (A. L.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
