<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0104-0093-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TAYLOR, Jeremy (9th edition, volume 23, page
                    93)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993547">Laude</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1113216">Sermons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h10">Sermons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n104/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TAYLOR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jeremy</hi></label> (1613—1667),
                    was a native of Cambridge, and was baptized on the 15th August 1613. His father,
                    Nathaniel, though a barber, was a man of some education, respected by his
                    townsmen, and lineally descended from Dr Rowland Taylor, Cranmer’s chaplain, who
                    suffered martyrdom under Mary. Jeremy, after passing through the grammar school,
                    was entered at Caius College as a sizar in 1626, eighteen months after Milton
                    had entered Christ’s, and while George Herbert was public orator and Edmund
                    Waller and Thomas Fuller were undergraduates of the university. He was elected a
                    fellow of his college in 1633, but the best evidence of his diligence as a
                    student is the enormous learning of which he showed so easy a command in after
                    years. Accepting the invitation of Risden, a fellow-student, to supply his place
                    for a short time as lecturer in St Paul’s, he at once attracted attention by his
                    remarkable eloquence as well as by his handsome face and youthful appearance.
                    Archbishop Laud, ever on the outlook for men of capacity, sent for Taylor to
                    preach before him at Lambeth, and, discerning that his genius was worth
                    fostering, dismissed him from the overpressure of the metropolis to the quiet of
                    a fellowship in All Souls, Oxford, and at the same time, by making him one of
                    his own chaplains, showed his desire to keep him in permanent connexion with
                    himself. At Oxford Chillingworth was then busy with his great work, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Religion of Protestants,</hi> and it is possible that by
                    intercourse with him Taylor’s mind may have been turned <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n105/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0105-0094"/> towards the liberal movement of his age.
                    After two years in Oxford, in March 1638 he was presented by Juxon, bishop of
                    London, to the rectory of Uppingham, in Rutlandshire. In the autumn of the same
                    year he was appointed to preach in St Marys on the an ni versai y of the
                    Gunpowder Plot, and apparently used the occasion to clear himself of a
                    suspicion, which, however, haunted him through life, of a secret leaning to the
                    Romish communion. This suspicion seems to have arisen chiefly from his intimacy
                    with Christopher Davenport, better known as Francis a Sancta Clara, a learned
                    Franciscan friar who became chaplain to Queen Henrietta; but it may have been
                    strengthened by his known connexion with Laud, as well as by his ascetic habits
                    and ritualistic propensities. More serious consequences followed his attachment
                    to the Royalist cause, when in 1642 the livings of the loyal clergy were
                    sequestered by decree of parliament. The author of <hi rend="italic">Episcopacy
                        Asserted against the Amans and Acephali New and Old,</hi> ineffective as
                    that work seems in the light of modern research, could scarcely hope to retain
                    his parish. Along with Fuller, Chillingworth, and others, he found temporary
                    refuge with the king at Oxford. His two little boys must have been cared for by
                    friends, for his wife, Phoebe Langsdale, whom he had married the year after his
                    settlement at Uppingham, had died with her third child in that disastrous year
                    1642.</p>
                <p>During the next fifteen years Taylor’s movements are not easily traced. Sometimes
                    he appears with the king, from whom at his last interview he received, in token
                    of his regard, his watch and some jewels which had ornamented the ebony case in
                    which he kept his Bible. He is supposed to be the Dr Taylor who was taken
                    prisoner with other Royalists while besieging Cardigan castle. In 1646 he is
                    found in partnership with two other deprived clergymen, keeping a school at
                    Newton Hall, in the parish of Llanvihangel. It was while resident here that he
                    attracted the friendship of one of his kindest patrons, Richard Vaughan, earl of
                    Carbery, whose hospitable mansion, Golden Grove, is immortalized in the title of
                    Taylor’s still popular manual of devotion, and whose countess had the greater
                    distinction of being the original of the “Lady” in Milton’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Cornus.</hi> It was also while resident in Wales that Taylor married his
                    second wife, Joanna Bridges, w ho was generally understood to be a natural
                    daughter of Charles I., and who owned a good estate, though probably
                    impoverished by Parliamentarian exactions, at Mandinam, in Carmarthenshire. From
                    time to time he appears in London in the company of his friend Evelyn, at whose
                    table he met such men as Boyle, Berkeley, and Wilkins. Thrice he was imprisoned:
                    in 1653-4 for a well-intended but injudicious preface to his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Golden Grove</hi>; again in Chepstow castle, from May to October 1655, on
                    what charge does not appear; and a third time in the Tower in 1657-8, on account
                    of the indiscretion of his publisher, Royston, who had adorned his “Collection
                    of Offices” with a print representing Christ in the attitude of prayer. This
                    unsettled life, with its interruptions, harassments, andψrivations, would seem
                    rather to have stimulated than to have stinted the productiveness of his genius.
                    In 1647 appeared his most important work, <hi rend="italic">The Liberty of
                        Prophesying,</hi> and in the following year the complete edition of his <hi
                        rend="italic">Apology for Authorized and Set Forms of Liturgy against the
                        Pretence of the Spirit,</hi> as well as his <hi rend="italic">Life of
                        Christ, or the Great Exemplar,</hi> a book which at once won a popularity it
                    still in large measure retains. Then followed in rapid succession the <hi
                        rend="italic">Twenty-seven Sermons,</hi> “for the summer half-year,” and the
                        <hi rend="italic">Twenty-five</hi> “for the winter half-year,” <hi
                        rend="italic">Holy Living, Holy Dying,</hi> a controversial treatise on the
                    Real Presence, the <hi rend="italic">Golden Grove,</hi> and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Unum Necessarium,</hi> which by its Pelagianism gave great
                    offence. During these years he was also busy with his <hi rend="italic">Ductor
                        Dubitantium</hi> (published in 1660), which he intended to be the standard
                    manual of casuistry and ethics for the Christian people.</p>
                <p>In 1658 settlement was at length reached through the kind offices of the earl of
                    Carbery, who obtained for Taylor a lectureship in Lisburn. At first he declined
                    a post in which the duty was to be shared with a Presbyterian, or, as he
                    expressed it, “where a Presbyterian and myself shall be like Castor and Pollux,
                    the one up and the other down,” and to which also a very meagre salary was
                    attached. He was, however, induced to take it, and found, near his patron’s
                    mansion on Lough Neagh, so congenial a retirement that even after he was raised
                    to a bishopric he continued to make it his home. At the Restoration, instead of
                    being recalled to England, as he probably expected and certainly desired, he was
                    appointed to the see of Down and Connor, to which was shortly added the small
                    and adjacent diocese of Dromore. He was also made a member of the Irish privy
                    council and vice-chancellor of the university of Dublin. None of these honours
                    were sinecures. Of the university he writes, “I found all things in a perfect
                    disorder . . . . a heap of men and boys, but no body of a college, no one
                    member, either fellow or scholar, having any legal title to his place, but
                    thrust in by tyranny or chance.” Accordingly he set himself vigorously to the
                    task of framing and enforcing regulations for the admission and conduct of
                    members of the university, and also of establishing lectureships. His episcopal
                    labours were still more arduous/ There were, at the date of the Restoration,
                    about seventy Presbyterian ministers in the north of Ireland, and most of these
                    were from the west of Scotland, and were imbued with the dislike of Episcopacy
                    which distinguished the Covenanting party. No wonder that Taylor, writing to the
                    duke of Ormonde shortly after his consecration, should have said, “I perceive
                    myself thrown into a place of torment.” His letters perhaps somewhat exaggerate
                    the danger in which he lived, but there is no doubt that his authority w as
                    resisted and his overtures rejected. His writings also were ransacked for matter
                    of accusation against him, “a committee of Scotch spiders being appointed to see
                    if they can gather or make poison out of them.” Here, then, was Taylor’s
                    opportunity for exemplifying the wise toleration he had in other days
                    inculcated. These Presbyterians had, like himself, suffered under Cromwell for
                    their loyalty, and might have been expected to evoke his sympathy; but the new
                    bishop had nothing to offer them but the bare alternative—submission to
                    episcopal ordination and jurisdiction or deprivation. Consequently, in his first
                    visitation, he declared thirty-six churches vacant; and of these forcible
                    possession was taken by his orders. At the same time many of the gentry were won
                    by his undoubted sincerity and devotedness as well as by his eloquence. With the
                    Romanist element of the population he was less successful. Ignorant of the
                    English language, and firmly attached to their ancestral forms of worship, they
                    were yet compelled to attend a service they considered profane, conducted in a
                    language they could not understand. As Heber says, “No part of the
                    administration of Ireland by the English crown has been more extraordinary and
                    more unfortunate than the system pursued for the introduction of the Reformed
                    religion.” At the instance of the Irish bishops Taylor undertook his last great
                    work, the <hi rend="italic">Dissuasive from Popery</hi> (in two parts, 1664 and
                    1667), but, as he himself seemed partly conscious, he might have more
                    effectually gained his end by adopting the methods of Ussher and Bedell, and
                    inducing his clergy to acquire the Irish tongue.</p>
                <p>Nor were domestic sorrows awanting in these later years.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n106/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0106-0095"/>
                <p>Ια 1661 he buried, at Lisburn, Edward, the only surviving son of his second
                    marriage. His oldest son, an officer in the army, was killed in a duel; and his
                    second son, Charles, intended for the church, left Trinity College and became
                    companion and secretary to the duke of Buckingham, at whose house he died. The
                    day after his son’s funeral Taylor sickened, and, after a ten days’ illness, he
                    died at Lisburn on the 13th August 1667, in the fifty-fifth year of his life and
                    the seventh of his episcopate.</p>
                <p>Taylor’s fame has been maintained by the popularity of his sermons and devotional
                    writings rather than by his influence as a theologian or his importance as an
                    ecclesiastic. His mind was neither scientific nor speculative, and he was
                    attracted rather to questions of casuistry than to the deeper problems of pure
                    theology. His wide reading and capacious memory enabled him to carry in his mind
                    the materials of a sound historical theology, but these materials were unsifted
                    by criticism. His immense learning served him rather as a storehouse of
                    illustrations, or as an armoury out of which he could choose the fittest weapon
                    for discomfiting an opponent, than as a quarry furnishing him with material for
                    building up a completely designed and enduring edifice of systematized truth.
                    Indeed, he had very limited faith in the human mind as an instrument of truth.
                    “Theology,” he says, “is rather a divine life than a divine knowledge.” His
                    great plea for toleration is based on the impossibility of erecting theology
                    into a demonstrable science. “It is impossible all should be of one mind. And
                    what is impossible to be done is not necessary it should be done.” Differences
                    of opinion there must be; but “heresy is not an error of the understanding but
                    an error of the will.” His aim in life was practical; his interests were in men
                    rather than in ideas, and his sympathies were evoked rather by the experiences
                    of individuals than by great movements. Of a decidedly poetic temperament,
                    fervid and mobile in feeling, and of a prolific fancy, he had also the sense and
                    wit that come of varied contact with men. All his gifts were made available for
                    influencing other men by his easy command of a style rarely matched in dignity
                    and colour. With all the majesty and stately elaboration and musical rhythm of
                    Milton’s finest prose, Taylor’s style is relieved and brightened by an
                    astonishing variety of felicitous illustrations, ranging from the most homely
                    and terse to the most dignified and elaborate. His sermons especially abound in
                    quotations and allusions, which have the air of spontaneously suggesting
                    themselves, but which must sometimes have baffled his hearers. This seeming
                    pedantry is, however, atoned for by the clear practical aim of his sermons, the
                    noble ideal he keeps before his hearers, and the skill with which he handles
                    spiritual experience and urges incentives to virtue. But, through all his
                    gorgeous eloquence and genial interest in human nature, there breaks from time
                    to time some dead and laboured irrelevancy, the growth of his training in
                    scholastic dialectics; for “like some other writers of the 17th century he seems
                    almost to have two minds,—one tender, sweet, luxuriant to excess, the other
                    hard, subtle, formal, prone to definition and logomachy.”</p>
                <p>The first collected edition of his works was published by Bishop Heber (with a
                    life) in 1822, reissued after careful revision by Charles Page Eden, 1852-61.
                    (Μ. D. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
