<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0094-0083-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TAVERNIER, Jean Baptiste</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 83</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b40p0ww6s">Journeys</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:843075">Butlers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1093581">Relationism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n94/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TAVERNIER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean Baptiste</hi></label>
                    (1605-1689), the celebrated traveller and pioneer of French trade with India,
                    was born (1605) at Paris, where his father Gabriel and uncle Melchior,
                    Protestants from Antwerp, pursued with reputation and success the profession of
                    geographers and engravers. The conversations he heard in his father’s house
                    inspired Jean Baptiste with an early desire to travel, and in his sixteenth year
                    he had already visited England, the Low Countries, and Germany, and seen
                    something of war with the imperialist Colonel Hans Brenner, whom he met at
                    Nuremberg. Four and a half years in the household of Brenner’s uncle, the
                    viceroy of Hungary (1624-29), and a briefer connexion in 1629 with the duke of
                    Rethel and his father the duke of Nevers, prince of Mantua, gave him the habit
                    of courts, which was invaluable to him in later years, and at the defence of
                    Mantua in 1629, and in Germany in the following year with Colonel Walter Butler
                    (afterwards notorious through the death of Wallenstein), <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n95/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0095-0084"/> he gained some military experience. When he left
                    Butler to view the diet of Ratisbon in 1630, he had seen Italy, Switzerland,
                    Germany, Poland, and Hungary, as well as France, England, and the Low Countries,
                    and spoke the principal languages of these regions. He was now eager to visit
                    the East, and at Ratisbon he found the opportunity to join two French fathers,
                    M. de Chapes and M. de St Liebau, who had received a mission to the Levant. In
                    their company he reached Constantinople early in 1631, and here he spent eleven
                    months, and then proceeded by Tokat, Erzerum, and Erivan to Persia. His farthest
                    point in this first journey was Ispahan; he returned by Baghdad, Aleppo,
                    Alexandretta, Malta, and Italy, and was again in Paris in 1633. Of the next five
                    years of his life nothing is known with certainty, but it is probable that it
                    was during this period that he became controller of the household of the duke of
                    Orleans. In September 1638 he began a second journey (1638-43) by Aleppo to
                    Persia and thence to India as far as Agra and Golconda. His visit to the court
                    of the Great Mogul and to the famous diamond mines was, of course, connected
                    with the plans realized more fully in his later voyages, in which Tavernier
                    travelled as a merchant of the highest rank, trading in costly jewels and other
                    precious wares, and finding his chief customers among the greatest princes of
                    the East. The second journey was followed up by four others. In his third
                    journey (1643-49) he went as far as Java and returned by the Cape; but his
                    relations with the Dutch proved not wholly satisfactory, and a long lawsuit on
                    his return yielded but imperfect redress. In his last three journeys (1651-55,
                    1657-62, 1664-68) he did not proceed beyond India. The details of these voyages
                    need not detain us here, and indeed are often obscure; but they completed an
                    extraordinary knowledge of the routes of overland Eastern trade, and brought the
                    now famous merchant into close and friendly communication with the greatest
                    Oriental potentates. They also secured for him a large fortune and great
                    reputation at home. He was presented to Louis XIV., “in whose service he had
                    travelled sixty thousand leagues by land,” received letters of nobility (16th
                    February 1669), and in the following year purchased the barony of Aubonne, near
                    Geneva. In 1662 he had married Madeleine Goisse, daughter of a Parisian
                    jeweller.</p>
                <p>Thus settled in ease and affluence, Tavernier occupied himself, as it would seem
                    at the desire of the king, in publishing the account of his journeys. He had
                    neither the equipment nor the tastes of a scientific traveller, but in all that
                    referred to commerce his knowledge was vast and could not fail to be of much
                    public service. He set to work therefore with the aid of Samuel Chappuzeau, a
                    French Protestant littérateur, and produced a <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle
                    Relation de VInterieur du Serail du Grand Seigneur</hi> (4to, Paris, 1675),
                    based on two visits to Constantinople in his first and sixth journeys. This was
                    followed by <hi rend="italic">Le Six Voyages de J. B. Tavernier</hi> (2 vols.
                    4to, Paris, 1676) and by a supplementary <hi rend="italic">Recueil de Plusieurs
                    Relations</hi> (4to, Paris, 1679), in which he was assisted by a certain La
                    Chapelle. This last contains an account of Japan, gathered from merchants and
                    others, and one of Tong-king, derived from the observations of his brother
                    Daniel, who had shared his second voyage and settled at Batavia; it contained
                    also a violent attack on the agents of the Dutch East India Company, at whose
                    hands Tavernier had suffered more than one wrong. This attack was elaborately
                    answered in Dutch by H. van Quellenburgh (<hi rend="italic">Vindiciae
                    Bata-vicae,</hi> Amst., 1684), but made more noise because Arnauld drew from it
                    some material unfavourable to Protestantism for his <hi rend="italic">Apologie
                    pour les Catholiques</hi> (1681), and so brought on the traveller a ferocious
                    onslaught in Jurieu’s <hi rend="italic">Esprit de Μ. Arnauld</hi> (1684).
                    Tavernier made no reply to Jurieu; he was in fact engaged in weightier matters,
                    for in 1684 he travelled to Berlin at the invitation of the Great Elector, who
                    commissioned him to organize an Eastern trading company,—a project never
                    realized. The closing years of Tavernier’s life are obscure; the time was not
                    favourable for a Protestant, and it has even been supposed that he passed some
                    time in the Bastille. What is certain is that he left Paris for Switzerland in
                    1687, that in 1689 he passed through Copenhagen on his way to Persia through
                    Muscovy, and that in the same year he died at Moscow. It appears that he had
                    still business relations in the East, and that the neglect of these by his
                    nephew, to whom they were intrusted, had determined the indefatigable old man to
                    a fresh journey.</p>
                <p>Tavernier’s travels, though often reprinted and translated, have two defects: the
                    author uses other men’s material without distinguishing it from his own
                    observations; and the narrative is much confused by his plan of often deserting
                    the chronological order and giving instead notes from various journeys about
                    certain routes. The latter defect, it is true, while it embarrasses the
                    biographer, is hardly a blemish in view of the object of the writer, who sought
                    mainly to furnish a guide to other merchants. A careful attempt to disentangle
                    the thread of a life still in many parts obscure has been made by Charles Joret,
                    <hi rend="italic">Jean Baptiste Tavernier d'après des Documents Nouveaux,</hi>
                    8vo, Paris, 1886, where the literature of the subject is fully given.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
