<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0194-0181-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TENNIS, Lawn (9th edition, volume 23, page 181)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5wd7c">Lawns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cf8t">Nets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n87332f">Netting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4697014k">Drops</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1036191">Nets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1036214">Netting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937529">Games</term>
                    <term ref="fast:898380">Drops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:994321">Lawns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n194/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TENNIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Lawn</hi></label>. Lawn-tennis
                    is a modern adaptation of the first principle of tennis, in the simplest form,
                    to a ball-game played on grass with rackets. The balls are of india-rubber,
                    hollow, and covered with white cloth. The rackets are lighter and broader than
                    those used at tennis. The court for the single-handed game, one player against
                    one, is shown in fig. 1, that for the three or four-handed game in fig. 2. The
                    dimensions of the courts, the size</p>
                <p>Lawn-tennis courts. Fig. 1, for single game; fig. 2, for double game, and weight
                    of the balls, the mode of scoring, and other details are given in the laws of
                    the game (see below). The only requisites for the game are the balls, rackets,
                    net and posts, and a hard level surface of grass. It may be, and often is,
                    played upon surfaces of wood, asphalt, cement, gravel, or other substance. The
                    grass requires constant mowing, rolling, and in dry weather watering, to keep it
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n195/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0195-0182"/> in order. In the winter months it should be
                    sedulously weeded, sown where necessary, and swept and rolled whenever the
                    weather permits.</p>
                <p>The choice of sides depends upon a toss or spin of a racket, as in tennis. The
                    winner chooses the service or the preferable side, as he pleases. The server
                    begins the game by striking the ball with his racket so that it passes (without
                    touching) over the net, which is hung across the court from the posts A, A. The
                    ball served must drop in the space which is diagonally opposite to him on the
                    other side of the net,—a space bounded by the net, the side line, the half-court
                    line, and the service line. His adversary, called the “striker-out,” must return
                    the ball before it touches the ground a second time; and the server must
                    similarly return it again; and so on, until one or other player fails to return
                    it over the net so that it shall drop on the ground anywhere on the side of the
                    net furthest from him, and within or upon any of the lines which bound that
                    space, technically called his adversary’s <hi rend="italic">court.</hi> When one
                    player thus fails, he loses a stroke, which the other is deemed to win, and it
                    is added to the score of the latter. The score is kept as at tennis, but there
                    are no chases.</p>
                <p>Activity and condition have great value in lawn-tennis, though there is room for
                    much skill in placing the ball in the corners with hard, low strokes, and in
                    intercepting and returning the ball by the volley while in the air, before it
                    reaches the ground. But in matches temper, endurance, and quickness of movement
                    count for very much.</p>
                <p>Lawn-tennis, in one form or another, has been played for many centuries
                    out-of-doors. The present variety of the game was first introduced, in a form
                    which was soon shown to be impracticable, about the year 1874. It was then taken
                    up by the All England Club at Wimbledon, who in 1877 remodelled the size and
                    shape of the court, and the laws, and altered the system of scoring to that
                    which obtains in the parent game. Thereupon, with the consent of the M.C.C. at
                    Lord’s, who lent the authority of their name to the movement, the code of laws
                    which now prevails, and has been occasionally amended only in a few details, was
                    promulgated by the All England Club. The championship of the game, which is open
                    to gentlemen amateurs only, was instituted at Wimbledon by the A.E.C. in 18.77.
                    A lady’s championship and a championship for pairs (gentlemen) have also been
                    instituted, and are annually competed for on the grounds of the A.E.C. at
                    Wimbledon. Lawntennis, in the short time which has elapsed since its
                    introduction, has achieved immense popularity. Prize-meetings are held annually
                    at Bath, Cheltenham, Dublin, Edinburgh, Manchester, Liverpool, and many other
                    places in the United Kingdom; the game is also played with as great enthusiasm
                    in the United States, Canada, Australia, and India. In all those countries
                    prize-meetings are held and championships are instituted.</p>
                <p>Laws.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Printed by
                            permission of the All England Lawn-Tennis Club.</p></note> i <hi
                        rend="italic">Single-Handed Game.</hi></p>
                <p>1. For the single-handed game the court is 27 feet in width and 78 feet in
                    length. It is divided across the middle by a net, the ends of which are attached
                    to the tops of two posts A and A (see fig. 1), which stand 3 feet outside the
                    court on each side. The height of the net is 3 feet 6 inches at the posts and 3
                    feet at the centre. At each end of the court, parallel to the net, and at a
                    distance of 39 feet from it, are drawn the base lines CD and EF, the extremities
                    of which are connected by the side lines CE and DF. Half-way between the side
                    lines, and parallel to them, is drawn the half-court line GH, dividing the space
                    on each side of the net into two equal parts, called the right and left courts.
                    On each side of the net, at a distance of 21 feet from it, and parallel to it,
                    are drawn the service lines XX and YY.</p>
                <p>2. The balls shall be not less than 21 inches nor more than 2, <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 9</hi><hi rend="subscript"> s</hi> inches in diameter,
                    and not less than 1J oz. nor more than 2 oz. in weight.</p>
                <p>3. In matches where umpires are appointed their decision shall be final; but
                    where a referee is appointed an appeal shall lie to him from the decision of an
                    umpire on a question of law.</p>
                <p>4. The choice of sides and the right of serving during the first game shall be
                    decided by toss, provided that, if the winner of the toss choose the right to
                    serve, the other player shall have the choice of sides, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >vice versa.</hi></p>
                <p>5. The players shall stand on opposite sides of the net. The player who first
                    delivers the ball shall be called the server, the other the striker-out.</p>
                <p>6. At the end of the first game the striker-out shall become server and the
                    server shall become striker-out; and so on alternately in the subsequent games
                    of the set.</p>
                <p>7. The server shall stand with one foot beyond <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi>
                    further from the net than) the base line, and with the other foot upon the base
                    line, and shall deliver the service from the right and left courts alternately,
                    beginning from the right.</p>
                <p>8. The ball served must drop within the service line, half-court line, and side
                    line of the court which is diagonally opposite to that from which it was served,
                    or upon any such line.</p>
                <p>9. It is a fault if the service be delivered from the wrong court, or if the
                    server do not stand as directed in law 7, or if the ball served drop in the net
                    or beyond the service line, or if it drop out of court or in the wrong court; it
                    is not a fault if the server’s foot which is beyond the base line do not touch
                    the ground at the moment at which the service is delivered.</p>
                <p>10. A fault may not be taken.</p>
                <p>11. After a fault, the server shall serve again from the same court from which he
                    served that fault, unless it was a fault because served from the wrong
                    court.</p>
                <p>12. A fault may not be claimed after the next service has been delivered.</p>
                <p>13. The service may not be volleyed, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> taken before it
                    touches the ground.</p>
                <p>14. The server shall not serve until the striker-out is ready. If the latter
                    attempt to return the service, he shall be deemed to be ready.</p>
                <p>15. A ball is in play from the moment at which it is delivered in service (unless
                    a fault) until it has been volleyed by the striker-out in his first stroke, or
                    has dropped in the net or out of court, or has touched either of the players or
                    anything that he wears or carries, except his racket in the act of striking, or
                    has been struck by either of the players λvith his racket more than once
                    consecutively, or has been volleyed before it has passed over the net, or has
                    failed to pass over the net before its first bound (except as provided in law
                    17), or has touched the ground twice consecutively on either side of the net,
                    though the second time may have been out of court.</p>
                <p>16. It is a let if the ball served touch the net, provided the service be
                    otherwise good, or if a service or fault be delivered when the striker-out is
                    not ready, or if either player be prevented by an accident beyond his control
                    from serving or returning the ball in play. In case of a let, the service or
                    stroke counts for nothing, and the server shall serve again.</p>
                <p>17. It is a good' return although the ball touch the net, or, having passed
                    outside either post, drop on or within any of the lines which bound the court
                    into which it is returned.</p>
                <p>18. The server wins a stroke if the striker-out volley the service, or fail to
                    return the service or the ball in play (except in the case of a let), or return
                    the service or ball in play so that it drop outside any of the lines which bound
                    his opponent’s court, or otherwise lose a stroke, as provided by law 20.</p>
                <p>19. The striker-out wins a stroke if the server serve two consecutive faults, or
                    fail to return the ball in play (except in the case of a let), or return the
                    ball in play so that it drop outside any of the lines which bound his opponent’s
                    court, or otherwise lose a stroke, as provided by law 20.</p>
                <p>20. Either player loses a stroke if the ball in play touch him or anything that
                    he wears or carries, except his racket in the act of striking, or if he touch or
                    strike the ball in play with his racket more than once consecutively, or if he
                    touch the net or any of its supports while the ball is in play, or if he volley
                    the ball before it has passed the net.</p>
                <p>21. On either player winning his first stroke, the score is called 15 for that
                    player; on either player winning his second stroke, the score is called 30 for
                    that player; on either player winning his third stroke, the score is called 40
                    for that player; and the fourth stroke won by either player is scored game for
                    that player, except as below.</p>
                <p>If both players have won three strokes, the score is called deuce; and the next
                    stroke won by either player is scored advantage for that player. If the same
                    player win the next stroke, he wins the game; if he lose the next stroke, the
                    score is again called deuce; and so on until either player win the two strokes
                    immediately following the score of deuce, when the game is scored for that
                    player.</p>
                <p>22. The player who first wins six games wins a set, except as below.</p>
                <p>If both players win five games, the score is called games all; and the next game
                    won by either player is scored advantage game for that player. If the same
                    player win the next game, he wins the set; if he lose the next game, the score
                    is again called games all; and so on until either player win the two games
                    immediately following the score of games all, when he wins the set.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note.—</hi> Players may agree not to play advantage sets, but
                    to decide the set by one game after arriving at the score of games all.</p>
                <p>23. The players shall change sides at the end of every set; but the umpire, on
                    appeai from either party before the toss for choice, may direct the players to
                    change sides at the end of every game if in his opinion either side have a
                    distinct advantage, owing to the sun, wind, or any other accidental cause; but,
                    if the appeal be made after a match has been begun, the umpire may only direct
                    the players to change sides at the end of every game of the odd and concluding
                    set.</p>
                <p>24. when a series of sets is played, the player who was server in the last game
                    of one set shall be striker-out in the first game of the next.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Odds.</hi></p>
                <p>25. A bisque is one stroke, which may be claimed by the receiver of the odds at
                    any time during a set, except as below.</p>
                <p>A bisque may not be taken after the service has been delivered.</p>
                <p>The server may not take a bisque after a fault; but the striker-out may do
                    so.</p>
                <p>26. One or more bisques may be given in augmentation or diminution of other
                    odds.</p>
                <p>27. Half-fifteen is one stroke given at the beginning of the second and every
                    subsequent alternate game of a set.</p>
                <p>28. Fifteen is one stroke given at the beginning of every game of a set.</p>
                <p>29. Haif-thirty is one stroke given at the beginning of the first game, two
                    strokes at the beginning of the second game; and so on, alternately, in all the
                    subsequent games of a set.</p>
                <p>30. Thirty is two strokes given at the beginning of every game of a set.</p>
                <p>31. Half-forty is two strokes given at the beginning of the first game, three
                    strokes at the beginning of the second game; and so on, alternately, in all the
                    subsequent games of a set.</p>
                <p>32. Forty is three strokes given at the beginning of every game of a set.</p>
                <p>33. Half-court: the players having agreed into which court the giver of the odds
                    shall play, the latter loses a stroke if the ball, returned by him, drop outside
                    any of the lines which bound that court.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Three-Handed and Four-Handed Games.</hi></p>
                <p>34. The above laws shall apply to the three-handed and four-handed games, except
                    as below. . .</p>
                <p>35. For the three-handed and four-handed games the court is 36 feet in width.
                    Within the side lines, at a distance of 4⅜ feet from them, and parallel to them,
                    are drawn the service side lines IK and LM. The service lines are not drawn
                    beyond the points I, L, K, and M, towards the side lines. In other respects, the
                    court is similar to that which is described in law 1.</p>
                <p>36. In the three-handed game the single player shall serve in every alternate
                    game. .... .</p>
                <p>37. In the four-handed game, the pair who have the right to serve in the first
                    game may decide which partner shall do so, and the opposing pair may decide
                    similarly for the second game. The partner of the player who served in the first
                    game shall serve in the third; and the partner of the player who served in the
                    second game shall serve in the fourth; and so on in the same order in all the
                    subsequent games of a set.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n196/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0196-0183"/>
                <p>38. The players shall take the service alternately throughout each game. No
                    player shall receive or return a service delivered to his partner. The order of
                    service and of striking-out once arranged shall not be altered, nor shall the
                    strikers-out change courts to receive the service, before the end of the
                    set.</p>
                <p>39. The ball served must drop within the service line, half-court line, and
                    service side line of the court which is diagonally opposite to that from which
                    it was served, or upon any such line.</p>
                <p>40. It is a fault if the ball served do not drop as provided in law 39, or if it
                    touch the server’s partner or anything that he wears or carries.</p>
                <p>41. If a player serve out of his turn, the umpire, as soon as the mistake is
                    discovered by himself or by one of the players, shall direct the player to serve
                    who ought to have served; but all strokes scored and any fault served before
                    such discovery shall be reckoned. If a game shall have been completed before
                    such discovery, then the service in the next alternate game shall be delivered
                    by the partner of the player who served out of his turn; and so on in regular
                    rotation. (J. MA*.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
