<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0508-0489-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TOURNAMENTS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 489</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94n5q">Weapons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sh1s">Tournaments</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43x83k73">Firearms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4416t25p">Doubt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r392">Baldness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1173008">Weapons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1939378">Tournaments</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:825760">Baldness</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:800130">Age</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n508/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TOURNAMENTS</label>. Tournaments and jousts were the chief
                    military exercises and displays of the age of chivalry. Besides being the
                    appropriate sports and pastimes of a warlike era and caste, they were intended
                    to test the skill and exhibit the prowess of the knights and squires who took
                    part in them. Considered under their more serious aspect, apart from their
                    association with pomp and festivity, they were, practically speaking, the
                    equivalents of the reviews and sham-fights of later times, and were designed as
                    a preparation for the actual manoeuvres and real conflicts of the battlefield.
                    Tournaments and jousts differed from one another principally in the circumstance
                    that in the first several combatants on each side were engaged at once, and in
                    the second the contention was between two combatants only. The former consisted
                    of the mutual charges of equal troops of cavalry, while the latter consisted of
                    a duel on horseback. Du Cange says that the French <hi rend="italic"
                    >tournoi,</hi> English “tournament,” “was a general expression which
                    comprehended all sorts of combats that were performed by way of exercise. But it
                    more properly meant such as were performed by companies, where many were in
                    conflict against the same number, representing the form of a battle. When those
                    general combats were ended, then single ones commenced <hi rend="italic">;
                    for</hi> all who were desirous of displaying their address, and attracting
                    public notice for their valour, offered single combat with sword or lance
                    against all who should present themselves”; and he adds that these combats were
                    called by the old French writers “joustes,” which is the same word as the
                    English “jousts.” But jousts were held far more frequently than, and quite
                    independently of, regular tournaments throughout the period in which the customs
                    of chivalry were observed, and, according to some authorities, the lance alone
                    was used in them, while in the others all weapons except firearms were employed.
                    In both cases such weapons were usually although not invariably rendered
                    innocuous, and it was only rarely that the combatants were killed or injured by
                    wounds, as distinguished from falls and bruises. But in one way or another
                    tournaments and jousts were always extremely dangerous, and a long list of
                    eminent persons met their deaths in them, from Raoul, Comte de Guines, to Henry
                    II. of France. It may be assumed that jousts in some shape existed at all
                    periods, in which men fought in armour and on horseback, and were in the habit
                    of practising themselves in time of peace for the exigencies of warfare. But it
                    is very doubtful when and where tournaments, in the proper sense of the term,
                    were originally instituted. The older writers on the subject sought to connect
                    them with the “Troja” or “ludus Trojae” among the Romans. But this is a piece of
                    archaeology of the same sort as that which identified the knighthood of the
                    Middle Ages with the ancient “ordo equestris,” and will not, of course, bear
                    examination. Much reliance again has been placed by some of them on the account
                    of a sham-fight which was held at the celebrated interview between the emperor
                    Louis and Charles the Bald in 841, which in certain respects bore a close
                    resemblance to a tournament, and was no doubt the kind of exhibition out of
                    which the tournament of a later age was developed. Others attribute the
                    institution of tournaments to the emperor Henry the Fowler, who died in 936, or
                    to Geoffrey de Preuilly, the ancestor of the counts of Tours, who died in 1066.
                    However this may be, it is certain that they were in vogue on the Continent at
                    the end of the 11th century, and that in the early part of the 12th century they
                    were introduced into England. In the 13th and 14th centuries they were common
                    all over Christendom, including the Eastern as well as the Western empire and
                    the states comprised in or adjacent to it. It was not until the end of the 16th
                    century that tilts and hastiludes passed out of fashion in Britain, and even in
                    the earlier years of the 17th century they were occasionally celebrated under
                    the patronage of Henry, prince of Wales, son of King James I.</p>
                <p>The older authorities on tournaments and jousts are exceedingly numerous. But all
                    that is material in what they have written will be found in Ste Palaye’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoires sur l'Ancienne Chevalerie</hi> and Mills’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Chivalry.</hi> The “Dissertations” of Du Cange at the
                    end of Joinville’s <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chronicles</hi> of Froissart and Monstrelet may also be consulted. Ste Palaye
                    and Mills were both industrious compilers, and the second is much indebted to
                    the first.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
