<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0409-0390-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TILLOTSON, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 390</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h10">Sermons</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892f8z">Faith</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198492">Faith</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:832891">Birch</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1113216">Sermons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1043068">Occasionalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n409/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TILLOTSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label>
                    (1630-1694), archbishop of Canterbury, was the son of a Puritan clothier in
                    Sowerby, Yorkshire, where he was born in October 1630. He entered as a pensioner
                    of Clare Hall, Cambridge, in 1647, graduated in 1650, and was made fellow of his
                    college in 1651. Chillingworth’s <hi rend="italic">Religion of
                    Protestantism,</hi> biassed his mind against Puritanism, and the bias was
                    further confirmed by intercourse with Cudworth and others at Cambridge. In 1656
                    he became tutor to the son of Edward Prideaux, attorney-general to Cromwell. In
                    what year he took orders is unknown, but, according to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Life</hi> published in 1717, the person who ordained him was Dr T. Sydserf, a
                    Scottish bishop. Tillotson was present at the Savoy Conference in 1661, and
                    remained identified with the Presbyterians till the passing of the Act of
                    Uniformity in 1662. Shortly afterwards he became curate of Cheshunt, Herts, and
                    in June 1663 rector of Keddington, Suffolk. For several years after his
                    ordination he devoted himself to an exact study of the Scriptures, ancient
                    ethics, and the writings of the early fathers, especially Basil and Chrysostom.
                    The result was seen in the general tone of his preaching, whioh was practical
                    rather than theological, and, though regarded by some as latitudinarian, was
                    characterized by the earnestness of sincere conviction and the balanced wisdom
                    gained by thoughtful reflexion. He was, moreover, a man of the world as well as
                    a divine, and in his sermons he exhibited a certain indefinable tact which
                    enabled him at once to win the ear of his audience. His style is chiefly
                    remarkable for its simplicity and clearness, and in this respect it mirrored his
                    own candour and sincerity. The qualities above mentioned won him in his lifetime
                    the reputation of “having brought preaching to perfection ”; and probably it was
                    because he was neither brilliant, original, nor profound that his preaching was
                    so universally admired. “His sermons,” says Burnet, “were so well heard and
                    liked, and so much read, that all the nation proposed him as a pattern and
                    studied to copy after him.” In 1664 he became preacher at Lincoln’s Inn. The
                    same year he married Miss French, daughter of the canon of Christ Church,
                    Oxford, and niece of Oliver Cromwell; and he also became Tuesday lecturer at St
                    Lawrence, Jewry. Tillotson employed his controversial weapons with some skill
                    against “atheism” and “Popery.” In 1663 he published a characteristic sermon on
                    “The Wisdom of being Religious,” and in 1666 replied to Sergeant’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Sure Footing in Christianity</hi> by a pamphlet on the <hi
                    rend="italic">Rule of Faith.</hi> The same year he received the degree of D.D.
                    In 1670 he became prebendary and in 1672 dean of Canterbury. Through his wife
                    Tillotson became connected with Dr Wilkins, the second husband of her mother. In
                    1675 he edited Wilkins’s <hi rend="italic">Principles of Natural Religion,</hi>
                    completing what was left unfinished of it, and in 1682 his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sermons,</hi> with a preface in which he vindicated Wilkins from certain
                    misrepresentations of Wood in his <hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities of
                    the University of Oxford.</hi> In 1680 he brought out Barrow’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Treatise of the Pope’s Supremacy,</hi> and in 1683 his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sermons.</hi> On 5th November 1678 Tillotson preached a sermon against Popery
                    before the House of Commons, in which he maintained that it was their duty to
                    make provision against the propagation of a religion more mischievous than
                    irréligion itself; but in a sermon on the Protestant religion in 1680 before the
                    king he propounded the proposition that Catholics could enjoy their own faith,
                    but not openly draw men off from the profession of the established religion.
                    Along with Burnet, Tillotson attended Lord Russell on the scaffold in 1683, and
                    after the publication of Lord Russell’s speech was appointed to appear before
                    the privy council; but his explanations were regarded as satisfactory, the chief
                    suspicions in connexion with the speech resting on Burnet. Tillotson afterwards
                    enjoyed the friendship of Lady Russell, and it was partly through her that he
                    obtained so much influence with Princess Anne, who followed his advice in regard
                    to the settlement of the crown on William of Orange. He possessed the special
                    confidence of William and Mary, and was made clerk of the closet to the king,
                    27th March 1689. It was chiefly through his advice that the king appointed an
                    ecclesiastical commission for the reconciliation of the Dissenters, and he was
                    regarded as the representative in the commission of the views of the king and
                    queen. In August of this year he was appointed by the chapter of his cathedral
                    to exercise the archiépiscopal jurisdiction of the province of Canterbury during
                    the suspension of Sancroft. He was also about the same time named dean of St
                    Paul’s. Soon afterwards he was elected to succeed Sancroft; but he accepted the
                    promotion with extreme reluctance, and it was deferred from time to time at his
                    request till April 1691. His attempts to reform certain abuses of the church,
                    especially that of non-residence among the clergy, awakened against him much
                    ill-will, and of this the Jacobites took every possible advantage and pursued
                    him to the end of his life with insult and reproach. “This,” Burnet says, “could
                    neither provoke him, nor fright him from his duty; but it affected his mind so
                    much that this was thought to have shortened his days.” He died of palsy on 24th
                    November 1694.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n410/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0410-0391"/>
                <p>For his manuscript sermons Tillotson’s widow received. 2500 guineas, then an
                    unexampled sum, and for many years their popularity remained unrivalled. During
                    his lifetime he published <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Several Occasions,</hi>
                    1671, republished with a second volume added in 1678; <hi rend="italic">Fifty
                    Sermons and the Rule of Faith,</hi> 1691; <hi rend="italic">Four Sermons
                    concerning the Divinity and Incarnation of our Blessed Saviour,</hi> 1693; <hi
                    rend="italic">Six Sermons on Several Occasions,</hi> 1694. His <hi rend="italic"
                    >Posthumous Sermons,</hi> edited by Dr Ralph Baker, appeared in 14 vols., 1694;
                    third edition, 1704. His <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> were published in 1707-
                    1710, and were frequently reprinted. In 1752 an edition appeared in 3 vols, with
                    <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> by Thomas Birch, D.D., compiled from Tillotson’s
                    original papers and letters. Of the many subsequent editions the best is that,
                    with <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> by Birch, of 1820,10 vols. Various selections
                    from his sermons and works have been published separately.</p>
                <p>See in addition to Birch's <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> Welford’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Memorials,</hi> Burnet’s <hi rend="italic">Own Times,</hi> and
                    Macaulay’s <hi rend="italic">History of England.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
