<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0093-0082-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TAUNTON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 82</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vt1gs41">Marketing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r22w">Markets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1010167">Marketing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1010316">Markets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:959074">Home</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n93/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TAUNTON</label>, a municipal borough and market-town of
                    Somerset, England, is situated in the beautiful and fertile vale of Taunton
                    Dene, on the river Tone, on the Taunton and Bridgwater Canal, and on several
                    branches of the Great Western Railway, 45 miles south-south-west of Bristol, 31
                    north-east of Exeter, and 163 -west-south-west of London. The river is crossed
                    by a stone bridge of three arches. The town is -well built, the three main
                    streets being wide and regular, and meeting in a triangular space in the centre
                    called the Parade, where there is a market cross. The castle, now occupied by
                    the museum of the Somerset Archaeological and Natural History Society, is
                    reputed to have been founded by Ine, king of the West-Saxons. The earliest
                    portion of the present building was erected by Walter Gifiard, bishop of
                    Winchester, in the time of Henry I., but the whole building was repaired in
                    1496, and an embattled gateway erected by Bishop Langton. The church of St Mary
                    Magdalene, a spacious building with double aisles both north and south of the
                    nave, is chiefly Perpendicular, but has remains of Norman work in <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n94/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0094-0083"/> the chancel arch, and of Early English in the
                    north aisles and transepts. It possesses one of the finest of the characteristic
                    towers of Somerset, but only a facsimile reproduction (erected 1857-62) of the
                    old one. There are still some remains of the Augustinian priory founded by
                    Bishop Giffard, and there are also two modern convents. Taunton is an important
                    centre of education, the principal institutions being the grammar school
                    (founded in 1522 by Richard Fox, bishop of Winchester), Huish’s schools, the
                    Independent college (1841), and the Wesleyan collegiate institution (1847). The
                    other principal public buildings are the old market-house, the assembly rooms,
                    the new market in the Ionic style, and the shire hall in the Elizabethan style,
                    opened in 1858 at a cost of £28,000. The charitable institutions include the
                    Taunton and Somerset hospital (opened in 1809 and extended in 1870 and 1873),
                    the eye infirmary (1816), Gray’s almshouses and chapel (1635), St Saviour’s home
                    for boys (1870), and the servants’ training home (1882). The town possesses
                    manufactories of silk, collars and cuffs, and gloves, iron and brass foundries,
                    coach-building works, and breweries. There is also a considerable agricultural
                    trade. The population of the municipal and parliamentary borough (area 1249
                    acres) in 1881 was 16,614. The population of the same area in 1871 was
                    15,466.</p>
                <p>Taunton has played a prominent part during the troubled periods of English
                    history. Various Roman remains prove it to have been occupied by the Romans; but
                    it first obtained historical notice when Ine, king of the West-Saxons, made it
                    the border fortress of his kingdom. It takes the name Taunton, or Thoneton, from
                    its situation on the Tone or Thone. The castle was razed by Ethelburg after
                    expelling Edbricht, king of the South-Saxons. About the time of λVilliam the
                    Conqueror the town and castle were granted to the bishop of Winchester, and for
                    many years the castle was the bishop’s principal residence. In the reign of
                    William it possessed a mint. In 1497 the town and castle were seized by the
                    impostor Perkin Warbeck. Taunton was made the seat of the suffragan see of
                    Taunton and Bridgwater in 1538, but, on the death of William Finch, the first
                    bishop, in 1559, the Act had no further operation in reference to Tauuton. Like
                    the other towns of Somerset, Taunton was strongly Puritan in its sympathies.
                    Situated at a point where the main roads of the county met, it was during the
                    Civil War almost constantly in a state of siege by one or other of the rival
                    parties. Having been garrisoned by the Parliamentary forces, it was captured by
                    the Royalists in the summer of 1643, but on 8th July 1644 it was, after a long
                    siege, taken by Blake, who held it with heroic pertinacity till relieved by
                    Fairfax on the 11th May 1645, and again after it was invested by 10,000 troops
                    under Goring till the siege was finally raised on the 3d July. Still constant to
                    its Puritan traditions, Taunton welcomed Monmouth in 1685 with acclamation, and
                    he was proclaimed king there on the 20th J une, the maidens of the town
                    presenting him with a standard. As a consequence, Taunton was made the chief
                    example of the fearful vengeance of Jeffreys, who, at the assizes held in the
                    castle, condemned no fewer than 134 inhabitants of the town and neighbourhood to
                    death, and a much larger number to transportation. Taunton obtained a municipal
                    charter from Charles I. in 1627, which was revoked in 1660. A second charter,
                    granted by Charles II. in 1677, was permitted to lapse in 1792 owing to the
                    corporation allowing a majority of their number to die without filling up the
                    vacancies. From this time until it again received municipal government, 17th
                    April 1877, it was under the care of two bailiffs appointed at the court leet of
                    the lord of the manor. Formerly the town returned two members to parliament, but
                    in 1885 the number-was reduced to one.</p>
                <p>See Totilmin’s <hi rend="italic">History of Taunton,</hi> edited by Savage, 1822;
                    and several papers in the <hi rend="italic">Proceedings</hi> of the Somerset
                    Archaeological Society for 1872.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
