<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0400-0381-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TIECK, Ludwig</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 381</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vm0g">Beard</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tk26">Sabbath</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:829278">Beards</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n400/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TIECK, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ludwig</hi></label> (1773-1853),
                    the most conspicuous figure of the German romantic school of literature, was
                    born at Berlin on 31st May 1773. His father, a ropemaker, was dry, sarcastic,
                    and matter-of-fact; his mother, gentle and pious, with a leaning to mysticism.
                    Tieck partook of both characteristics: half his work and half his genius seem a
                    sceptical commentary on the other half. He emancipated himself from the prosaic
                    influence of his father’s house by a passionate study of Shakespeare. After a
                    brilliant career at school he repaired in 1792 to the university at Halle, and,
                    returning to Berlin in 1794, devoted himself to authorship, in which he had
                    already made experiments. As is so commonly the case with young writers of
                    genius, his first tales <hi rend="italic">(Abdallah, William Lovell)</hi>
                    partook too largely of the melodramatic, and have little permanent value. But
                    the romantic school of Germany, a movement comparable to the Lake school of
                    England, was already in the air, and Tieck was deeply sensitive to its
                    influence. He was strongly fascinated by two of its aspects in particular—the
                    reaction in favour of German mediaeval art and the revived interest in fairy
                    tales and folk-lore in general. Inspired by his friend Wackenroder, a youth of
                    pious ardour and most pious simplicity, he wrote his unfortunately unfinished
                    romance <hi rend="italic">Stembalds Travels,</hi> a very gospel for the artist,
                    at once the complement and the antitype of <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm
                    Meister.</hi> His studies in popular literature resulted in the entertaining
                    adaptation of Blue Beard entitled <hi rend="italic">Peter Lebrecht</hi> and
                    several kindred works. <hi rend="italic">Fair</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Eckbert,</hi> his masterpiece, and the masterpiece of all romantic fiction,
                    came to him, he said, by inspiration. He may well be believed: no artifice could
                    have created the pervading sensation of dreamy solitude or the intense thrill of
                    the catastrophe. The happy idea of dramatizing popular legend led to the
                    production of a greatly improved <hi rend="italic">Blue Beard,</hi> and
                    subsequently of <hi rend="italic">Puss in Boots,</hi> a satire on Kotzebue and
                    Iffland, such an alliance of broad humour and dainty irony as we might expect to
                    find in the lost Middle Comedy of Athens.</p>
                <p>It might almost have been better if Tieck had continued to walk in his own way.
                    His was a susceptible nature, too sensitive for perfect independence. In 1798 he
                    made the acquaintance of the Schlegels, and was drawn into their circle.
                    Novalis, undoubtedly the greatest genius of the romantic school, was for a time
                    a compensation to him for the death of Wackenroder, whose essays on art he
                    edited with additions of his own. But Novalis himself soon died, and the
                    influence of the Schlegel circle, with its bickerings and its “chopping and
                    changing of ribs,” was not wholly salutary either in a moral or a literary point
                    of view. August Schlegel inspired Tieck with a passion for the Spanish drama. He
                    also spent much time on a translation of <hi rend="italic">Don Quixote,</hi>
                    certainly a masterpiece, and rendered Ben Jonson’s <hi rend="italic">Silent
                    Woman,</hi> having previously adapted <hi rend="italic">Volpone.</hi> One
                    important production of his own nevertheless belongs to this period, the
                    romantic drama of <hi rend="italic">Genoveva,</hi> enthusiastically admired by
                    so clear-headed and impartial a judge as Bishop Thirlwall. He also produced his
                    delightful miniature drama of <hi rend="italic">Little Ped Puling Hood,</hi> and
                    was working with great spirit on <hi rend="italic">The Emperor Octavian</hi>
                    when he was suddenly attacked by rheumatic gout, which tormented him more or
                    less for the remainder of his life. Between pain and unpleasant literary
                    disputes his activity was long greatly impeded. The narrowness of his means also
                    troubled him. He had married the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n401/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0401-0382"/> daughter of Pastor Alberti, and, although he was
                    an amiable man and nothing is alleged against his wife, his household does not
                    seem to have been entirely comfortable. He lived alternately in Jena, Berlin,
                    and Dresden, where he became very intimate with Steffens, and wrote his powerful
                    but dismal tale, <hi rend="italic">The</hi><hi rend="italic">Runenberg.</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">The Emperor Octavian</hi> was completed in 1804, with less success
                    than had been hoped. In the following year Tieck repaired to Italy, nominally to
                    visit the baths of Pisa; but he made this medical injunction the plea for a long
                    stay in the country. The effect of Italian scenery, plastic art, and new
                    impressions in general was to wean him from much of the mysticism in which he
                    had hitherto indulged, and to direct him to the criticism of life. The
                    transition to his new manner is indicated by the additions to his former tales
                    and dramas, which, after several years spent in wandering and in sickness, he
                    published in 1812. <hi rend="italic">The Elves, The Philtre,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">The Goblet</hi> are tales, distinguished, the last two more
                    especially, by brilliant colouring and elaborate art. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fortunatus,</hi> a drama in two parts, added in 1816, wants the spirit of its
                    predecessors, but is pervaded by a quiet sarcastic humour exceedingly enjoyable.
                    Plays and stories were set in a framework of aesthetic conversation, and the
                    entire collection was entitled <hi rend="italic">Phantasus.</hi> By this
                    publication Tieck settled accounts with the romantic school, and could no more
                    be regarded as its leader.</p>
                <p>Tieck’s power of original composition failed him for some years. He devoted
                    himself especially to antiquarian and dramatic studies. In pursuance of the
                    latter he visited England, saw Kemble and Kean on the stage, and renewed
                    acquaintance with Coleridge, whom he had known in Italy. The friendship of
                    Solger was highly important to him, and helped him to the clear definite
                    principles of composition and criticism in which he had previously been
                    deficient. The period of reflexion gradually worked itself into a period of
                    productiveness, beginning with his charming novelette of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Pictures,</hi> translated by Thirlwall. It was followed by a series of similar
                    works extending over nearly twenty years, very unequal in value, but in their
                    best examples belonging to a very high class of art. Their great peculiarity is
                    the blending of narrative with disquisition and comment, so thoughtful and
                    ingenious that, interesting as the action commonly is, the interruption is not
                    resented. They have usually a strongly marked ironical element, as though the
                    writer were only half in earnest, a self-criticism of which a great creative
                    genius would have been incapable, but which bestows unusual piquancy on
                    productions of the second order. <hi rend="italic">The Pictures,</hi> already
                    mentioned, is a fine instance of the masterly conduct of a story, and contains a
                    very original figure, the shrewd, sottish, graceless old painter Eulenböck, who,
                    with talent enough to have made a name and a fortune, gains a precarious
                    livelihood by forging old masters. <hi rend="italic">The Betrothal,</hi> also
                    translated by Thirlwall, is a severe satire on hypocritical pietism. Among the
                    best of the other novelettes in this style may be mentioned <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Travellers,</hi> one of the most perfect specimens of the author’s irony;
                    <hi rend="italic">Luck brings Brains,</hi> a fine study of the power of a weak
                    character to rise to its opportunities when elevated by a sense of
                    responsibility; and <hi rend="italic">The Superfluities of Life,</hi> an
                    anecdote delightfully told. <hi rend="italic">The Old Book</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">The Scarecrow,</hi> two of the most fantastically imaginative,
                    resolve themselves into literary satire. The motive of the latter was borrowed
                    by Hawthorne in his <hi rend="italic">Mother Rigby’s Pipe.</hi> Of fictions with
                    an historical basis, the most popular are those derived from the lives of poets—
                    <hi rend="italic">A Poet’s Life,</hi> of which Shakespeare is the hero, and <hi
                    rend="italic">A Poet’s Death,</hi> relating the sad history of Camoens. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Revolt in the Cevennes</hi> is an historical romance of
                    Considerable compass; but Tieck’s masterpiece in this department is his <hi
                    rend="italic">Witches’ Sabbath,</hi> a tale almost unparalleled in literature
                    for its delineation of heart-breaking, hopeless misery. <hi rend="italic">The
                    Young Carpenter</hi> (1836, but commenced much earlier) can hardly be assigned
                    to any of these classes. It has a strong affinity to <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm
                    Meister,</hi> and may be compared with <hi rend="italic">Sternbald,</hi> both
                    for its resemblance and its contrast. Finally, in <hi rend="italic">Vittoria
                    Accorambona</hi> (1840) Tieck takes yet another new departure, indicating
                    affinities with the modern French school of fiction. The novel has been
                    translated into English, but is probably best known to English readers by Mrs
                    Carlyle’s half-earnest half-mocking admiration of the hero Bracciano, a Blue
                    Beard on the highest principles, and her wish that she could have lived two
                    hundred years before, “to have been—his mistress, not his wife.”</p>
                <p>These novels were all written at Dresden, where Tieck had settled in 1819. He
                    enjoyed especial favour at court, took an active part in the direction of the
                    royal theatre, and gained a new description of celebrity by his semipublic
                    readings from dramatic poets in the court circle. According to the almost
                    unanimous testimony of his hearers, he was the finest dramatic reader of his
                    age. His daughter Dorothea, who united her father’s literary talent to her
                    grandmother’s mystic piety, was of great assistance to him, especially in the
                    translation of Shakespeare which passes under his name. Schlegel had translated
                    seventeen plays. Tieck had undertaken to translate the remainder, and it has
                    been generally supposed that he kept his word. In fact the translation was
                    almost entirely executed by Dorothea Tieck and Count Wolf Baudissin, Tieck
                    contributing hardly anything but his advice and his name. The truth slips out
                    quite innocently in the pages of his biographer Köpke, and is fully told by
                    Gustav Freytag <hi rend="italic">(Im</hi><hi rend="italic">Neuen</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Reich,</hi> January 1880). During his residence at Dresden he
                    collected his critical writings, produced his excellent translation of the
                    English dramatists anterior to Shakespeare, and edited the works of Novalis,
                    Kleist, Lenz, and other contemporaries. In 1842 he accepted the invitation of
                    Frederick William IV. to settle in Berlin, where he had already been to conduct
                    the representation of the <hi rend="italic">Antigone</hi> with Mendelssohn’s
                    music. He found himself but little in his element in the city of his birth, and
                    the dramatic representations directed by him, including revivals of some of his
                    own plays, were rarely successful. In 1851 his health failed entirely, and he
                    withdrew altogether from the world. He died on 28th April 1853.</p>
                <p>Though not a writer of the highest rank, Tieck is nevertheless a most original
                    genius, very unjustly neglected by his countrymen. The best of his compositions
                    in the taste of the romantic school are absolute masterpieces; and his later
                    productions, if imperfect, occupy a unique position in literature. He may be
                    compared to Wieland, whom he decidedly surpasses, and to Ariosto, whom he would
                    have more than rivalled if he had been capable of a great sustained effort. His
                    susceptibility and self-distrust checked his genius, but at the same time gave
                    it that peculiar ironic flavour which constitutes its special distinction. He is
                    like an exquisite side dish, not sufficiently substantial for a full meal. The
                    attempts to extract a moral significance from the stories in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phantasus</hi> seem entirely thrown away; the purpose of his later writings,
                    when there is any, is always definite. Perhaps the soundest criticism upon him,
                    at bottom, is Heine’s in his <hi rend="italic">Romantic School,</hi> though
                    written at a time when it was his cue to show the works of that school as little
                    quarter as possible. Carlyle’s criticism is excellent, but only refers to the
                    <hi rend="italic">Phantasus.</hi></p>
                <p>The principal contribution to Tieck’s biography is the delightful book of Rudolf
                    Köpke (Leipsic, 1855), chiefly drawn from his oral communications and containing
                    his opinions on a number of subjects. Particulars of his residence at Dresden,
                    more especially of his connexion with the theatre, are given in the memoirs of
                    Friesen (Weimar, 1871). Tales from <hi rend="italic">Phantasus</hi> have been
                    translated in Carlyle’s <hi rend="italic">Specimens of German Romance,</hi> and
                    are reprinted in his miscellanies. A greatly inferior version, in some places
                    unscrupulously altered from Carlyle, was published in 1845 with an elaborate
                    preface signed by J. A. F., who does not, however, appear to have been the
                    translator. Several of Tieck’s other works have been translated into English,
                    but the only remarkable rendering is Bishop Thirlwall’s of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Pictures</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Betrothal.</hi> A complete<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n402/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0402-0383"/> chronological list of his writings is appended to
                    Köpke’s work. (R. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
