<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0069-0060-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TARANTULA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 60</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1129749">Spiders</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1143086">Tarantulas</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:919113">Eye</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:887581">Dancers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1143083">Tarantellas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4377640v">Tarantula</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q47s">Eye</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8th29">Sight</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fx73x98">Spiders</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n69/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TARANTULA</label>. The tarantula <hi rend="italic">lfLycosa
                    tarantula)</hi> belongs to the mining section of the family <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lycosidae</hi> or Wolf Spiders. Its cephalothorax is dorsally of a brownish
                    grey colour, whilst the abdomen is more distinctly brown, and marked with either
                    two or three pairs of triangular black spots above the apex of the triangles
                    pointing backwards. One of the most striking specific characteristics of this
                    spider is a large circular black spot which covers the anterior ventral half of
                    the abdomen, the remainder of this surface presenting an ochreous hue. The
                    largest species does not exceed f inch in length. The eight eyes are arranged in
                    three transverse rows, the anterior containing four small eyes, while behind
                    this two pairs of larger eyes are arranged in two rows, the eyes of the
                    hindermost row having between them a wider interval than the first pair.</p>
                <p>The tarantula is widely distributed in southern Europe, round the shores of the
                    Mediterranean. It occurs throughout Spain and is found in southern France, and
                    extends into Asia. In Italy it is said to be especially common in Apulia, round
                    the town of Taranto, from which place the name of this spider is usually
                    derived. A species has also been described from northern Africa. It is usually
                    to be found in dry pieces of waste land exposed to the sun. It lives in an
                    underground passage, which it digs for itself and lines with its web. These
                    passages are round in section, and sometimes an inch in diameter, and may extend
                    to a depth of a foot or more below the surface. The tube first descends
                    vertically for some inches, then bends at an obtuse angle, becoming vertical
                    again near its closed end. The tarantula takes up its position at the first
                    bend, where it can command the entrance, on the lookout for prey. In some cases
                    the tube is prolonged above the surface of the earth by the formation of a small
                    funnel, built up of fragments of wood and earth, and lined like the walls of the
                    tunnel by the web. The females show considerable maternal care for their
                    offspring, and sometimes sit upon their egg sacs; and the species, although
                    somewhat fierce and combative amongst themselves, are capable of being
                    tamed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Tarantism.</hi> The tarantula has given its name to one of
                    those dancing manias which overspread Europe during the Middle Ages. The bite of
                    the spider threw the sufferer into a depressed state of melancholy, accompanied
                    by various nervous disorders. The condition was accompanied by an increased
                    sensibility to the power of music. The excitement of the nervous system amounted
                    in some cases almost to insanity. The symptoms of the patient seem to have
                    varied a good deal with the character of the individual attacked: the most
                    common were a lividity of the body, icy coldness, great depression, nausea,
                    sexual excitement, and loss of sight and hearing. The only means of arousing the
                    sufferer from the lethargy into which he sank was music. Under the influence of
                    this he awoke as it were, and commenced moving rhythmically, then began to
                    dance, and continued increasing the rapidity of the motion until he fell
                    exhausted to the ground. By this means it was considered that the poison of the
                    tarantula was distributed through the system and worked out through the skin. If
                    the music ceased whilst the patient was dancing, he at once sank back into the
                    state of lethargy from which he had been aroused, but when thoroughly exhausted
                    he generally awoke relieved and cured at least for a time. This dancing mania
                    became contagious: one person caught it from another quite independently of the
                    bite of the tarantula, and in this way whole districts became affected. One of
                    the most peculiar characteristics was the attraction that bright pieces of
                    metal, or brilliant pieces of colour, exercised over the imagination of the
                    dancers. This was particularly marked in the later history of the disease. Each
                    sufferer apparently admired one particular hue, the sight of which seemed to
                    cause him the greatest rapture. Red was a very general favourite, though this
                    colour threw St Vitus’s dancers into a frenzy of rage; green, yellow, and other
                    colours also had numerous admirers. Other colours, on the contrary, they
                    detested, and attempted to destroy articles of the obnoxious shade.</p>
                <p>In marked contrast to the effect produced by hydrophobia, tarantism appeared to
                    evoke in its victims an intense longing for the sea, into which at times they
                    would precipitate themselves; at all times they seemed to prefer the vicinity of
                    water, sometimes carrying globes of this fluid whilst dancing.</p>
                <p>In its origin tarantism appears to have been contemporaneous with the St Vitus’s
                    dance of Germany. It first appeared towards the end of the 14th century in
                    Apulia; theuce it spread gradually throughout Italy, and reached its height
                    during the 17th century, by which time the dancing manias of the North had
                    already died out. It affected not only inhabitants of the country but foreigners
                    visiting it; age appears to have had no saving influence: children and old
                    people alike commenced dancing at the sound of the tarantella, but as a rule
                    women were more susceptible than men. From the 17th century onwards it has
                    gradually declined, and is now practically unknown, the only relic of it being
                    the graceful dance of southern Italy called the tarantella. The bite of the
                    tarantula is painful but not dangerous, and the real cause of the phenomena
                    described above must be sought in the temporary ej&gt;idemic prevalence of an
                    hysterical condition.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Lycοsα tarantula</hi> is figured in <hi rend="italic">Ann.
                    Sc. Nat.,</hi> 2d ser., iii. Zoologie, 1835.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
