<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0182-0171-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TEMPLE, Sir William</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 171</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49z90c2b">Avars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4br3k">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n182/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TEMPLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir William</hi></label>
                    (1628-1699), English statesman, diplomatist, and author, was born in London in
                    1628. He came of an old English family, but of the younger branch of it, which
                    had for some time been settled in Ireland. He was the eldest son of Sir John
                    Temple, master of the rolls in that country. His mother was Mary Hammond, sister
                    of a well-known Tory divine. Temple received a liberal education, calculated to
                    produce that moderation of judgment for which he was afterwards remarkable. He
                    was first a pupil of his uncle Dr Hammond, after which he went to the
                    grammar-school at Bishop Stortford, and then to the Puritan college of Emmanuel
                    at Cambridge, where he came under the influence of Cudworth. At the commencement
                    of the civil troubles his father embraced the popular cause and was deprived of
                    his office. Coming to England, he sat in the Long Parliament as member for
                    Chichester, and was one of the recalcitrant members turned out by Colonel Pride.
                    Before this event happened his son had left Cambridge, without taking a degree,
                    and in 1647 started to travel abroad. In the Isle of Wight, while on his way to
                    France, he fell in with Dorothy Osborne, and won her affections. Her father, Sir
                    Peter Osborne, was governor of Guernsey and a Royalist. Her family were
                    naturally opposed to the match, and threw difficulties in the way, which
                    hindered its consummation for seven years. During this period Temple travelled
                    in France, Spain, Holland, and other countries, gaining knowledge of the world
                    and keeping up a constant correspondence with his betrothed. At length,
                    apparently in 1654, the difficulties were surmounted and the marriage took
                    place. In 1655 Temple and his wife went to Ireland. The next five years were
                    spent in the house of Sir John Temple, who had made his peace with Cromwell, and
                    had resumed his official position. His son took no part in politics, but lived
                    the life of a student and a country gentleman.</p>
                <p>The accession of Charles II. rescued Temple, like many others, from obscurity. In
                    1660 he sat in the convention parliament at Dublin as member for Carlow, and he
                    represented the same county along with his father in the regular parliament that
                    followed. After a short visit to England in 1661, as commissioner from the Irish
                    parliament, he finally removed thither in 1663. There he attached himself to
                    Arlington, secretary of state, and two years later received his first employment
                    abroad. It was in March 1665 that the disastrous Avar Avith the L <hi
                    rend="superscript"> τ</hi> nited Netherlands began. Charles II. was anxious to
                    obtain allies, especially as Louis XIV. was taking up a hostile attitude. At
                    this juncture the bishop of Münster sent an envoy to England, offering to attack
                    the Dutch if the English Government would supply the means. Temple was sent over
                    to negotiate a treaty, and in this business gave evidence not only of the
                    diplomatic skill but of the peculiar candour and frankness for which he was
                    afterwards so distinguished. He was successful in making the treaty, but it was
                    rendered ineffectual by the declaration of Avar by France, the threats of Louis,
                    and the doubledealing of the prelate, who, after receiving a great part of the
                    subsidy, made a separate peace Avith the Netherlands. As a reAvard for his
                    services Temple was created a baronet, and in October 1665 became the English
                    representative at the viceregal court at Brussels. While the war continued,
                    Temple’s duties consisted chiefly in cultivating good relations with Spain,
                    Avhich was a neutral in the quarrel between England and the Dutch, but Avas
                    threatened by the claims of Louis XIV. on the Spanish Netherlands. Louis’s
                    designs became apparent in the spring of 1667, when he marched an army into
                    Flanders. This event was one of those Avhich led to the peace of Breda, and to
                    the subsequent negotiations, which are Temple’s chief title to fame. The French
                    conquests were made at the expense of Spain, but were almost equally dangerous
                    to the United Netherlands, whose independence would have been forfeited had
                    Louis succeeded in annexing Flanders. While the French were taking toAvn after
                    town, Temple made a journey into Holland and visited De Witt. The friendship
                    established and the community of views discovered during this interview
                    facilitated the subsequent negotiations. Temple had for some time pressed on his
                    GθA <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> ernment the necessity of stopping the French
                    advance, and had pointed out the way to do so, but it was not till December 1667
                    that he received instructions to act as he had suggested. He at once set out for
                    The Hague, and in January 1668 a treaty was made between England and the United
                    Netherlands, which, being joined shortly afterwards by Sweden, became known as
                    the Triple Alliance. It was a defensive treaty, made against the encroachments
                    of France. Whether we regard the skill and celerity with which the negotiations
                    were conducted or the results of the treaty, the transaction reflects great
                    credit on Temple. The French king was checked in midcareer, and, without a blow
                    being struck, was obliged to surrender almost all his conquests. Pepys records
                    public opinion on the treaty by saying that it Avas “the only good public thing
                    that hath been done since the king came into England.”</p>
                <p>Unfortunately the policy thus indicated was but shortlived. In taking up a
                    hostile attitude towards France Charles’s object had apparently been only to
                    raise his price. Louis took the hint, increased his offers, and two years later
                    the secret treaty of Dover reversed the policy of the Triple Alliance. Meanwhile
                    Temple had developed the good understanding with the Dutch by contracting a
                    commercial treaty with them (February 1668), and had acted as English
                    plenipotentiary at Aix-la-Chapelle, where peace between France and Spain was
                    made in May 1668. Shortly afterwards he was appointed ambassador at The Hague.
                    Here he lived for two years on good terms both with De <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n183/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0183-0172"/> Witt and with the young prince of Orange,
                    afterwards William III. The treaty of Dover led to Temple’s recall; but the plot
                    was not yet ripe, and Temple nominally held his post for another year. He
                    perceived, however, that his day was over and retired to his house at Sheen. In
                    June 1671 he received his formal dismissal. The war with the Netherlands broke
                    out next year, and was almost as discreditable to England as that of 1665. Want
                    of success and the growing strength of the opposition in parliament forced
                    Charles to make peace, and Temple was brought out of his retirement to carry
                    through the change of front. After a negotiation of three days, carried on
                    through the medium of the Spanish ambassador, the treaty of Westminster was made
                    (February 1674). As a recognition of his services Temple was now offered the
                    embassy to Spain. This he declined, as well as the offer of a far more important
                    post, that of secretary of state, but accepted instead a renewal of his embassy
                    to The Hague, whither he went in July 1674. In the March following he was
                    nominated ambassador to the congress at Nimeguen; but, owing to the tortuousness
                    of Charles’s dealings, it was not till July 1676 that he entered that town. The
                    negotiations dragged on for two years longer, for Charles was still receiving
                    money from France, and English mediation was no more than a ruse. In the summer
                    of 1677 Temple was summoned to England and received a second offer of the
                    secretaryship of state, which he again declined. In the autumn of the same year
                    he had the satisfaction of removing the last difficulties which hindered the
                    marriage of William and Mary, an event which seemed to complete the work of 1668
                    and 1674. Louis still remaining obstinate in his demands, Temple was
                    commissioned in July 1678 to make an alliance with the states, with the object
                    of compelling France to come to terms. This treaty was instrumental in bringing
                    about the general pacification which was concluded in January 1679.</p>
                <p>This was Temple's last appearance in the field of diplomacy; but his public life
                    was not yet over. A third offer of the secretaryship was made to him; but,
                    unwilling as ever to mix himself up with faction and intrigue, he again
                    declined. He did not, however, withdraw from politics; on the contrary, he was
                    for a short time more prominent than ever. The state was passing through a grave
                    crisis. Political passion was embittered by religious fanaticism. Parliament was
                    agitated by the popish plot, and was pressing on the Exclusion Bill. The root of
                    all the mischief lay in the irresponsibility of the cabinet to parliament and
                    its complete subservience to the crown. To remedy this, Temple brought forward
                    his plan for a reform of the privy council. This body was to consist of thirty
                    members, half of whom were to be the chief officers of the crown, the other half
                    being persons of importance, lords and commoners, chosen without reference to
                    party. Special care was taken to select men of wealth, which Temple considered
                    as the chief source of political influence. By the advice of this council the
                    king promised to act. The parliament, it was supposed, would trust such a body,
                    and would cease to dictate to the crown. The scheme was accepted by the king,
                    but was a failure from the outset. Intended to combine the advantages of a
                    parliament and a council, it created a board which was neither the one nor the
                    other. The conduct of affairs fell at once into the hands of a junta of four, of
                    whom Temple was at first one, and the king violated his promise by dissolving
                    parliament without asking the advice of the council. Temple retired in disgust
                    to his villa at Sheen, and appeared only occasionally at the council, where he
                    soon ceased to exercise any influence. In 1680 he was nominated ambassador to
                    Spain, but stayed in England in order to take his seat in parliament as member
                    for the university of Cambridge.</p>
                <p>He took no part in the debates on the great question of the day, and acting on
                    the king’s advice declined to sit in the parliament of 1681. Early in that year
                    his name was struck off the list of the council, and henceforward he disappeared
                    from public life. He continued to live at Sheen till 1686,when he handed over
                    his estate there to his son, the only survivor of seven children, and retired to
                    Moor Park in Surrey. When William III. came to the throne Temple was pressed to
                    take office,· but refused. His son became secretary at war, but committed
                    suicide immediately afterwards. Sir William, though occasionally consulted by
                    the king, took no further part in public affairs, but occupied himself in
                    literature, gardening, and other pursuits. It should not be omitted that Swift
                    lived with him as secretary during the last ten years (with one short interval)
                    of his life. Temple died at Moor Park on 27th January 1699.</p>
                <p>Temple’s literary works are mostly political, and are of considerable importance.
                    Among them may be mentioned <hi rend="italic">An Essay on the Present State and
                    Settlement of Ireland</hi> (1668); <hi rend="italic">The Empire, Sweden,</hi>
                    &amp;c., a survey of the different Governments of Europe and their relations to
                    England (1671); <hi rend="italic">Observations upon the United Provinces</hi>
                    (1672); <hi rend="italic">Essay upon the Original and Nature of Government</hi>
                    (1672); <hi rend="italic">Essay upon the Advancement of Trade in Ireland</hi>
                    (1673). Some of these were published in the first part of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Miscellanea</hi> (1679). In the same year apparently his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Poems</hi> were privately printed. In 1683 he began to write his <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs.</hi> The first part, extending from 1665 to 1671, he
                    destroyed unpublished; the second, from 1672 to 1679, was published without his
                    authority in 1691; the third, from 1679 to 1681, was published by Swift in 1709.
                    In 1692 he published the second part of his <hi rend="italic">Miscellanea,</hi>
                    containing among other subjects the essay <hi rend="italic">Upon the Ancient
                    and, Modern Learning,</hi> which is remarkable only as haying given rise to the
                    famous controversy on the “Letters of Phalaris.” His <hi rend="italic"
                    >Introduction to the History of England,</hi> a short sketch of English history
                    to 1087, was published in 1695. Several collections of his letters were
                    published by Swift and others after his death.</p>
                <p>His fame rests, however, far more on his diplomatic triumphs than on his literary
                    work. His connexion with domestic affairs was slight and unsuccessful. He was
                    debarred both by his virtues and his defects,—by his impartiality, his honesty,
                    and his want of ambition,—from taking an active part in the disgraceful politics
                    of his time. But in the foreign relations of his country he was intimately
                    concerned for a period of fourteen years, and in all that is praiseworthy in
                    them he had a principal hand. He cannot be called great, but he will be
                    remembered as one of the ablest negotiators that England has produced, and as a
                    public servant who, in an unprincipled age and in circumstances peculiarly open
                    to corruption, preserved a blameless record.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Life and Works of Sir William Temple,</hi> 2 vols,
                    fol.,'1720; 2d ed., with Life by Lady GifΓard, 1731; a more complete edition,
                    including the <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> was published in <hi rend="italic"
                    >4</hi> vols. 8vo, 1814; Burnet, <hi rend="italic">History of his own Time;</hi>
                    Courtenay, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Life,</hi> &lt;⅛c., <hi
                    rend="italic">of Sir William Temple,</hi> 2 vols., 1836; Macaulay, <hi
                    rend="italic">Essay on Sir William Temple.</hi> (G. W. P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
