<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0273-0256-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">THEODORIC</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 256</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:814376">Arianism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:945091">Goths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1750271">Ostrogoths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1093581">Relationism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198642">Conquest</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v36q">Arianism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n273/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THEODORIC</label>, king of the Ostrogoths (c. 454-526).
                    Referring to the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Goths</hi> for a general statement
                    of the position of this, the greatest ruler that the Gothic nation produced, we
                    add here some details of a more personal kind. Theodoric was born about the year
                    454, and was the son of Theudemir, one of three brothers who reigned over the
                    East Goths, at that time settled in Pannonia. The day of his birth coincided
                    with the arrival of the news of a victory of his uncle Walamir over the sons of
                    Attila. The name of Theodoric’s mother was Erelieva, and she is called the
                    concubine of Theudemir. The Byzantine historians generally call him son of
                    Walamir, apparently because the latter was the best known member of the royal
                    fraternity. At the age of seven he was sent as a hostage to the court of
                    Constantinople, and there spent ten years of his life, which doubtless exercised
                    a most important influence on his after career. Shortly after his return to his
                    father (about 471) he secretly, with a <hi rend="italic">comitatus</hi> of
                    10,000 men, attacked the king of the Sarmatians, and wrested from him the
                    important city of Singidunum (Belgrade). In 473 Theudemir, now chief king of the
                    Ostrogoths, invaded Maesia and Macedonia, and obtained a permanent settlement
                    for his people near Thessalonica. Theodoric took the chief part in this
                    expedition, the result of which was to remove the Ostrogoths from the now
                    barbarous Pannonia, and to settle them, as “faederati” in the heart of the
                    empire. About 474 Theudemir died, and for the fourteen following years Theodoric
                    was chiefly engaged in a series of profitless wars, or rather plundering
                    expeditions, partly against the emperor Zeno, but partly against a rival Gothic
                    chieftain, another Theodoric, son of Triarius.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>In one of the intervals of friendship with
                    the emperor in 483 Theodoric was made master of the household troops and in 484
                    consul.</p></note> In 488 he set out at the head of his people to win Italy from
                    Odoacer. There is no doubt that he had for this enterprise the sanction of the
                    emperor, only too anxious to be rid of so troublesome a guest. But the precise
                    nature of the relation which was to unite the two powers in the event of
                    Theodoric’s success was, perhaps purposely, left vague. Theodoric’s complete
                    practical independence, combined with a great show of deference for the empire,
                    reminds us somewhat of the relation of the old East India Company to the Mogul
                    dynasty at Delhi, but the Ostrogoth was sometimes actually at war with his
                    imperial friend. The invasion and conquest of Italy occupied more than four
                    years (488-493). Theodoric, who marched round the head of the Venetian Gulf, had
                    to fight a fierce battle with the Gepidae, probably in the valley of the Save.
                    At the Sontius (Isonzo) he found his passage barred by Odoacer, over whom he
                    gained a complete victory (28th August 489). A yet more decisive victory
                    followed on the 30th September at Verona. Odoacer fled to Ravenna, and it seemed
                    as if the conquest of Italy was complete. It was delayed, however, for three
                    years by the treachery of Tufa, an officer who had deserted from the service of
                    Odoacer, and of Frederic the Rugian, one of the companions of Theodoric, as well
                    as by the intervention of the Burgundians on behalf of Odoacer. A sally was made
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n274/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0274-0257"/> from Ravenna by the besieged king, who was
                    defeated in a bloody battle in the Pine Wood. At length (26th February 493) the
                    long and severe blockade of Ravenna was ended by a capitulation, the terms of
                    which Theodoric disgracefully violated by slaying Odoacer with his own hand
                    (15th March 493). See <hi rend="smallcaps">Odoacer.</hi></p>
                <p>The thirty-three years’ reign of Theodoric was a time of unexampled happiness for
                    Italy. Unbroken peace reigned within her borders (with the exception of a
                    trifling raid made by Byzantine corsairs on the coast of Apulia in 508). The
                    venality of the Roman officials and the turbulence of the Gothic nobles were
                    sternly repressed. Marshes were drained, harbours formed, the burden of the
                    taxes lightened, and the state of agriculture so much improved that Italy, from
                    a corn-importing, became a corn-exporting country. Moreover Theodoric, though
                    adhering to the Arian creed of his forefathers, was during the greater part of
                    his reign so conspicuously impartial in religious matters that a legend which
                    afterwards became current represented him as actually putting to death a
                    catholic deacon who .had turned Arian in order to win his favour. At the time of
                    the contested papal election between Symmachus and Laurentius (496-502),
                    Theodoric’s mediation was welcomed by both contending parties. Unfortunately, at
                    the very close of his reign (524), the emperor Justin’s persecution of the
                    Arians led him into a policy of reprisals. He forced Pope John to undertake a
                    mission to Constantinople to plead for toleration, and on his return threw him
                    into prison, where he died. Above all, he sullied his fame by the execution of
                    Boetius and Symmachus (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Boetius).</hi> It should be
                    observed, however, that the motive for these acts of violence was probably
                    political rather than religious,—jealousy of intrigues with the imperial court
                    rather than zeal on behalf of the Arian confession. Theodoric’s death, which is
                    said to have been hastened by remorse for the execution of Symmachus, occurred
                    on 30th August 526. He was buried in the mausoleum which is still one of the
                    marvels of <hi rend="smallcaps">Ravenna</hi><hi rend="italic">{q.vf),</hi> and
                    his grandson Athalaric, a boy of ten years, succeeded him, under the regency of
                    his mother Amalasuntha.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> The authorities for the life of Theodoric
                    are very imperfect. Jordanes, Procopius, and the curious fragment known as
                    Anonymus Valesii (printed at the end of Ammianus Marcellinus) are the chief
                    direct sources of narrative, but far the most important indirect source is the
                    <hi rend="italic">Variae</hi> (state-papers) of Cassiodorus, chief minister of
                    Theodoric. Malchus furnishes some interesting particulars as to his early life,
                    and it is possible to extract a little information from the turgid panegyric of
                    Ennodius. Among German scholars Dahn <hi rend="italic">{Könige der
                    Germanen,</hi> ii., iii,, and iv.), Manso <hi rend="italic">{Geschichte des
                    Ostgothischen Reichs in Italien),</hi> and. Sartorius <hi rend="italic">(
                    Versuch über die Regierung der Ostgothen,</hi> &amp;c. ) have done most to
                    illustrate Theodoric’s principles of government. The English reader may consult
                    Gibbon’s <hi rend="italic">Decline and Fall,</hi> chap, xxxix., and Hodgkin’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Italy and herlnvaders,</hi> vol. iii., and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters of Cassiodorus.</hi> (T. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
