<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0116-0105-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TEAL (9th edition, volume 23, page 105)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n87327d">Ducks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xc2x">Ana</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808411">Anas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899294">Ducks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:987598">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n116/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TEAL</label> (Old English <hi rend="smallcaps">Tele),</hi> a
                    word of uncertain origin, but doubtless cognate with the Dutch <hi rend="italic"
                        >Taling</hi> (formerly <hi rend="italic">Talingh</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >TeliηgK),</hi> and this apparently with the Scandinavian <hi rend="italic"
                        >Atteling-And</hi> (Briinnich, <hi rend="italic">Orηithol. Borealis,</hi> p.
                    18) and <hi rend="italic">Atling,</hi> which it seems impossible not to connect
                    with the Scottish <hi rend="italic">Atteile</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >Atteal,</hi> to be found in many old records, though this last word
                    (however it be spelt) is generally used in conjunction with Teal, as if to mean
                    a different kind of bird; and commentators have shewn a marvellous ineptitude in
                    surmising what that bird was.</p>
                <p>The Teal is the <hi rend="italic">Anas crecca</hi> of Linnaeus, and the smallest
                    of the European <hi rend="italic">Anaticlae,</hi> as well as one of the most
                    abundant and highly esteemed for the table. It breeds in many parts ofthe
                    British Islands, making its nest in places very like those chosen by the Wild
                    Duck, <hi rend="italic">A. bοscas</hi>; but there is no doubt that by far the
                    greater number of those that are taken in decoys, or are shot, during the autumn
                    and winter are of foreign origin. While the female presents the usual
                    inconspicuous mottled plumage of the same sex in most species of <hi
                        rend="italic">Anatinae,</hi> the male is one of the handsomest of his kind.
                    His deep chestnut head and throat are diversified on either side by a line of
                    buff, which, springing from the gape, runs upward to the eye, in front of which
                    it forms a fork, one prong passing backward above and the other below, enclosing
                    a dark glossy-green patch, and both losing themselves in the elongated feathers
                    of the hind-head and nape. The back and sides of the body appear to be grey, an
                    effect produced by delicate transverse pencillings of black on a dull white
                    ground. The outer lanceolate scapulars have one-half of their webs pure white,
                    forming a conspicuous stripe along the side of the back. The breast is of a pale
                    salmon or peach-blossom colour, each feather in front bearing a roundish dark
                    spot, but these spots lessen in number and size lower down, and the warm tint
                    passes into white on the belly. The tail-coverts above and below are velvety
                    black, but those at the side are pale orange.</p>
                <p>The Teal inhabits almost the whole of Europe and Asia,—from Iceland to Japan,—in
                    winter visiting Northern Africa and India. It occasionally occurs on the western
                    shores of the Atlantic; but its place in North America is taken by its
                    representative, <hi rend="italic">A. carolinensis,</hi> the male of which is
                    easily to be recognized by the absence of the upper buff line on the side of the
                    head and of the white scapular stripe, while he presents a whitish crescentic
                    bar on the sides of the lower neck just in front of the wings.</p>
                <p>Species more or less allied to these two are found in most other parts of the
                    world, and among such species are some (for instance, the <hi rend="italic">A.
                        gibberifrons</hi> of the Australian Region and the <hi rend="italic">A.
                        eatoni</hi> of Kerguelen Island) in which the male wears almost the same
                    inconspicuous plumage as the female. But the determination of the birds which
                    should be technically considered “Teals,” and belong to the subgenus <hi
                        rend="italic">Nettium</hi> (generally misspelt <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nettiorι),</hi> as distinguished from other groups of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Anatinae,</hi> is a task not yet successfully attempted, and much confusion
                    has been caused by associating with them such species as the <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Garganey</hi> (vol. x. p. 80) and its allies of the group
                        <hi rend="italic">Querquedula.</hi> Others again have not yet been
                    discriminated from the <hi rend="smallcaps">Wigeons</hi> (ÿ.v.), the
                    Pintail-Ducks, <hi rend="italic">Dafila,</hi> or even from the typical form of
                        <hi rend="italic">Anas (ef.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Duck,</hi> vol. vii. p.
                    505), into each of which subgenera the Teals, <hi rend="italic">Nettium,</hi>
                    seem to pass without any great break. In ordinary talk “Teal” seems to stand for
                    any Duck-like bird of small size, and in that sense the word is often applied to
                    the members of the genus <hi rend="italic">Nettopus,</hi> though systematists
                    will have it that they are properly Geese. In the same loose sense the word is
                    often applied to the two most beautiful of the Family <hi rend="italic"
                        >Anaticlae,</hi> belonging to the genus √7⅛ (commonly misspelt <hi
                        rend="italic">AiT)—</hi> the Carolina Duck of North America, <hi
                        rend="italic">Ae. sponsa</hi> (not to be confounded with the above-named <hi
                        rend="italic">Anas carolinensis</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Nettium
                        carolinense),</hi> and the Mandarin-Duck of China, <hi rend="italic">Ae.
                        galericulata.</hi> Hardly less showy than these are the two species of the
                    subgenus <hi rend="italic">Eunetta,—</hi> the Falcated Duck, <hi rend="italic"
                        >E. falcata,</hi> and the Baikal Teal, <hi rend="italic">E. formosa,—</hi>
                    both from eastern Asia, but occasionally appearing in Europe. Some British
                    authors have referred to the latter of these well-marked species certain Ducks
                    that from time to time occur, but they are doubtless hybrids, though the secret
                    of their parentage may be unknown; and in this way a so-called Bimaculated Duck,
                        <hi rend="italic">Anas bimaculata,</hi> was for many years erroneously
                    admitted as a good species to the British list, but of late this has been
                    properly discarded. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
