<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0528-0509-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TRANSBAIKALIA (9th edition, volume 23, page
                    509)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp6g">Cossacks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40p0x090">Tunguses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t14tt4h">Highways</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880643">Cossacks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208752">Mongolia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n528/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TRANSBAIKALIA</label> (<hi rend="italic">Zabaikalskaya
                        Oblast),</hi> a province of Eastern Siberia, to the east of Lake Baikal, has
                    Irkutsk on the west, Yakutsk on the north, the province of Amur on the east, and
                    Mongolia on the south. Its area (240,780 square miles) is about as great as that
                    of Austria-Hungary, but its population is under half a million. With regions of
                    a purely Siberian character on the one hand, and including on the other the
                    outer borders of the Mongolian steppes and the upper basin of the Amur,
                    Transbaikalia forms an intermediate link between Siberia, Mongolia, and the
                    northern Pacific littoral. The mountains of the Yablonovoi Khrebet, which run in
                    a north-easterly direction from the sources of the Keruleñ to the bend of the
                    Olekma in 56° N. lat., divide the province into two quite distinct parts: to the
                    west the upper terrace of the high East Asian plateau continued from the upper
                    Selenga and Yenisei (from 4000 to 5000 feet high) towards the plateau of the
                    Vitim (3500 to 4000 feet); and to the east the lower terrace of the same plateau
                    (about 2800 feet high), which appears as a continuation of the eastern Gobi. The
                    continuity of the high plateau extending from the upper Selenga to the upper
                    Vitim was for a long time overlooked in consequence of a broad and deep valley
                    by which it is intersected. Beginning at Lake Baikal, it pierces the huge
                    north-western border-ridge of the plateau, and runs eastward up the Uda, with an
                    imperceptible gradient, like a gigantic railway cutting enclosed between two
                    steep slopes, sending another branch south towards Kiakhta. After having served,
                    through a succession of geological periods, as an outlet for the water and ice
                    which accumulated on the plateau, it is now utilized for the two highways which
                    lead from Lake Baikal over the plateau (3500-4000 feet) to the Amur in the east
                    and the Chinese depression in the south. Elsewhere, the high and massive
                    border-ridge on the north-western edge of the plateau can be crossed only by
                    difficult footpaths. The border-ridge just mentioned, pierced by the wide
                    opening of the Selenga, runs from south-west to north-east under different
                    names, being known as Khamar-daban to the south of Lake Baikal (the Khamar-daban
                    peak raising its bald summit to a height of 6900 feet above the sea), and as the
                    Barguzin Mountains (7000 to 8000 feet) along the eastern bank of the Barguzin
                    river, while farther to the north-east it has been described by the present
                    writer under the names of the South Muya and Tchara Mountains (6000 to 7000
                    feet). Resting its south-east base on the plateau, it descends steeply on the
                    north-west to the lake, or to the broad picturesque valleys of the Barguzin, the
                    Muya, and the Tchara. Larch, fir, and cedar forests thickly clothe the ridge,
                    whose dome-shaped rounded summits <hi rend="italic">(goltsy)</hi> rise above the
                    limits of tree vegetation, but do not reach the snow line (here above 10,000
                    feet). The high plateau itself has the aspect of an undulating table-land,
                    intersected by low ranges, which rise some 1500 or 2000 feet above its surface,
                    and are separated by broad, flat, and marshy valleys, which the rivers languidly
                    traverse till they find their way across the border-ridges. Those of the valleys
                    which are better drained have fine meadow lands, but as a whole the plateau has
                    the appearance, especially in the north, of a wet or marshy prairie in the
                    hollows, while the hills are thickly clothed with forests (almost exclusively of
                    larch and birch). Numberless lakes and ponds occur along the river courses.
                    Tungus hunters find a livelihood in the forests and on the meadows, but
                    permanent agricultural settlements are impossible, corn seldom ripening on
                    account of the early frosts. The lower parts of the broad and flat valley of the
                    Djida have, however, a few Cossack settlements, and on the upper Selenga and
                    Yenisei Mongolian shepherds (Uryankhes and Darkhates) inhabit the high grassy
                    valleys about Lake Kossogol (5560 feet above the sea). Quite different is the
                    lower terrace of the plateau, occupied by the eastern Gobi and the Nertchinsk
                    region of Transbaikalia, and separated from the above by the Yablonovoi ridge.
                    This last is the south-eastern border ridge of the higher terrace. It rises to
                    8250 feet in the Sokhondo peak, but elsewhere its dome-shaped summits do not
                    exceed 5000 or 6000 feet. When crossing it from the north-west, about Tchita,
                    the traveller hardly perceives that he is approaching the great water-parting
                    between the Arctic and the Pacific oceans. Numberless lakes, with flat undefined
                    borders, feed streams which flow lazily amidst marshes, some of them to join the
                    great northward rivers, others to find their way to the Amur and the Pacific.
                    Low hills rise gently above the edge of the plateau, but an abrupt slope
                    descends towards the south-east, where the hill-foots of the Yablonovoi are
                    nearly 1500 and 2000 feet lower than on the north-west. Climate, flora, and
                    fauna suddenly change as soon as the Yablonovoi has been crossed; the steppes of
                    Dauria (continuations of those of the Gobi), covered with a bright luxuriant
                    vegetation, meet the view of the spectator. The Siberian flora gives way to the
                    much richer Daurian flora, which in turn is exchanged for the Pacific littoral
                    flora as soon as the traveller descends from the lower terrace of the plateau
                    towards the Manchurian plains and lowlands.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n529/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0529-0510"/>
                <p>The lower terrace, occupied in Transbaikalia by the Nertchinsk district, has the
                    character of a steppe, but is also intersected by a number of ranges, all
                    running southwest to north-east, and all being plications of Silurian and
                    Devonian rocks, containing silver, lead, and copper, and also auriferous sands.
                    Agriculture can be easily carried on in the broad prairies, the only drawbacks
                    being droughts, and also frosts in the settlements in the higher close valleys
                    of the Nertchinsk or Gazimur Mountains. The lower terrace is in its turn fringed
                    by a border-ridge—the Great Khingan —which has, with reference to the lower
                    terrace, the same characters as the Yablonovoi in relation to the upper, and
                    separates Siberia from northern Manchuria. This important ridge, as shown
                    elsewhere (vol. xxii. pp. 3, 4), does not run from south to north, as
                    represented on the old maps, but from south-west to north-east; it is pierced by
                    the Amur near Albazin, and joins the Okhotsk ridge, which in its turn does not
                    join the Yablonovoi Mountains. The mountains drawn west and east on older maps
                    to connect the Yablonovoi with the Okhotsk ridge have no actual existence.</p>
                <p>The rivers belong to three different systems,—the affluents of Lake Baikal, of
                    the Lena, and of the Amur. Of the first the Selenga (800 miles long) rises in
                    the Hanghai Mountains of northwestern Mongolia, one of its great tributaries
                    (the Ebin-gol) being an emissary of Lake Kossogol. It flows past Selenghinsk and
                    enters Lake Baikal from the south-east, forming a wide delta. The Tchikoi, the
                    Khiɫok, and the Uda are its chief tributaries in Transbaikalia.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Steamers have ascended
                            the lower Selenga and the Uda up to Verkneudinsk.</p></note> The
                    Barguzin and the Upper Angara are two large tributaries of Lake Baikal from the
                    north-east. Of the tributaries of the Lena, the Vitim with its affluents
                    (Karenga, Tsipa, Muya, Kaɫar, Kaɫakan) flows on the high plateau through
                    uninhabited regions, as also does the Olekma. The tributaries of the Amur, which
                    is formed by the junction of the Shilka and the Argun, are much more important.
                    The Argun, which at a quite recent epoch received the waters of the Dalai-nor,
                    and thus had the Keruleñ for its source, is no longer in communication with the
                    rapidly drying Mongolian lake, and has its sources in the Gan, which flows from
                    the Great Khingan. It is not navigable, but receives the Gazimur and several
                    other streams which water the Nertchinsk mining district. The Shilka is formed
                    by the union of the Onon and the Tchita rivers, and is navigable from the town
                    of Tchita, thus being an important channel of transit to the Amur.</p>
                <p>Lake Baikal, with an area of 12,430 square miles (nearly equal to that of
                    Switzerland), extends in a half crescent from south-west to north-east; it has a
                    length of over 400 miles and a width of from 20 to 53 miles. Its level is 1561
                    feet above the sea.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>According to the levelling made in 1875-76 from Zverinogolovsk, in
                            Orenburg, to Lake Baikal. There is uncertainty as to the absolute
                            altitude, that of Zverinogolovsk, 318 feet, having still to be verified.
                            See <hi rend="italic">Mem. Russ. Geοgr. Soc.: Phys. Geogr.,</hi> vol.
                            xv., 1885.</p></note> About the middle it is divided into two parts, the
                    Great Lake and the Little Lake, by the island Olkhon and the peninsula of
                    Svyatoi Nos, which closely approach one another. Between the two there is a
                    submerged ridge, which must be considered as a continuation of the Barguzin
                    Alps. The wide delta of the Selenga narrows the Great Lake in its middle part,
                    and renders it more shallow in the east than in the west—the greatest depth
                    (4186 feet) having been reached by Dr Godlevski in the south-west. The depth of
                    the Little Lake does not exceed 210 feet. According to Tchersky, the trough now
                    occupied by the base had its origin in three separate synclinal valleys, which
                    date from the Azoic epoch, and were gulfs of the ocean during the Silurian or
                    Huronian period. They coalesced at a much later epoch.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>I. Tchersky, “Results of the Exploration
                            of Lake Baikal,” in <hi rend="italic">Mem. Russ. Geogr. Soc., Phys.
                                Geogr.,</hi> vol. xv., 1886, with a geological map on a scale of 7
                            miles to an inch; Fr. Schmidt’s report in the yearly <hi rend="italic"
                                >Report</hi> of the Russian Geographical Society for 1886 (both
                            Russian).</p></note> Of other lakes, the Gusinoye and Lake Baunt on the
                    Vitim plateau, and Oron at its base, are worthy of notice. Many lakes yield
                    common salt or sulphate of natron.</p>
                <p>The high plateau consists of granites, gneisses, and syenites, covered with
                    Laurentian schists. Silurian and Devonian marine deposits occur only on the
                    lower terrace. Since that time the region has not been under the sea, and only
                    freshwater Jurassic deposits and coal-beds are met with in the depressions.
                    During the Glacial period most of the high terrace of the plateau and its border
                    ridges were undoubtedly covered with vast glaciers. Volcanic rocks of more
                    recent origin (Mesozoic ?) are met with in the north-western border ridge and on
                    its slopes, as well as on the Vitim plateau. During the Glacial period the fauna
                    of the lowest parts of Transbaikalia was decidedly arctic; while during the
                    Lacustrine or Post-Glacial period it was covered with numberless lakes, the
                    shores of which were inhabited by Neolithic man. Only few traces of these have
                    remained, and they are rapidly drying up. Earthquakes are very frequent on the
                    shores of Lake Baikal, especially at the mouth of the Selenga, extending as far
                    as Irkutsk, Barguzin, and Selenghinsk; in 1862 an extensive area was submerged
                    by the lake. Numerous mineral springs, some of them of high repute, are spread
                    all over Transbaikalia. The chief of them are the hot alkaline springs (130° F.
                    ) at Turka, at the mouth of the Barguzin, whither hundreds of patients resort
                    annually, those of Pogromna on the Uda (very similar to the Seltzer springs),
                    those of Moɫokova near Tchita, and those of Darasun in the Nertchinsk district
                    (very rich in carbonic acid and phosphate of iron).</p>
                <p>The flora and fauna of Transbaikalia, owing to their intermediate character
                    between a purely Siberian flora and fauna and those characteristic of the
                    Mongolian and Manchurian regions, have been the subject of many careful
                    investigations since the time of Pallas down to those of Turczaninoff,
                    Middendorff, Schrenck, Radde, and Polyakoff. Their various characters in
                    different parts of this extensive territory could not be described without
                    entering too largely into details. The reader may consult the works of the
                    authors just named (see vol. xxii. p. 12).</p>
                <p>The climate is, as a whole, exceedingly dry and extreme. The winter is cold and
                    dry; snow is so trifling that the horses of the Buriats find their food
                    throughout the winter on the steppes, and in the very middle of the winter
                    wheeled vehicles are used all over the west. To the east of the Yablonovoi ridge
                    the Nertchinsk district feels the influence of the North Pacific monsoon region,
                    and snow falls more thickly, especially in the valleys, but the summer continues
                    to be hot and dry. On the high plateau, even the summer is cold, owing to the
                    altitude and the humidity arising from the marshes, and the soil is frozen to a
                    great depth. In the vicinity of Lake Baikal the moderating influence of the
                    great water-basin is felt to some extent, and there is a cooler summer; in
                    winter exceedingly deep snow covers the <hi rend="italic">goltsys</hi> and
                    valleys of the mountains around the lake.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>“Das Klima von Ost-Sibirien," by A. Woyeikoff, in <hi
                                rend="italic">Meteor. Zeitsch.,</hi> 1884.</p></note></p>
                <p>The population (497,760 in 1882) is exceedingly sparse, unless the immense
                    uninhabitable spaces of the plateaus be left out of account. Even on the lower
                    terrace nearly the whole of the region on the left bank of the Shilka is
                    unsuited for agriculture, as also are the Gazimur Mountains, where only a few
                    settlers gain a livelihood in some of the valleys, straggling against an
                    unhealthy climate and the influence of goitre. The Russian population there
                    gathers around the crown mines of the Nertchinsk district, while the steppes are
                    occupied by Buriats. A succession of villages, supported partly by agriculture
                    and partly by hunting and trade with Mongolia, are settled along the Shilka
                    between Tchita and Sryetensk, while farther down the river flows in such a wild
                    mountain region that only a few families are settled, at distances some 20 miles
                    apart, to maintain communication. The same is true with regard to the lower
                    Argun. The valleys of the Uda, the lower Selenga, and especially the Tchikoi and
                    the Khiɫok have been occupied since the beginning of the century by Raskolniks,
                    who have received the name of <hi rend="italic">Semeiskiye</hi> on account of
                    their large (compound) families, and there one finds, in a condition of
                    prosperity such as is unknown in Russia proper, some of the finest
                    representatives of the Russian race. The remainder of the steppe of the Uda is
                    occupied by Buriats, while the forests and marshes of the plateau are the
                    hunting grounds of the nomad Tunguses. Only the valley of the Djida in the south
                    of the Khamar-daban is settled in its lower parts.</p>
                <p>The Russians of Transbaikalia present a great variety of ethnological types.
                    Mainly owing to the difficulties of communication, many Great Russian Raskolniks
                    and Little Russian settlers have preserved their ethnographical features pure
                    from any admixture; while there are, on the other hand, villages in the
                    Nertchinsk district, chiefly composed of the earliest Russian settlers, where a
                    great admixture of Tungusian or Mongolian blood is observable. On the upper
                    Argun the Cossacks are in features, character, language, and manners largely
                    Mongolian. The Russians along the Chinese frontier constitute a separate <hi
                        rend="italic">voisko</hi> of the Transbaikalian Cossacks. There is great
                    uncertainty as to the numbers of the Buriats; they are estimated at about
                    150,000. The Tunguses number only a very few thousands.</p>
                <p>Agriculture is carried on to a limited extent by the Buriats and in all Russian
                    settlements; but it prospers only in the valleys of west Transbaikalia, and
                    partly in the Nertchinsk region, while in the steppes of the Argun and Onon even
                    the Russians resort chiefly to cattle-breeding and trade, or to hunting. On the
                    whole, corn has to be imported; summer wheat and summer rye, oats, and barley
                    are the chief crops in the east, winter rye not being sown in consequence of the
                    want of snow. Cattle-rearing is extensively carried on, especially by the
                    Buriats, but their herds and flocks, which wander freely over the steppes
                    throughout the winter, are often destroyed in great numbers by the snow-storms
                    of spring. Hunting is an important occupation, even with the Russians, many of
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n530/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0530-0511"/> whom leave their homes in October to spend
                    six weeks in the <hi rend="italic">taiga</hi> (forest-region). The fisheries of
                    Lake Baikal and the lower parts of its affluents are important. Enormous
                    quantities of <hi rend="italic">Salmo omul</hi> are taken every year; and,
                    although the curing is most primitive, the annual yield is valued at £20,000.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Salmo thymalus, S. oxyrhynchus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >S</hi>. <hi rend="italic">fluviatilis</hi> are also taken largely.</p>
                <p>The possibilities of discoveries of gold are absorbing all the industrial forces
                    of Transbaikalia. Gold-diggings occur chiefly in the basins of the Shilka and
                    the upper Vitim, also on the Tchikoi and the Khilok. No less than 25,400 lb is
                    extracted annually by private enterprise, and about 3200 lb by the crown, at the
                    Kara gold-diggings, where nearly 1400 convicts are employed. The silver mining
                    formerly carried on at several crown works is now on the decrease (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Nertchinsk);</hi> the quantity extracted in 1884 was only
                    241 lb. Every kind of manufactured ware has to be imported from Russia; and even
                    petty trades are almost unknown in the villages.</p>
                <p>The trade of the province is chiefly represented by that of Kiakhta. The Cossacks
                    on the frontier carry on some trade in brick-tea, cattle, and hides with
                    Mongolia. The export of furs is of considerable value.</p>
                <p>The communications of Transbaikalia are limited to the great Amur highway, which
                    fringes the south coast of Lake Baikal and passes through Verkhneudinsk, Tchita,
                    and Nertchinsk to Sryetensk, whence steamers ply down to the mouth of the Amur;
                    in winter, further communication with the Amur beyond Sryetensk is maintained on
                    sledges on the ice of the Shilka, but in the autumn and spring a horseback
                    journey as far as Kumara is the only possible method of reaching the middle
                    Amur. Steamer communication is also maintained for six or seven months across
                    Lake Baikal, from Posolskoye, at the mouth of the Selenga, to Listvenichnaya, 40
                    miles from Irkutsk. A highway connects Verkhneudinsk with Seleng-hinsk and
                    Kiakhta, and communication on the steppes of the Argun and the Onon as well as
                    up the Barguzin is easy. The rest of Transbaikalia can be visited only on
                    horseback.</p>
                <p>Transbaikalia is divided into five districts, the chief towns of which (with
                    populations in 1880) are Tchita, capital of the province (12,600 inhabitants),
                    Barguzin (800), Nertchinsk (4070), Seleng-hinsk (1150), and Verkhneudinsk
                    (4150). Kiakhta has 4290 inhabitants, and Sryetensk, being at the head of the
                    navigation, is a rising town. (P. A. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
