<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0465-0446-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TOPAZ (9th edition, volume 23, page 446)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:884667">Crystals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884644">Crystallization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152648">Topaz</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838162">Brazilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ht2gm61">Topaz</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s42j">Crystallization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q52ff6p">Heat</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210251">Colorado</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206536">Tasmania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204563">Utah</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n465/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TOPAZ</label>. It appears that the stone described by ancient
                    writers under the name of <hi rend="italic">τοπάζιος,</hi> in allusion to its
                    occurrence on the island of Topazion in the Red Sea, was the mineral which we
                    now know as the. chrysolite or <hi rend="smallcaps">Peridote</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">(⅛.v.).</hi> The topaz of modern mineralogists was unknown
                    to the ancients. Topaz occurs either crystallized, in association with granitic
                    rocks, or in the form of rolled pebbles in the beds of streams. The crystals are
                    orthorhombic prisms, with a perfect cleavage parallel to the base, or transverse
                    to the long axis of the prism. This cleavage is recognized by the lapidary as
                    the “grain” of the stone. It is notable that crystals of topaz are commonly
                    hemimorphic; in other words, the prisms are terminated by dissimilar faces. This
                    hemimorphism is associated with the property of pyroelectricity (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Mineralogy,</hi> vol. xvi. p. 376). The chemical
                    composition of the topaz has given rise to much discussion, but the mineral is
                    now generally regarded as a silicate of aluminium associated with the fluorides
                    of aluminium and silicon. When strongly heated it suffers considerable loss of
                    weight. Brewster, examining the topaz microscopically, detected numerous fluid
                    cavities, whence he concluded that it had been formed in the wet way. Two of the
                    fluids obtained from these cavities have received the names of <hi rend="italic"
                        >l&gt;rewsteτ-liηite</hi> and <hi rend="italic">cryptolinite.</hi> Some of
                    the finest topazes are almost colourless, and may be occasionally mistaken for
                    diamonds. The topaz, however, is inferior in hardness; it lacks “fire”; and it
                    becomes electric when heated—a property not possessed by the diamond. Colourless
                    topazes are known to French jewellers as <hi rend="italic">gouttes</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">djeau</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> i</hi> and in Brazil as
                        <hi rend="italic">pingas Tagoa—</hi> names which refer to the limpidity of
                    the stone—while in England they pass in trade under the curious name of <hi
                        rend="italic">minas</hi><hi rend="italic">novas.</hi> The beauty of the
                    stone is best developed when in the form of a brilliant. The topaz is cut on a
                    leaden wheel by means of emery, and is polished with tripoli. Coloured topazes
                    are usually either yellow or blue. The pleochroism of the stone is very marked:
                    thus the colour of the sherry-yellow crystals from Brazil is resolved by the
                    dichroiscope into brownish yellow and rose-pink. The colour is unstable, the
                    yellow topaz especially being liable to suffer bleaching by exposure to
                    sunlight. Hence the fine series of crystals of Siberian topaz from the
                    Kochscharow collection, now in the British Museum, is carefully protected from
                    light by means of opaque pasteboard caps. In 1750 a Parisian jeweller named
                    Dumelle discovered that the yellow topaz of Brazil, when exposed to a moderate
                    heat, assumed a rose-pink colour. It is generally believed that all the pink
                    topaz occurring in jewellery owes its tint to artificial treatment. Formerly it
                    was the practice to heat the stone in a sandbath, but the change of colour is
                    now generally effected by wrapping the stone in German tinder, which is then
                    ignited. This “burnt topaz” is sometimes known to jewellers as “Brazilian ruby.”
                    In like manner the blue topaz occasionally passes under the name of “Brazilian
                    sapphire,” and the pale green as “aquamarine ”—a name which is strictly
                    applicable only to the sea-green beryl. The largest known cut topaz is a fine
                    brilliant, weighing 368 carats, and termed the “Maxwell Stuart topaz.”</p>
                <p>The topaz is occasionally found in Britain, but usually in small crystals-unfit
                    for jewellery. It occurs in granite at St Michael’s Mount in Cornwall, in Lundy
                    Island, and in Arran, but the finest British specimens are obtained from the
                    Highlands of Scotland. Ben-a-bourd, one of the Cairngorm group, yields good blue
                    crystals. Topaz occurs in colourless and blue crystals in the granite of the
                    Mourne Mountains in Ireland; and microscopic crystals are not uncommon in
                    certain other granites. The famous topaz-rock of the Schneckenstein, in Saxony,
                    yields pale yellow crystals of great beauty as mineralogical specimens, but not
                    suited for cutting. The yellow Saxon topaz does not seem to change colour on
                    exposure to heat. Some of the finest topaz comes from near Odon Tchelon, in
                    Siberia; while the well-known deep-yellow crystals of Brazil occur near Villa
                    Rica (Ouro Preto). Fine topaz, pale blue and colourless, is found, as rolled
                    crystals, in Tasmania and on Flinders Island in Bass’s Strait. It also occurs in
                    the tin-drifts of New South Wales; and beautifully-formed limpid crystals, of
                    small size, accompany stream-tin at Durango, in Mexico. Fine topaz fit for
                    jewellery has recently been worked at the Platte Mountain, near Pike’s Peak,
                    Colorado. One stone, weighing 125 carats, has been described as being “as fine a
                    gem as America has produced of any kind” (Kunz, 1885). Topaz also occurs in
                    cavities in rhyolite at Nathrop and Chalk Mountain, Colorado, and in trachyte
                    near Sevier Lake, Utah. It is likewise found in Arizona, in New Mexico, and at
                    Stoneham, Maine.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Oriental topaz</hi> is the name sometimes given to yellow
                    corundum, a mineral which is readily distinguished from ordinary topaz by its
                    superior hardness and density. The yellow and smoky varieties of quartz, or
                    cairngorm, are often known in trade as <hi rend="italic">Scotch topaz,</hi> but
                    these are inferior to true topaz in hardness and in density. The chief
                    differences between the three may be thus expressed:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p/></cell>
                        <cell><p>í Scotch Topaz.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>True Topaz.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Oriental Topaz.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Hardness</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>8</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>9</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Specific gravity</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2·6</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3·5 -</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Crystallization</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hexagonal.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Orthorhombic.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Hexagonal.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
