<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0647-0626-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TURENNE, Henri de la Tour d’ Auvergne, Vicomte de (9th
                    edition, volume 23, page 626)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825070">Back</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828986">Bavarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139996">Swedes</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw47w7c">Bavarians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vt81">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n647/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TURENNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Henri de la Tour d’ Auvergne,
                            Vicomte de</hi></label> (1611-1675), a famous French general of the 17th
                    century, was the second son of Henri, Duc de Bouillon, by Elizabeth, daughter of
                    William I., prince of Orange, and was born at Sedan on 11th September 1611. He
                    was carefully educated in the strictest doctrines of the Reformed religion, and
                    at the age of thirteen was sent to learn war from his uncles Maurice and Henry
                    of Nassau in the campaigns of these princes against the Spaniards. In 1626 he
                    received a commission as captain of infantry in the service of Holland, and by
                    1630 had shown such military capacity that Richelieu invited him back to France
                    and appointed him colonel of a regiment. He was present at the relief of Casale,
                    and on 21st June 1635 was made a maréchal de camp for his services at the siege
                    of La Motte in Lorraine under De la Force. In that year he took command of a
                    division in the army under Cardinal La Valette in the defence of Mainz, and,
                    when the cardinal’s army had to fall back on Metz from want of provisions,
                    Turenne commanded the rear-guard, covering the retreat with admirable skill. In
                    1636 he was present under La Valette at the siege of Saverne, where he was
                    wounded, and in the campaign in Franche Comté; in 1637 he served under the same
                    commander in Flanders, took Landrecies, and drove back the cardinal infant from
                    Maubeuge. In 1638 he served under Bernhard of Saxe-Weimar at the siege of
                    Breisach, and in the following year was transferred to the army of D’Harcourt in
                    Italy. It was at this epoch that he established his fame as a general. In
                    November 1639 he covered the retreat of the army, and fought a famous
                    engagement, known as the battle of the “route de Quiers”; in 1640 he saved
                    Casale, and insisted upon not abandoning the siege of Turin, which town
                    surrendered on 24th September; in 1641 he took Coni, Ceva, and Mondovi; and on
                    11th March 1642 he was promoted to the rank of lieutenant-general. After he had
                    served for a short time in Roussillon, he was appointed by Richelieu in 1643 to
                    the command of the army in Italy, under Thomas of Savoy, although his brother,
                    the Duc de Bouillon, had just before been arrested as an accomplice in the
                    conspiracy of Cinq Mars. Mazarin did not exhibit quite so much confidence in
                    Turenne, and in December 1643 removed him from Italy, sending him to collect the
                    remains of Bernhard of Saxe-Weimar’s army and form them once more into an
                    organized force; but he softened the transference by creating Turenne a marshal
                    of France on 16th May 1644.</p>
                <p>Turenne’s four campaigns in Germany, which largely contributed to the peace of
                    Westphalia, have always been regarded as models in the art of war. In June 1644
                    he crossed the Rhine at Breisach, and was marching against the Comte de Mercy,
                    the Imperialist general, who was at Freiburg, when he was superseded by the Duc
                    d’Enghien, better known by his later title of the Prince de Condé. D’Enghien,
                    after fighting the three days’ battle of Freiburg, left the army again to
                    Turenne, who took Philippsburg and Mainz, and then went into winter quarters. In
                    May 1645 Turenne was surprised by Mercy at Marienthal and defeated; but he
                    skilfully concentrated the remains of his army and retreated into Hesse, where
                    he was soon joined by D’Enghien. The two marshals, having reorganized their
                    army, marched against Mercy and totally defeated him at Nördlingen on 3d August
                    1645, when Mercy was killed. D’Enghien again left the army to Turenne, who in
                    conjunction with the Swedish army under Wrangel overran Franconia and Swabia,
                    taking all the fortresses there in 1646. In 1647 he conducted a still more
                    masterly campaign, and after beating the Bavarians and Imperialists in two
                    engagements he and the Swedes occupied Bavaria, and drove the old duke out of
                    his dominions.</p>
                <p>When the troubles of the Fronde (see <hi rend="smallcaps">France,</hi> vol. ix.
                    p. 572, and <hi rend="smallcaps">Mazarin)</hi> broke out, Turenne, who was in
                    command of the veteran troops of Bernhard of Saxe-Weimar in Alsace, hesitated
                    which side to take, till the Duchesse de <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Longueville</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.</hi>), with whom he fell violently
                    in love, persuaded him to side with the parlement. But his troops refused to
                    follow him, and he had to fly with her to Flanders. He there took a command in
                    the Spanish army under Don Estevan Gomar, and, when trying to raise the siege of
                    Réthel, was utterly defeated by Du Plessis-Praslin. But in 1652 he defeated
                    Condé at Gien, and nearly annihilated his army in the battle of the Faubourg St.
                    Antoine. When the troubles of the Fronde were over, Turenne marched upon the
                    frontier, and in several campaigns defeated the Spaniards over and over again,
                    by these victories paving the way for the peace of the Pyrenees (1659), the
                    natural complement of the peace of Westphalia. In these campaigns he had once
                    more to fight against Condé, general-in-chief of the armies of Spain, and in
                    1654 he showed his superiority by raising the siege of Arras and driving the
                    Spaniards from their lines. In 1656 Condé, assisted by Don John of Austria, won
                    an exactly similar victory and relieved Valenciennes, which Turenne was
                    besieging. The prolonged contest between the two was decided in 1658 by
                    Turenne’s victory of the Dunes, in which Cromwell’s contingent of 6000 soldiers
                    took part.</p>
                <p>Louis XIV. now began to rule in reality, and one of his first acts was to create
                    Turenne in 1660 marshal-general of the armies of France. Seven years later
                    Turenne occupied French Flanders and took all the fortresses in that province,
                    though the king was nominally in command of the army,—an exploit equalled in the
                    following year by Condé’s rapid occupation of Franche Comté. It was in 1668 that
                    Turenne made his notorious change of faith. Born of Calvinist parents and
                    educated a Protestant, he had in compliance with the tenets of his religion
                    refused to marry one of Richelieu’s nieces in 1639, and had eventually married a
                    daughter of the Protestant Marshal de la Force. But it can hardly be believed
                    that he was converted at the age of fifty-seven from religious convictions. In
                    1672 the second great European war broke out, brought about by the ambition of
                    Louis XIV. Turenne once more took command of the army, which the king
                    accompanied, and speedily occupied the greater part of Holland, which, however,
                    they were forced to evacuate owing to the Dutch cutting their dykes. In the
                    following year Turenne marched into Westphalia to oppose the imperialist forces,
                    and, though his army was small compared to that of Montecuculi, the imperialist
                    general, he managed to make head against both him and the elector of
                    Brandenburg. In 1673 he was compelled to act on the defensive: but in 1674 in
                    spite of his inferiority of numbers <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n648/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0648-0627"/> he boldly resumed the aggressive. Crossing
                    the Rhine at Philippsburg in June, and marching rapidly to Sinsheim, he defeated
                    the imperialist general Caprara and the duke of Lorraine. He then retired for a
                    time, but in December of the same year he made a sudden rush into the enemy’s
                    winter quarters and utterly routed the elector of Brandenburg, who was then
                    general of the imperialists, at Colmar. Between the battle of Sinsheim and the
                    dash at Colmar, Turenne, under orders from Louvois, committed the acts which are
                    the greatest blot upon his fame by devastating the Palatinate. After the rout of
                    Colmar, and the defeat of Türkheim which followed it, he laid waste the greater
                    part of Alsace, as a defensive measure against another advance of the
                    imperialists. He then advanced into the heart of Germany, and again met
                    Montecuculi, who had succeeded the elector of Brandenburg as generalin-chief.
                    The two generals manoeuvred for four months in much the same way as Wellington
                    and Marmont marched and counter-marched before the battle of Salamanca; at last,
                    on 27th July 1675, their field of battle was chosen, and, as Turenne was
                    directing the position of a battery, he was struck by a cannon ball and killed
                    on the spot. The news of his death was received with universal sorrow; Fléchier,
                    Mascaron, Saint-Évremond, and Lamoignon wrote <hi rend="italic">éloges</hi> of
                    him; and Madame de Sevigné describes the consternation caused by his sudden
                    loss. His body was taken to St-Dénis, and buried with the kings of France. Even
                    the extreme revolutionists of 1793 respected it, and, when the bones of the
                    sovereigns were thrown to the winds, the remains of Turenne were preserved at
                    the museum of natural history until 23rd September 1800, when they were removed
                    by order of Bonaparte to the church of the Invalides at Paris, where they still
                    rest.</p>
                <p>Turenne’s fame rests on his military achievements; as a man he was not more
                    distinguished for his virtues than the duke of Marlborough, whom in many
                    respects he resembled. He had indeed the calmness of all philosophic,
                    cold-minded temperaments, but few other praiseworthy qualities. As a politician
                    he holds no high place. (H. Μ. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
