<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0697-0672-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TVER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 672</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42z12q4d">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h7x">Valleys</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4697039w">Lithuanians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1000435">Lithuanians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1068347">Poles</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:986277">Karelians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1066776">Plateaus</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942866">Girls</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1010775">Marshes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n697/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TVER</label>, a government of central Russia, on the upper
                    Volga, bounded by Pskoff and Novgorod on the W. and N., Yaroslavl and Vladimir
                    on the E., and Moscow and Smolensk on the S.; it has an area of 25,225 square
                    miles. Lying on the southern slope of the Valdai plateau, and intersected by
                    deep valleys, it has the aspect of a hilly region, but is in reality a plateau
                    ranging from 800 to 1000 feet in height. Its highest parts are in the northwest,
                    where the Volga, Western Dwina, and Msta rise in marshes and lakes. The plateau
                    is chiefly built up of Carboniferous limestones, Lower and Upper, underlain by
                    Devonian and Silurian deposits, which appear only in the denudations of the
                    lower valleys. The whole is covered by a thick sheet of boulder-clay (the
                    bottom-moraine of the Scandinavo-Russian ice-sheet) and subsequent lacustrine
                    deposits. A number of åsar (see vol. x. p. 368) occur on the slopes of the
                    plateau. Ochre, brick, and pottery clays, as also limestone for building, are
                    obtained, and there are chalybeate springs. The soil, which is clayey for the
                    most part, is not fertile as a rule.</p>
                <p>Nearly the whole of Tver is watered by the upper Volga (350 miles) and its
                    tributaries, several of which (Vazuza, Dubna, Sestra, Tvertsa, and the
                    tributaries of the Mologa) are navigable. The Vyshnevołotsk system of canals
                    connects the Volga (navigable some 60 miles from its source) with the Baltic,
                    and the Tikhvin system connects the Mologa with Lake Ladoga. The Msta, which
                    flows into Lake Ilmeñ, and its tributary the Tsna, water Tver in the north-west,
                    and the Western Dwina rises in Ostashkoff. This network of rivers highly favours
                    navigation: as many as 3000 boats yearly pass through the Vyshnevołotsk system,
                    and corn, linseed, spirits, flax, hemp, timber, metals, and manufactured ware to
                    the annual value of £1,500,000 are shipped from, or brought to, the river ports
                    of the government. Lakes, ponds, and marshes are numerous in the west and
                    north-west, Lake Seliger—the source of the Volga—and Lake Mstino being the most
                    important. The forests—coniferous in the north and deciduous in the south—are
                    rapidly disappearing, but still cover 890,000 acres. The climate is continental;
                    the average yearly temperature at Tver (41°∙5 Fahr.) is the same as that of Orel
                    and Tamboff (January 11°, July 67°). The population (1,646,683 in 1883, as
                    against 1,567,300 in 1872) is unequally distributed, and in the districts of
                    Kalyazin and Kashin attains a density not much less than that of the more highly
                    favoured black-earth provinces of south east Russia (16 and 17 per square mile).
                    Apart from some 100,000 Karelians and a few Poles and foreigners, the people are
                    all Great Russians. Some traces of Finnish Ves and of Lithuanians are found in
                    the north-east and south. The official returns give the number of Raskolniks as
                    25,000. Only 157,110 are urban; but agriculture is not the chief occupation.
                    While barley and oats are exported, rye is imported. The crops for 1883-18'85
                    averaged 2,889,400 quarters of corn and 4,078,400 bushels of potatoes.
                    Cattle-rearing does not prosper, and the increase shown by the returns for 1883
                    (351,630 horses, 583,670 cattle, and 373,780 sheep) as against those of 1872 is
                    simply due to better registration. Cheese-making has recently, been introduced
                    on the co-operative principle (2168 cwts. of cheddar exported to Britain in
                    1881). The fisheries in the lakes and rivers are productive. The peasants are
                    principally engaged in various manufactures. The total production of the larger
                    manufactures in 1883 was valued at £2,237,250 (tanneries £244,460, cottons
                    £803,270, distilleries £320,010, flour-mills £263,500), and that of the petty
                    trades carried on in combination with agriculture (preparation of pitch, tar,
                    and turpentine, boat-building, construction of cars, sledges, wheels, boxes,
                    tubes, and wooden vessels, and cabinet-making) was estimated in 1884 at
                    £3,000,000, giving occupation to 101,400 persons. Certain branches of the
                    leather industry are important, Kimry and Ostashkoff sending to the market
                    £650,000 worth of boots annually. The small workshops of Tver and the
                    surrounding district work some 4500 cwts. of iron into nails every year, and the
                    Ostashkoff smiths use some 7000 cwts. of iron annually in the manufacture of
                    hatchets, scythes, sickles, and different agricultural implements. Weaving,
                    lace-making, leather embroidery, stocking-making, felting, and the like are also
                    important petty trades, several of these being organized on co-operative
                    principles by the <hi rend="italic">zemstvos.</hi> The railway from St
                    Petersburg to Moscow crosses Tver, and sends off' two branches to Rzheff and to
                    Rybinsk, all three lines being among the busiest in Russia. The river traffic
                    also is considerable. The chief centres of trade, besides the city of Tver, are
                    Byezhetsk, Rzheff, Kashin, Ostashkoff, Torshok, Krasnyi Kholm, and Vesiegonsk
                    during its fair. The provincial assembly of Tver is one of the most prominent in
                    Russia for its efforts in the cause of education and sanitary improvement. In
                    1883 there were 997 primary schools with 47,680 scholars (8500 girls), 17
                    gymnasia and progymnasia (1697 boys and 1263 girls), and two normal schools for
                    teachers. The government is divided into twelve districts, the chief towns of
                    which, with their populations in 1884, are— <hi rend="smallcaps">Tver</hi> (see
                    below), Byezhetsk (5890), Kalyazin (5200), Kashin (5730), Kortcheva (2275),
                    Ostashkoff (9900), Rzheff (26,480), Staritsa (2700), Torshok (12,910),
                    Vesiegonsk (3370), Vyshniy Vototchok (11,590), and Zubtsoff (3160).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
