<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0036-0027-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TALES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 27</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1086604">Racing</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1086436">Race</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1159626">Turning</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:915242">Eskimos</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:970716">Indos</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86v83">Race</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fr3m">Racing</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4rj49113">Turning</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09x43">Eskimos</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nz3s">Hunting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1242804">Scandinavia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n36/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TALES</label> are, in the usual acceptance of the word,
                    fictitious narratives, long or short, ancient or modern. In this article “tale”
                    is used in a stricter sense, as equivalent to the German “Volks-märchen” or the
                    French “conte populaire.” Thus understood, popular tales mean the stories handed
                    down by oral tradition from an unknown antiquity, among savage and civilized
                    peoples. So understood, popular tales are a subject in mythology, and indeed in
                    the general study of the development of man, of which the full interest and
                    importance is scarcely yet recognized. Popular tales won their way into
                    literature, it is true, at a very distant period. The Homeric epics, especially
                    the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey,</hi> contain adventures which are manifestly
                    parts of the general human stock of popular narrative. Other examples are found
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Rigveda,</hi> and in the myths which were handled by
                    the Greek dramatists. Collections of popular tales, more or less subjected to
                    conscious literary treatment, are found in Sanskrit, as in the work of</p>
                <p>Somadeva, whose <hi rend="italic">Kathd Sard Sagara,</hi> or “Ocean of the
                    Streams of Story,” has been translated by Mr Tawney (Calcutta, 1880). The <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Thousand and One Nights (⅛.v.)</hi> are full of popular tales,
                    and popular tales are the staple of the mediaeval <hi rend="italic">Gesta
                    Romanorum,</hi> and of the collections of Straparola and other Italian conteurs.
                    In all these and similar gatherings the story, long circulated from mouth to
                    mouth among the people, is handled with conscious art, and little but the
                    general outline of plot and character of incident can be regarded as original.
                    In the <hi rend="italic">Histoires ou Contes du Temps Passe</hi> of Perrault
                    (Elzevir, Amsterdam, 1697; the Parisian edition is of the same date) we have one
                    of the earliest gatherings of tales which were taken down in their nursery shape
                    as they were told by nurses to children. This at least seems probable, though M.
                    Alfred Maury thinks Perrault drew from literary sources. Perrault attributed the
                    composition to his son, P. Darmau-cour, at that time a child, and this pretext
                    enabled him to give his stories in a simple and almost popular guise. In the
                    dedication signed by the boy, Perrault offers remarks which really do throw a
                    certain light on the origin and characteristics of “märchen.” He says, “Ils
                    renferment tous une morale très sensée et donnent une image de ce qui se passe
                    dans les moindres familles, où la louable impatience d’instruire les enfans fait
                    imaginer des histoires dépourvûes de raison pour s’accomoder à ces mêmes
                    enfants, qui n’en ont pas encore.” It seems that popular tales in many cases
                    probably owe their origin to the desire of enforcing a moral or practical
                    lesson. It appears that their irrational and “infantile” character—“dépourvûes
                    de raison ”—is derived from their origin, if not actually among children, at
                    least among childlike peoples, who have not arrived at “raison,” that is, at the
                    scientific and modern conception of the world and of the nature of man.</p>
                <p>The success of Perrault’s popular tales brought the genre into literary fashion,
                    and the Comtesse d’Aulnoy invented, or in some cases adapted, “contes,” which
                    still retain a great popularity. But the precise and scientific collection of
                    tales from the lips of the people is not much earlier than our century. The
                    chief impulse to the study was given by the brothers Grimm. The first edition of
                    their <hi rend="italic">Kinder-und Haus-Harchen</hi> was published in 1812. The
                    English reader will find a very considerable bibliography of popular tales, as
                    known to the Grimms, in Mrs Alfred Hunt’s translation, <hi rend="italic">Grimm's
                    Household Tales, with Notes</hi> (London, 1884). “How unique was our collection
                    when it first appeared,” they exclaim, and now merely to enumerate the books of
                    such traditions would occupy much space. In addition to the märchen of
                    Indo-European peoples, the Grimms became acquainted with some Malay stories,
                    some narratives of Bechuanas, Negroes, American Indians, and Finnish, Esthonian,
                    and Magyar stories. Thus the Grimms’knowledge of non-European märchen was
                    extremely slight. It enabled them, however, to observe the increase of
                    refinement “in proportion as gentler and more humane manners develop
                    themselves,” the monstrosities of Finnish and Red-Indian fancy gradually fading
                    in the narratives of Germans and Italians. The Grimms notice that the evolution
                    of popular narrative resembles the evolution of the art of sculpture, from the
                    South-Sea idol to the frieze of the Parthenon, “from the strongly marked, thin,
                    even ugly, but highly expressive forms of its earliest stages to those which
                    possess external beauty of mould.” Since the Grimms’ time our knowledge of the
                    popular tales of nonEuropean races has been greatly enriched. We possess numbers
                    of North-American, Brazilian, Zulu, Swahili, Eskimo, Samoan, Maori, Kaffir,
                    Malagasy, Bushman, and even Australian märchen, and can study them in comparison
                    with the stories of Hesse, of the West Highlands of Scotland, of
                    Scandinavia.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n37/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0037-0028"/>
                <p>While the popular romances of races of all colours must be examined together,
                    another element in this subject is not less important. It had probably been
                    often observed before, but the fact was brought out most vividly by Von Hahn <hi
                    rend="italic">{Griechische und albanesische Marchen,</hi> Leipsic, 1864), that
                    the popular tales of European races turn on the same incidents, and display the
                    same succession of situations, the same characters, and the same plots, as are
                    familiar in the ancient epic literature of Greece, India, Germany, and
                    Scandinavia. The epics are either fully-developed märchen evolved by the
                    literary genius of poets and saga-men, or the märchen are degenerate and
                    broken-down memories of the epics and sagas, or perhaps there may be examples of
                    both processes. The second view,—namely, that the popular tales are, so to
                    speak, the scattered grains of gold of which the epic is the original “pocket”
                    or “placer,”—the belief that the märchen are the detritus of the saga,—was for a
                    long time prevalent. But a variety of arguments enforce the opposite conclusion,
                    namely, that the märchen are essentially earlier in character than the epic,
                    which is the final form to which they have been wrought by the genius of Homer
                    or of some other remote yet cultivated poet. If this view be accepted, the
                    evolution of märchen and of certain myths has passed through the following
                    stages :—</p>
                <p>(1) The popular tale, as current among the uncultivated peoples, such as
                    Iroquois, Zulus, Bushmen, Samoans, Eskimo, and Samoyedes. This tale will reflect
                    the mental condition of rude peoples, and will be full of monstrous and
                    miraculous events, with an absence of reason proper, as Perrault says, “a ceux
                    qui n’en ont pas encore.” At the same time the tale will very probably enforce
                    some moral or practical lesson, and may even appear to have been invented with
                    this very purpose, for man is everywhere impressed with the importance of <hi
                    rend="italic">conduct.</hi></p>
                <p>(2) The same tale—or rather a series of incidents and a plot essentially the
                    same—as it is discovered surviving in the oral traditions of the illiterate
                    peasantry of European races. Among them the monstrous element, the ferocity of
                    manners observed in the first stage, will be somewhat modified, but will be
                    found most notable among the Slavonic tribes. Nowhere, even in German and
                    Scottish märchen, is it extinct, cannibalism and cruel torture being favourite
                    incidents.</p>
                <p>(3) The same plot and incidents as they exist in the heroic epics and poetry of
                    the cultivated races, such as the Homeric books, the Greek tragedies, the Cyclic
                    poets, the <hi rend="italic">Kalewala</hi> of the Finns, certain hymns of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Rigveda,</hi> certain legends of the Brahmanas, the story of
                    the λ"olsungs,—in these a local and almost historical character is given by the
                    introduction of names of known places, and the adventures are attributed to
                    national heroes,—Odysseus, Oedipus, Sigurd, Wainamoinen, Jason, Pururavas, and
                    others. The whole tone and manners are nobler and more refined in proportion as
                    the literary workmanship is more •elaborate.</p>
                <p>This theory of the origin of popular tales in the fancy •of peoples in the savage
                    condition (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mythology),</hi> of their survival as
                    märchen among the peasantry of Indo-European and other civilized races, and of
                    their transfiguration into epics, could only be worked out after the •discovery
                    that savage and civilized popular tales are full of close resemblances. These
                    resemblances, when only known to exist among Indo-European peoples, were
                    explained as part of a common Aryan inheritance, and as the result of a malady
                    of language. This system, when applied to myths in general, has already been
                    examined (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mythology).</hi> According to another view,
                    märchen everywhere resemble each other because they all arose in India, and have
                    thence been borrowed and transmitted. For this theory consult Benfey’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Panchatantra</hi> aud M. Cosquin’s <hi rend="italic">Contes de
                    Lorraine</hi> (Paris, 1886). In opposition to the Aryan theory, and the theory
                    of borrowing from India, the system which is here advocated regards popular
                    tales as kaleidoscopic arrangements of comparatively few situations and
                    incidents, which again are naturally devised by the early fancy. Among these
                    incidents may be mentioned, first, kinship and intermarriage between man and the
                    lower animals and even inorganic phenomena. Thus a girl is wooed by a frog,
                    pumpkin, goat, or bear, or elephant, in Zulu, Scotch, Walachian, Eskimo,
                    Ojibway, and German märchen. This incident is based on the lack of a sense of
                    difference between man and the things in the world which is prevalent among
                    savages (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mythology).</hi> Other incidents familiar in
                    our nursery tales (such as ‘ ‘ Cinderella” and “Puss in Boots ”) turn on the
                    early belief in metamorphosis, in magic, in friendly or protecting animals
                    (totems or beast manitous). Others depend on the early prevalence of cannibalism
                    (compare Grimm, 47, “The Juniper Tree ”). This recurs in the mad song of
                    Gretchen in <hi rend="italic">Faust,</hi> concerning which a distinguished
                    student writes, “This ghost of a ballad or rhyme is my earliest remembrance, as
                    crooned by an old East-Lothian nurse.” (Compare Chambers’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Popular Rhymes of Scotland,</hi> 1870, p. 49.) The same legend occurs among the
                    Bechuanas, and is published by Casalis. Yet another incident springs from the
                    taboo on certain actions between husband and wife, producing the story of Cupid
                    and Psyche (see Lang’s <hi rend="italic">Custom and Myth,</hi> 1884, p. 64).,
                    Once more, the custom which makes the youngest child the heir is illustrated in
                    the märchen of the success, despite the jealousy of the elders, of Cinderella,
                    of the Zulu prince (Callaway’s <hi rend="italic">Tales from the Λma∑ulu,</hi>
                    pp. 64, 65), and in countless other märchen. In other cases, as in the
                    world-wide märchen corresponding to the Jason epic, we seem in presence of an
                    early romantic invention,—how diffused it is difficult to imagine. Moral
                    lessons, again, are inculcated by the numerous tales which turn on the duty of
                    kindness, or on the impossibility of evading fate as announced in prophecy. In
                    opposition to the philological explanation of the story of Oedipus as a
                    nature-myth, this theory of a collection of incidents illustrative of moral
                    lessons is admirably set forth in Prof. Cauparetti’s <hi rend="italic">Edipo e
                    la Mitologiα Comparata</hi> (Pisa, 1867).</p>
                <p>On a general view, then, the stuff of popular tales is a certain number of
                    incidents and a certain set of combinations of these incidents. Their strange
                    and irrational character is due to their remote origin in the fancy of men in
                    the savage condition; and their wide distribution is caused, partly perhaps by
                    oral transmission from people to people, but more by the tendency of the early
                    imagination to run everywhere in the same grooves. The narratives, in the ages
                    of heroic poetry, are elevated into epic song, and in the Middle Ages they were
                    even embodied in legends of the saints. This view is maintained at greater
                    length, and with numerous illustrations, in the introduction to Mrs Hunt’s
                    translation of Grimm’s <hi rend="italic">Kinder-und Haus-Märchen,</hi> and in
                    <hi rend="italic">Custom and Myth,</hi> already referred to.</p>
                <p>A complete bibliography of the literature of popular tales would fill many pages.
                    The reader who is curious about savage popular tales may turn to TheaΓs <hi
                    rend="italic">Kaffir Folk Lore</hi> (2d ed., London, 1886); Callaway’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Nursery Tales of the Amazulu</hi> (London, 1868); Schoolcraft’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Algie Researches·,</hi> Gill’s <hi rend="italic">Myths and
                    Tales of the South Pacific·,</hi> Petitot’s <hi rend="italic">Traditions
                    Indiennes</hi> (1886); Shortland’s <hi rend="italic">Maori Religion and
                    Mythology</hi> (London, 1882); The <hi rend="italic">South African Folk Lore
                    Record;</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Folk Lore Record</hi> (London, 1879-85,
                    Malagasy stories); Rink’s <hi rend="italic">Tales and Traditions of the
                    Eskimo;</hi> Bleek’s <hi rend="italic">Hottentot Tales and Fables</hi> (London,
                    1864); Castrén’s <hi rend="italic">Samoyedischc Märchen</hi>; and Leland’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Algonquin Legends</hi> (London, 1884). For European tales, the
                    bibliography in the translation of Grimm already referred to may be used, and
                    the Maisonneuve collection, <hi rend="italic">Les Littératures populaires</hi>
                    may be recommended. The names of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n38/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0038-0029"/> Liebrecht, Köhler, Dasent, Ralston, Nigra, Pitre,
                    Cosquin, Afanasief, Gaidoz, Sébillot, may serve as clues through the enchanted
                    forest of the nursery tales of Europe. (A. L. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
