<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0066-0057-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TAR (9th edition, volume 23, page 57)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205503">Finland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204694">Alabama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cr5nn1b">Tar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gb1xr6p">Spirit</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44746z94">Pitch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1143040">Tar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795828">Acids</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1064885">Pitch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865087">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130061">Spirits</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1130040">Spirit</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n66/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TAR</label> is a product of the destructive distillation of
                    organic substances. It is a highly complex material, varying in its composition
                    according to the nature of the body from which it is distilled,—different
                    products, moreover, being obtained according to the temperature at which the
                    process of distillation is carried on. As commercial products there are two
                    principal classes of tar in use—(1) wood tar, the product of the special
                    distillation of several varieties of wood, and (2) coal tar, which is primarily
                    a bye-product of the distillation of coal for the manufacture of illuminating
                    gas. These tars are intimately related to the bitumen, asphalt, mineral pitch,
                    and petroleum obtained in very many localities throughout the world.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Wood Tar.—</hi> Wood tar, known also as Stockholm and as
                    Archangel tar, is principally prepared in the great pine forests of central and
                    northern Russia, Finland, and Sweden. The material chiefly employed is the
                    resinous stools and roots of the Scotch fir <hi rend="italic">(Pinus
                        sylvestris)</hi> and the Siberian larch <hi rend="italic">(Larix
                        sibiηca),</hi> with other less common fir-tree roots. A large amount of tar
                    is also prepared from the roots of the swamp pine <hi rend="italic">(P.
                        australis)</hi> in North and South Carolina, Georgia, and Alabama, in the
                    United States. In the distillation of wood a series of products, including gas,
                    tar, pyroligneous acid and wood spirit, and charcoal may be obtained, and any of
                    these may be the primary object of the operation. When tar is the substance
                    sought, the ancient and crude method of working is yet largely adopted in the
                    north of Europe. The wood to be treated is closely piled up into a huge conical
                    stack or pile on an elevated platform, the sole of which is covered with clay
                    and tiles. The sole slopes inwards from every side to the centre, where an
                    opening communicates with a vaulted cavity under the elevated platform. The pile
                    of wood is closely covered over with layers of turf and earth or sand to a depth
                    of several inches, but leaving at first near the bottom numerous apertures for
                    the admission of air to promote ignition. The pile is ignited from below, and as
                    the fire spreads through the heap the various apertures are closed up and a slow
                    smouldering combustion goes on for some days till, by the sinking of the pile,
                    the top of the stack falls in, and a bright flame springs up at that point.
                    About ten days after ignition tar first begins to flow, and it is at once
                    collected into barrels. According to the size of the pile, the distillation may
                    continue several weeks, the tar secured amounting to about 17 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 5 per cent, of the w ood operated on. In this
                    method several valuable products—the gas, the crude pyroligneous acid, and much
                    charcoal—are lost or wasted; and a more economical process of treating the wood
                    in closed stills or retorts is now largely used in Russia, the gas evolved
                    serving as fuel under the retorts. The heavier tar products of the distillation
                    collect at the bottom of the retort, whence they are carried off by a pipe to a
                    receiver; the volatile portion passes off at the upper part of the retort, and
                    is separately condensed, the lightest portion passing through a worm condenser.
                    From treatment in close retorts resinous roots yield from 16 to 20 per cent, of
                    tar, with some oil of turpentine and pyroligneous acid.</p>
                <p>Wood tar is a semi-fluid substance, of a dark brown or black colour, with a
                    strong pungent odour and a sharp taste. Owing to the presence of acetic
                    (pyroligneous) acid, which is a collateral product, it has an acid reaction; it
                    is soluble in that acid, as well as in alcohol and the fixed and essential oils,
                    &lt;fcc. Tar consists essentially of a mixture of homologous hydrocarbons, and
                    by redistillation it can be fractionated into a series of bodies having fixed
                    boiling points. Some varieties of tar have a granular appearance, from the
                    presence of minute crystals of pyrocatechin, which dissolve and disappear on
                    heating the substance. Pyrocatechin dissolves freely in water, and to it the tar
                    water <hi rend="italic">(liquor picis)</hi> of pharmacy probably owes its
                    value.</p>
                <p>Crude tar from retorts, when submitted to redistillation, gives off w ood spirit
                    (methyl-alcohol), and then acetic (pyroligneous) acid, and finally, on forcing
                    the heat, pitch oil is driven off. The residuum left in the still hardens into a
                    solid vitreous mass, which forms the black pitch of commerce. Tar and pitch are
                    most largely used as protective coatings for woodwork and other materials much
                    exposed to water and the weather. Thus tar is of great value in connexion with
                    shipbuilding and shipping generally. A considerable quantity is used in
                    manufacturing tarred ropes, and in the “smearing” of highland sheep to afford a
                    protection against the weather. Pitch also is the basis of the Berlin black or
                    Brunswick black used for coating cast-iron goods and for “japanning”
                    preparations.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Coal Tar.—</hi> The art of distilling coal for the production
                    of tar was discovered and patented by the earl of Dundonald in 1787, and till
                    the general introduction of coal gas some amount of coal was yearly distilled in
                    Scotland for the production of coal tar. The demand for the substance was
                    limited, it being principally used for coating iron castings and smith work, for
                    making an inferior lamp black, and as a source of a solvent oil. With the
                    extensive use of coal gas the necessity for this separate distillation ceased,
                    and soon tar was produced in the manufacture of gas in quantities that could not
                    be disposed of. It was burned up for heating gas-retorts; it was mixed with coal
                    dust, sawdust, &lt;tc., for making patent fuel; and it was distilled for
                    producing a series of hydrocarbon oils, heavy tar, and pitch; but it was only
                    after the discovery and introduction of “tar-colours” that the substance came
                    for some time to be really valuable. Since that time its price has fluctuated
                    greatly; and in the United Kingdom alone there are now distilled annually about
                    10,000,000 tons of coal for gas-making, producing 120,000,000 gallons of crude
                    tar,—a quantity greatly in excess of the ordinary demand.</p>
                <p>If wood be distilled slowly at low temperatures, the gases consist chiefly of
                    carbonic oxide and carbonic acid, mixed with only very little of carburetted
                    hydrogens, and consequently little luminous on combustion; the watery part of
                    the tar includes relatively much of methyl-alcohol, acetone, and acetic acid;
                    the oily part of the tar (tar proper) has a certain proximate composition
                    characteristic of this mode of distillation. Our present knowledge in regard to
                    this last-named point is very incomplete; of definite species the following have
                    been discovered :—</p>
                <p>(1) Phenol, C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> OH
                    (synonym carbolic acid).</p>
                <p>(2) Cresol, (C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.CH <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 3</hi>)OH.</p>
                <p>(3) Phlorol, (C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>.OH)C
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>.</p>
                <p>(4) Pyrocatechine, (C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript">
                    4</hi>)(OH) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, one of three isomerldes.</p>
                <p>(5) Guaiacol, <hi rend="smallcaps">C</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">
                        6</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">H</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 4</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">∣q^</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> h</hi>,
                    methyl-ester of No. 4.</p>
                <p>(6) Homo-pyrocatechjne, {C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> II <hi rend="subscript">
                        3</hi> (CH <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>)j(0Il) <hi rend="subscript">
                    2</hi>.</p>
                <p>(7) Creosol, {c <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> (CH
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>)j-øc <hi rend="subscript"> H</hi> 3,
                    methyl-ester of No. 6.</p>
                <p>Genuine creosote consists of (1), (2), (5), and (7). In addition, there are
                    numberless bodies which still await scientific definition.</p>
                <p>If the distillation of wood is carried out at a very high temperature,—if, for
                    instance, the wood is placed in a relatively large retort <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n67/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0067-0058"/> previously brought up to a bright red heat
                    and kept at such temperature, or if the vapours produced at a relatively low
                    temperature are passed through intensely heated pipes before reaching the
                    condenser (Pettenkofer’s method for producing illuminating gas from wood),—the
                    gas produced contains a considerable admixture of luminiferous hydrocarbons, the
                    proportions of methyl-alcohol, acetone, and acetic acid get less, and the tar
                    proper assumes more of the character of coal-gas tar (see below). Similar
                    observations we make in the case of coal. About 1862 Wigan cannel coal used to
                    be distilled industrially at low temperatures to produce “light oils.”
                    Schorlemmer examined these and found them to consist chiefly of “paraffins” (see
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Paraffin)</hi> from C <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> H
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 12</hi> upwards. A similar result is obtained with
                    ordinary coal, although in its case the “benzols” are more largely represented.
                    If we distil any kind of coal at high temperatures— <hi rend="italic">i.e.</hi>,
                    in the way customary for illuminating-gas making—the distillable part of the tar
                    proper consists chiefly of benzene, C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> β</hi>, and benzene-derivatives, <hi rend="italic"
                        >i.e.,</hi> benzols, C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript">
                        β</hi> + nCH <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> j phenols, C <hi rend="subscript">
                        6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> O, and homologues, (C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>.πCH <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>)OH; amido-bodies, C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi> NH <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> (aniline), and
                    homologues; condensed benzols, such as naphthalene, C <hi rend="subscript">
                        10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi> = 2C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi>-C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 4</hi> 5 anthracene, C <hi rend="subscript"> 14</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 10</hi> = 3C <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 6</hi>-C <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 8</hi>; chrysene, <hi rend="smallcaps">Ci</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript smallcaps"> 8</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">H</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript smallcaps"> 12</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">=</hi> 4C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> β</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> g</hi>- C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 12</hi>, &amp;c. The
                    paraffins then become an altogether subordinate feature.</p>
                <p><hi rend="underline">A</hi> great and meritorious research of Berthelot’s has
                    thrown considerable light on the chemical mechanism of dry distillation. As
                    found by him, even the most complex of the substances named are producible by
                    the interaction upon one another of a few bodies of very simple constitution, or
                    even one or other of these by the mere action of a high temperature. To give a
                    few examples. Marshgas, CH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, when passed through
                    red-hot tubes, yields olefines, C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, C <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 6</hi>, C <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, &amp;c., with elimination of hydrogen, H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>. The same CH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, if
                    subjected to a spark-current (t.e., local application of intense heat), yields
                    acetylene and hydrogen, 2CH <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> =∙C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> + 3H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, and the acetylene produced passes partly into
                    benzene, C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> =3C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>. Ethylene, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, when passed through
                    a porcelain tube kept at a moderate red heat, yields benzene, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi>, styrolene = phenyl
                    - ethylene, C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 3</hi>.C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 5</hi>, naphthalene, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, and perhaps also
                    its hydride, C <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi>.
                    Acetylene, <hi rend="italic">qua</hi> potential benzene, and ethylene yield
                    styrolene and hydrogen, <hi rend="smallcaps">C</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript                     smallcaps"> 6</hi><hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >H</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 6</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">+
                        C</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">H</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript smallcaps"> 4</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">= C</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript smallcaps"> 6</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">H</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript smallcaps"> 5</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">.C</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">H</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript smallcaps"> 3</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">+ H</hi><hi
                        rend="subscript smallcaps"> 2</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">j</hi> and styrolene
                    plus ethylene yields hydrogen and naphthalene, C <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> H
                        <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>,</p>
                <p>Benzol at a high temperature loses hydrogen, and, so to say, doubles up into
                    di-phenyl, C <hi rend="subscript"> 12</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi>; and
                    this latter, when heated with ethylene, yields anthracene, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 14</hi> Hι <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi>, and hydrogen,
                    ^12∏10 ^t 0 <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript"> =</hi> C <hi rend="subscript"> 14</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 10</hi> + 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>. Conversely,
                    hydrogen may, so to say, turn out its equivalent of a hydrocarbon; thus, for
                    instance, chrysene, C <hi rend="subscript"> 18</hi> H <hi rend="subscript">
                        12</hi> + 2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, yields di-phenyl, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 12</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi>, + benzene, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi>.</p>
                <p>Pyrogenic reactions generally are reversible; thus, any of the following three
                    equations is correct, whether we read it from the left to the right or from the
                    right to the left :—</p>
                <p>(1) C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> TI <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> (ethane), at a
                    red heat becomes C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi>
                    +H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">(2)</hi> Ci <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 10</hi> +C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 6</hi> =C <hi rend="subscript"> 18</hi> Hi <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> +2H <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>(3) Cι <hi rend="subscript"> 4</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> q-2H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi> =2C <hi rend="subscript"> β</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> β</hi> +C <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>.</p>
                <p>Hence no single pyrogenic reaction goes to the end; if it does not, so to say,
                    check its own progress, other secondary reactions set in and do so, the general
                    result being that ultimately, but in general slowly, a state of dynamic
                    equilibrium is attained in which a set of synthetic reactions on the one hand
                    and a set of analytic reactions on the other compensate one another.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Industrial Working of Coal Tar.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >—</hi> Coal tar, as it comes from the gas-works, is used for a variety of
                    purposes, such as—(1) for fuel, the tar being made into a spray by means of a
                    steam-injector and the spray kindled; (2) for the preservation of building
                    materials, porous stones, and bricks, &amp;c.; (3) for making roofingfelt (in
                    1868, five-sixths of the 9000 tons of tar produced at the Berlin gas-works was
                    thus utilized; the case, however, is different now); (4) for making a low
                    quality of lamp-black. At present, however, most of the tar produced, in centres
                    of industry at least, is worked up by distillation. The tar as it comes from the
                    gasworks is allowed to rest in a “pond” until the tar-water (solution chiefly of
                    ammonia and certain ammonia salts) has gone to the top. The tar proper is then
                    pumped into a large wrought-iron still (of upright-cylinder form preferably) and
                    therein subjected to distillation over a naked fire. A necessary preliminary,
                    however, is the removal of the unavoidable remnant of water, which is best
                    effected by cautiously heating the tar in the still so as to render it more
                    fluid and enable the water to rise to the top and then letting the upper stratum
                    run out by an overflow tap at the side. The distillation is then started. It
                    involves the formation of two sets of volatile products, namely—(1) combustible
                    gases (including sulphuretted hydrogen and bisulphide of carbon vapour), which
                    must be led away to avoid nuisance and danger of fire, and (2) a very complex
                    liquid or semi-liquid distillate. This latter is collected in successive
                    fractions, generally in this manner:—(1) as “first runnings,” what comes over at
                    temperatures below 105° to 110° C.; (2) as “light oils,” at temperatures between
                    110° and 210° C.; (3) as “carbolic oil,” at temperatures between 210° to 240°
                    C.; (4) as</p>
                <p>“creosote oil,” at temperatures between 240° to 270° C.; (5) as anthracene oil,
                    at temperatures above 270°.</p>
                <p>In the earlier part of the “first runnings” and light-oil period the condenser
                    must be kept cold; towards the end it must be kept warm to prevent choking by
                    solidified naphthalene. In practice, the operator does not go entirely by the
                    boiling point, but to a great extent by the specific gravity of the distillate,
                    which, in general, increases as the boiling point rises. As soon as a drop of
                    the last runnings floats in water (exhibits the specific gravity 1), the “light
                    oil” is supposed to be over. That the fractionation is not always and everywhere
                    effected in the same way needs hardly be said. If the manufacture of carbolic
                    acid is aimed at, it is best (according to Lunge) to select the fraction 170° to
                    230° C. for this purpose. Naphthalene boils as high as 217°, yet a deal goes
                    into this carbolic-acid fraction. As soon as naphthalene begins to crystallize
                    out largely (on cooling down a sample of distillate), the carbolic acid may be
                    presumed to be over. What follows next is put aside as creosote oil, until,
                    after the disappearance of the naphthalene, a new solid product, namely,
                    anthracene, begins to show itself. With any tar that contains a remunerative
                    proportion of anthracene, the anthracene oil is the most valuable of the
                    products, as the raw material for the making of artificial alizarins.</p>
                <p>Supposing the anthracene to have been extracted as completely as practicable, the
                    residue in the still consists of “hard pitch,” a viscid black fluid which on
                    cooling freezes into a fragile solid. In former times more commonly than now
                    “soft pitch’’used to be produced by leaving more or less of the anthracene oil
                    and even creosote oil in the still. At the end of the anthracene stage of the
                    distillation it is as well, if not necessary, to help the very high boiling
                    vapour out of the still by means of superheated steam, and to keep the worm at
                    100° C. to prevent choking. At a German establishment a vacuum is used with
                    great advantage.</p>
                <p>We come now to explain briefly how the several fractions are worked up.</p>
                <p>The pitch (which we assume to be “hard pitch ”) must be run off hot through a tap
                    at the bottom of the still and led into a low-roofed and well closed-in “house,”
                    because it would take fire in the open air. After it has cooled down
                    sufficiently in the “house,” the pitch is run into pitch-holes in front of the
                    house and allowed to freeze there. The depth of pitch in a hole is about 12
                    inches. The solid pitch is hacked out with pickaxes and sent into commerce. A
                    superior apparatus for the recovery of the pitch, which precludes all danger of
                    conflagration and many inconveniences of the ordinary system, has been devised
                    for the Paris gas-works by Régnault. <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> Lunge found,
                    from many distillations, that tar from the midland counties yields about 55 per
                    cent, of hard pitch.</p>
                <p>Hard pitch is used chiefly for making the following. (1) <hi rend="italic"
                        >Asphalt.—</hi> The pitch is fused up—perhaps in the still which produced
                    it—with the requisite proportion of creosote and anthracene oil, previously
                    freed from their valuable components. Such asphalt is used for street-paving,
                    t.e., filling up the spaces between the paving-s*tones, and, in admixture with
                    sand and generally more or less of natural asphalt, for the making of footpaths
                    and floorings generally. In Germany it serves for the making of pipes for
                    conveying acid liquids in works and chemical laboratories, &amp;c. Endless
                    hemp-paper is soaked in liquefied asphalt and wound spirally around an iron
                    core, previously smeared over with soft soap, in about 100 layers. The whole is
                    then exposed to strong pressure while still hot, and is separated from the core
                    after being allowed to cool. Such pipes stand almost any kind of acid, but they
                    must not be used for hot liquids. (2) <hi rend="italic">Varnishes.—</hi> The
                    pitch is dissolved in suitable tar oils,—creosote oil for a lower and light oil
                    for a higher quality. (3) <hi rend="italic">Coke.—</hi> In former times more
                    frequently than now pitch was made into coke by transferring it to a special
                    flat still and distilling as long as any volatile products came off. The coke
                    which remains is a very pure and consequently valuable fuel. (4) <hi
                        rend="italic">Lamp Black</hi> (as a last resource, if no other mode of
                    utilization is practicable).—The pitch is subjected to partial combustion on hot
                    iron plates and the smoke conveyed into chambers to deposit its carbon. The
                    yield is about 40 per cent.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Anthracene Oil.—</hi> The oil is allowed to stand cold for a
                    week or so until the anthracene has crystallized out as completely as possible.
                    The mother-liquor is then eliminated, the bulk by means of a filter-press, the
                    rest, at a higher than the ordinary temperature, by hydraulic pressure. The
                    crude product includes far more than half its weight of impurities—phenanthrene,
                    paraffin, naphthalene, &amp;c. To remove these as far as possible, the crude
                    anthracene is ground up and treated with petroleum spirit (boiling at 70° to
                    100° C. ) or coal tar naphtha (12(r to 190°), in which real anthracene is
                    relatively insoluble. The insoluble part is separated by filtering arrangements
                    and presses (so constructed as to avoid danger of fire), and at last sublimed,
                    more with the view of bringing it into a customary convenient form than with the
                    object of effecting further purification. Such final anthracene may contain 50
                    to 65 per cent, of pure substance. The only reliable method for <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi> For wood tar, see <hi rend="smallcaps">wood
                        Spirit</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Vinegab.</hi><hi rend="superscript">
                        2</hi> It is described in Lunge’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise on the
                        Distillation of Coal Tar,</hi> London, 1882. to which this article is
                    largely indebted.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n68/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0068-0059"/>
                <p>determining its strength is to convert a known weight into anthraquinone, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 11</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> O <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, by boiling it with a glacial acetic acid solution
                    of chromic acid, separating out the quinone by diluting with water, collecting
                    and -weighing the product. One part of quinone corresponds to 0'8558 of
                    anthracene.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Creosote Oil</hi> is either used as it is for pickling timber,
                    softening of pitch, &amp;c., or else redistilled to extract from it what there
                    is of anthracene oil and carbolic acid oil, which are worked up with the
                    respective principal quantities.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Carbolic Oil.—</hi> Assuming this oil to have been collected
                    (as it should be if intended for the making of carbolic acid) between 170° and
                    230°, the process of extraction is, briefly, as follows. The oil is mixed with a
                    suitable proportion of caustic-soda ley (ascertained by an assay) in an iron
                    vessel at 40° to 50° C. Charles Lowe recom-' mends ley of l <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 34 sp. gr., diluted with water to five times its
                    volume. After settling, the aqueous layer is withdrawn into a lead-lined vessel,
                    and the soda supersaturated by sulphuric acid. Crude carbolic acid rises to the
                    top as an oil, and is withdrawn to be sold as such or purified. See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Carbolic Acid.</hi><hi rend="italic">Naphthalene</hi>
                    abounds in the oil left after extraction of the carbolic acid by caustic soda
                    and in the more volatile fractions of the creosote oil. From these it separates
                    out (not completely), on standing, in crystals. These are collected, best in a
                    filter-press, and then subjected to hydraulic pressure to force out the rest of
                    the mother-liquor. The crude naphthalene thus obtained contains an impurity
                    which causes it to become red on standing in the air. To remove it, the crude
                    product is mixed with 5 to 10 per cent, of vitriol of at least 1 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 7 sp. gr., at a moderate heat (addition of a
                    little binoxide of manganese is an improvement, Lunge); it is then washed, first
                    with water, then with dilute alkali, and lastly again with water, to be
                    ultimately distilled or sublimed. In the latter case it is obtained in the form
                    of thin colourless plates of great beauty. It fuses at 80° C. and boils at 217°
                    C. Naphthalene is used largely in the making of certain tar colours, such as
                    Manchester yellow, C <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript">
                        6</hi> (NO <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>) <hi rend="subscript"> 2</hi>, and
                    the beautiful scarlets and crimsons made by the “färb werke” in Höchst, Germany;
                    these latter are diazocompounds derived from Ø-naphthol, C <hi rend="subscript">
                        10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> (OH). Coal gas, if impregnated at a
                    suitable temperature with naphthalene vapour immediately before issuing from the
                    burner, gains greatly in luminosity. This is the principle of the “albo-carbon”
                    gas lamps.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">First Runnings and Light Oil.—</hi> These may be said to
                    include all the industrially valuable “benzols” (taking “benzol” as a generic
                    term for benzol or benzene itself and its higher homologues, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi>, C <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 7</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">C</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> 8</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">H</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> io</hi><hi
                        rend="smallcaps">,</hi> &amp;c.). As the distiller in most cases does not
                    aim at an actual separation of all the individual benzols from one another, but
                    at the production of certain benzol mixtures demanded by the trade, the mode of
                    working may assume a great variety of forms; yet the first aim in all cases is
                    the same, being the elimination of all the non-benzol from the given oil or
                    oils. For this purpose the light oil is, as a rule, subjected to a preliminary
                    fractionation over a naked fire to split it up into fractions fit to be worked
                    for (crude) benzol (C <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi> H <hi rend="subscript">
                        6</hi> and C <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>),
                    for carbolic acid (C <hi rend="subscript"> fi</hi> H <hi rend="subscript">
                        β</hi> 0), and to be incorporated with the creosote oil respectively; the
                    carbolic acid is extracted, and the creosote-oil part put aside, and thus one or
                    more mixtures of “benzols” are obtained.</p>
                <p>The first runnings contain the bulk of the benzene, C <hi rend="subscript">
                        6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi>, and a little of its higher
                    homologues, associated, however, with bisulphide of carbon, low-boiling
                    olefines, C <hi rend="subscript"> n</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 2n</hi>, traces
                    of carbolic acid, &amp;c. To remove these impurities as far as possible, the oil
                    is thoroughly agitated with concentrated oil of vitriol (which takes up the
                    impurities except the bisulphide of carbon), and the “dirty” acid allowed to
                    settle out. The acid is then withdrawn as neatly as possible, and the residual
                    oil washed, first with water, then with dilute caustic soda, and, lastly, again
                    with pure water. The washed oil then is subjected to a preliminary fractionation
                    by distillation over a naked flame in the “crude benzol still.”</p>
                <p>The’ several mixed benzols obtained are subjected finally to a further
                    fractionation in stills worked with steam, to be divided into mixed products
                    known by specific names in commerce. But these we cannot possibly consider here.
                    We will rather give an idea of the way in which the several chemical species
                    (benzene, toluene, &amp;c.) are being isolated in a state of approximate purity
                    to meet the demands of the tar-colour industry. To do so even for one named
                    component by means of ordinary stills would require an endless number of
                    fractional distillations. The work is very materially shortened if, as proposed
                    by Mansfield long ago, we combine the still with an inverted condenser
                    (still-head, dephlegmator), inserted between the still and the worm, and keep
                    that intermediate condenser at a suitable constant temperature, so that all the
                    less volatile part of the vapour is recondensed and sent back to the still. An
                    excellent apparatus of this kind was constructed and worked successfully by
                    Coupler. His apparatus consists of three parts, viz.:—(1) a still heated by
                    means of a coil of close steam pipes; (2) a columnar
                    rectifier—“colonnen-apparat” as the Germans call it,—which communicates with the
                    still, and which is divided into many compartments by horizontal septa so
                    contrived that the vapour in passing from a compartment to the next higher one
                    must bubble through the liquid condensed there from preceding vapour,—an
                    overflow pipe, trapped below by condensate, hindering accumulation of the liquid
                    in any compartment beyond a certain level; (3) a constant temperature
                    still-head, consisting of a succession of communicating ring-shaped tubes, which
                    are immersed in a bath of water or molten paraffin kept at a prescribed constant
                    temperature. Only the most volatile part of the vapour survives as such in the
                    columnar rectifier, the degree of its volatility depending, of course, other
                    things being equal, on the rate at which we distil. This most volatile part
                    suffers partial condensation at the prescribed temperature in the still-head;
                    the condensed parts are sent back to compartments of the “column” by pipes bent
                    into the shape of a U at the point where they join the “column,” so as to
                    prevent vapour from entering them. The uncondensed vapour goes to the worm, and
                    is condensed as usual.</p>
                <p>To prepare benzene, the still-head is kept at 60° to 70° C. At first a mixture of
                    low-boiling bodies and benzene goes over, which is rejected, but soon pure
                    benzol follows and continues until almost all this component has distilled over.
                    The benzol obtained boils between 80° and 82° C., and consequently is
                    practically pure. In order now to extract the toluene, C <hi rend="subscript">
                        7</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi>, we raise the temperature of the
                    still-head to 100° C. A small quantity of a mixture of benzene and toluene
                    follows, which is rejected. After it comes a continuous distillation of almost
                    pure toluene, boiling at 110° to 112° C. In a similar manner (relatively) pure
                    xylene, C <hi rend="subscript"> 8</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi>, boiling
                    point 137° to 140°, and tri-methyl-benzene, C <hi rend="subscript"> 9</hi> H <hi
                        rend="subscript"> 12</hi>, boiling point 148° to 150°, can be extracted
                    successively; but the process becomes troublesome with anything above toluene on
                    account of the high temperatures involved for still and still-head. Coupler’s
                    apparatus is now superseded by other constructions, but they all work on the
                    same principle,—that of the Coffey still, as used for the rectifying of spirit
                    of wine.</p>
                <p>Pure benzene, toluene, and xylene are used largely for the manufacture of
                    tar-colours. The following (and other) mixtures are produced directly from the
                    light oil or first runnings :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell> (1) 90 per cent, benzol </cell>
                        <cell> initial boiling point </cell>
                        <cell> 82’ </cell>
                        <cell> C. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> (2) 50 per cent, benzol </cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="subscript"> n n</hi></cell>
                        <cell> 88 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> (3) “Toluol” </cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="subscript"> w n</hi></cell>
                        <cell> 100 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> (4) Carburetting naphtha </cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="smallcaps">,,</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps">
                            m</hi></cell>
                        <cell> 108 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> (5) Solvent naphtha </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 110 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> (6) Burning naphtha </cell>
                        <cell> ,∖ </cell>
                        <cell> 138 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>No. 4 serves for enriching coal-gas and adding to its luminiferous power, No. 5
                    for varnishes, No. 6 for feeding primitive lamps used in the open air, where
                    smoke is no objection.</p>
                <p>The following percentage table for the tar from the Berlin gasworks (given in <hi
                        rend="italic">Chemische Industrie</hi> for 1879) gives an idea of the
                    quantitative composition of this most complex material :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Benzol (including toluol, &lt;fcc.) </cell>
                        <cell> 0-80 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Higher benzols </cell>
                        <cell> 0∙60 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Crystallized carbolic acid </cell>
                        <cell> 0∙20 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Cresol for disinfecting purposes </cell>
                        <cell> 0∙30 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Naphthalene </cell>
                        <cell> 3∙70 </cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Creosote oil </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 24-00 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Anthracene (pure) </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 0∙20 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Pitch </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 55-00 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> Water and loss </cell>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell> 15∙20 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
