<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0230-0213-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TEZA, or TÂZÀ</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 213</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:919892">Fairs</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:919882">Fairings</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:919888">Fairness</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4804p">Fairs</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06587">Drum</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4445hd4m">Diamonds</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n230/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TEZA, or TÂZÀ</label>. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Morocco,</hi>
                    vol. xvi. p. 834.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n231/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0231-0214"/>
                <p>T <hi rend="underline">H A</hi> CKER AV, <hi rend="smallcaps">William
                    Makepeace</hi> (1811-1863), one of the greatest of English authors and
                    novelists, son of Richmond Thackeray (Mrs Richmond Thackeray was born Miss
                    Becher), and grandson of W. R. Thackeray of Hadley, Middlesex, was born at
                    Calcutta on July 18, 1811. Both his father and grandfather had been Indian civil
                    servants. His mother, who was only nineteen at the date of his birth, was left a
                    widow in 1816, and afterwards married Major Henry Carmichael Smyth. Thackeray
                    himself was sent home to England from India as a child, and went to
                    Charterhouse, since his time removed to Godalming from its ancient site near
                    Smithfield. Anthony Trollope, in his book on Thackeray in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >English Men of Letters</hi> series, quotes a letter written to him about
                    Thackeray’s school-days by Mr G. S. Venables. “He came to school young,” Mr
                    Venables wrote, “a pretty, gentle, and rather timid boy.” This accords with the
                    fact that all through Thackeray’s writings the student may find traces of the
                    sensitiveness which often belongs to the creative mind, and which, in the boy
                    who does not understand its meaning and its possible power is apt to assume the
                    guise of a shy disposition. To this very matter Mr Venables tersely refers in a
                    later passage of the letter quoted by Trollope: “When I knew him better, in
                    later years, I thought I could recognize the sensitive nature which he had as a
                    boy.” Another illustration is found in the statement, which will be recognized
                    as exact by all readers of Thackeray, that “his change of retrospective feeling
                    about his school-days was very characteristic. In his earlier books he always
                    spoke of the Charterhouse as Slaughter House and Smithfield. As he became famous
                    and prosperous his memory softened, and Slaughter House was changed into Grey
                    Friars, where Colonel Newcome ended his life.” Even in the earlier references
                    the bitterness which has often been so falsely read into Thackeray is not to be
                    found. In “Mr and Mrs Frank Berry” <hi rend="italic">(Men's Wives)</hi> there is
                    a description of a Slaughter-House fight, following on an incident almost
                    identical with that used in <hi rend="italic">Vanity Fair</hi> for the fight
                    between Dobbin and Cuff. In both cases the brutality of school life, as it then
                    was, is very fully recognized and described, but not to the exclusion of the
                    chivalry which goes alongside with it. In the first chapter of “Mr and Mrs Frank
                    Berry,” Berry himself and Old Hawkins both have a touch of the heroic. In the
                    story which forms part of <hi rend="italic">Men's Wives</hi> the bully whom
                    Berry gallantly challenges is beaten, and one hears no more of him. In <hi
                    rend="italic">Vanity Fair</hi> Cuff the swaggerer is beaten in a similar way,
                    but regains his popularity by one well-timed stroke of magnanimity, and
                    afterwards shows the truest kindness to his conqueror.</p>
                <p>In February 1829 Thackeray went to Trinity College, Cambridge, and in that year
                    contributed some engaging lines on <hi rend="italic">Timbuctoo,</hi> the subject
                    for the prize poem, to a little university paper called <hi rend="italic">The
                    Snob,</hi> the title of which he afterwards utilized in the famous <hi
                    rend="italic">Snob Papers.</hi> The first stanza has become tolerably well
                    known, but is worth quoting as an early instance of the direct comic force
                    afterwards employed by the author in verse and prose burlesques :— In Africa—a
                    quarter of the world—</p>
                <p>Men’s skins are black; their hair is crisp and curled; And somewhere there,
                    unknown to public view, A mighty city lies, called Timbuctoo.</p>
                <p>One other passage at least in <hi rend="italic">The Snob,</hi> in the form of a
                    skit on a paragraph of fashionable intelligence, seems to bear traces of
                    Thackeray’s handiwork. At Cambridge James Spedding, Monckton Milnes (Lord
                    Houghton), Edward Fitzgerald, W. H. Thompson (afterwards master of Trinity), and
                    other distinguished persons were among his friends. In 1830 he left Cambridge
                    without taking a degree, and went to Weimar and to Paris. His visit to Weimar
                    bore fruit in the sketches of life at a small German court which appear in <hi
                    rend="italic">Fitz-Boodlds Confessions</hi> and in <hi rend="italic">Vanity
                    Fair.</hi> In 1832 he came of age, and inherited a sum which Trollope’s book
                    describes as amounting to about five hundred a year. The money was soon lost,—
                    some in an Indian bank, some in two newspapers which in <hi rend="italic">Lovel
                    the Widower</hi> are referred to under one name as <hi rend="italic">The
                    Museum,</hi> in connexion with which our friends Honeyman and Sherrick of <hi
                    rend="italic">The Newcomes</hi> are briefly brought in. His first regular
                    literary employment after the loss of his patrimony was on <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fraser's Magazine,</hi> in which in 1837-38 appeared <hi rend="italic">The
                    History of Mr Samuel Titmarsh and the Great Hoggarty Diamond,</hi> a work filled
                    with instances of the wit, humour, satire, pathos, which found a more ordered if
                    not a fresher expression in his later and longer works. For freshness, indeed,
                    and for a fine perception which enables the author to perform among other feats
                    that of keeping up throughout the story the curious simplicity of its supposed
                    narrator’s character, the <hi rend="italic">Great Hoggarty Diamond</hi> can
                    scarce be surpassed. The characters, from Lady Drum, Lady Fanny, Lady Jane, and
                    Edmund Preston down to Brough, his daughter, Mrs Roundhand, Gus Hoskins, and, by
                    no means least, Samuel Titmarsh’s pious aunt with her store of “Rosolio,” are
                    living; the book is crammed with honest fun; and, for pure pathos, the death of
                    the child, and the meeting of the husband and wife over the empty cradle (a
                    scene illustrated by the author himself with that suggestion of truth which no
                    shortcoming in drawing could spoil), stands, if not alone in its own line, at
                    least in the company of very few such scenes in English fiction. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Great Hoggarty Diamond,</hi> oddly enough, met with the fate that
                    afterwards befell one of Lever’s best stories which appeared in a periodical
                    week by week,—it had to be cut short at the bidding of the editor. In the same
                    year in which it appeared Thackeray married Isabella, daughter of Colonel
                    Matthew Shawe. Of the daughters born of the marriage, one, Mrs Richmond Ritchie,
                    has earned distinction as a novelist. Mrs Thackeray, to quote Trollope, “became
                    ill and her mind failed her,” and Thackeray thereupon “became as it were a
                    widower till the end of his days.” In 1840 came out <hi rend="italic">The Paris
                    Sketch Book.</hi> Much of it had been written and published at an earlier date,
                    and in the earlier writings there are some very curious divagations in
                    criticism. The book contains also a striking story of card-sharping, afterwards
                    worked up and put into Altamont’s mouth in <hi rend="italic">Pendennis,</hi> and
                    a very powerful sketch of a gambler’s death and obsequies. Three years before,
                    in 1837, Thackeray had begun, in <hi rend="italic">Fraser,</hi> the <hi
                    rend="italic">Yellowplush Papers,</hi> with their strange touches of humour,
                    satire, tragedy (in one scene, the closing one of the history of Mr Deuceace),
                    and their sublimation of fantastic bad spelling (M <hi rend="superscript">
                    i</hi> Arony for macaroni is one of the typical touches of this); and this was
                    followed by <hi rend="italic">Catherine,</hi> a strong story, and too
                    disagreeable perhaps for its purpose, founded closely on the actual career of a
                    criminal named Catherine Hayes, and intended to counteract the then growing
                    practice of making ruffians and harlots prominent characters in fiction. There
                    soon followed <hi rend="italic">Fitz-Boodlds Confessions and Professions,</hi>
                    including the series <hi rend="italic">Men's Wives,</hi> already referred to;
                    and, slightly before these, <hi rend="italic">The Shabby Genteel Story,</hi> a
                    work interrupted by Thackeray’s domestic affliction and afterwards republished
                    as an introduction to <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of Philip,</hi> which
                    took up the course of the original story many years after the supposed date of
                    its catastrophe. Tn 1843, and for some ten years onwards according to Trollope,
                    Thackeray was writing for <hi rend="italic">Punch,</hi> and the list of his
                    contributions included among many others the celebrated <hi rend="italic">Snob
                    Papers</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Ballads of Policeman X.</hi> In 1843 also
                    came out the <hi rend="italic">Irish Sketch Book,</hi> and in 1844 the account
                    of the journey <hi rend="italic">From Cornhill to Grand Cairo,</hi><pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n232/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0232-0215"/> in which was published the excellent poem of <hi
                    rend="italic">The White Squall.</hi> In 1844 there began in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Fraser</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Barry Lyndon,</hi> called in the
                    magazine <hi rend="italic">The Luck of Barry Lyndon, a Romance of the Last
                    Century. Barry Lyndon</hi> has, with a very great difference in treatment, some
                    resemblance to Smollett’s <hi rend="italic">Count Fathom</hi>;—the hero, that is
                    to say, is or becomes a most intolerable scoundrel, who is magnificently
                    unconscious of his own iniquity. The age and pressure of the time depicted are
                    caught with amazing verisimilitude, and in the boyish career of Barry Lyndon
                    there are fine touches of a wild chivalry, simplicity, and generosity, which
                    mingle naturally with the worse qualities that, under the influence of
                    abominable training, afterwards corrupt his whole mind and career. The man is so
                    infatuated with and so blind to his own roguery, he has so much dash and daring,
                    and is on occasions so infamously treated, that it is not easy to look upon him
                    as an entirely detestable villain until, towards the end of his course, he
                    becomes wholly lost in brutish debauchery and cruelty. His latter career is
                    founded on that of Andrew Robinson Stoney Bowes, who married the widow of John,
                    ninth earl of Strathmore. There is also no doubt a touch of Casanova in Barry
                    Lyndon’s character. Besides the contributions to <hi rend="italic">Punch</hi>
                    specially referred to, there should be noticed <hi rend="italic">Punch's Prize
                    Novelists,</hi> containing some brilliant parodies of Edward Lytton Bulwer,
                    Lever, Mr D’Israeli (in <hi rend="italic">Codlingshy,</hi> perhaps the most
                    perfect of the series), and others. Among minor but admirable works of the same
                    period are found <hi rend="italic">A Legend of the Rhine</hi> (a burlesque of
                    the great Dumas’s <hi rend="italic">Cthon l'Archer),</hi> brought out in a
                    periodical of George Cruikshank’s, <hi rend="italic">Cox's Diary</hi> (on which
                    has been founded a well-known Dutch comedy, <hi rend="italic">Janus Tulp),</hi>
                    and the <hi rend="italic">Fatal Boots.</hi> This is the most fitting moment for
                    mentioning also <hi rend="italic">Rebecca and Rowena,</hi> which towers, not
                    only over Thackeray’s other burlesques, excellent as they are, but over every
                    other burlesque of the kind ever written. Its taste, its wit, its pathos, its
                    humour, are unmatchable; and it contains some of the best songs of a particular
                    kind ever written—songs worthy indeed to rank with Peacock’s best. In 1846 was
                    published, by Messrs Bradbury and Evans, the first of twenty-four numbers of <hi
                    rend="italic">Vanity Fair,</hi> the work which first placed Thackeray in his
                    proper position before the public as a novelist and writer of the first rank. It
                    was completed in 1848, ’ when Thackeray was thirty-seven years old; and in the
                    same year Abraham Hayward paid a tribute to the author’s powers in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Edinburgh Review.</hi> It is probable that on <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vanity Fair</hi> has been largely based the foolish cry, now heard less and
                    less frequently, about Thackeray’s cynicism, a cry which he himself, with his
                    keen knowledge of men, foresaw and provided against, amply enough as one might
                    have thought, at the end of the eighth chapter, in a passage which is perhaps
                    the best commentary ever written on the author’s method. He has explained how he
                    wishes to describe men and women as they actually are, good, bad, and
                    indifferent, and to claim a privilege—</p>
                <p>“Occasionally to step down from the platform, and talk about them: if they are
                    good and kindly, to love and shake them by the hand; if they are silly, to laugh
                    at them confidentially in the reader’s sleeve; if they are wicked and heartless,
                    to abuse them in the strongest terms politeness admits of. Otherwise you might
                    fancy it was I who was sneering at the practice of devotion, which Miss Sharp
                    finds so ridiculous; that it was I who laughed good-humouredly at the railing
                    old Silenus of a baronet—whereas the laughter comes from one who has no
                    reverence except for prosperity, and no eye for anything beyond success. Such
                    people there are living and. flourishing in the world—Faithless, Hopeless,
                    Charityless: let us have at them, dear friends, with might and main. Some there
                    are, and very successful too, mere quacks and fools: and it was to combat and
                    expose such as those, no doubt, that laughter was made.”</p>
                <p>As to another accusation which was brought against the book when it first came
                    out, that the colours were laid on too thick, in the sense that the villains
                    were too villainous, the good people too goody-goody, the best and completest
                    answer to that can be found by any one who chooses to read the work with care.
                    Osborne is, and is meant to be, a poor enough creature, but he is an eminently
                    human being, and one whose poorness of character is developed as he allows bad
                    influences to tell upon his vanity and folly. The good in him is fully
                    recognized, and comes out in the beautiful passage describing his farewell to
                    Amelia on the eve of Waterloo, in which passage may be also found a sufficient
                    enough answer to the statement that Amelia is absolutely insipid and
                    uninteresting. So with the companion picture of Rawdon Crawley’s farewell to
                    Becky: who that reads it can resist sympathy, in spite of Rawdon’s vices and
                    shady shifts for a living, with his simple bravery and devotion to his wife? As
                    for Becky, a character that has since been imitated a host of times, there is
                    certainly not much to be said in her defence. We know of her, to be sure, that
                    she thought she would have found it easy to be good if she had been rich, and we
                    know also what happened when Rawdon, released without her knowledge from a
                    spunging-house, surprised her alone with and singing to Lord Steyne in the house
                    in May Fair. After a gross insult from Steyne, “Rawdon Crawley, springing out,
                    seized him by the neckcloth, until Steyne, almost strangled, writhed and bent
                    under his arm. ‘You lie, you dog,’ said Rawdon; ‘ you lie, you coward and
                    villain! ’ And he struck the peer twice over the face with his open hand, and
                    flung him bleeding to the ground. It was all done before Rebecca could
                    interpose. She stood there trembling before him. She admired her husband,
                    strong, brave, and victorious.” This admiration is, as Thackeray himself thought
                    it, the capital touch in a scene which is as powerful as any Thackeray ever
                    wrote—as powerful, indeed, as any in English fiction. Its full merit, it may be
                    noted in passing, has been curiously accented by an imitation of it in M.
                    Daudet’s <hi rend="italic">Fromont Jeune et Risler Aîné.</hi> As to the extent
                    of the miserable Becky’s guilt in the Steyne matter, on that Thackeray leaves it
                    practically open to the reader to form what conclusion he will. There is, it
                    should be added, a distinct touch of good in Becky’s conduct to Amelia at Ostend
                    in the last chapter of the book, and those who think that too little punishment
                    is meted out to the brilliant adventuress in the end may remember this to her
                    credit. It is supreme art in the treatment of her character that makes the
                    reader understand and feel her attractiveness, though he knows her
                    extraordinarily evil qualities; and in this no writer subsequent to Thackeray
                    who has tried to depict one of the genus Becky Sharp has even faintly succeeded.
                    Among the minor characters there is not one—and this is not always the case even
                    with Thackeray’s chief figures—who is incompletely or inconsistently depicted;
                    and no one who wishes to fully understand and appreciate the book can afford to
                    miss a word of it.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Vanity Fair</hi> was followed by <hi rend="italic">Pendennis,
                    Esmond,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Newcorn.es,</hi> which appeared
                    respectively in 1850, 1852, and 1854. It might be more easy to pick holes
                    critically in <hi rend="italic">Pendennis</hi> than in <hi rend="italic">Vanity
                    Fair.</hi> Pendennis himself, after his boyish passion and university escapades,
                    has disagreeable touches of flabbiness and worldliness; and the important
                    episode of his relations with Fanny Bolton, which Thackeray could never have
                    treated otherwise than delicately, is so lightly and tersely handled that it is
                    a little vague even to those who read between the lines; the final announcement
                    that those relations have been innocent can scarcely be said to be led up to,
                    and one can hardly see why it should have been so long delayed. This does not of
                    course affect the value of the book as a picture of middle and upper class life
                    of the time, the time when Vauxhall still existed, and the haunt for suppers and
                    songs <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n233/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0233-0216"/> which Thackeray in this book called the Back
                    Kitchen, and it is a picture filled with striking figures. In some of these,
                    notably in that of Foker, Thackeray went, it is supposed, very close to actual
                    life for his material, and in that particular case with a most agreeable result.
                    As for the two <hi rend="italic">umbrae</hi> of the marquis of Steyne, it is
                    difficult to believe that they were intended as caricatures from two well-known
                    persons. If they were, for once Thackeray’s hand forgot its cunning. Here, as in
                    <hi rend="italic">Vanity Pair,</hi> the heroism has been found a little insipid;
                    and there may be good ground for finding Laura Pendennis dull, though she has a
                    spirit of her own. In later books she becomes, what Thackeray’s people very
                    seldom are, a tiresome as well as an uninviting person. Costigan is unique, and
                    so is Major Pendennis, a type which, allowing for differences of period and
                    manners, will exist as long as society does, and which has been seized and
                    depicted by Thackeray as by no other novelist. His two encounters, from both of
                    which he comes out victorious, one with Costigan in the first, the other with
                    Morgan in the second volume, are admirable touches of genius. In opposition to
                    the worldliness of the major, with which Pendennis does not escape being
                    tainted, we have Warrington, whose nobility of nature has come unscathed through
                    a severe trial, and who, a thorough gentleman if a rough one, is really the
                    guardian of Pendennis’s career. There is, it should be noted, a characteristic
                    and acknowledged confusion in the plot of Pendennis, which will not spoil any
                    intelligent reader’s pleasure.</p>
                <p>Probably most readers of <hi rend="italic">The Newcomes</hi> (1854) to whom the
                    book is mentioned think first of the grand, chivalrous, and simple figure of
                    Colonel Newcome, who stands out in the relief of almost ideal beauty of
                    character against the crowd of more or less imperfect and more or less base
                    personages who move through the novel. At the same time, to say, as has been
                    said, that this book “is full of satire from the first to the last page” is to
                    convey an impression which is by no means just. There is plenty of kindliness in
                    the treatment of the young men who, like Clive Newcome himself and Lord Kew,
                    possess no very shining virtue beyond that of being honourable gentlemen; in the
                    character of J. J. Ridley there is much tenderness and pathos; and no one can
                    help liking the Bohemian F. B., and looking tolerantly on his failings. It maybe
                    that both the fiendish temper of Mrs Mackenzie and the sufferings she inflicts
                    on the Colonel are too closely insisted on; but it must be remembered that this
                    heightens the singular pathos of the closing scenes of the Colonel’s life. It
                    has seemed convenient to take <hi rend="italic">The Newcomes</hi> after <hi
                    rend="italic">Pendennis,</hi> because Pendennis and his wife reappear in this
                    book as in the <hi rend="italic">Adventures of Philip·,</hi> but <hi
                    rend="italic">Esmond</hi> (1852) was written and published before <hi
                    rend="italic">The Newcomes.</hi> To some students <hi rend="italic">Esmond</hi>
                    seems and will seem Thackeray’s capital work. It has not been rivalled, and only
                    a few times approached by Mr Besant, as a romance reproducing with unfailing
                    interest and accuracy the figures, manners, and phrases of a past time, and it
                    is full of beautiful touches of character. But Beatrix, upon whom so much
                    hinges, is an unpleasing character, although one understands fully why men were
                    captivated by her insolent beauty and brilliancy; and there is some truth in
                    Thackeray’s own saying, that “Esmond was a prig.” Apart from this, the story is,
                    like the illusion of a past time in the narrative, so complete in all its
                    details, so harmoniously worked out, that there is little room for criticism. As
                    to Esmond’s marriage with the lady whom he has served and loved as a boy, that
                    is a matter for individual judgment. Beatrix, it has been indicated above, is
                    wonderfully drawn; and not the least wonderful thing about her is her
                    reappearance as the jaded, battered, worldly, not altogether unkindly, Baroness
                    in <hi rend="italic">The Virginians.</hi> It was just what Beatrix must have
                    come to, and the degradation is handled with the lightest and finest touch.</p>
                <p>In 1851 Thackeray had written <hi rend="italic">The English Humourists of the
                    Eighteenth Century,</hi> delivered as a series of lectures at Willis’s Rooms in
                    the same year, and re-delivered in the United States in 1852 and 1853, as was
                    afterwards the series called <hi rend="italic">The Four Georges.</hi> Both sets
                    were written for the purposes of lecturing. In 1857 Thackeray stood
                    unsuccessfully as a parliamentary candidate for Oxford against Mr Cardwell, and
                    in the same year appeared the first number of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Virginians,</hi> a sequel to <hi rend="italic">Esmond.</hi> This is a most
                    unequal work,—inferior, as sequels are apt to be, to <hi rend="italic"
                    >Esmond</hi> as an historical romance, less compact and coherent, prone to
                    divagation and desultoriness, yet charming enough in its lifelikeness, in the
                    wit and wisdom of its reflexions, and, as has been said, in its portrait of
                    Beatrix grown old. The last number of <hi rend="italic">The Virginians</hi> came
                    out in 1859, and in the same year Thackeray undertook the editorship of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Cornhill Magazine.</hi> This was a task which, as readers of his
                    <hi rend="italic">Roundabout</hi> paper “Thorns in the Cushion” will remember,
                    the kindliness and sensitiveness of his disposition made irksome to him, and he
                    resigned the editorship iu April 1862, though he continued towrite for the
                    magazine until he died. In the <hi rend="italic">Cornhill</hi> appeared from his
                    pen <hi rend="italic">Lovel the Widower,</hi> previously written, with different
                    names for some of the personages, in dramatic form; <hi rend="italic">The
                    Adventures of Philip·,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Roundabout Papers·,</hi> and
                    the story, unhappily never finished, called <hi rend="italic">Denis Duval. Lovel
                    the Widower,</hi> changed from the dramatic to the narrative form, remains a
                    piece of high comedy in which the characters are indicated rather than fully
                    worked out, with a bold and practised touch. It contains some references to
                    Thackeray’s early and unfortunate newspaper speculations, and it was provided by
                    the author with illustrations which as in others of his books have a value which
                    is entirely their own in furnishing, as it were, a far completer commentary on
                    the letterpress than could have been given by any draughtsman, however
                    perspicacious and finished, who approached the pictorial representation of the
                    characters from the outside. To the general statement thus indicated an
                    exception should be made in the case of Doyle’s illustrations to <hi
                    rend="italic">The Newcomes</hi> and to <hi rend="italic">Rebecca and
                    Rowena.</hi> On the other hand, not even Doyle could have matched the fun and
                    spirit of Thackeray’s own illustrations to another burlesque story, one of his
                    best, <hi rend="italic">The Rose and the Ring.</hi> The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Roundabout Papers,</hi> a small storehouse of some of Thackeray’s best
                    qualities as an essayist, came out in the <hi rend="italic">Cornhill
                    Magazine</hi> simultaneously with <hi rend="italic">Lovel the Widower</hi> and
                    with <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of Philip.</hi> Among them is one
                    differing in form from the rest, called <hi rend="italic">The Notch on the Axe—a
                    Story à la Mode.</hi> It is an almost perfect specimen of the author’s genius
                    for burlesque story-telling; but it contains an odd instance, which a careful
                    reader will not fail to discover, of the odd habit of inaccuracy of which
                    Thackeray himself was conscious. <hi rend="italic">The Adventures of Philip</hi>
                    is, as has been before said, in the nature of a sequel to or a completion of <hi
                    rend="italic">A Shabby Genteel Story.</hi> As with the other direct sequel, it
                    is a work of great inequality. It contains scenes of humour, pathos, satire,
                    which rank with Thackeray’s best work; some old friends from others of the
                    novels make brief but pleasant reappearances in its pages; there are fine
                    sketches of journalistic, artistic, and diplomatic life, and the scene from the
                    last-named in Paris is inimitable. The Little Sister is altogether delightful;
                    the Twysden family are terribly true and vastly diverting; the minor characters,
                    among whom old Ridley, J. J.’s father, should be mentioned, are wonderfully hit
                    off; nor did Thackeray ever write a better scene than that of the quarrel
                    between Bunch, Baynes, and M <hi rend="superscript"> ζ</hi> Whirter in the Paris
                    pension. Philip himself is impossible<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n234/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0234-0217"/>; one cannot say that the character is
                    ill-drawn—it is not drawn at all. It is an entirely different personage in
                    different chapters; and it has here and there a very unpleasant touch which must
                    have come of rapid writing. Yet so admirable are many parts of the book that it
                    cannot be left out of the list of Thackeray’s most considerable works. <hi
                    rend="italic">Denis Duval,</hi> which reached only three numbers, promised to be
                    a first-rate work, more or less in the <hi rend="italic">Esmond</hi> manner. The
                    author died while it was in progress, on the day before Christmas day 1863. He
                    was buried in Kensal Green, and a bust by Marochetti was put up to his memory in
                    Westminster Abbey.</p>
                <p>Little has yet been said of Thackeray’s performances in poetry. They formed a
                    small but not the least significant part of his life’s work. The grace and the
                    apparent spontaneity of his versification are beyond question. Some of the more
                    serious efforts, such as <hi rend="italic">The Chronicle of the Drum</hi>
                    (1841), are full of power, and instinct with true poetic feeling. Both the
                    half-humorous half-pathetic ballads and the wholly extravagant ones must be
                    classed with the best work in that kind; and the translations from Béranger are
                    as good as verse translations can be. He had the true poetic instinct, and
                    proved it by writing poetry which equalled his prose in grace and feeling.</p>
                <p>It is not necessary to discuss the precise place which Thackeray will in future
                    hold, in respect to his immediate contemporaries. What seems absolutely certain
                    is that the force and variety of his genius and art will always hold for him a
                    place as one of the greatest of English novelists and essayists, and, it should
                    be added, as by no means the least of English critics. (w. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >h. p.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
