<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0417-0398-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TIMOTHEUS (9th edition, volume 23, page 398)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:878901">Corcyra</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128747">Spartanism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:935174">Friendship</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93g2m">Friendship</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4707wx1r">Ships</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n5c">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n417/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TIMOTHEUS</label>, a distinguished Athenian general, was a
                    son of Conon, who restored the walls of Athens. To the military qualities of his
                    father he added a love of letters, which found scope in his friendship with
                    Isocrates. The considerable fortune which he inherited from his father seems to
                    have been exhausted by him in the public service. In 375 B.c. the Athenians,
                    then at war with Sparta, sent Timotheus with a fleet to the Ionian Sea, where he
                    gained over Cephalonia and secured the friendship of the Acarnanians and of
                    Alcetas, king of the Molossians. He also made himself master of Corcyra, but
                    used his victory with a moderation which won the goodwill of the conquered. At
                    the same time he defeated a Spartan fleet at Alyzia on the Acarnanian coast. In
                    373 he was appointed to the command of a fleet destined for the relief of
                    Corcyra, then beleaguered by the Spartans. But his ships were not fully manned,
                    and to recruit their strength he first cruised in the Aegean. The delay excited
                    the indignation of the Athenians, who brought him to trial; but, thanks to the
                    exertions of his friends, Jason, tyrant of Pherae, and Alcetas, king of the
                    Molossians, both of whom came to Athens personally to plead his cause, he was
                    acquitted, but removed from the command, Iphicrates being appointed in his room.
                    Being reduced to great poverty—for he had pledged his private property in order
                    to put the fleet in an efficient state—he left Athens and took service with the
                    king of Persia. We next hear of him in 367 or 366, when he was sent by the
                    Athenians with an armament to support Ariobarzanes, satrap of Phrygia. But,
                    finding that the satrap was in open revolt against Persia, Timotheus abstained
                    from helping him and turned his arms against Samos, which was occupied by a
                    Persian garrison. He took it after a ten months’ siege (365 B.c.). Sailing
                    north, he then captured Sestus, Crithote, Torone, Potidaea, Methone, Pydna, and
                    many more cities. In 358 or 357, when Eubaea was in danger of falling into the
                    hands of Thebes, the Athenians, in response to a spirited appeal of Timotheus,
                    crossed over into the island and expelled the Thebans in three days. In the
                    course of the Social War, which broke out shortly afterwards, Timotheus was
                    despatched with Iphicrates, Menestheus, son of Iphicrates, and Chares to put
                    down the revolt. The hostile fleets sighted each other in the Hellespont; but a
                    gale was blowing, and Iphicrates and Timotheus decided not to engage. Chares,
                    disregarding their opposition, lost many ships, and in his despatches he
                    incriminated his colleagues so bitterly that the Athenians recalled them and put
                    them on their trial for having taken bribes from the enemy to betray the fleet.
                    The accusers were Chares and Aristophon. The former was an officer of
                    notoriously bad character; the latter had himself stood in the dock no less than
                    seventy-five times. Iphicrates was not above browbeating the jury, who
                    accordingly acquitted him and his son. Timotheus, who condescended to no such
                    means of securing an acquittal, was condemned to pay a very heavy fine. Being
                    unable to pay, he withdrew to Chalcis. The time and place of his death are not
                    mentioned by ancient writers. The Athenians afterwards did what they could to
                    repair the wrong they had done to Timotheus by remitting the greater part of the
                    fine to his son Conon, by burying his remains in the Ceramicus, and by raising
                    statues to his memory in the agora and the acropolis.</p>
                <p>Our materials for the life of Timotheus are very imperfect, and the chronology is
                    in some points uncertain. The chief authorities are Isocrates, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Or.</hi>, xv.; Xenophon, <hi rend="italic">Hellenica,</hi> v. and vi.;
                    Diodorus, XV. and xvi.; Cornelius Nepos, <hi rend="italic">Vit.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Tim.</hi>; and Polyaenus, <hi rend="italic">Strat.,</hi> iii.
                    10. Other scraps are to be gleaned from the orators, Plutarch, &amp;c. The
                    speech <hi rend="italic">Against</hi><hi rend="italic">Timotheus</hi> which has
                    come down to us <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n418/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0418-0399"/> under the name of Demosthenes is probably not
                    by the orator. It is chiefly interesting as illustrating the straits to which
                    Timotheus was reduced by his sacrifices in the public cause.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
