<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0192-0179-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TENNIS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 179</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="26" ref="fasttopic:1066938">Play</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:937529">Games</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:927635">Floors</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:927616">Flooring</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1036191">Nets</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="26" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tx6q">Play</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42r3nw89">Games</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d58r">Floors</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cf8t">Nets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n192/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TENNIS</label>. This, the oldest, perhaps, of all existing
                    ball-games, is at once the most difficult to learn, on account of the intricacy
                    of its laws, and the most interesting when learnt, because of the great variety
                    of its combinations and the difficulty of solving rapidly the problems which are
                    constantly presented to the player. It derives an additional claim to attention
                    from numberless historical associations. Of the origin of tennis it is not
                    possible to speak with certainty; but it may be confidently assumed that it
                    sprang from some very simple sport. It first appeared in Europe in the Middle
                    Ages, when we find it played in open courts, in the parks or ditches of the
                    feudal castles of France and Italy. It was at first the pastime of kings and
                    nobles, but afterwards became popular with all classes. The French seem to have
                    borrowed it from the Italians, and to have contributed some of its refinements;
                    and the English took it from the French. Though mentioned in the Arthurian
                    romances, the game was certainly not known in England in the time of Arthur. The
                    name <hi rend="italic">tennis</hi> is supposed to be derived from the
                    exclamation “Tenez !” employed by early French players in serving the ball. In
                    Italy the game is called “giuoco della palla”; in France, “jeu de paume,” which
                    also means the tennis court; in Germany it is called by the generic title of
                    “Ballspiel”; in Spain, “juego al ble” or “jugar al ble.” It is clear from the
                    French name that the ball was originally struck with the palm of the hand. This
                    was afterwards protected by a glove, as is still the practice in the Basque
                    country. Upon the glove strings and cross-strings were next stretched, to give a
                    faster impulse; and the addition of a short handle made an easy transition to
                    the racket. In the time of Henry VII. the hand still sometimes met the racket,
                    even in the royal court at Windsor.</p>
                <p>One of the first improvements in the game consisted in the building of closed
                    courts, first with walls, then with walls and roof. It is still played in the
                    open air in some places in France, and “pallone,” a rude and violent variety of
                    the game, is yet seen in Italy. There are twenty-seven courts in England and one
                    in Dublin.</p>
                <p>As now played, tennis in France is virtually the same as in England, though there
                    are a few differences of detail. The court is rectangular (see the annexed
                    plan). An inner wall runs round three sides, to the height of 7 feet, from which
                    a sloping roof, called the penthouse, reaches to the outer -wall. The
                    surrounding passage thus enclosed (not shown in plan) is 7 feet wide. Opposite
                    to the long penthouse is the main wall, in which there is at one point a
                    projection called the <hi rend="italic">tambour, E,</hi> which deflects the ball
                    across the court. In the inner wall, below the penthouse, there are several
                    openings, the one at the end, on the service side, being called the <hi
                    rend="italic">dedans, B,</hi> the others the <hi rend="italic">galleries.</hi>
                    At the further end of the court is the <hi rend="italic">grille,</hi> a square
                    opening adjacent to the main wall. Across the court, halfway between the two
                    ends, is stretched a net <hi rend="italic">n,</hi> 3 feet high in the middle and
                    5 feet at the sides. The game may be played by two, or by three, or by four
                    players, one against one, one against two, or two against two. At the
                    commencement the players toss or “spin” a racket, to decide which shall serve
                    first, calling “rough” (for the knotted side) or “smooth.” The party which wins
                    the “spin” has the choice of the service or the “first stroke,” the latter term
                    meaning the return of the service. The server then begins at the “dedans” end of
                    the court, technically called the “service side,” pitches the ball in the air,
                    and strikes it with his racket so that it shall drop on the side penthouse or on
                    the wall above it, and then from the penthouse upon the floor on the other side
                    of the net (called the “hazard side ”), within the “service court” bounded by
                    the “service line” <hi rend="italic">x</hi> and the “pass line” <hi
                    rend="italic">p.</hi> If he fail to do this, a “fault” is called, or a “pass” if
                    the ball has gone beyond the pass line. If he serves a second fault, his
                    adversary scores a point, called a “stroke.” A pass counts for nothing, but
                    annuls a previous fault.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>In the Manchester Club this law (8) has been wisely abolished.</p></note> It
                    now becomes the duty of the adversary, called the “striker-out,” to return the
                    ball by striking it with his racket in such a manner that it shall pass back
                    over the net to the service side. The server must now strike it again and return
                    it to the hazard side; and the player who first returns the ball into the net or
                    “out of court” <hi rend="italic">{i.e.,</hi> to the roof, or above the play line
                    on the walls) loses the stroke, which is scored to his antagonist. But, if a
                    player fail or refuse to strike the ball in the air (a “volley ”) or on its
                    first bound and before it touches the floor a second time, then, except on the
                    hazard side beyond the service line, a “chase” is made or reckoned on the floor,
                    according to the lines on or between which the ball has dropped the second time.
                    This chase is a stroke in abeyance. When one has been made it is called by the
                    marker, but does not affect the score until one of the players has scored 40,
                    "when they change sides, and the player who has allowed the chase to be made
                    must then endeavour to win it, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> to place the second
                    bound of the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n193/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0193-0180"/> ball returned by him better, <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> nearer to the end wall, than the point at which the chase was
                    marked. As often as his adversary returns his stroke, he must again endeavour to
                    do this, until he succeeds or fails. If he succeed, he scores the stroke; if
                    not, it is scored to his adversary. If two chases have been made at any stage of
                    the score, even at the beginning of a game, then the players must change sides
                    and play for the chases, as above described. A player who succeeds in sending
                    the ball into the grille, the dedans, or the last division of the gallery—called
                    the “λvinning gallery ”—on the hazard side, scores at all times a stroke. The
                    minutiae of the game and the mode of scoring cannot be more succinctly described
                    than in the annexed laws.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Reprinted from the present writer’s <hi rend="italic">Annals of Tennis,</hi>
                    1878, by the kind consent of the publisher Mr H. Cox.</p></note><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Laws.</hi><hi rend="italic">Single-Handed Game.</hi></p>
                <p>1. The balls shall be not less than 2∣ in. and not more than 2j in. in diameter,
                    and shall be not less than 2⅜ oz. and not more than 2∣ oz. in weight.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note.—</hi> There is no restriction as to the shape or size of
                    the rackets.</p>
                <p>2. (a) The choice of sides at the beginning of the first set is determined by a
                    spin.</p>
                <p>(δ) In subsequent sets of a series, the players shall begin each set on the side
                    on which they finished the set before it.</p>
                <p>3. The ball served must be struck with the racket, and may be delivered from any
                    part of the service side.</p>
                <p>4. The ball served must touch the service penthouse before touching any other
                    part of the court, except the rest of the side penthouse and the service wall;
                    and it must drop in the service court or on one of the lines which bound it.</p>
                <p>5. The service is good,</p>
                <p>(a) if the ball served touch in its descent any part of the service penthouse so
                    as to rise again from it, or <hi rend="italic">(b)</hi> if the ball served
                    strike the service wall and afterwards touch iu its descent any part of the
                    sendee penthouse, even though it do not rise again from it, or</p>
                <p>(c) if the ball served drop in the winning gallery.</p>
                <p>6. A fault may not be returned.</p>
                <p>7. A pass may not be returned; but a ball served, which has not gone across the
                    pass line on the penthouse, may be volleyed, although if untouched it might have
                    dropped in the pass court. If a pass touch the striker-out, or if a service
                    before it has dropped touch him when standing λvith both feet in the pass court,
                    and not having attempted to strike the ball, it is still counted a pass.</p>
                <p>8. A pass annuls a previous fault.</p>
                <p>9. If the striker-out declare himself not ready for a service, and have made no
                    attempt to return it, that service is counted for nothing, though it be a fault.
                    It annuls a previous fault. The striker-out, having been asked if he is ready,
                    and having declared himself ready, may not similarly refuse a second
                    service.</p>
                <p>10. The server continues to serve until two chases be made, or one chase when the
                    score of either player is at forty or advantage (see law 25). The players then
                    change sides, the server becoming striker-out and the striker-out becoming
                    server.</p>
                <p>11. The return is good if the ball in play be struck with the racket so that it
                    pass the net without touching a gallery post or anything fixed or lying in an
                    opening on the side from which it is struck, and without going out of court.</p>
                <p>12. The return is not good,</p>
                <p>(a) if not in accordance with the terms of law 11, or <hi rend="italic">(b)</hi>
                    if the ball be struck more than once, or be not definitely struck, or</p>
                <p>(c) if the ball in play, having passed the net, come back and drop on the side
                    from which it was struck, unless it should have touched a gallery post or
                    anything fixed or lying in an opening on that side of the court which is
                    opposite to the striker.</p>
                <p>13. A ball which is no longer in play may not be returned.</p>
                <p>14. The server wins a stroke (except as provided in law 9),</p>
                <p>(a) if a good service enter the winning gallery or the grille, or <hi
                    rend="italic">(b)</hi> if the striker-out fail to return a good service (except
                    when it makes a chase; see laws 17-19), or</p>
                <p>(c) if the striker-out fail to return the ball in play (except when it makes a
                    chase; see laws 17-19), or <hi rend="italic">(cl)</hi> if he himself return the
                    ball in play so that it enter the winning gallery or grille, or fall on or
                    beyond the service line, or</p>
                <p>(e) if he serve or return the ball in play so that it drop or fall upon a ball or
                    other object which is on or beyond the service line, or</p>
                <p>(∕) if he win a chase (see law 20), or</p>
                <p>(&lt;0 if the striker-out lose a stroke (see law 16).</p>
                <p>15. The striker-out wins a stroke (except as provided in law 9), (a) if the
                    server serve two consecutive faults (except as provided in law 31 (5)), or</p>
                <p>(&amp;) if the server fail to return the ball in play (except when it makes a
                    chase; see laws 17-19), or</p>
                <p>(c) if he himself return the ball in play so that it enter the dedans, or</p>
                <p>(d) if he win a chase, or</p>
                <p>(e) if the server lose a stroke (see law 16).</p>
                <p>16. Either player loses a stroke,</p>
                <p>(a) if he lose a chase (see law 21), <hi rend="italic">(b)</hi> if the ball in
                    play (except as provided in law 7) touch him or anything which he wears or
                    carries, except his racket in the act of returning the ball, or</p>
                <p>(c) if he touch or strike the ball in play with his racket more than once, or do
                    not definitely strike it.</p>
                <p>17. When a ball in play on either side of the net, not being that on which the
                    striker is standing,</p>
                <p>(a) falls on any part of the floor, except on or beyond the service line, or</p>
                <p>(5) enters any gallery, except the winning gallery, or</p>
                <p>(c) touches a gallery post, it is marked a chase</p>
                <p>(a) at that line on the floor on which it fell, or <hi rend="italic">[β)</hi>
                    better or worse than that line on the floor which is nearest to the point at
                    which it fell, or</p>
                <p>(γ) at that gallery the post of which it touched, except as provided in laws 18
                    and 19.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note (a).—A.</hi> ball in play which touches the net post and
                    drops on the side opposite to the striker is marked a chase at the line on the
                    side on which it drops.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note</hi> (b).—A ball in play which enters a gallery is marked
                    a chase at that gallery which it enters, notwithstanding that it may have
                    touched an adjacent gallery post without touching the floor in the interim.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note</hi> (c).—The gallery lines on the floor correspond And
                    are equivalent to the galleries of which they bear the names.</p>
                <p>18. When a ball in play</p>
                <p>(a) drops or falls in the net, on the side opposite to the striker, or <hi
                    rend="italic">(b)</hi> drops on the floor, on the side opposite to the striker,
                    and, bounding over the net, falls on that side of it from which it was struck,
                    whether it touch the net in its bound or not, it is marked a chase at the line
                    on the side opposite to the striker.</p>
                <p>19. When a ball in play drops or falls upon a ball or other object which is on
                    the floor (except when it is on or beyond the service line; see law 14 (e)), it
                    is marked a chase at the point at which that ball or other object was when the
                    ball iu play dropped or fell upon it.</p>
                <p>20. Either player wins a chase,</p>
                <p>(a) if he serve or return the ball so that it enter a winning opening, or <hi
                    rend="italic">(b)</hi> if he serve or return the ball so that it fall better
                    than the chase for which he played, or enter a gallery or touch a gallery post
                    better than the gallery or the gallery line at which the chase was for which he
                    played, or</p>
                <p>(c) if he serve or return the ball so that it drop or fall upon a ball or other
                    object which is at a point on the floor better than that at which, or at the
                    gallery corresponding to which, the chase was for which he played, or</p>
                <p>(d) if his antagonist fail to return the ball in play, except when it falls worse
                    than the chase in question.</p>
                <p>21. Either player loses a chase,</p>
                <p>(a) if he fail to return the ball in play, except when it falls worse than the
                    chase in question, or</p>
                <p>(5) if he return the ball in play so that it fall worse than the chase, or enter
                    a gallery or touch a gallery post worse than the gallery or the gallery line at
                    which the chase was for which he played, or</p>
                <p>(c) if he return the ball in play so that it drop or fall upon a ball or other
                    object which is at a point on the floor worse than that at λvhich the chase was
                    for which he played.</p>
                <p>22. When a ball in play</p>
                <p>(a) falls at a point on the floor neither better nor worse than that at which, or
                    at the gallery corresponding to which, the chase was for which the striker
                    played, or</p>
                <p>(δ) enters that gallery or the gallery corresponding to that gallery line, or
                    touches the post of that gallery, or falls on the gallery line corresponding to
                    that gallery, at which the chase was for which the striker played, or</p>
                <p>(c) drops or falls upon a ball or other object which is at a point on the floor
                    neither better nor worse than that at which, oi’ at the gallery corresponding to
                    which, the chase was for which the striker played, it is marked chase-off: it is
                    not scored as a stroke won by either player; the chase is annulled, and the
                    striker has not to play for it again.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n194/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0194-0181"/>
                <p>23. As soon as two chases are marked, or one chase when the score of either
                    player is at forty or advantage (see law 25), the players change sides. The
                    player who made the first chase now defends it, while the other plays to win it;
                    and so with the second chase, except when only one has been marked.</p>
                <p>24. If by an error three chases have been marked, or two chases when the score of
                    either player is at forty or advantage (see law 25), the last chase in each case
                    is annulled.</p>
                <p>25. On either player winning his first stroke, the score is called fifteen for
                    that player; on either player winning his second stroke, the score is called
                    thirty for that player; on either player winning his third stroke, the score is
                    called forty for that player; and the fourth stroke won by either player is
                    scored game for that player, except as below.</p>
                <p>If both players have won three strokes, the score is called deuce, and the next
                    stroke won by either player is scored advantage for that player. If the same
                    player win the following stroke, he wins the game; if he lose the following
                    stroke, the score is again called deuce; and so on, until either player win the
                    two strokes immediately following the score of deuce, when the game is scored
                    for that player.</p>
                <p>26. The player who first wins six games wins a set, except as below.</p>
                <p>If both players win five games, the score is called games all, and the next game
                    won by either player is scored advantage game for that player. If the same
                    player win the following game, he wins the set; if he lose the following game,
                    the score is again called games all; and so on, until either player win the two
                    games immediately following the score of games all, when he wins the set.</p>
                <p>JVo⅛.—Players often agree not to play advantage sets, but to decide the set by
                    one game after arriving at the score of games all.</p>
                <p>27. Every chase is marked, and every stroke scored, by the marker, who is
                    entitled to consult the dedans when he is in doubt. A player who is dissatisfied
                    with the marker’s decision is entitled to appeal to the dedans. A majority of
                    the dedans confirms or reverses the marker’s decision. An appeal must be made
                    before a recommencement of play.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note.—</hi> The dedans should not give a decision unasked on a
                    question of marking a chase or stroke, but may, and should, correct inaccurate
                    scoring of chases, strokes, games, or sets.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Three-Handed and Four-Handed Games, sometimes called Double
                    Games.</hi></p>
                <p>28. The partners serve and strike-out in alternate games, unless it shall have
                    been previously agreed to the contrary.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note.—</hi> It is usually, but not always, agreed that the
                    striker-out may leave to his partner such services as pass him.</p>
                <p>The former laws apply to these as well as to single games, the advantages and
                    disadvantages attaching to a single player under the former laws here attaching
                    to a pair of players.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Odds.</hi></p>
                <p>29. (a) A bisque or a half-bisque may not be taken after the service has been
                    delivered.</p>
                <p>(δ) The server may not take a bisque after a fault; but the striker-out may do
                    so.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note.—</hi> A bisque is a stroke which may be claimed by the
                    recipient of odds at any time during a set, subject to the provisions of laws 29
                    and 30.</p>
                <p>30. A player who wishes to take a bisque or a half-bisque, there being a chase or
                    two chases marked, may take it either before or after changing sides; but he may
                    not, after changing sides, go back to take it.</p>
                <p>31. (a) When the odds of round services are given, the ball served by the giver
                    of the odds must touch the grille penthouse after touching the service penthouse
                    and before dropping in the service court or on one of the lines which bound
                    it.</p>
                <p>(δ) Neither faults nor failure in complying with the above</p>
                <p>. condition are counted against the giver of the odds; but the recipient of the
                    odds may decline to return such services as do not touch both the penthouses;
                    if, however, he attempt and fail to return any such service, it is counted
                    against him.</p>
                <p>32. Half-court: the players having agreed into which half-court on each side of
                    the net the giver of the odds shall play, the latter loses a stroke if the ball
                    returned by him drop in either of the other half-courts.</p>
                <p>But a ball returned by the giver of the odds which</p>
                <p>(a) drops on the half-court line, or <hi rend="italic">{b)</hi> drops in his
                    half-court and touches the dedans post before falling, or</p>
                <p>(c) drops in his half-court and falls in the dedans, even though on the other
                    side of the dedans post, or</p>
                <p>(&lt;Z) touches the dedans post before dropping, is counted for the giver of the
                    odds.</p>
                <p>And a return boasted against any wall by the giver of the odds which</p>
                <p>(e) drops in his half-court, or <hi rend="italic">(f)</hi> drops on the
                    half-court line, or <hi rend="italic">(g)</hi> touches the dedans post before
                    dropping, or</p>
                <p>(Λ) touches any penthouse, battery, or wall before dropping in his half-court,
                    dropping on the half-court line, or touching the dedans post, is also counted
                    for the giver of the odds.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Note.—</hi> It is, of course, evident that the giver of these
                    odds may make a chase, or win a chase or a stroke, with a ball which drops in
                    his half-court, or on the half-court line, but faUs in the other half-court.</p>
                <p>33. When the odds of “touch no walls” or “touch no side walls” are given, a ball
                    returned by the giver of the odds which on falling makes a nick is counted for
                    the striker.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Directions to the Marker.</hi></p>
                <p>It is the duty of the marker to call the faults, and the passes; to call the
                    strokes, when won, or when he is asked to do so; to call the games and sets at
                    the end of each, or when asked to do so; to mark the chases, when made; to call
                    the chases when there are two in the order in which they were made, or the chase
                    when there is one with the score at forty or advantage; and then to direct the
                    players to change sides; to call the chase or chases again, in order as above,
                    when the players have changed sides, and each chase as a player has to play for
                    it; not to call <hi rend="italic">play</hi> or <hi rend="italic">not play</hi>
                    in doubtful cases before the conclusion of the rest, unless asked to do so; to
                    decide all doubtful and disputed strokes, subject to an appeal to the dedans; to
                    warn the players of any balls lying on the floor in their way, or to their
                    dauger or disadvantage, and to remove all such balls; to collect the balls into
                    the ball-basket; and to keep the ball-troughs constantly replenished in the
                    dedans and last gallery, and the latter especially in three-handed and
                    four-handed games. (J. MA*. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
