<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0699-0674-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TYLER, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 674</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:863821">Clay</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1151043">Time</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166263">Vices</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166236">Vice</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1078723">Progress</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:945704">Governors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m6290g">Vice</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j960b1w">Clay</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w744">Progress</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204598">Pennsylvania</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n699/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TYLER, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1790-1862),
                    tenth president of the United States, was accustomed with pride, but with the
                    support of conjecture rather than evidence, to claim relationship with Wat Tyler
                    of the reign of Richard II. The earliest of his American ancestors was Henry
                    Tyler, a reputed native of Shropshire, England, who in 1652 settled at Middle
                    Plantation, Va., on the outskirts of what is now the city of Williamsburg. John
                    Tyler was the son of Judge John Tyler, some time governor of Virginia, and was
                    born at Greenway in that State, 29th March 1790. In 1802 he entered the grammar
                    school of William and Mary, where, though fond of fun and frolic and cultivating
                    an inherited taste for the violin, he made good progress in his studies. After
                    graduating in 1806 he entered on the study of law, and in 1809 was called to the
                    bar, where his progress from the first was rapid. He became a member of the
                    State legislature in December 1811. In 1813 he raised a company in defence of
                    Richmond, in command of which he subsequently served with the fifty-second
                    regiment at Williamsburg and Providence Forge. In December 1816 he was elected
                    to the house of representatives at Washington, where he displayed much readiness
                    and skill in debate as an uncompromising advocate of popular rights. In 1825 he
                    was elected governor of Virginia by a large majority, and the following year was
                    re-elected unanimously. In 1827 he was chosen a senator. He opposed Clay on the
                    tariff question in 1832, delivering a speech against the protective duties which
                    lasted three days; but he voted for Clay’s Compromise Bill of 1833. He was the
                    only senator who voted against the Force Bill on 20th February of this year, a
                    singularity of conduct which somewhat damaged his reputation in Virginia.
                    Although opposed to the establishment of the United States Bank, he supported
                    the resolutions in 1835 censuring President Jackson for the removal of the
                    deposits, on the ground that the procedure was unconstitutional. In consequence
                    of a vote of the Virginia legislature instructing him to vote for the
                    expurgation of these resolutions from the senate journal he resigned, 21st
                    February 1836. His action led the Whigs to bring him forward as a candidate for
                    the vice-presidency, but he only received forty-seven votes. For some time after
                    this he ceased to take an active part in politics; removing in the end of the
                    year from Gloucester to Williamsburg, where he had better opportunities for
                    legal practice, he devoted his chief attention to his professional duties. At
                    the Whig convention which met at Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, 4th December 1839, he
                    was nominated again for the vice-presidency on the Harrison ticket, and elected
                    in November 1840. On the death of Harrison, soon after his inauguration in 1841,
                    Tyler succeeded him. His elevation<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n700/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0700-0675"/> to the presidency was thus accidental in a double
                    sense, for he had been nominated for the vice-presidency to reconcile the
                    extreme faction. His policy in office (see <hi rend="smallcaps">United
                    States)</hi> was opposed to the party who nominated him and was on Democratic
                    lines. In 1845 he was succeeded by Polk, and he spent the remainder of his life
                    in retirement from active duties. He was nominated in 1861 for the lower house
                    of the permanent congress, but died at Richmond on the 18th of the following
                    January.</p>
                <p>See L. G. Tyler, <hi rend="italic">Life and Times of the Tylers,</hi> 2 vols.,
                    1884.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
