<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0055-0046-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TANJORE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 46</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1097334">Rice</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1023771">Missions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:890004">Deltas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:866134">Cocoa</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cg69">Mahrattas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qb5b">Rice</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2md37">Missions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46q1sk44">Deltas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n55/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TANJORE</label>, a district of British India, in the Madras
                    presidency, lying between 9° 50' and 11° 25' N. lat. and between 78° 55' and 79°
                    55' E. long., with an area of 3654 square miles. It forms a portion of the
                    Southern Carnatic, and is bounded on the N. by the river Coleroon, which
                    separates it from Trichinopoly and South Arcot districts, on the E. and S.E. by
                    the Bay of Bengal, on the S.W. by Madura district, and on the W. by Madura and
                    Trichinopoly and Pudukotta state. Tanjore <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n56/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0056-0047"/> is known as the garden of Southern India. It is
                    well watered by an elaborate system of dams, cuts, and canals in connexion with
                    the rivers Cauvery and Coleroon, and the soil is exceedingly productive. The
                    delta of the Cauvery occupies the flat northern part, which is highly cultivated
                    with rice, dotted over with groves of cocoa-nut trees, and densely populated.
                    Tanjore is a land of temples, many of them being of very early date. The great
                    temple of Tanjore city is said to be the finest in India; it is of the 11th
                    century, and remains in excellent preservation to the present day. The district
                    has a coast-line of 140 miles, but communication with shipping is unsafe, owing
                    to a heavy surf which breaks incessantly on the shore. The rainfall, as
                    elsewhere on the Coromandel coast, varies considerably from year to year; the
                    mean annual fall, as observed at ten stations for four years, was 47 T 4 inches.
                    Tanjore is amply provided with means of communication. It is traversed by two
                    branches of the South Indian Railway.</p>
                <p>The census of 1881 returned the population of the district at 2,130,383 (males
                    1,026,528, females 1,103,855), of whom 1,939,421 were Hindus, 112,058
                    Mohammedans, and 78,258 Christians. Tanjore is the first district in which
                    Protestant missions began, and now it is second only to Tinnevölly in the number
                    of its Christian missions. These establishments were taken over in 1826 by the
                    Society for the Propagation of the Gospel, which subsequently founded missions
                    in several parts of the district. The total number of native Protestants
                    belonging to the various societies in 1881 was 8255. Roman Catholic missions in
                    Tanjore date from the first half of the 17th century, and the number of native
                    Roman Catholics in 1881 was 67,745. Five towns have populations exceeding
                    10,000, viz., Tanjore (see below), Negapatam 53,855, Combaconum 50,098,
                    Mayavaram 23,044, and Muunargudi 19,409.</p>
                <p>Of the total area of the district, reckoned at 2,392,117 acres, 1,468,500 were
                    returned in 1884-85 as cultivated, and 149,228 as available for cultivation,
                    while forests covered 21,422 acres. Rice is the staple crop, and is raised
                    almost entirely by artificial irrigation; green crops are common; plantain and
                    betel-vine gardens abound in the delta, where sugar-cane and tobacco are also
                    cultivated. The chief manufactures are metal wares, silk cloths, carpets, and
                    pith-work. Imports consist chiefly of cotton piece goods, twist and yarn,
                    metals, timber, and betel nuts. Rice is by far the most important article of
                    export alike by sea and land. The gross revenue in 1884-85 was £549,982, the
                    land yielding £389,755.</p>
                <p>The modern history of Tanjore commences with its occupation by the Mahrattas in
                    1678 under Venkaji, the brother of Sivajτ the Great. The British first came into
                    contact with Tanjore by their expedition in 1749 with a view to the restoration
                    of a deposed raja. In this they failed, and a subsequent expedition was bought
                    off. The Mahrattas practically held Tanjore until 1799. In October of that year
                    it was ceded to the East India Company in absolute sovereignty by Raja
                    Sharabhoji, pupil of the missionary Schwartz, the company engaging to pay the
                    raja of Tanjore one-fifth of the net revenue of the territory which was
                    transferred to them, with a further sum of £35,000. Raja Sharabhoji retained
                    only the capital and a small tract of country around. He died in 1833, and was
                    succeeded by his son Sivaji, on whose death in 1855 without an heir the house
                    became extinct, the rights and privileges appertaining to it ceased, and Tanjore
                    became British territory.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
