<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0080-0071-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TARTINI, Giuseppe (9th edition, volume 23, page
                    71)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1125798">Sonata</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1125801">Sonatas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891974">Devil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167350">Violin</term>
                    <term ref="fast:2002543">Violin</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mn33">Violin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk98">Devil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn21">Sonata</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n80/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TARTINI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Giuseppe</hi></label>
                    (1692-1770), violinist, composer, and musical theorist, was born at Pirano,
                    April 12, 1692, and in early life studied, with equal want of success, for the
                    church, the law courts, and the profession of arms. His life as a young man was
                    wild and irregular, and his temper extremely violent and impulsive. His
                    unfitness for an ecclesiastical career was manifest: and, after failing in
                    jurisprudence, he crowned his improprieties by clandestinely marrying the niece
                    of Cardinal Cornaro, archbishop of Padua. Though the family of Tartini had been
                    legally ennobled, the cardinal resented the marriage as a disgraceful
                    mésalliance, and denounced it so violently that the unhappy bridegroom, thinking
                    his life in danger, fled for safety to a monastery at Assisi, where, calmed by
                    the soothing influence of the religious life, his character underwent a complete
                    change. Docile and obedient, as he had before been passionate and headstrong, he
                    studied the theory of music under Padre Boemo, the organist of the monastery,
                    and, without any assistance whatever, taught himself to play the violin in so
                    masterly a style that his performances in the church became the wonder of the
                    neighbourhood. For more than two years his identity remained undiscovered, but
                    one day the wind blew aside a curtain behind which he was playing, and one of
                    his hearers recognized him and betrayed his retreat to the cardinal, who,
                    hearing of his changed character, readmitted him to favour and restored him to
                    his wife.</p>
                <p>Tartini next removed to Venice, where the fine violinplaying of Veracini excited
                    his admiration and prompted him to repair, by the aid of good instruction, the
                    shortcomings of his own self-taught method. After this he studied for some time
                    at Ancona; and here, about 1714, he made the curious acoustical discovery on
                    which his fame as a theorist chiefly rests. He observed that, when two notes are
                    sounded together on the violin with sufficient intensity, a third sound,
                    distinct from both, is simultaneously produced. For the production of this
                    “third sound,” as he called it, Tartini failed to account on strict mathematical
                    principles. When the two primary notes form an impure consonance, the “third
                    sound” of Tartini (now known as a difference tone of the first order) is
                    accompanied by beats due to the presence of different tones of higher orders,
                    the existence of which, unknown of course to Tartini, has been established by
                    Helmholtz. Tartini made his observations the basis of a theoretical system which
                    he set forth in his <hi rend="italic">Trattato di Musica, secondo la vera
                        scienzia dell</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Armonia</hi> (Padua, 1754) and <hi
                        rend="italic">Dei Principij dell</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Armonia
                        Musicale</hi> (Padua, 1767). In 1721 he returned to Padua, where he was
                    appointed solo violinist at the church of San Antonio. From 1723 to 1726 he
                    acted as conductor of Count Kinsky’s private band, but afterwards returned to
                    his old post at Padua, where he died on February 16, 1770.</p>
                <p>Tartini’s compositions are very numerous, and faithfully illustrate his
                    passionate and masterly style of execution, which surpassed in brilliancy and
                    refined taste that of all his contemporaries. He frequently headed his pieces
                    with an explanatory poetical motto, such as “Ombra cara,” or “Volgete il riso in
                    pianto o mie pupille.” Concerning that known as <hi rend="italic">ll Τrillο del
                        Diαvοlο,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">The Devil’s Sonata,</hi> he told a
                    curious story to Lalande, in 1766. He dreamed that the devil had become his
                    slave, and that he one day asked him if he could play the violin. The devil
                    replied that he believed he could pick out a tune, and thereupon he played a
                    sonata so exquisite that Tartini thought he had never heard any music to equal
                    it. On awaking, he tried to note down the composition, but succeeded very
                    imperfectly, though the resulting <hi rend="italic">Devil’s Sonata</hi> is one
                    of his best and most celebrated productions.</p>
                <p>Besides the theoretical works we have mentioned, Tartini wrote a <hi
                        rend="italic">Trattato delle Appogiature,</hi> posthumously printed in
                    French, and an unpublished work, <hi rend="italic">Delle Ragioni e delle
                        Broporzioni,</hi> the MS. of which has been lost.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
