<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0246-0229-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">THEBES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 229</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1152439">Tombs</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:995592">Legends</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:933357">Fountains</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1004739">Macedonians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x31n">Tombs</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j62t">Legends</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vq1n">Fountains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n246/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THEBES</label> (anciently Θi)∕3αt, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thebae,</hi> or in poetry sometimes Θry∕3a, in modern Greek <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phiva,</hi> or, according to the corrected pronunciation, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Thivae),</hi> one of the most interesting towns in Greece, is situated on low
                    hilly ground of gentle slope a little north of the range of Cithaeron, which
                    divides Boeotia from Attica, and on the edge of the Boeotian plain, about 44
                    miles from Athens, whence it is now reached by two carriage-roads. It has about
                    3500 inhabitants, and is the seat of a bishop. The present town occupies the
                    site of the ancient citadel, the Cadmea; two fragments of ancient wall are
                    visible on the north, and another, belonging either to the citadel or the outer
                    wall, on the south. Two streams, rising a little south of the town, and
                    separated by an average distance of about half a mile, flow on the two sides,
                    and are lost in the plain. These are the ancient Ismenus on the east and Dirce
                    (Δipκ77) on the west, which gave to the town its name δi7roτα∕Λos. The Dirce,
                    now Platziétissa, has several springs. From the west side of the Cadmea another
                    copious fountain (Paraporti) falls to the Dirce. In a suburb to the east is
                    another (Fountain of St Theodore), and north-west are two more. The Cadmea
                    itself is supplied with water brought from an unknown source to the south by
                    works supposed of prehistoric antiquity. It now enters the town by an aqueduct
                    of twenty arches of Frankish construction. The “waters” of Thebes are celebrated
                    both by Pindar and by the Athenian poets, and the site is still, as described by
                    Dicaearchus (3d century B.C.), “all springs,” <hi rend="italic">κάθνδρος
                    πάσα.</hi> One, from which a pasha of Negroponte (Euboea) is said to have
                    supplied his table, is still called “the spring of the cadi.” Some of the marble
                    basins, seats, &amp;c., remain, and, with the fragments of w all above
                    mentioned, are the only relics of the classic time. The most curious of later
                    buildings is the church of St Luke, south-east of the Cadmea, believed to
                    contain the tomb of the evangelist. From the abundance of water the place is
                    favourable to gardens, and the neighbouring plain is extremely fertile. But the
                    population is scanty, and the town at present of no importance.</p>
                <p>In prehistoric times the Cadmea, with the enlarged city of Thebes into which it
                    developed, was a power of the first rank, as is shown by its unrivalled legends.
                    More particularly the mythical wars with Argos (see below) point to a time when
                    the “Hellenes” of North Greece were still contending unequally against the
                    “Achaeans” of the Peloponnesus. In the legend as given by Aeschylus these names
                    are accurately preserved. At the beginning of continuous history (6th century
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> Thebes had long been possessed by immigrants
                    from Thessaly, who knew the previous inhabitants as Cadmeans (Καδ/χείοι).</p>
                <p>The history of the town to the end of the 4th century is part of the general
                    history of the nation (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Greece).</hi> It had an
                    aristocratic constitution, and claimed a contested sovereignty over the other
                    towns of Boeotia. Down to 371 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> this status was not
                    essentially changed. The battle of Coronea (394) showed the increasing military
                    strength of the Thebans, and in 371 the genius of Epaminondas raised them by the
                    victory of Leuctra for a brief period to the leading position in Hellas. Philip
                    of Macedon spent part of his youth as a hostage at Thebes, and probably learnt
                    there important lessons in war. By him and his successor the state was
                    destroyed. In 338 the Thebans shared with the Athenians the defeat of Chaeronea,
                    and received a Macedonian garrison; the lion-monument erected by them on the
                    field of battle, and still existing there, though in fragments, is a more
                    impressive memorial of their greatness than anything now visible at the town
                    itself. In 335, after the death of Philip, they revolted, and were punished by
                    Alexander with a fearful vengeance. It is said that 6000 Thebans were slain at
                    the capture and 30,000 taken prisoners. The population was dispersed, and the
                    town entirely razed (except, according to tradition, the house of the poet
                    Pindar); and, though it was soon restored by the Macedonian Cassander (315), it
                    never again played a leading part in history. In 86 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.,</hi> having sided against the Romans in the Mithradatic war, it was
                    plundered by Sulla, and fell into such decay that Strabo describes it as little
                    better than a village. In the 2d century the traveller Pausanias, who gives a
                    full account of it (ix. 5 <hi rend="italic">sq.),</hi> found only the citadel
                    inhabited. In 395 A.D., however, it had some strength, for Alaric, on his way to
                    the capture of Athens, did not think fit to attack it. In the later times of the
                    Eastern empire (10th to 12th century) it again became wealthy and important,
                    being specially celebrated for the manufacture of silk and cloth. In 1143 it was
                    plundered by the Normans of Sicily (who transferred thither the chief artisans
                    of the silk trade), and, after the capture of Constantinople by <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n247/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0247-0230"/> the crusaders (1204), became with Athens a fief
                    of the feudal empire. In 1311 it was again plundered by the Catalan Grand
                    Company, a body of Spanish mercenaries, and appears to have had no return of
                    prosperity.</p>
                <p>Of more lasting effect than the politics of Thebes have been its legends.
                    Boeotia, or rather the Cadmeis (Thucyd., i. 12), was a land of poetry from
                    extremely ancient times, and the stories of Thebes are in Greek literature as
                    important as those of Troy. The legends of the five chief groups will be found
                    under the names indicated in the following division :—(1) the foundation of the
                    Cadmea by Cadmus; (2) the foundation by Amphion,—to this belong originally the
                    “seven-gated” wall, the name of <hi rend="italic">iτrτaπυλos Θi∣βη,</hi> and the
                    legends of Zethus, Antiope, and Dirce; (3) war of the “Seven” (under Adrastus of
                    Argos); war of the Epigoni, or “descendants” of the Seven; the story of Oedipus;
                    (4) legends of Bacchus,—at Thebes as elsewhere this religion was comparatively
                    late, but became characteristic of the town; (5) legends of Heracles (commonly
                    found with those of Bacchus; Thebes was reputed the birthplace of both). From
                    the epic poems, of which little but titles remain, these tales descended to the
                    Attic tragedians; upon them are founded the <hi rend="italic">Seven against
                    Thebes</hi> of Aeschylus, the <hi rend="italic">Oedipus Tyrannus, Oedipus
                    Coloneus,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Antigone</hi> of Sophocles, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Phcenissae, Supplices,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bacchae</hi> of
                    Euripides, &amp;c., with innumerable plays not extant. Apart from direct
                    imitation of these works, the stories themselves, through Statius, Boccaccio,
                    and others, have exercised a great influence on modern literature. In historical
                    times the Thebans were not conspicuous for intellectual accomplishments, but
                    their reputation is sufficiently sustained by Pindar, perhaps the most
                    distinctively Hellenic of all the national poets.</p>
                <p>The most famous monument of ancient Thebes was the outer wall with its seven
                    gates, which even as late as the 6th century <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> was
                    probably the largest of artificial Greek fortresses. The names of the gates
                    vary, but four are constant,—the Proetides, Electrae, Neistae or Neitae, and
                    Homoloides; Pausanias gives the others as Ogygiae, Hypsistae, Crenaeae. There is
                    evidence that the gate Electrae was on the south, and near it was the tomb of
                    the Thebans who fell at the capture by Alexander. The gates shown to Pausanias
                    as Neistae and Proetides led respectively north-west and north-east. Two of the
                    springs have been identified with some probability,—that of St Theodore with the
                    (Edipodea, in which Oedipus is said to have purged himself from the pollution of
                    homicide, and the Paraporti with the dragon-guarded fountain of Ares (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Cadmus).</hi> Dicaearchus, referring to the town of Cassander,
                    gives two measurements for the circuit, equal to about 9 miles and 5⅜ miles, but
                    even the smaller is impossible for the wall, and they probably refer to the
                    territory' proper of the town, or γi} <hi rend="italic">Q-ηβais.</hi> Beyond
                    this the topography is wholly uncertain. From the interest of the site in
                    history and still more in literature, as the scene of so many dramas, the
                    temptation to fix details has been specially strong. Conjectural plans or
                    descriptions, differing widely, are given by Leake, Forchhammer, Ulrichs,
                    Bursian, and others (references below). All are based on the assumption that the
                    description of Pausanias and the allusions of the Attic tragedians may be read
                    together and combined, and that the result will give the plan as it existed in
                    the 5th and 4th centuries <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> But to this two
                    objections must be taken. (1) The account of Pausanias, even when clear in
                    itself, is very' uncertain evidence for anything earlier than the destruction by
                    Alexander. It is said indeed that the restored town occupied the same area, but
                    this is consistent with great disturbance of tradition; and we have further to
                    allow for inaccurate transmission through 450 years of decadence, and finally
                    for the quality of Pausanias’s information, given apparently by casual guides to
                    a traveller extremely uncritical. (2) It may be doubted whether the tragedians
                    had accurate knowledge of Theban topography, and they had certainly no reason
                    for introducing it in their plays. Their plots are laid in a remote past; and it
                    is difficult to suppose them on the one hand so careful as to fit their scenes
                    to the actual Thebes, and on the other hand so careless as to presume that it
                    had suffered no great change between the times of Cadmus or of Oedipus and their
                    own days. Indeed they did not make this mistake. The plays which contain most
                    references to topography are the <hi rend="italic">Seven against Thebes</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Phoenissae.</hi> In the <hi rend="italic">Seven</hi> the
                    name of “Thebes” does not occur at all (the title is a misnomer, probably not
                    given by the author); the town is called by its ancient name “The Cadmea”
                    (Kαδμeiα ιroλ&lt;s), and the whole play assumes that the “city of Cadmus” was
                    much smaller than the Thebes contemporary with Aeschylus can have been. In the
                    <hi rend="italic">Phoenissae</hi> the circuit of the walls is said to be so
                    small that a person within must necessarily know all that had taken place in a
                    general attack (v. 1356). None of the conjectural plans would approximately
                    satisfy this, nor can it have been true for the time of Euripides. After this,
                    it is not surprising to find that the attempt to use the plays as evidence is
                    involved in unanswered difficulties, a few of which are given below.</p>
                <p>In itself, however, and as relating to the ruins of the restored town merely, the
                    description of Pausanias is curious and interesting. The principal buildings
                    were at that time (2d century) the temple of Apollo Ismenius, which must have
                    stood somewhere about the present church of St Luke, the theatre, near the gate
                    Proetides, the Heracleum, with a gymnasium and race-course, and the temples of
                    Artemis Eucleia, of Ammon, and of Fortune (Τύχη). Besides these Pausanias was
                    shown all the gates, all the legendary sites, the house of Pindar (north-west
                    beyond the Dirce), statues, &amp;c., dedicated by him, several statues of
                    immense antiquity, others attributed to the greatest artists, and in fact much
                    more than it is easy to believe.</p>
                <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Apollo Ismenius</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Apollo
                    Spodius.—</hi> Sophocles (ffi ’. <hi rend="italic">T.,</hi> 21) mentions, as one
                    of the Theban sanctuaries, “the oracular ashes of Ismenus,” ’ <hi rend="italic"
                    >lσμ∙ηvoι∣ μavτtia στr0δos.</hi> Pausanias, who calls the river not Ismenus but
                    Ismenius, describes (1) a temple of Ismenius or Apollo Ismenius (ix. lθ, 2), and
                    (2) an altar of Apollo Spodius, made of ashes and used in a peculiar manner as
                    an oracle (ix. 11,7). We should suppose from Sophocles that both observations
                    related to the same sanctuary; and Sophocles clearly identified the two. But in
                    Pausanias they are in different places and have no connexion at all. Either
                    therefore the topography and ritual of the one period differed from those of the
                    other, or, which is equally probable, the poet used Theban names without regard
                    to accuracy.</p>
                <p>2. <hi rend="italic">The Fountain of Ares.—</hi> Euripides, in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Supplices</hi> (v. 650 <hi rend="italic">sq.),</hi> describes an
                    army advancing on Thebes from the south as having its right at the Ismenian
                    hill, its left at the fountain of Ares, and “the chariots below the monument of
                    Amphion.” Pausanias also places the Ismenian hill on the right of the southern
                    gate. But the fountain of Ares he places on the same side, a description quite
                    inconsistent with this and other allusions. Ulrichs, while insisting on the
                    agreement about the hill, merely observes on this that Pausanias is
                    unintelligible. Of a still greater difficulty he says nothing. The tomb of
                    Amphion is placed by Aeschylus north of the town, and there or in that direction
                    was shown to Pausanias. The topographers accordingly 'suppose that the
                    “chariots” of Euripides were in the plain to the north. But there is no
                    suggestion in the passage that any part of the advancing army was separated from
                    the rest, and the observer expressly says that <hi rend="italic">he was at the
                    place where the chariots fought and had a particularly good view of this part of
                    the battle</hi> (v. 684). Now he stood on the gate Electrae, <hi rend="italic"
                    >i.e.,</hi> as far as possible from the tomb of Amphion, as placed by Aeschylus
                    and Pausanias. It is impossible to make a consistent account of this, and it
                    seems plain that Euripides took up the name “tomb of Amphion” at hazard, and
                    ignored or forgot that the real tomb could not be brought into his picture.</p>
                <p>3. <hi rend="italic">The Altar of {Athena) 0nca.—</hi> This was shown to
                    Pausanias (ix. 12, 1), who was told that it marked the place where the lying
                    down of a cow indicated to Cadmus the site destined for his city (eδeι f <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> rταv0α obcη&lt;raι). “It is said,” he continues,
                    “that in tho acropolis there was formerly the house of Cadmus (Κάδμου <hi
                    rend="italic">o∖κia)."</hi> No other indication is given as to the place of the
                    altar, and the natural inference is that it was shown in the Cadmea. But
                    Aeschylus <hi rend="italic">{Septem,</hi> 501) places it outside the walls.
                    Accordingly it is suggested that the oracular sign only indicated the
                    neighbourhood of the destined site, and that the altar shown to Pausanias was
                    near that of Apollo Spodius, which is mentioned last before it, and may have
                    been outside the wall. But this juxtaposition proves nothing about the place of
                    0nca, for Pausanias himself shows that mention of Onca here is suggested by a
                    reference to “oxen” in connexion with the altar of Spodius, which brought to his
                    mind the ‘ ‘ cow” of the other legend.</p>
                <p>4. <hi rend="italic">The Tomb of Amphion and Zethus.—</hi> Apart from the
                    confusion of Euripides already noticed, there is a difficulty about the mention
                    of this monument in Pausanias and Aeschylus. Pausanias, after describing several
                    buildings near the gate Proetides, concluding with some in the market-place,
                    mentions next (without further indication of place) the tomb of Amphion and
                    Zethus, and continues thus,—“the way from Thebes to Chalcis (north-east) is by
                    this gate Proetides, &amp;c.” Aeschylus places the tomb of Amphion outside the
                    wall opposite the north gate <hi rend="italic">{Seρtem,</hi> 527), and the
                    Proetides elsewhere. Ulrichs concludes that Pausanias “evidently” went out by
                    the north gate to view the monument and then returned to the Proetides. Of
                    course this is possible, but it is useless to draw exact inferences from
                    documents which require such an hypothesis. It is equally probable that
                    Pausanias identified the tomb with a monument called the Ampheion, which seems
                    (Ulrichs, p. 17) to have been somewhere near the market-place. Indeed, there is
                    no proof that they were not identical, for the)only evidence that the tomb was
                    outside the wall (and therefore different from the Ampheion) is that of
                    Aeschylus and Euripides, whose imaginary cities were not much larger than the
                    Cadmean hill, and must have excluded the Ampheion itself.</p>
                <p>On the history, see references under <hi rend="smallcaps">Grkkce;</hi> on the
                    topography and legends, Ulrichs, <hi rend="italic">Reisen und Forschungen in
                    Griechenland,</hi> ii. 1 <hi rend="italic">sq.;</hi> Leake, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Travels in Northern Greece,</hi> ii. xiv.; Bursian, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Geographie von Griechenland,</hi> i. 225 <hi rend="italic">sq.;</hi> and the
                    “<hi rend="italic">Seven against Thebes,”</hi> ed. by A. W. Verrail,
                    “Introduction.” (A. W. V.) <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n248/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0248-0231"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
