<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0640-0619-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TUNING FORK</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 619</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:932883">Forks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1064885">Pitch</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:830297">Bending</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1009087">Marching</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:918096">Exhibitionism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44746z94">Pitch</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sj6k">Fractions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xj9j">Steel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n640/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TUNING FORK</label>, a small bar of cast tool steel with
                    tolerably defined edges, bent into a fork with two prongs. A handle of the same
                    metal extending from the bend of the fork serves as a sound-post to transmit the
                    vibrations of the fork to any resonance board or body convenient for reinforcing
                    the sound. The fork is set in vibration by striking one of the prongs against
                    any hard substance, by pressing the prongs together if the fork is a light one,
                    or, if it is large, by drawing a double bass bow across one of the prongs. The
                    larger forks are sometimes made with a worm upon the handle in order that they
                    may be screwed into a resonance box, the dimensions of which should agree with
                    the pitch of the fork. The ordinary use of a tuning fork is to serve as a pitch
                    carrier or standard, for which it is particularly suited owing to the permanence
                    with which it maintains the pitch to which it may be tuned. It is flattened by
                    heat and sharpened by cold about 1 vibration in 20,000 for every degree Fahr.,
                    so that the exact pitch always depends upon the temperature. A tuning fork is
                    tuned by filing the ends of the prongs or between them near the ends to make it
                    sharper, or by filing between them near or at the bend to make it flatter. Less
                    filing is required to flatten than to sharpen. It should be allowed to rest
                    after tuning, on account of the disturbance of the molecular structure by the
                    filing, and after a few days should be compared again with the pitch required,
                    and corrected. The tuning fork is also of value in certain physical
                    investigations, from the constancy of its rate of vibration. In England it is
                    generally tuned to C in the treble clef, because organ-builders start their
                    tuning from that note; in France it is tuned to A in the treble clef, which is
                    the note of the third open string of the violin. The French diapason normal is
                    tuned to A at 15° C. ( = 59° Fahr.) and is fixed at 435 double vibrations in a
                    second. The inventor of the tuning fork was John Shore, royal trumpeter in 1711,
                    sergeant trumpeter at the entry of George I. in 1714, and lutanist to the chapel
                    royal in 1715.</p>
                <p>According to Chladni, whose analysis of the tuning fork has been generally
                    accepted, it has two nodes or points of least vibration at the bend, with a
                    ventral or vibrating loop between, by which its vibrations are transmitted to
                    the handle. That this is not the case has been shown by Mr W. F. Stanley.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic"
                    >Nature,</hi> vol. xxvi. pp. 166, 243,</p></note> The fundamental note appears
                    to be an octave below the note which the ear recognizes as the pitch of the
                    fork. Helmholtz, Tyndall, and others accept the latter as the fundamental, and
                    Helmholtz expressly says that each prong may be regarded as an elastic rod fixed
                    at one end.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi
                    rend="italic">Sensations of Tone</hi>; Eng. transl. by A. J. Ellis, 2d ed.,
                    1885, p. 70.</p></note> The fork is really a bent elastic rod vibrating at both
                    ends, with a node at the bend, through which, and in the same way as with the
                    bridge of any stringed instrument, the vibrations are conducted. As well as the
                    second partial, the third and fourth are in large forks frequently
                    distinguishable, but such partials above the octave are very weak. In addition
                    to the lower harmonic partials it is generally easy to produce with a blow a
                    very high inharmonic tinkle or ringing metallic note, that will continue to
                    sound for some time without blending with the true note of the fork. The precise
                    interval varies, but is usually two octaves and between a flat fifth and a major
                    sixth above the recognized pitch of the fork. With ordinary tuning forks this
                    tinkling note is to be found amongst the highest treble notes of the pianoforte.
                    Theorists give other inharmonic proper tones in due ascending order; they are
                    derived from calculation on the assumption that they proceed as the squares of
                    the odd numbers, but are beyond practical verification owing to their extreme
                    position in the scale of musical sounds and the variation of power in different
                    ears to distinguish them.</p>
                <p>The tuning fork was used by Scheibler (1777-1837) as the easiest means for
                    correctly determining the pitch numbers of vibrations. To make a Scheibler
                    tonometer, take a fork in which the octave can be easily heard and intercalate
                    as many forks as, giving countable beats with each other, will fill up the
                    octave. The addition of the whole number of beats and their fractions in the
                    octave will be the vibrating number, in double vibrations per second, of the
                    lower fork. In order to measure the fractions of vibrations accurately forks
                    should be chosen that are audible for 40, or at least 20 seconds. For instance,
                    60 beats counted in 20 seconds would be 3 a second, and 65 in the same time
                    3∙25. The forks should remain for three months after filing before their
                    differences are finally determined, and the whole examination should be
                    conducted in a known, uniform temperature. Scheibler considered four beats a
                    second between two forks a good number for counting; but Mr A. J. Ellis, who has
                    used Scheibler’s invention as a basis for an exhaustive historical statement of
                    musical pitch<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>“On the
                    History of Musical Pitch,” in <hi rend="italic">Journ. Soc. of Arts,</hi> 5th
                    March and 2d April 1880; see also 7th January 1881.</p></note> and as the novel
                    and exact means for determining the non-harmonic musical scales of various
                    nations, especially Eastern nations,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>“On Musical Scales,” <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> 27th
                    March and 30th October 1885.</p></note> considers three beats a second the best
                    counting number. This would increase the number of intermediate forks.</p>
                <p>Attempts have been made to use tuning forks instead of strings for key-board
                    instruments, the object being to obtain permanence of tuning with the soft,
                    unexciting quality of tone furnished by the fork. The inventions of Clagget,
                    London, 1788, of Riffelsen (the melodikon), Copenhagen, 1803, and of Schuster
                    (the adiaphonon), Vienna, 1819, were of this nature. The latest adaptation of a
                    keyboard to tuning forks has been effected by Mr Machell of Glasgow; it was
                    shown at the Inventions Exhibition, South Kensington, London, 1885.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
