<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0694-0669-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TURQUOISE (9th edition, volume 23, page 669)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q506">Aluminium</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133812">Stone</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133955">Stoning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834915">Blue</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1211700">Mexico</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204820">Arizona</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205660">Nevada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n694/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TURQUOISE</label>, a blue or bluish green mineral, valued,
                    when cut and polished, as an ornamental stone. The finest variety occurs in
                    Persia, whence it originally reached western Europe by way of Turkey, and thus
                    came to be called by the Venetians, who imported it, <hi rend="italic"
                        >turchesa,</hi> and by the French <hi rend="italic">turquoise.</hi> It is
                    chemically a hydrated phosphate of aluminium, associated with a variable
                    proportion of hydrated phosphate of copper, to which it owes much of its colour.
                    The green tints of certain varieties appear to be due to admixture with salts of
                    iron. A fine blue Persian turquoise, analysed by Prof. A. H. Church,
                    yielded—alumina 40∙19, phosphorus pentoxide 32∙86, water 19∙34, cupric oxide
                    5∙27, ferrous oxide 2∙21, and manganous oxide 0∙36. The most valued tint of the
                    turquoise is a delicate blue, inclining slightly to green; in many specimens the
                    green becomes more pronounced with age. Although the turquoise is practically
                    opaque, sections may be ground so thin as to admit of examination by transmitted
                    light. Its microscopic structure was first studied by Prof. Fischer of Freiburg
                    (Baden), afterwards by H. Bücking of Strasburg, and recently by Clarke and
                    Diller.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n695/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0695-0670"/>
                <p>Thin sections are almost colourless. Between crossed Nicols they show either a
                    fibrous texture or a finely-granular aggregate of doubly-refracting particles
                    without definite crystalline outlines. The mineral has never been found
                    crystallized, but occurs as veins, nodules, stalactitic masses, and
                    incrustations. Large pieces are exceedingly rare. The specific gravity of
                    turquoise is about 2∙75, and its hardness below 6; it takes a fair polish and
                    exhibits a feeble lustre. It is usually cut <hi rend="italic">en cabochon</hi>
                    or with a low convex surface, and in the East is frequently engraved with
                    Persian and Arabic inscriptions, generally passages from the Koran,— the incised
                    characters being in many cases gilt. Such objects are worn as amulets. The
                    turquoise has always been associated with curious superstitions, the most common
                    being the notion that it changes colour with variations in the state of its
                    owner’s health, or even in sympathy with his affections.</p>
                <p>Persia is the chief centre of the turquoise trade, where the same mines have been
                    worked for at least eight centuries. The finest stones are found near Nishápúr
                    in Khorasan (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Persia,</hi> vol. xviii. p. 622).
                    Tavernier, writing in the 17th century, states that the best turquoise, reserved
                    for the sole use of the shall, was obtained from the mine which he describes as
                    the <hi rend="italic">Vieille Roche,</hi> while inferior stones were got from
                    the <hi rend="italic">Nouvelle Roche.</hi> These terms still survive, all
                    turquoise of fine colour being said in trade to be from the “old rock,” and that
                    which is pale, or changes tint on exposure, is from the “new rock.” According to
                    a recent report by Consul Benjamin at Teheran the best turquoise is found at Abú
                    Riáh, and all the Khorasan mines are farmed by a few prominent officials, who
                    pay to the shah an annual rent of about £6500. Dr Tietze has lately described
                    specimens of the matrix of the mineral brought to Vienna from Persia by General
                    Schindler. These show that the turquoise occurs, not in clay-slate, as is often
                    stated, but in a porphyritic trachyte or trachytic breccia, and in loose
                    fragments in the neighbouring alluvium. The mineral is also found in Kerman in
                    southern Persia, but the stone is of pale colour, tending to fade, and the mines
                    which yield it are now nearly abandoned. In 1849 Major C. Macdonald found
                    turquoise in Wady Maghara and Wady Sidreh, near <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Sinai</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.</hi>), where, according to Mr H.
                    Bauerman, it lines the open joints of a ferruginous sandstone, and is also
                    embedded in small ochreous nodules in the rock itself. The redder the rock the
                    finer the colour of the associated turquoise. As the colour is liable to fade,
                    the Arabian turquoise has not a good name among jewellers, and the workings were
                    abandoned by Macdonald in 1865. In Wady Maghara there are relics of extensive
                    mining operations, presumably for turquoise, of so early a date that the rock
                    was wrought by flint implements. The early inhabitants of Mexico made much use
                    of this mineral for inlaying obsidian ornaments, and for mosaic work with
                    iron-pyrites. It was probably one of the stones known as <hi rend="italic"
                        >chalchihuitl.</hi> In 1858 Prof. W. P. Blake called attention to the
                    occurrence of turquoise at Cerillos, about 22 miles southwest of Santa Fé, in
                    New Mexico, where mining operations for this mineral were carried on two
                    centuries ago. The turquoise varies in colour from sky-blue to apple-green, and
                    is found as nodules and small veins in a felspathic rock of microgranitic
                    texture, probably of eruptive origin. The mines of Cerillos are no longer
                    worked. A similar green mineral is found at Turquoise Mountain in Cochise county
                    and at Mineral Park, Mohave county, Arizona. It also occurs to a small extent in
                    southern Nevada, where it is found as blue grains disseminated through a
                    sandstone. In Europe, the turquoise is found at Oelsnitz in Saxony and near
                    Jordansmühl in Silesia, occurring at the latter locality in clay-slate. Under
                    the names of <hi rend="italic">callais</hi> and <hi rend="italic">callaina</hi>
                    Pliny described a green mineral which, if not our turquoise, seems to have been
                    very closely related to it. A bright green mineral, wrought into beads, and
                    found with stone hatchets in ancient graves at Men-er Hroeck (Rock of the Fairy)
                    in Brittany, was described in 1864 by Μ. Damour, who, seeking to identify it
                    with Pliny’s <hi rend="italic">callais,</hi> revived this name. Dana afterwards
                    brought the word into harmony with our mineralogical nomenclature by writing it
                    callainite. The mineral in question is a hydrated phosphate of aluminium,
                    apparently identical with Breithaupt’s variscite. By many mineralogists the true
                    torquoise is called calaite (see vol. xvi. p. 405).</p>
                <p>Turquoise is commonly imitated by enamels, but of late some ingenious
                    counterfeits have been made with the same chemical composition as the natural
                    stone. To increase the deception, ]&gt;ieces of ochreous matter are inserted at
                    the back of the artificial turquoise, to imitate the natural matrix. In order to
                    distinguish between the genuine stone and its imitations, Pohl recommends that a
                    splinter should be strongly heated in a platinum capsule, when the true
                    turquoise is reduced to a brownish black powder or a friable mass with a
                    decrepitating sound; the false turquoise does not decrepitate, but either fuses
                    to a glass or is reduced to a frit.</p>
                <p>For recent information on the turquoise, see “Das Vorkommen der Türkise-bei
                    Nischapur in Persien,” by Dr E. Tietze, in <hi rend="italic">Verhandl</hi>. <hi
                        rend="italic">d. k. k. geolog. Reichsuη-stalt,</hi> No. 6,1884, p. 93;
                    “Mikroskopische Untersuchung des Türkis," by H. Bücking, in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Zeitsch. f. Krystallog.,</hi> vol. ii., 1878, p. 163; “Eine einfache und
                    sichere Unterscheidungsweise der echten Türkise von deren Nachahmungen,” in <hi
                        rend="italic">N. Jahrb. f. Mineralogie,</hi> 1878, p. 364; “Turqois from New
                    Mexico,” by F. W. Clarke and J. S. Diller, in <hi rend="italic">Americ. Journ.
                        Science,</hi> Sept. 1886, p. 211; “Revision of Mineral Phosphates, No. iv.,
                    Calaite," by A. H. Church, in <hi rend="italic">Chem. News,</hi> X. p. 290; and
                    note in <hi rend="italic">Journ. Soc. Arts,</hi> xxxii., 1884, p. 1084.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
