<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0010-0001-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TABARÎ and Early Arab Historians</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 1</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:979776">Islam</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:836401">Books</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:927291">Flight</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1079211">Prophets</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b40000538">Islam</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4gx44t5k">Koran</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c355">Flight</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4v698j66">Prophets</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n10/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TABARÎ <hi rend="smallcaps">and Early Arab
                    Historians</hi></label>. Arabian historians differ from all others in the unique
                    form of their compositions. Each event is related in the words of eye-witnesses
                    or contemporaries transmitted to the final narrator through a chain of
                    intermediate reporters <hi rend="italic">(ràwîs),</hi> each of whom passed on
                    the original report to his successor. Often the same account is given in two or
                    more slightly divergent forms, which have come down through different chains of
                    reporters. Often, too, one event or one important detail is told in several
                    -ways on the basis of several contemporary statements transmitted to the final
                    narrator through distinct lines of tradition. The writer therefore exercises no
                    independent criticism except as regards the choice of authorities; for he
                    rejects accounts of which the first author or one of the intermediate links
                    seems to him unworthy of credit, and sometimes he states which of several
                    accounts seems to him the best. Modern judgment does not always confirm this
                    choice; some authorities much esteemed by Moslems are by European scholars
                    deemed untrustworthy, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa.</hi> Fortunately the
                    various historians did not always give preference to the same account of a
                    transaction, and so one supplies what another omits.</p>
                <p>A second type of Arabian historiography is that in which an author combines the
                    different traditions about one occurrence into one continuous narrative, but
                    prefixes a statement as to the lines of authorities used and states which of
                    them he mainly follows. In this case the writer <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n11/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0011-0002"/> recurs to the first method, already described,
                    only when the different traditions are greatly at variance with one another. In
                    yet a third type of history the old method is entirely forsaken and we have a
                    continuous narrative only occasionally interrupted by citation of the authority
                    for some particular point. But the principle still is that what has been well
                    said once need not be told again in other words. The writer therefore keeps as
                    close as he can to the letter of his sources, so that quite a late writer often
                    reproduces the very words of the first narrator.</p>
                <p>From very early times the Arabs had great delight in verses and tales, and the
                    development of their language was certainly much influenced by this fact. In
                    ancient times story-tellers and singers found their subjects in the doughty
                    deeds of the tribe on its forays, in the merits of horse or camel, in hunting
                    adventures and love complaints, and sometimes in contests with foreign powers
                    and in the impression produced by the wealth and might of the sovereigns of
                    Persia and Constantinople. The appearance of the Prophet with the great changes
                    that ensued, the conquests that made the Arabs—till then a despised race—lords
                    of half the civilized world, supplied a vast store of new matter for relations
                    which men were never weary of hearing and recounting. They wished to know
                    everything about the apostle of God, whose influence on his own time was so
                    enormous, who had accomplished all that seemed impossible and had inspired the
                    Arabs with a courage and confidence that made them stronger than the legions of
                    Byzantium and Ctesiphon. Every one who had known or seen him was questioned and
                    was eager to answer. Moreover, the word of God in the Koran left many practical
                    points undecided, and therefore it was of the highest importance to know exactly
                    how the Prophet had spoken and acted in various circumstances. Where could this
                    be better learned than at Medina, where he had lived so long and where the
                    majority of his companions continued to live? So at Medina a school was
                    gradually formed, where the chief part of the traditions about Mohammed and his
                    first successors took a form more or less fixed. Soon divers fathers of Islam
                    began to assist memory by making notes, and their disciples sought to take
                    written jottings of what they had heard from them, which they could carry with
                    them when they returned to their homes. Thus by the close of the 1st century
                    many <hi rend="italic">dictata vfeτQ</hi> already in circulation. For example,
                    Hasan of Basra (d. 110 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.;</hi> 728 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.d.)</hi> had a great mass of such notes, and he was accused of sometimes
                    passing off as oral tradition things he had really drawn from books; for oral
                    tradition was still the one recognized authority, and it is related of more than
                    one old scholar, and even of Hasan of Basra himself, that he directed his books
                    to be burned at his death. The books were mere helps, and what they knew these
                    scholars had handed on by word of mouth. Long after this date, when all scholars
                    drew mainly from books, the old forms were still kept up. Tabari, for example,
                    when he cites a book expresses himself as if he had heard what he quotes from
                    the master with .whom he read the passage or from whose copy he transcribed it.
                    He even expresses himself in this wise: “Omar b. Shabba has related to me in his
                    book on the history of Basra.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Historians before Tabari</hi></p>
                <p>Naturally, then, no independent book of the 1st century from the Flight has come
                    down to us. But in the 2d century real books began to be composed. The materials
                    were supplied in the first place by oral tradition, in the second by the <hi
                    rend="italic">dictata</hi> of older scholars, and finally by various kinds of
                    documents, such as treaties, letters, collections of poetry, and genealogical
                    lists. Genealogical studies had become necessary through Omar’s system of
                    assigning state pensions to certain classes of persons according to their
                    kinship with the Prophet, or their deserts during his lifetime. This subject
                    received much attention even in the 1st century, but books about it were first
                    written in the 2d, the most famous being those of Ibn al-Kalbi (d. 146 A.H.), of
                    his son Hishâm<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Of Hishâm
                    b. al-Kalbi’s book there are copies in the British Museum and in the
                    Escorial.</p></note> (d. 204), and of Al-Sharki ibn al-Kotâmi. Genealogy, which
                    often called for elucidations, led on to history. Belâdhori’s excellent <hi
                    rend="italic">Λnsdb al-Ashraf</hi> (Genealogies of the Nobles) is a history of
                    the Arabs on a genealogical plan.</p>
                <p>The oldest extant history is the biography of the Prophet by Ibn Ishâk (d.
                    150).<note anchored="false" cert="medium" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Ibn
                    Ishâk’s original work seems to be still extant in the Kopriilii library at
                    Constantinople; the edition of it by Ibn Hishâm has been edited by Wiistenfeld
                    (Gottingen, 1858-60) and translated into German by Weil (Stuttgart,
                    1864).</p></note> This work is generally trustworthy. Mohammed’s life before he
                    appeared as a prophet and the story of his ancestors are indeed mixed with many
                    fables illustrated by spurious verses. But in Ibn Ishâk’s day these fables were
                    generally accepted as history—for many of them had been first related by
                    contemporaries of Mohammed— and no one certainly thought it blameworthy to put
                    pious verses in the mouth of the Prophet’s forefathers, though, according to the
                    <hi rend="italic">Fihrist</hi> (p. 92), Ibn Ishâk was duυed by others with
                    regard to the poems he quotes.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of the Prophet by Ibn Okba (d. 141), based on the
                    statements of two very trustworthy men, Orwa ibn az-Zobair (d. 94) and Az-Zohri
                    (d.124), seems to be quite lost, Sprenger having vainly made every effort to
                    find a copy. It was still much read in Syria in the 14th century. But we
                    fortunately possess the <hi rend="italic">Book of the Campaigns</hi> of the
                    Prophet by Al-Wâkidi (d. 207) and the important <hi rend="italic">Book of
                    Classes</hi> of his disciple Ibn Sa'd.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Wâkidi has been edited from an imperfect MS. by Kremer
                    (Calcutta, 1856). A condensed translation by Wellhausen appeared in 1882. The
                    great book of Ibn Sa'd is unpublished, but there are some usefid papers on it.
                    by Loth.</p></note> Wâkidi had much more copious materials than Ibn Ishâk, but
                    gives way much more to a popular and sometimes romancing style of treatment.
                    Nevertheless he sometimes helps us to recognize in Ibn Ishâk’s narrative
                    modifications of the genuine tradition made for a purpose, and the additional
                    details he supplies set various events before us in a clearer light. Apart from
                    this his chief merits lie in his studies on the subject of the traditional
                    authorities, the results of which are given by Ibn Sa <hi rend="superscript">
                    t</hi> d, and in his chronology, which is often excellent. A special study of
                    the traditions about the conquest of Syria made by De Goeje in 1864 led to the
                    conclusion that Wâkidi’s chronology is sound as regards the main events, and
                    that later historians have gone astray by forsaking his guidance. This result
                    has been confirmed by certain contemporary notices found by Nöldeke in 1874 in a
                    Syriac MS. of the British Museum. And that Ibn Ishâk agrees with Wâkidi in
                    certain main dates is important evidence for the trustworthiness of the former
                    also. For the chronology before the year 10 of the Flight Wâkidi did his best,
                    but here, the material being defective, many of his conclusions are precarious.
                    Yet, though we have good ground for doubts, we are seldom able to construct a
                    better chronology. Wâkidi had already a great library at his disposal. He is
                    said to have had 600 chests of books, chiefly <hi rend="italic">dictata</hi>
                    written by or for himself, but in part real books by Abù Mikhnaf (d. 130), Ibn
                    Ishâk (whom he uses but does not name), 'Awâna (d. 147), and other authors. Abù
                    Mikhnaf left a great number of monographs on the chief events from the death of
                    the Prophet to the caliphate of Walid II. These were much used by later writers,
                    and λve have many extracts from them, but none of the works themselves, except a
                    sort of romance based on his account of the death of Hosain, of which Wüstenfeld
                    has given a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n12/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0012-0003"/> translation. With regard to the history of 'Irak
                    in particular he was deemed to have the best lights, and for this subject he is
                    Tabari’s chief source, just as Madâini, a younger contemporary of Wâkidi, is
                    followed by preference in all that relates to Khorâsân. Madâini’s <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the Caliphs</hi> is the best if not the oldest
                    published before Tabari; but this book has quite disappeared and is known only
                    by the excerpts given by later writers, particularly Belâdhori and Tabari. From
                    these we judge that he had great narrative power with much clear and exact
                    learning, and must be placed high as a critical historian. His plan was to
                    record the various traditions about an event, choosing them with critical skill;
                    sometimes, however, he fused the several traditions into a continuous narrative.
                    A just estimate of the relative value of the historians can only be reached by
                    careful comparison in detail. This has been essayed by Brünnow in his study on
                    the Khârijites (Leyden, 1884), in which the narrative of Mobarrad in the Kâmil
                    is compared with the excerpts of Madâini given by Belâdhori and those of Abιi
                    Mikhnaf given by Tabari The conclusion reached is that Abιi Mikhnaf and Madâini
                    are both well informed and impartial.</p>
                <p>Among the contemporaries of Wâkidi and Madâini were Ibn Khidâsh (d. 223), the
                    historian of the family Mohallab, whose work was one of Mobarrad’s sources for
                    the <hi rend="italic">History of the Khârijites</hi>; Haitham ibn 'Adi (d. 207),
                    whose works, though now lost, are often cited; and Saif ibn Omar at-Tamimi,
                    whose book on the revolt of the tribes under Abιibekr and on the Mohammedan
                    conquests was much used by Tabari. Saif, however, seems to have been little
                    esteemed; Belâdhori very seldom cites him, and nothing can be found in Arabic
                    literature about his life and those of his authorities. He is barely mentioned
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Fihrist,</hi> the writer plainly having nothing to tell
                    of him, and blundering in the one thing he does say by representing his disciple
                    Sho'aib as his master. Hâjji Khalifa knows nothing but his name. His narratives
                    are detailed and often tinged with romance, and he is certainly much inferior to
                    Wâkidi in accuracy. Besides these are to be mentioned Abû Obaida (d. 209), who
                    was celebrated as a philologist and wrote several historical monographs that are
                    often cited, and Azraki, whose excellent <hi rend="italic">History of Mecca</hi>
                    was published after his death by his grandson (d. 244). With these writers we
                    pass into the 3d century of Islam. But we have still an important point to
                    notice in the 2d century; for in it learned Persians began to take part in the
                    creation of Arabic historical literature. Ibn Mokaffa' translated the great <hi
                    rend="italic">Book of Persian Kings,</hi> and others followed his example.
                    Tabari and his contemporaries, senior and junior, such as Ibn Kotaiba, Ya'kübi,
                    Dinawari, preserve to us a good part of the information about Persian history
                    made known through such translations.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>For details see the introduction to Nöldeke’s excellent
                    translation of Tabari’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Persians and Arabs in
                    the Sasanian Period,</hi> Leyden, 1879.</p></note> But even more important than
                    the knowledge conveyed by these works was their influence on literary style and
                    composition. Half a century later began versions from the Greek either direct or
                    through the Syriac. The pieces translated were mostly philosophical; but the
                    Arabs also learned something, however superficially, of ancient history.</p>
                <p>The 3d century was far more productive than the 2d. Abu Obaida was presently
                    succeeded by Ibn al-A'râbi (d. 231), who in like manner was chiefly famous as a
                    philologist, and who wrote about ancient poems and battles. Much that he wrote
                    is quoted in Tabrizi’s commentary on the <hi rend="italic">Jfamasa,</hi> which
                    is still richer in extracts from the historical elucidations of early poems
                    given by Ar-Riyâshi (d. 257). Of special fame as a genealogist was Ibn Habib</p>
                <p>(d. 245), of whom we have a booklet on Arabian tribal names published by
                    Wüstenfeld (1850). Azraki again was followed by Fâkihi, who wrote a <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Mecca</hi> in 272,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Published in excerpt by Wüstenfeld along with Azraki,
                    Leipsic, 1857-59.</p></note> and Omar b. Shabba (d. 262), who composed an
                    excellent history of Basra, known to us only by excerpts. Of the works of Zobair
                    b. Bakkâr (d. 256), one of Tabari’s teachers, a learned historian and
                    genealogist much consulted by later writers, there is a fragment in the Köprülü
                    library at Constantinople, and another in Göttingen, part of which has been made
                    known by Wüstenfeld <hi rend="italic">(Die Familie Al-Zobair,</hi> Göttingen,
                    1878). Ya'kübi or Ibn Wâdih wrote a short general history of much value,
                    published by Houtsma (Leyden, 1883). About India he knows more than his
                    predecessors and more than his successors down to BèrünL Ibn Khordâdbeh’s
                    historical works are lost. Ibn <hi rend="superscript"> c</hi> Abdalhakam (d.
                    257) wrote of the conquest of Egypt and the West. Extracts from this book are
                    given by De Slane in his <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Berbères,</hi> and
                    others by Karie and Jones, from which we gather that it was a medley of true
                    tradition and romance, and must be reckoned, with the book of his slightly
                    senior contemporary, the Spaniard Ibn Habib, to the class of historical romances
                    (see below, p. 5). A high place must be assigned to the historian Ibn Kotaiba
                    (d. 276), who, as Rosen has well shown, wrote a series of books with a view to
                    raising the scholarship of the large class of <hi rend="italic">kdtιbs</hi> or
                    official scribes. To this series belong his very useful <hi rend="italic"
                    >Handbook of History</hi> (ed. Wüstenfeld, Göttingen, 1850) and his <hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> t</hi><hi rend="italic">0yun al-Akhbar,</hi> though
                    the latter book according to the arrangement falls rather under the class of <hi
                    rend="italic">litterae humaniores.</hi> Much more eminent is Belâdhori (d. 279),
                    whose book on the Arab conquest (ed. De Goeje, Leyden, 1865-66) merits the
                    special praise given to it by Mas'üdi. Of his great <hi rend="italic">Ansol)
                    al-Ashrdf</hi> a large part exists at Paris in the valuable collection of M.
                    Schefer and another part was published by Ahlwardt in 1884. A contemporary, Ibn
                    abi Tâhir Taifür (d. 280), wrote on the 'Abbâsid caliphs and was drawn on by
                    Tabari. The sixth part of his work is in the British Museum. Of the universal
                    history of Dinawari (d. 282), entitled <hi rend="italic">The Long
                    Narratives,</hi> an edition by Girgas is now (1887) in the press.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Tabari.</hi></p>
                <p>All these histories are more or less thrown into the shade by the great work of
                    Tabari, whose fame has never faded from his own day to ours, and who well
                    deserves to have this article on early Arabic histories placed under his name.
                    Abû Ja'far Mohammed b. Jarir at-Tabari (so his full name runs) is described as a
                    tall lean figure, with large eyes, brown complexion, and hair which remained
                    black till his death. His learning was astounding and feλv could speak so well.
                    Born 224 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.</hi> (838-9 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi>
                    at Amol in Tabaristân, he came to Baghdad as a young man and heard there the
                    most famous teachers of the age. He travelled through Syria and Egypt (where he
                    was in 263), and finally settled down in Baghdad, where he remained till his
                    death in 310 (922 <hi rend="smallcaps">a,d.),</hi> always active and surrounded
                    by pupils. He is said to have written forty pages daily for forty years. This no
                    doubt is an exaggeration, but certainly he must have been a man of most
                    persistent industry. His two chief works are a great <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commentary on the Koran</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Annals.</hi> There is an
                    anecdote to the effect that each originally filled 30,000 leaves, but that his
                    pupils found them too extensive to be written to his dictation, and that he then
                    resolved to condense them to a tenth of their original size, exclaiming, “God
                    help us! Ambition is extinct.” One cannot say how far this story is true, but it
                    is probable enough that his materials, at least for the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Annals,</hi> were many times greater than the book itself.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n13/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0013-0004"/>
                <p>Where the same topic comes up in the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> and in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Commentary</hi> we often find different traditions quoted, or the
                    same tradition derived through different channels, and this shows the copious
                    variety of his sources. Various parts of the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> give
                    the impression of being condensed. The <hi rend="italic">Commentary</hi> was
                    published before the <hi rend="italic">Annals,</hi> and is better composed. It
                    is the head corner-stone of Koran exegesis, as the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi>
                    are of historiography. It came into general use mainly through the abridgment of
                    Baghawi in the beginning of the 6th century of the Flight, being itself too
                    large to be much read. The great book exists complete in the viceregal library
                    at Cairo, and ought to be published at once.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See the excellent article by Lo⅛ in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Z.D.M.G.,</hi> χχχv. 588 <hi rend="italic">sg.</hi></p></note></p>
                <p>The Annα⅛ are a general history from the creation to 302 A.H., and are in the
                    course of publication at Leyden. They will fill some 7000 to 7500 pages, one and
                    a half printed pages corresponding roughly to one leaf of Tabari’s original MS.
                    Tabari added a supplement about his authorities, an abridgment of which is to
                    follow the Leyden edition. It contains biographical notices of traditionalists,
                    contemporaries of Mohammed, and their successors to the second half of the 2d
                    century.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The MS.
                    containing this abridgment is described by Loth in <hi rend="italic"
                    >Z.H.M.G.,</hi> xxxii. 581 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi> It is now in the British
                    Museum.</p></note> Other works by Tabari will be spoken of in detail in the
                    preface to the Leyden edition.</p>
                <p>The success of the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commentary</hi> was due above all to the author’s personality. The respect paid
                    to him by his contemporaries appears in various anecdotes preserved in his
                    biography. His pupils had an unbounded admiration for his extraordinary
                    knowledge, and what he said seemed to them the best that could be said. In
                    truth, both his great works were the best of their kind, especially the <hi
                    rend="italic">Commentary,</hi> which, in the judgment of all impartial critics,
                    has not been equalled, before or since, in completeness, learning, and
                    independent judgment. A contemporary says that “it would be worth a journey to
                    China to procure the book.” So general was this view that the opinion of Tabari
                    was quoted as a legal authority.</p>
                <p>The inferiority of the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> as a literary composition
                    may be due partly to the author’s years, partly to the inequality of his
                    sources, sometimes superabundant, sometimes defective, partly perhaps to the
                    somewhat hasty condensation of his original draft. Nevertheless the value of the
                    book is very great: the author’s selection of traditions is usually happy, and
                    the episodes of most importance are treated with most fulness of detail, so that
                    it deserves the high reputation it has enjoyed from the first. This reputation
                    rose steadily; there were twenty copies (one of them written by Tabari’s own
                    hand) in the library of the Fâtimite caliph 'Aziz (latter half of the 4th
                    century), whereas, when Saladin became lord of Egypt, the princely library
                    contained 1200 copies (Ma⅛rizi, i. 408 <hi rend="italic">sqj).</hi> Only princes
                    and rich men could own a book which in the time of 'Aziz cost one hundred
                    dinars. We know that it had a place in most great libraries in other countries,
                    for we find that it was used in all lands. Thus the fact that no complete copy
                    can now be found anywhere, and that the Leyden edition rests on odd volumes
                    lying in various places, gives a striking image of what the East has suffered
                    from barbarism.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> soon came to be dealt with in various ways.
                    They were published in shorter form with the omission of the names of
                    authorities and of most of the poems cited; some passages quoted by later
                    writers are not found even in the Leyden edition. On the other hand, some
                    interpolations took place, one in the author’s lifetime and perhaps by his own
                    hand. Then many supplements were written, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> by
                    Ferghâni (not extant) and by Hamadhâni (partly preserved in Paris). ‘Arib of
                    Cordova made an abridg ment, adding the history of the West and continuing the
                    story to about 365.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Of
                    this work the Gotha library has a portion containing 290-320 Λ.H., of which the
                    part about the West has been printed by Dozy in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >BayΛn,</hi> and the rest is to be published at Leyden.</p></note> Ibn
                    Mashkawaih wrote a history from the creation to 369 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >a.h.,</hi> with the purpose of drawing the lessons of the story, following
                    Tabari closely, as far as his book is known, and seldom recurring to other
                    sources before the reign of Moktadir; what follows is his own composition, and
                    shows him to be a writer of talent.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>A fragment (198-251 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.)</hi> is
                    printed in De Goeje, <hi rend="italic">Fragrn. Hist. Ar.,</hi> vol. ii., Leyden,
                    1871. Schefer possesses an excellent MS. of the years 249-315; Oxford has
                    another fragment, 345-360 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.h.</hi>; the second part is in
                    the Escorial.</p></note> In 352 an abridgment of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Annals</hi> was translated into Persian by BaΓami, who, however, interwove many
                    fables.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The first part
                    was rendered into French by Dubeux in 1836. We have now an excellent French
                    translation by Zotenberg, 1874.</p></note> Ibn al-Athir (d. 630) abridged the
                    whole work, usually with judgment, but sometimes too hastily. Though he
                    sometimes glided lightly over difficulties, his work is of service in fixing the
                    text of Tabari. He also furnished a continuation to the year 620. Later writers
                    took Tabari as their main authority, but fortunately sometimes consulted other
                    sources, and so add to our knowledge,—- especially Ibn al-Jauzi (d. 597), who
                    adds many important details. These later historians had valuable help from the
                    biographies of famous men and special histories of countries and cities,
                    dynasties and princes, on which much labour was spent from the 4th century
                    onwards.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Historians after Tabari.</hi></p>
                <p>The chief historians after Tabari may be briefly mentioned in chronological
                    order. Razi (d. 325) wrote a <hi rend="italic">History of Spain</hi>; Eutychius
                    (d. 328) wrote <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> (published by Pocock, Oxford,
                    1656), which arc very important because he gives the Christian tradition; Ibn
                    'Λbd Rabbihi (d. 328) has very valuable historical passages in his famous
                    miscellany called <hi rend="italic">Al-'Ikd al-Farid</hi> (3 vols., Cairo, 1293
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">λ.h.)</hi>; Sιili (d. 335) wrote on the <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> Abbasid caliphs, their viziers and court poets;
                    Mas'ùdi (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Mλs'udy)</hi> composed various historical and
                    geographical works (d. 345). Of Tabari’s contemporary Hamza Is-ρahanι we have
                    the <hi rend="italic">Annals</hi> (published by Gottwaldt, St. Petersburg,
                    1844); Abu Ί-Faraj al-Ispaham (d. 356) in his <hi rend="italic">Book of Songs
                    {Kitab al-Aghäni,</hi> 20 vols., Cairo, 1285) gave the lives of poets whose
                    songs were sung: Ibn al-Kùtïya (d. 367) wrote a <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Spain</hi>; Ibn Zιilak (d. 387) a <hi rend="italic">History of Egypt·,</hi>
                    '0tbi wrote the <hi rend="italic">History of Mahmud of Ghazna</hi> (d. 421), at
                    whose court he lived (printed on the margin of the Egyptian edition of Ibn
                    al-Athir); Tπa'labi (d. 427) wrote a well-known <hi rend="italic">History of the
                    Old Prophets</hi>; Abu No ’ aim al-Ispalιani (d. 430) wrote a <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Ispahan,</hi> chiefly of the scholars of that city; Tha'âlibi (d.
                    429 or 430) wrote, <hi rend="italic">inter alia,</hi> a well-known <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the Poets of his Time,</hi> now (1887) in course of
                    publication at Damascus. Bèrùni (d. 440) takes a high place among historians by
                    his <hi rend="italic">Chronology of Ancient Nations</hi> (ed. Sachau, Leipsic,
                    1878; Eng. tι ’ ans., London, 1879) and his contributions to the history of
                    India and Khwarizm; Koda ’ i (d. 454) wrote <hi rend="italic">a Description of
                    Egypt</hi> and also various historical pieces, of which some are extant; Ibn
                    Sa'id of Cordova (d. 462) wrote a <hi rend="italic">View of the History of the
                    Various Nations.</hi> Baghdad and its learned men found an excellent historian
                    in Al-Khatib al-Baghdadi (d. 463), and Spain in Ibn Hayan (d. 469), and half a
                    century later in Ibn Khakan (d. 529) and Ibn Bassâm (d. 542). Sam ani (d. 562)
                    wrote an excellent book on genealogies; Ibn ’ Asakir (d. 571) a <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Damascus and her Scholars,</hi> which is of great
                    value, and exists in whole or in part in several libraries. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary</hi> of the Spaniard Ibn Pascual (d. 578)
                    and that of I)abbi, a somewhat junior contemporary, are edited in Codera’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Bibliotheca Arab. Hisp.</hi> (1883-1885); Saladin found his
                    historian in the famous 'Imad addin (d. 597). Ibn al-Jauzi, who died in the same
                    year, has been already mentioned. Abdalwahid’s <hi rend="italic">History of the
                    Almohades,</hi> written in 621, was published by Dozy (2d eα., 1881). The
                    geographer Yakrit (d. 626) wrote also some historical works, now lost.
                    Abdallatif (d. 629) is known by his writings about Egypt (trans. De Sacy, 1810);
                    Ibn al-Athir (d. 630) wrote, in addition to the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi>
                    already mentioned, a <hi rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary of Contemporaries
                    of the Prophet.</hi> Kifti (d. 646) is especially known by his <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Arabic Philologists.</hi> Sibt ibn al-Jauzi (d. 654), grandson of
                    the Ibn al-Jauzi already mentioned, wrote a great <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chronicle,</hi> of which much the larger part still exists. Codera has edited
                    (Madrid, 1886) Ibn al-'Abbar’s (d. 658) <hi rend="italic">Biographical
                    Lexicon,</hi> already known by Dozy’s excerpts from it. Ibn al- <hi
                    rend="superscript"> t</hi> Adim (d. 660) is <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n14/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0014-0005"/> famed for his <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Aleppo,</hi> and Abu Shama (d. 665) wrote a well-known <hi rend="italic">History
                    of Saladin and Nureddin,</hi> taking a great deal from 'Imâd addin. A. Müller
                    has recently published (1885) Ibn abi Osaibia’s (d. 668) <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Physicians.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">History</hi> of Ibn al-'Amid
                    (d. 675), better known as <hi rend="smallcaps">Elmacin</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(y.vf</hi> was printed by Erpenius in 1625. Ibn Sa'id al-Maghribi (d. 673 or
                    685) is famous for his histories, but still more for his geographical writings.
                    The noted theologian <hi rend="smallcaps">Nawawi</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(q.v.</hi>; d. 676) wrote a <hi rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary of the
                    Worthies of the Birst Ages of Islam.</hi> Pre-eminent as a biographer is Ibn
                    Khallikan (d. 681), whose much-used work was partly edited by De Slane and
                    completely by Wüstenfeld (1835- 40), and translated into English by the former
                    scholar (4 vols., 1843-71).</p>
                <p>Abu ’ 1-Faraj, better known as Bar-Hebraeus (d. 685), wrote besides his Syriac
                    <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> an Arabic <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Dynasties</hi> (ed. Pocock, Oxford, 1663). Ibn 'Adhan’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Africa and Spain</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> }∖αs</hi> been
                    published by Dozy (2 vols., Leyden, 1848-51), and the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kartcis</hi> of Ibn abi Zar' by Tornberg (1843). One of the best known of Arab
                    writers is Abulfeda (d. 732), whose <hi rend="italic">Annales Muslemicae</hi>
                    were published with a Latin version by Reiske (Copenhagen, 5 vols. 4to,
                    1789-94). The <hi rend="italic">History of the Time before Mohammed</hi> has
                    been published by Fleischer (1831). Not less famous is the great <hi
                    rend="italic">Encyclopaedia</hi> of his contemporary Nowairi (d. 732), but only
                    some extracts are as yet in print. Ibn Sayyid an-Nas (d. 734) wrote a full
                    biography of the Prophet; Mizzi (d. 742) an extensive work on the men from whom
                    traditions have been derived. We still possess, nearly complete, the great <hi
                    rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> of Dhahabi (d. 748), a very learned biographer and
                    historian. A complete edition of the geographical and historical <hi
                    rend="italic">MasΛlik al-Absdr</hi> of Ibn Fadlallah (d. 749) is much to be
                    desired. It is known at present by extracts given by Quatremère and Amari. Ibn
                    al-Wardi (d. 749 or 750), best known by his <hi rend="italic">Cosmography,</hi>
                    wrote a <hi rend="italic">Chronicle</hi> which has been printed in Egypt. Safadi
                    (d. 764) got a great name as a biographer. Yafi'ι (d. 768) wrote a <hi
                    rend="italic">Chronicle of Islam</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Lives of
                    Saints.</hi> Sobki (d. 771) published <hi rend="italic">Lives of the Theologians
                    of the ShΛfi'ite School.</hi> Of Ibn Kathir’s <hi rend="italic">History</hi> the
                    greatest part is extant. For the history of Spain and the Maghrib the writings
                    of Ibn al-Khatib (d. 776) are of acknowledged value. Another history, of which
                    we possess the greater part, is the large work of Ibn al-Forât (d. 807). Far
                    superior to all these, however, is the famous Ibn Khaldun (d. 808), who proves
                    himself a great thinker in the <hi rend="italic">Prolegomena to his Universal
                    History.</hi> Of the <hi rend="italic">Prolegomena</hi> there are an edition by
                    Quatremère (1858) and a French version by De Slane (1863). The latter scholar
                    also published text and version of the <hi rend="italic">History of the
                    Berbers,</hi> and there is a poor Egyptian edition of the λvhole work. Of the
                    historical works of the famous lexicographer Finizabadi (d. 817) only a <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of the Prophet</hi> remains. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Makrizi</hi> (d. 845) is spoken of in a separate article; Ibn Hajar (d. 852) is
                    best known by his <hi rend="italic">Biographical Dictionary of Contemporaries of
                    the Prophet,</hi> now in course of publication in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bibliotheca Indica.</hi> Ibn 'Arabshâh (d. 854) is known by his <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Timûr</hi> (Leeuwarden, 1767). 'Aini (d. 855) wrote a
                    <hi rend="italic">General History,</hi> still extant. Abu Ί-Mahâsin (d. 874)
                    wrote at length on the history of Egypt; the first two parts have been published
                    by Juynboll. Flügel has published Ibn Kotlubogha’s <hi rend="italic">Biographies
                    of the Ifanafite Jurists.</hi> Ibn Shihna (d. 890) wrote a <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Aleppo.</hi> Of Sa-khâwi we possess a bibliographical work on the
                    historians. The polymath Soyuti (d. 911) contributed a <hi rend="italic">History
                    of the Caliphs</hi> and many biographical pieces. Samhudi’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Medina</hi> is known through the excerpts of Wüstenfeld (1861). Ibn
                    Iyas (d. 930) wrote a <hi rend="italic">History of Egypt,</hi> and Diyârbekri
                    (d. 966) a <hi rend="italic">Life of Mohammed.</hi> To these names must be added
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Makkari</hi><hi rend="italic">(y.v.)</hi> and Hàjji
                    Khalifa, the famous Turkish bibliographer (d. 1068), who, besides his <hi
                    rend="italic">Bibliographical Lexicon</hi> and his well-known geography, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Jihàn-numa,</hi> wrote histories, mostly in Turkish. He made use
                    of European sources, and with him Arabic historiography may be said to cease,
                    though he had some unimportant successors.</p>
                <p>A word must be said of the historical romances, the beginnings of which go back
                    to the first centuries of Islam. The interest in all that concerned Mohammed and
                    in the allusions of the Koran to old prophets and races led many professional
                    narrators to choose these subjects in place of the doughty deeds of the
                    Bedouins. The increasing veneration paid to the Prophet and love for the
                    marvellous soon gave rise to fables about his childhood, his visit to heaven,
                    &amp;c., which have found their way even into sober histories, just as many
                    Jewish legends told by the converted Jew Ka'b al-Ahbâr and by Wahb ibn Monabbih,
                    and many fables about the old princes of Yemen told by 'Abid, are taken as
                    genuine history (see, however, Mas'ιidi, iv. 88 <hi rend="italic">sqf</hi> A
                    fresh field for romantic legend was found in the history of the victories of
                    Islam, the exploits of the first heroes of the faith, the fortunes of 'Ali and
                    his house. Even under the first Omayyads there were in the mosques of most great
                    cities preachers who edified the people by stories about Islam and its
                    victories, and there is ample evidence that these men did not stick to actual
                    fact. Sho'ba said of them ‘ ‘they get from us a handbreadth of tradition and
                    make it an ell.” Then, too, history was often expressly forged for party
                    ends.</p>
                <p>The people swallowed all this, and so a romantic tradition sprang up side by side
                    with the historical, and had a literature of its own, the beginnings of which
                    must be placed as early as the second century of the Flight. The oldest samples
                    still extant are the fables about the conquest of Spain ascribed to Ibn Habib
                    (d. 238), and those about the conquest of Egypt and the West by Ibn 'Abdalhakam
                    (d. 257). In these truth and falsehood are mingled, as Dozy has shown in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Recherches.</hi> But most of the extant literature of this kind
                    is, in its present form, much more recent; <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> the <hi
                    rend="italic">Story of the Death of Hosain</hi> by the Pseudo-Abιi Mikhnaf
                    (translated by Wüstenfeld); the <hi rend="italic">Conquest of Syria</hi> by Abιi
                    Isma'il al-Baçri (edited by Nassau Lees, Calcutta, 1854, and discussed by De
                    Goeje, 1864); the Pseudo-Wakidi (see Hamaker, <hi rend="italic">De Expugnatione
                    Memphidis et Alexandriae,</hi> Leyden, 1835); the Pseudo-Ibn Kotaiba (see Dozy,
                    <hi rend="italic">Recherches')</hi>; the book ascribed to A'sam Kιifi, &amp;c.
                    Further inquiry into the origin of these works is called for, but some of them
                    were plainly directed to stir up fresh zeal against the Christians. In the 6th
                    century some of these books had gained so much authority that they were used as
                    sources, and thus many untruths crept into accepted history. (Μ. J. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">de</hi> G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
