<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0091-0080-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TATIAN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 80</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xd69">Canonization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4np1wt1r">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rw58">Apologetics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1141359">Syrians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1939177">Logos</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n91/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TATIAN</label>, one of the earliest Christian apologists,
                    whose personality and work had an important influence on the history of the
                    church during the period of the Antonines. He was by birth an Assyrian
                    (according to Zahn of Semitic descent), but received a Greek education, and,
                    after acquiring a very extensive knowledge of Greek literature, began to travel
                    about the Roman empire as a wandering teacher or “sophist.” But his inquiring
                    disposition and his earnest spirit remained unsatisfied alike with the religions
                    and the philosophies he encountered, while the doings of men, their greed for
                    amusement and pleasure, their vanity and treachery, disgusted him. In this
                    temper, about 150 A.D., he reached Rome, where the Old Testament fell into his
                    hands, and at the same time he came into closer relations with the Christians;
                    thθir firm faith, chaste morals, fearless courage, and close fellowship deeply
                    impressed him, and in the end the spectacle of their life and their monotheistic
                    doctrine founded upon prophetic revelation completely conquered him.
                    Henceforward the whole unchristian world, with all its philosophy and culture,
                    presented itself to him as mere darkness and the deception of demons, but the
                    “barbarian philosophy” (for so he called Christianity) as the wisdom of God. He
                    became a convert, and soon afterwards (152-153) wrote (most probably in Greece,
                    where he stayed for some time) his <hi rend="italic">Oratio ad Graecos,</hi>
                    which gained him great repute <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n92/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0092-0081"/> among the Christians, and is still extant. This
                    discourse is distinguished from the other apologies of that century by the
                    brusqueness with which its author repudiates the culture of the Greeks; his
                    scorn, however, does not forget to avail itself of the resources of Greek
                    philosophy and rhetoric. His polemic often reminds the reader of the Cynics and
                    of such scoffers as Lucian; his view of things, however, is very different from
                    that of the last-named writer, for with Tatian the “barbarian philosophy,” on
                    behalf of which he speaks, which teaches a monotheistic cosmology and inculcates
                    rigid asceticism and renunciation of the world, is indisputably certain. In many
                    details, and even in the general outline of his philosophy, Tatian the Christian
                    continued without knowing it to be a Platonizing philosopher; but that he had
                    undergone a radical change is shown by his views of history and civilization,
                    his faith in one living God, his conviction that truth is contained nowhere else
                    than in the Christian Scriptures, his attitude of trust towards the Logos, made
                    man in Jesus Christ, and finally by his earnest and world-forsaking expectation
                    of judgment to come. The <hi rend="italic">Oratio,</hi> which is polemical
                    rather than apologetic in its character, has a special importance in the history
                    of Christian dogma, inasmuch as it gives an elaborated exposition of the
                    doctrine of the Logos; it was also read by subsequent writers, as, for example,
                    by Julius Africanus, for its chronological data. Tatian was the first apologist
                    to undertake, on behalf of Christianity, a work of the class which afterwards
                    developed into the numerous “world-histories” written from the Christian point
                    of view. Tatian’s diction is often rough, harsh, and abrupt, his sentences
                    involved and inelegant. He has the art, indeed, of expressing himself with
                    uncommon freedom and independence, and can put things also in a very graphic
                    way, but at the same time he is a careless stylist, or rather, as an apostate
                    from the Greek view of things, he has tried to accentuate his breach with
                    classical traditions by elaborate carelessness and deliberate eccentricity.</p>
                <p>Tatian soon returned from Greece to Rome, and came into close relations with the
                    famous apologist Justin, whom he reverenced greatly. He himself established a
                    school, to which the afterwards celebrated ecclesiastical writer Rhodon belonged
                    for a time. So long as Justin lived <hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> till 166)
                    Tatian’s doctrines excited no feelings of offence in the Christian community,
                    although even in his <hi rend="italic">Orαtio</hi> there are germs of
                    questionable and unorthodox views. These germs, however, he continued to develop
                    until about 172; and, as about this very time the Roman church became severely
                    opposed to everything Gnostic and heretical, a rupture was inevitable; the date
                    of the breach is given by Eusebius (doubtless following Julius Africanus) as
                    having been 172. But the teaching of Tatian had really become open to challenge.
                    He drew a distinction between the supreme God and the demiurge, considering the
                    latter to be good in his nature indeed, but quite a subordinate being; he
                    accepted the doctrine of a variety of aeons; he utterly rejected marriage and
                    the use of animal food; he denied the blessedness of Adam; he began to abandon
                    the allegorical interpretation of the Scriptures and to see genuine difficulties
                    and contradictions in them; he sought to demonstrate from the epistles of Paul
                    the indispensableness of the most rigid asceticism; but indeed all his
                    “heresies” (and he has also been charged with docetism) have their explanation
                    in this desire of his to establish a theoretical basis for his doctrine of the
                    Christian duty of complete world-renunciation. He joined the “Encratites,” a
                    sect which indeed had existed before this time, but which received new life from
                    his presence. Of his numerous writings belonging to this period nothing has
                    survived the hostility which sought their repression save a few titles <hi
                    rend="italic">(βίβλίον προβλημάτων, πcpl</hi> του <hi rend="italic">κατά, τον
                    σωτηρα κaτapτarμου,</hi> &amp;c.) and one or two very interesting fragments in
                    the works of Clement of Alexandria, Origen, and Jerome. Clement of Alexandria
                    seems personally to have known Tatian, and even to have been his pupil for a
                    time. Soon Tatian began also to be assailed in writing by the teachers of the
                    church, and to be set aside as a very prodigy among heretics, and as a man who
                    united the errors of Marcion with those of Valentine. Musanus, Rhodon, Irenaeus,
                    the author of the Muratorian fragment (see below), Tertullian, Hippolytus,
                    Clement of Alexandria, and Origen all took part in refuting him.</p>
                <p>Towards the end of his life, or perhaps even between 152 and 172, Tatian went
                    from Rome to Mesopotamia, and there—probably in Edessa—wrought a great deal. It
                    is probable that he was in Rome about the year 172, but whether he died there or
                    in his native country is not ascertained. It is very possible that in Syria,
                    where ecclesiastical matters had not been developed so far as in the West, the
                    doctrines of Tatian met with toleration within the Christian communities, but
                    neither of this can we be certain.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The author of the <hi rend="italic">Acta Archelai</hi>
                    treats him as a heretic.</p></note> But this we do know, that a work of Tatian’s
                    not yet mentioned, the <hi rend="italic">Diatessaron,</hi> held its ground in
                    the Syrian churches and even in ecclesiastical use for two whole centuries.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Dialessaron</hi> is a gospel very freely and boldly
                    constructed by Tatian out of the four Gospels known to us. It cannot have been
                    produced during his latter years, for all traces of dualism are absent. On the
                    other hand, however, it exhibits certain peculiarities of the theology of its
                    compiler. Probably one would not be far wrong in assigning it to the first years
                    of the reign of Marcus Aurelius. It was written by Tatian in Greek, not in
                    Syriac as Zahn has tried to make out; this is shown—(1) by the title, it being
                    known even among the Syrians as <hi rend="italic">Dialessaron</hi>; (2) by a few
                    Greek fragments which still survive; (3) by the Latin redaction which it
                    received in the 6th century; (4) by its rejection in the Muratorian fragment—for
                    that the word “m-tia-i,” carelessly corrected by the transcriber, stood
                    originally “tatiani” may be regarded as certain.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi rend="italic">Zeilschr. f. d. lulh.
                    Theol.,</hi> 1874 and 1875; <hi rend="italic">Zeilschr. f. wiss. Theol.,</hi>
                    1877; <hi rend="italic">Zeilschr. f Kirchengesch.</hi>, iii. p. 400.</p></note>
                    In estimating the work scholars were formerly entirely dependent on certain
                    meagre notices in Eusebius, Theodoret, Ephraem Syrus, Epiphanius, and the later
                    Syrians,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Credner,
                    <hi rend="italic">Einl.,</hi> i. 437 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>; Sernisch, <hi
                    rend="italic">Taliani Dialessaron,</hi> 1856.</p></note> but we have recently
                    become possessed of large portions of it, and are now in a position to form for
                    ourselves an idea of its character and plan. In 1877 there was published<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Evangelii
                    Concordantis Expositio facta a S. Ephraemo,</hi> Venice.</p></note> a Latin
                    translation, by Λucher the Mechitarist, of Ephraem’s gospel commentary, which
                    had been preserved in Armenian, and it then became apparent that Ephraem had
                    taken the <hi rend="italic">Dialessaron</hi> as his basis. This led to further
                    research.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Harnack,
                    <hi rend="italic">Zlschr. f. Kirchengesch.,</hi> iv. p. 471 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.</hi></p></note> Recognizing with other scholars that other Syrian writers
                    also, down to the middle of the 4th century, had used the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dialessaron</hi> (Theodoret tells us that in his diocese alone he caused more
                    than 300 copies to be withdrawn from use), Zahn undertook the laborious task of
                    restoring the work with the help of Ephraem’s commentary and other sources.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Zahn, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tatian’s Dialessaron,</hi> 1881.</p></note> In details much of what Zahn has
                    given as belonging to the text of the <hi rend="italic">Dialessaron</hi> remains
                    problematical,—in particular he has not been sufficiently careful in his
                    examination of the work of Aphraates,—but in all the main points his restoration
                    has been successful. The rediscovery of such a work is in a variety of ways of
                    the very highest importance for the early history of Christianity. (1) It is of
                    interest for the history of the canon. It shows that in Tatian’s time there was
                    still no recognized New Testament canon, and that the texts of the Gospels were
                    not regarded as inspired. He could not possibly have treated them with such
                    freedom had they been held to be otherwise. But the ecclesiastical use made of
                    his work in Syria shows that Tatian intended it for the church, and, as we are
                    informed further by Eusebius that Tatian also edited the Pauline epistles, we
                    are entitled to conclude that, like Marcion, he wished to frame a special New
                    Testament canon. (2) It is of importance for the Gospels as we now have them. We
                    learn from the <hi rend="italic">Dialessaron</hi> that about 160 A.D. our four
                    Gospels had already taken a place of prominence in the church and that no others
                    had done so; that in particular the Fourth Gospel had taken a fixed place
                    alongside of the three <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n93/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0093-0082"/> synoptics. (3) As regards the text of the
                    Gospels, we can conclude from the <hi rend="italic">Diatessaron</hi> that the
                    texts of our Gospels about the year 160 already ran essentially as we now read
                    them, but that intentional changes were not wanting about the middle of the 2d
                    century. Thus, for example, Tatian in his Gospel according to Matthew found
                    nothing about the “church” and about the building of the church upon Peter the
                    rock. These sentences therefore are very probably of later interpolation. (4) It
                    is of importance for the light it throws on Tatian’s Christianity. The Syriac
                    translation of the <hi rend="italic">Diatessaron</hi> still falls within the 2d
                    century, but Zahn was mistaken in assuming it to presuppose a prior Syriac
                    translation of the separate Gospels (the so-called <hi rend="italic">Syrus
                    Curetonianus');</hi> Baethgen<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Evangelienfragmente: Der Griechische Text
                    des Cureton sehen Syrers,</hi> Leipsic, 1885.</p></note> has shown the latter to
                    be the later. It was only gradually that the “evangelium der Getrennten”
                    superseded the “evangelium der Gemischten.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>On the <hi rend="italic">Diatessaron,</hi> its later history
                    and various editions, see (besides Zahn, as cited a⅛ove) the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Codex Fuldensis,</hi> ed. Ranke, 1868; Schmeller, <hi rend="italic">Ammonii
                    Alex, quae et Tatiani dicitur Harmonia Evang.,</hi> 1841; Sievers, <hi
                    rend="italic">Tatian,</hi> Lat. and Ger., Paderborn, 1872; Martin, “De Tatiani
                    Diatessaron Arabica Versione,” in Pitra’s <hi rend="italic">Analecta Sacra,</hi>
                    vol. iv. (1883), pp. 465, 487.</p></note></p>
                <p>The best editions of the <hi rend="italic">Oratio ad Graecos</hi> are those of
                    worth (Oxford, 1700), Maranus (Paris, 1742), and Otto (Jena, 1851). See Daniel,
                    <hi rend="italic">Tatian der Apologet,</hi> 1837; Zahn, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Tatian’s Diatessaron,</hi> Erlangen, 1881 (compare also his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Erang.- Comm. des Theophilus,</hi> Erlangen, 1883, p. 286 <hi rend="italic"
                    >sq.)-,</hi> Harnack, <hi rend="italic">Texte u. Untersuchungen z. Gesch. d.
                    altchr. Lit.,</hi> i. 1; Id., <hi rend="italic">Ztschr. f. Kirchengesch.,</hi>
                    iv. 471 <hi rend="italic">sq.;</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Tatian’s Rede an die
                    Griechen übersetzt u. eingeleitet,</hi> Giessen, 1884; Hilgenfeld, <hi
                    rend="italic">Ketzergesch.,</hi> Leipsic, 1884; Möller, art. “Tatian,” in
                    Herzog-Plitt’s <hi rend="italic">Encykl.,</hi> vol. XV.; and Donaldson, <hi
                    rend="italic">Hist, of Christ. Lit.,</hi> ili. p. 3-62. (A. HA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
