<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0103-0092-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TAYLOR, Brook</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 92</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47w67b9q">Mathematicians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1005112">Machining</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n103/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TAYLOR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Brook</hi></label> (1685-1731),
                    a distinguished mathematician of Newton’s school, was the son of John Taylor, of
                    Bifrons House, Kent, by Olivia, daughter of Sir Nicholas Tempest, Bart., of
                    Durham, and was born at Edmonton in Middlesex, August 18, 1685. He entered St
                    John’s College, Cambridge, as a fellow-commoner in 1701, and took degrees of
                    LL.B, and LL.D, respectively in 1709 and 1714. Having studied mathematics with
                    applause under Machin and Keill, he obtained in 1708 a remarkable solution of
                    the problem of the “centre of oscillation,” which, however, remaining
                    unpublished until May 1714 <hi rend="italic">(Phil. Trans.,</hi> vol. xxviii. p.
                    11), his claim to priority was unjustly disputed by John Bernoulli. Taylor’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Methodus Incrementorum Directa et Inversa</hi> (London, 1715)
                    added a new branch to the higher mathematics, now designated the “calculus of
                    finite differences.” Among other ingenious applications, he used it to determine
                    the form of movement of a vibrating string, by him first successfully reduced to
                    mechanical principles. The same work contained (p. 23) the celebrated formula
                    known as “Taylor’s theorem.” It is of extensive use in almost every analytical
                    inquiry; but its full importance remained unrecognized until pointed out in 1772
                    (Berlin <hi rend="italic">Memoirs)</hi> by Lagrange, who later termed it “le
                    principal fondement du calcul différentiel.”</p>
                <p>In his essay on <hi rend="italic">Linear Perspective</hi> (London, 1715) Taylor
                    set forth the true principles of the art with much originality, and in a more
                    general form than any of his predecessors. The little work suffered, however,
                    from the brevity and obscurity which affected most of his writings, and needed
                    the elucidation bestowed on it in the treatises of Joshua Kirby (1754) and
                    Daniel Fournier (1761).</p>
                <p>Taylor was elected a fellow of the Royal Society early in 1712, sat in the same
                    year on the committee for adjudicating the claims of Newton and Leibnitz, and
                    acted as secretary to the society January 13, 1714, to October 21, 1718. During
                    a visit to Paris in 1716 he made acquaintance with Bossuet and the Comte de
                    Caylus, and knit a warm friendship with Bolingbroke, whom he visited at La
                    Source in 1720. From 1715 his studies took a philosophical and religious bent.
                    He corresponded, in that year, with the Comte de Montmort on the subject of
                    Malebranche’s tenets; and unfinished treatises, “On the Jewish Sacrifices” and
                    “On the Lawfulness of Eating Blood,” written on his return from Aix-la-Chapelle
                    in 1719, were afterwards found among his papers. His marriage in 1721 with Miss
                    Brydges of Wallington, Surrey, led to an estrangement from his father, a person
                    of somewhat morose temper, which terminated in 1723 after the death of the lady
                    in giving birth to a son. The ensuing two years were spent by him with his
                    family at Bifrons, and in 1725 he married, with the paternal approbation,
                    Sabetta, daughter of Mr Sawbridge of Olantigh, Kent, who, by a strange fatality,
                    died also in childbed in 1730; in this case, however, the infant, a daughter,
                    survived. Weighed down by repeated sorrows, Taylor’s fragile health gave way; he
                    fell into a decline, died December 29, 1731, at Somerset House, and was buried
                    at St Ann’s, Soho. By his father’s death in 1729 he had inherited the Bifrons
                    estate. Socially as well as intellectually gifted, he possessed a handsome
                    person and engaging manners, and was accomplished to an uncommon degree in music
                    and painting. As a mathematician, he was the only Englishman after Newton and
                    Cotes capable of holding his own with the Bernoullis; but a great part of the
                    effect of his demonstrations was lost through his failure to express his ideas
                    fully and clearly.</p>
                <p>A posthumous work entitled <hi rend="italic">Contemplatio Philosophica</hi> was
                    printed for private circulation in 1793 by his grandson, Sir William Young,
                    Bart., prefaced by a life of the author, and with an appendix containing letters
                    addressed to him by Bolingbroke, Bossuet, &amp;c. Several short papers by him
                    were published in <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trans.,</hi> vols, xxvii. to xxxii.,
                    including accounts of some interesting experiments in magnetism and capillary
                    attraction. He issued in 1719 an improved version of his work on perspective,
                    with the title <hi rend="italic">New Principles of Linear Perspective,</hi>
                    revised by Colson in 1749, and printed again, with portrait and life of the
                    author, in 1811. A French translation appeared in 1753 at Lyons. Taylor gave <hi
                    rend="italic">{Methodus Incrementorum,</hi> p. 108) the first satisfactory
                    investigation of astronomical refraction.</p>
                <p>See watt, <hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Britannica</hi>; Hutton, <hi
                    rend="italic">Phil, and Math. Dictionary</hi>; Fût is, <hi rend="italic">Biog.
                    des Musiciens;</hi> Th. Thomson, <hi rend="italic">Hist, of the It.
                    Society,</hi> p. 302; Grant, <hi rend="italic">Hist. Phys. Astronomy,</hi> p.
                    377; Marie, <hi rend="italic">Hist, des Sciences,</hi> vii. p. 231.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
