<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0248-0231-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THEFT (9th edition, volume 23, page 231)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46m3337r">Civilization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2t79r">Digestion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025265">Money</term>
                    <term ref="fast:882984">Crime</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n248/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THEFT</label> is, in modern legal systems, universally
                    treated as a crime, but the conception of theft as a crime is not one belonging
                    to the earliest stage of law. To its latest period Roman law regarded theft <hi
                        rend="italic">(furtum)</hi> as a delict <hi rend="italic">prima facie</hi>
                    pursued by a civil remedy,—the <hi rend="italic">actio furti</hi> for a penalty,
                    the <hi rend="italic">vindicatio</hi> or <hi rend="italic">condictio</hi> for
                    the stolen property itself or its value. In later times, no doubt, a criminal
                    remedy to meet the graver crimes gradually grew up by the side of the civil, and
                    in the time of Justinian the criminal remedy, where it existed, took precedence
                    of the civil (CW., iii. 8, 4). But to the last criminal proceedings could only
                    be taken in serious cases, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> against stealers of
                    cattle <hi rend="italic">(abigei)</hi> or the clothes of bathers <hi
                        rend="italic">(balnearii).</hi> The punishment was death, banishment, or
                    labour in the mines or on public works. In the main the Roman law of theft
                    coincides with the English law. The definition as given in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Institutes</hi> (iv. 1, 1) is “furtum est contrectatio rei fraudulosa, vel
                    ipsius rei, vel etiam ejus usus possessionisve,” to which the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Digest</hi> (xlvii. 2, 1, 3) adds “lucrifaciendi gratia.” The earliest
                    English definition, that of Bracton (150δ), runs thus: “furtum est secundum
                    leges contrectatio rei alienae fraudulenta cum animo furandi invito illo domino
                    cujus res illa fuerit.” Bracton omits the “lucri faciendi gratia” of the Roman
                    definition, because in English law the motive is immaterial,<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Thus destruction of a
                            letter by a servant, with a view of suppressing inquiries into her
                            character, makes the servant guilty of larceny in English
                        law.</p></note> and the “usus ejus possessionisve,” because the definition
                    includes an intent to deprive the owner of his property permanently. The “animo
                    furandi” and “invito domino” of Bracton’s definition are expansions for the sake
                    of greater clearness. They seem to have been implied in Roman law. <hi
                        rend="italic">Furtum</hi> is on the whole a more comprehensive term than
                    theft. This difference no doubt arises from the tendency to extend the bounds of
                    a delict and to limit the bounds of a crime. Thus it was <hi rend="italic"
                        >furtum</hi> (but it would not be theft at English common law) to use a
                    deposit of pledge contrary to the wishes of the owner, to retain goods found, or
                    to steal a human being, such as a slave or <hi rend="italic">filius
                        familias</hi> (a special form of <hi rend="italic">furtum</hi> called <hi
                        rend="italic">plagium).</hi> The latter would be in English law an abduction
                    under certain circumstances, but not a theft. On the other hand, one of two
                    married persons could not commit <hi rend="italic">furtum</hi> as against the
                    other, but theft may be so committed in England since recent legislation. As a
                        <hi rend="italic">furtum</hi> was merely a delict, the οόΖψαίιο <hi
                        rend="italic">ex delicto</hi> could be extinguished by agreement between the
                    parties; it will be seen that this cannot be done in England. In another
                    direction English law is more considerate of the rights of third parties than
                    was Roman. As will appear hereafter, the thief can give a good title to stolen
                    goods; in Roman law he could not do so, except in the single case of a <hi
                        rend="italic">hereditas</hi> acquired by <hi rend="italic">usucapio.</hi>
                    The development of the law of <hi rend="italic">furtum</hi> at Rome is
                    historically interesting, for even in its latest period is found a relic of one
                    of the most primitive theories of law adopted by courts of justice: “They took
                    as their guide the measure of vengeance likely to be exacted by an aggrieved
                    person under the circumstances of the case” (Maine, <hi rend="italic">Ancient
                        Law,</hi> ch. x.). This explains the reason of the division of <hi
                        rend="italic">furtum</hi> into <hi rend="italic">manifestum</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">nec manifestum.</hi> The manifest thief was one taken
                    red-handed,—“taken with the manner,” in the language of old English law. The
                    Twelve Tables denounced the punishment of death against the manifest thief, for
                    that w ould be the penalty demanded by the indignant owner in whose place the
                    judge stood. The severity of this penalty was afterwards mitigated by the
                    praetor, who substituted for it the payment of quadruple the value of the thing
                    stolen. The same penalty was also given by the praetor in case of theft from a
                    fire or a wreck, or of prevention of search. No doubt the object of this large
                    penalty was to induce injured persons to refrain from taking the law into their
                    own hands. The Twelve Tables mulcted the non-manifest thief in double the value
                    of the thing stolen. The actions for penalties were in addition to the action
                    for the stolen goods themselves or their value. The quadruple and double
                    penalties still remain in the legislation of Justinian. The search for stolen
                    goods, as it existed in the time of Gaius, was a survival of a period when the
                    injured person was, as in the case of summons <hi rend="italic">(in jus
                        vocatio),</hi> his own executive officer. Such a search, by the Twelve
                    Tables, might be conducted in the house of the supposed thief by the owner in
                    person, naked except for a cincture, and carrying a platter in his hand,
                    safeguards apparently against a violation of decency and against any possibility
                    of his making a false charge by depositing some of his own property on his
                    neighbour’s premises. This mode of search became obsolete before the time of
                    Justinian. Robbery <hi rend="italic">(bona vi rapta)</hi> was violence added to
                        <hi rend="italic">furtum.</hi> By the <hi rend="italic">actio vi bonorum
                        raptorum</hi> quadruple the value could be recovered if the action were
                    brought within a year, only the value if brought after the expiration of a year.
                    The quadruple value, it is to be noted, included the stolen thing itself, so
                    that the penalty was in effect only a triple one. It was inclusive, and not
                    cumulative, as in <hi rend="italic">furtum.</hi></p>
                <p>In England theft appears to have been very early regarded by legislators as a
                    matter calling for special attention. The pre-Conquest compilations of laws are
                    full of provisions on the subject. It is noticeable that the earlier ones appear
                    to regard theft as a delict which may be compounded for by payment. Considerable
                    distinctions of person are made, both in regard to the owner and the thief.
                    Thus, by the laws of Ethelbert, if a freeman stole from the king he was to
                    restore ninefold, if from a freeman or from a dwelling threefold. If a theow
                    stole, he had only to make a twofold reparation. In the laws of Alfred ordinary
                    theft was still only civil, but he who stole in a church was punished by the
                    loss of his hand. The laws of Ina named as the penalty death or redemption
                        accoτd-ing<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n249/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0249-0232"/> to the wer-gild of the thief. By the same
                    laws the thief might be slain if he fled or resisted. Gradually the severity of
                    the punishment increased. By the laws of Athelstan death in a very cruel form
                    was inflicted. At a later date the <hi rend="italic">Leges Henrici Primi</hi>
                    placed a thief in the king’s mercy, and his lands were forfeited. Putting out
                    the eyes and other kinds of mutilation were sometimes the punishment. The
                    principle of severity continued down to the present century, and until 1827
                    theft of certain kinds remained capital. Both before and after the Conquest
                    local jurisdiction over thieves was a common franchise of lords of manors,
                    attended with some of the advantages of modern summary jurisdiction. It might be
                    exercised either over thieves who committed a theft or were apprehended within
                    the lordship <hi rend="italic">(infangthef),</hi> or over those inhabitants of
                    the lordship who were apprehended elsewhere <hi rend="italic"
                        >(outfaηgthef).</hi> Either or both franchises might be enjoyed by grant or
                    prescription. As lately as 1 Ph. and M. c. 15 infangthef and outfangthef were
                    confirmed to the lords marchers of Wales. An analogous franchise was <hi
                        rend="italic">theam,</hi> or the right of calling upon the holder of stolen
                    goods to vouch to warranty, t.e., to name from w hom he received them. In the
                    old law of theft there were to be found two interesting survivals of the
                    primitive legal notions which were found in Roman law. Up to a comparatively
                    recent date a distinction analogous to that between <hi rend="italic">furtum
                        manifestum</hi> and <hi rend="italic">nec manifestum</hi> was of importance
                    in English criminal practice. The thief “taken with the manner” was by the
                    Statute of Westminster the First not to be admitted to bail (see <hi
                        rend="italic">Letters of Junius,</hi> lxviii.). In modern procedure the
                    probable guilt or innocence of the accused is not so much to be considered in a
                    question of bail as the probability of his appearance at the trial. The other
                    matter worthy of notice is the old pursuit <hi rend="italic">(secta)</hi> by hue
                    and cry. In the pre-Conquest codes the owner was generally allowed to take the
                    law into his own hand, as in early Roman law, and get back his goods by force if
                    he could, no doubt with the assistance of his neighbours where possible. From
                    this arose the later development of the hue and cry, as the recognized means of
                    pursuing a thief. The Statutes of Westminster the First and of <hi rend="italic"
                        >De officio coronatoris</hi> enacted that all men should be ready to pursue
                    and arrest felons, and ten years later the Statute of Winchester (1285) enforced
                    upon all the duty of keeping arms for the purpose of following the hue and cry.
                    It also made the hundred liable for thefts with violence committed in it, an
                    adoption no doubt in feudal law of the old pre-Conquest liability of the
                    frith-borg. As justice became more settled, the hue and cry was regulated more
                    and more by law, and lost much of its old natural simplicity. This led to its
                    gradually becoming obsolete, though the Statutes of Westminster the First and
                        <hi rend="italic">De officio coronatoris</hi> are still nominally law as far
                    as they relate to the hue and cry. The Statute of Winchester as to the liability
                    of the hundred was repealed in 1827.</p>
                <p>The term theft in modern English law is sometimes used as a synonym of larceny,
                    sometimes in a more comprehensive sense. In the latter sense it is used by Mr
                    Justice Stephen, who defines it as “the act of dealing from any motive whatever,
                    unlawfully and without claim of right, with anything capable of being stolen, in
                    any of the ways in which theft can be committed” (for which see § 296—300),
                    “with the intention of permanently converting that thing to the use of any
                    person other than the general or special owner thereof” <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Digest of the Criminal Law,</hi> § 295). In this broader sense the term
                    applies to all cases of depriving another of his property, whether by removing
                    or withholding it. It thus includes larceny, robbery, cheating, embezzlement,
                    and breach of trust. Embezzlement is a statutory crime created as a separate
                    form of offence in the last century (see vol. viii. p. 159). The difference
                    between larceny and embezzlement turns mainly on the fact of the master’s being
                    in actual or constructive possession of the stolen property (see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Possession).</hi> Fraudulent breach of trust was not made a
                    specific offence until 1857 (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Trust).</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Larceny</hi> (a corruption of <hi rend="italic"
                        >latrocinium),</hi> or theft proper, was felony at common law. The common
                    law of larceny has been affected by numerous statutes, the main object of
                    legislation being to bring within the law of larceny offences which were not
                    larcenies at common law, either because they were thefts of things of which
                    there could be no larceny at common law, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> beasts <hi
                        rend="italic">ferae nativrae,</hi> title deeds, or choses inaction, or
                    because the common law regarded them merely as delicts for which the remedy was
                    by civil action, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> fraudulent breaches of trust. The
                    earliest Act in the statutes of the realm dealing with larceny appears to be the
                        <hi rend="italic">Carta Forestae</hi> of 1225, by which line or imprisonment
                    was inflicted for stealing the king’s deer. The next Act appears to be the
                    Statute of Westminster the First (1275), dealing again with stealing deer. From
                    this it seems as though the beginning of legislation on the subject was for the
                    purpose of protecting the chases and parks of the king and the nobility. An
                    immense mass of the old Acts will be found named in the repealing Act of 1827, 7
                    and 8 Geo. IV. c. 27. An Act of the same date, 7 and 8 Geo. IV. c. 29, removed
                    the old distinction between grand and petit larceny.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This provision was most unnecessarily
                            repeated in the Larceny Act of 1861.</p></note> The former was theft of
                    goods above the value of twelve pence, in the house of the owner, not from the
                    person, or by night, and was a capital crime. It was petit larceny where the
                    value was twelve pence or under, the punishment being imprisonment or whipping.
                    The gradual depreciation in the value of money afforded good ground for Sir
                    Henry Spelman’s sarcasm that, while everything else became dearer, the life of
                    man became continually cheaper. The distinction between grand and petit larceny
                    first appears in statute law in the Statute of Westminster the First, c. 15,
                    but-it was not created for the first time by that statute. It is found in some
                    of the pre-Conquest codes, as that of Athelstan, and it is recognized in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Leges Henrici Primi.</hi> A distinction between simple and
                    compound larceny is still found in the books. The latter is larceny accompanied
                    by circumstances of aggravation, as that it is in a dwellinghouse or from the
                    person. The law of larceny is now contained chiefly in the Larceny Act, 1861, 24
                    and 25 Vict. c. 96 (which extends to England and Ireland), a comprehensive
                    enactment including larceny, embezzlement, fraud by bailees, agents, bankers,
                    factors, and trustees, sacrilege, burglary, housebreaking, robbery, obtaining
                    money by threats or by false pretences, and receiving stolen goods, and
                    prescribing procedure, both civil and criminal. There are still, however, some
                    earlier Acts in force dealing with special cases of larceny, such as 33 Hen.
                    VIII. c. 12, as to stealing the goods of the king, and the Game, Post-Office,
                    and Merchant Shipping Acts. Later Acts provide for larceny by a partner of
                    partnership property (31 and 32 Vict. c. 116), and by a husband or wife of the
                    property of the other (45 and 46 Vict. c. 75). Proceedings against persons
                    subject to naval or military law depend upon the Naval Discipline Act, 1866, and
                    the Army Act, 1881. There are several Acts, both before and after 1861,
                    directing how the property is to be laid in indictments for stealing the goods
                    of counties, friendly societies, trades unions, &amp;c. The principal conditions
                    which must exist in order to constitute larceny are these :— (1) there must be
                    an actual taking into the possession of the thief, though the smallest removal
                    is sufficient; (2) there must be an intent to deprive the owner of his property
                    for an indefinite period, and to assume the entire dominion over it, an intent
                    often described in Bracton’s words as <hi rend="italic">animus furandi</hi>; (3)
                    this intent must exist at the time of taking; (4) the thing taken must be one
                    capable of larceny either at common law or by statute. One or two cases falling
                    under the law of larceny are of special interest. It was held more than once
                    that a servant taking corn for the purpose of feeding his master’s horses, but
                    without any intention of applying it for his own benefit, was guilty of larceny.
                    To remedy this hardship, 26 and 27 Vict. c. 103 was passed to declare such an
                    act not to be felony. The case of appropriation of goods which have been found
                    has led to some difficulty. It now seems to be the law that in order to
                    constitute a larceny of lost goods there must be a felonious intent at the time
                    of finding, that is, an intent to deprive the owner of them, coupled with
                    reasonable means at the same time of knowing the owner. The mere retention of
                    the goods when the owner has become known to the finder does not make the
                    retention criminal. Larceny of money may be committed when the money is paid by
                    mistake, if the prisoner took it <hi rend="italic">animo furandi.</hi> In two
                    recent cases the question was argued before a very full Court for Crown Cases
                    Reserved, and in each case there was a striking difference of opinion. In Reg.
                        <hi rend="italic">υ.</hi> Middleton, <hi rend="italic">Law Rep.,</hi> 2
                    Crown <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n250/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0250-0233"/> Cases Reserved, 38, the prisoner, a depositor
                    in a post-office savings bank, received by the mistake of the clerk a larger sum
                    than he was entitled to. The jury found that he had the <hi rend="italic">animus
                        furandi</hi> at the time of taking the money, and that he knew it to be the
                    money of the postmaster-general. The majority of the court held it to be
                    larceny. In a case in 1885 (Reg. <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Ashwell, <hi
                        rend="italic">Law Rep.,</hi> 16 Queen’s Bench Division, 190), where the
                    prosecutor gave the prisoner a sovereign believing it to be a shilling, and the
                    prisoner took it under that belief, but afterwards discovered its value and
                    retained it, the court was equally divided as to whether the prisoner was guilty
                    of larceny at common law, but held that he was not guilty of larceny as a
                    bailee. The procedure in prosecutions for larceny has been considerably affected
                    by recent legislation. The inconveniences of the common-law rules of
                    interpretation of indictments led to certain amendments of the law, now
                    contained in the Larceny Act, for the purpose of avoiding the frequent failures
                    of justice owing to the strictness with which indictments were construed. Three
                    larcenies of property of the same person within six months may now be charged in
                    one indictment. On an indictment for larceny the prisoner may be found guilty of
                    embezzlement, and <hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi>; and if the prisoner be
                    indicted for obtaining goods by false pretences, and the offence turn out to be
                    larceny, he is not entitled to be acquitted of the misdemeanour. A count for
                    receiving may be joined with the count for stealing. In many cases it is
                    unnecessary to allege or prove ownership of the property the subject of the
                    indictment. The Act also contains numerous provisions as to venue and the
                    apprehension of offenders. In another direction the powers of courts of <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Summary Jurisdiction</hi> (y.v.) have been extended, in the
                    case of charges of larceny, embezzlement, and receiving stolen goods, against
                    children and young persons and against adults pleading guilty or waiving their
                    right to trial by jury. The maximum punishment for larceny is fourteen years’
                    penal servitude, but this can only be inflicted in certain exceptional cases,
                    such as horse or cattle stealing and larceny by a servant or a person in the
                    service of the crown or the police. The extreme punishment for simple larceny
                    after a previous conviction for felony is ten years’ penal servitude. . Whipping
                    may be part of the sentence on boys under sixteen.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Robbery</hi> is larceny accompanied by violence or threatened
                    violence. "Whether obtaining money by threats to accuse of crime was robbery at
                    common law was open to some doubt. It is now a specific offence under the
                    Larceny Act, punishable by penal servitude for life. Whipping may be added as
                    part of the sentence for robbery by 26 and 27 Vict. c. 44.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Cheating</hi> is either a common-law or statutory offence. An
                    indictment for cheating at common law is now of comparatively rare occurrence.
                    The statutory crime of obtaining money by false Pretences is the form in which
                    the offence generally presents itself.</p>
                <p>∣ike embezzlement, this offence dates as a statutory crime from the last century.
                    It now depends upon the Larceny Act. A false pretence is defined by Mr Justice
                    Stephen as “a false representation made either by words, by writing, or by
                    conduct that some fact or facts existed” <hi rend="italic">(Digest of the
                        Criminal Law,</hi> § 330). The principal points to notice are that the false
                    pretence must be of an existing fact <hi rend="italic">(e.g.,</hi> it was held
                    not to be a false pretence to promise to pay for goods on delivery), and that
                    property must have been actually obtained by the false pretence. The broad
                    distinction between this offence and larceny is that in the former the owner
                    intends to part with his property, in the latter he does not. By 22 and 23 Vict.
                    c. 17, no indictment for obtaining money by false pretences is to be presented
                    or found by the grand jury unless the defendant has been committed for trial or
                    the indictment is authorized in one of the ways mentioned in the Act. The
                    maximum punishment for the common-law offence is fine or imprisonment at
                    discretion, for the statutory five years’ penal servitude.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Stolen Goods.—</hi> The owner of the goods stolen has an action
                    against the thief for the goods or their value. How far he is entitled to pursue
                    his civil right to the exclusion of criminal prosecution does not seem very
                    clear upon the authorities. One of the latest statements of the law was that of
                    Mr Justice Watkin Williams :—“It has been said that the true principle of the
                    common law is that there is neither a merger of the civil right, nor is it a
                    strict condition precedent to such right that there shall have been a
                    prosecution of the felon, but that there is a duty imposed upon the injured
                    person not to resort to the prosecution of his private suit to the neglect and
                    exclusion of the vindication of the public law; in my opinion this view is the
                    correct one” (Midland Insurance Company <hi rend="italic">v.</hi> Smith, <hi
                        rend="italic">Law Rep.,</hi> 6 Queen’s Bench Division, 568). Dealing with
                    stolen goods by persons other than the thief may affect the rights of such
                    persons either criminally or civilly. Two varieties of crime arise from such
                    dealings. (1) Receiving stolen goods knowing them to have been stolen, a
                    misdemeanour at common law, is by the Larceny Act a felony punishable by penal
                    servitude for fourteen years where the theft amounts to felony, a misdemeanour
                    punishable by penal servitude for seven years where the theft is a misdemeanour,
                    as in obtaining goods by false pretences. Recent possession of stolen property
                    may, according to circumstances, support the presumption that the prisoner is a
                    thief or that he is a receiver. The Prevention of Crime Act, 1871, made
                    important changes in the law of evidence in charges of receiving. It allows,
                    under proper safeguards, evidence to be given in the course of the trial of the
                    finding of other stolen property in the possession of the accused, and of a
                    previous conviction for any offence involving fraud and dishonesty. (2)
                    Compounding theft, or theftbote, that is, taking back stolen goods or receiving
                    compensation on condition of not prosecuting, is a misdemeanour at common law.
                    It need not necessarily be committed by the owner of the goods. Under the
                    Larceny Act it is a felony punishable by seven years’ penal servitude to
                    corruptly take money or reward for helping to recover stolen goods without using
                    all due diligence to bring the offender to trial. By the same Act, to advertise
                    or print or publish any advertisement offering a reward for the return of stolen
                    goods, and using any words purporting that no questions will be asked, &amp;c.,
                    renders the offender liable to a penalty of £50. This penalty must, by 33 and 34
                    Vict. c. 65, be sued for within six months, and the assent of the
                    attorney-general is necessary. Various Acts provide for the liabilities of
                    pawnbrokers, publicans, marine-store dealers, and others into whose possession
                    stolen goods come. Search for stolen goods can only be undertaken by a police
                    officer under the protection of a search warrant. The law as to stolen goods, as
                    far as it affects the civil rights and liabilities of the owner and third
                    parties, is shortly as follows. As a general rule a purchaser takes goods
                    subject to any infirmities of title. The property in money, bank-notes, and
                    negotiable instruments passes by delivery, and a person taking any of these <hi
                        rend="italic">bona fide</hi> and for value is entitled to retain it as
                    against a former owner from whom it may have been stolen. In the case of other
                    goods, a <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> purchaser of stolen goods in market
                    overt (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Sale)</hi> obtains a good title (except as
                    against the crown), provided that the thief has not been convicted. After
                    conviction of the thief the property revests in the owner, and the court before
                    which the thief was convicted may order restitution, except in the cases
                    specially mentioned in the Larceny Act, i.e., the <hi rend="italic">bona
                        fide</hi> discharge or transfer of a security for value without notice and
                    the fraudulent dealing by a trustee, banker, &amp;c., with goods and documents
                    of title to goods entrusted to him. After conviction of the thief the goods must
                    be recovered from the person in whose hands they are at the time of the
                    conviction, for any sales and resales, if the first sale was in market overt,
                    are good until conviction of the thief. If the goods were obtained by false
                    pretences and not by larceny, the question then is whether the property in the
                    goods has passed or not, and the answer to this question depends upon the nature
                    of the false pretences employed. If the vendee obtains possession of goods with
                    the intention by the vendor to transfer both the property and the possession,
                    the property vests in the vendee until the vendor has done some act to disaffirm
                    the transaction. But if there was never any such intention,—if, for instance,
                    the vendor delivers the goods to A. B. under the belief that he is C. D.,—the
                    property does not vest in the transferee, and the owner may recover the goods
                    even from a <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> purchaser.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For the Roman and English law, see,
                            besides the authorities cited. Hunter, <hi rend="italic">Roman Law</hi>;
                            Muirhead, <hi rend="italic">Roman Law</hi>; 4 Stephen, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Commentaries,</hi> pt. vi. chap. v.; 3 Stephen, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Hist, of the Criminal Law,</hi> chap, xxviii.</p></note><hi
                        rend="italic">Scotland.—</hi> There is a vast quantity of Acts of the
                    Scottish parliament dealing with theft. The general policy of the Acts was to
                    make thefts what were not thefts at common law, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi>
                    stealing fruit, dogs, hawks, or deer, and to extend the remedies, <hi
                        rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> by giving the justiciar authority throughout the
                    kingdom, by making the master in the case of theft by the servant liable to give
                    the latter up to justice, or by allowing the use of firearms against thieves.
                    The general result of legislation in England and Scotland has been to assimilate
                    the law of theft in both kingdoms. As a rule, what would be theft in one would
                    be theft in the other. There can be theft of children in Scots as in Roman law,
                    under the name of <hi rend="italic">plagium.</hi> The crime of stouthrief is
                    robbery accompanied by exceptional violence. The English receiving stolen goods
                    and obtaining money under false pretences are represented by the reset and fraud
                    of Scots law. Theftbote or <hi rend="italic">redemptio furti</hi> appears in
                    legislation as early as the assizes of King William, c. 2. The offender was
                    there subjected to the ordeal of water if convicted on the oath of three
                    witnesses, to be immediately hanged if the oath of three <hi rend="italic"
                        >seniores</hi> were added. The offence was made punishable by 1436, c. 1,
                    1515, c. 2, and appears still to be a crime. Blackmailing, under that name, was
                    forbidden by 1567, c. 27. There is no consolidation Act for Scotland like the
                    Larceny Act for England and Ireland, but various Acts are in force dealing with
                    specific offences or with procedure. Thus 7 Anne c. 21, § 7, makes theft by
                    landed men no longer treason, as it had previously been. 4 Geo. II. c. 32 deals
                    with theft of lead, &amp;c., fixed to houses, 21 Geo. II. c. 34 with the
                    admissibility of an accomplice as witness in a charge of cattle stealing, 51
                    Geo. III. c. 41 with theft of linen, &amp;c. The most important Act relating to
                    procedure is 31 and 32 Viet c. 95, § 12, by which a previous conviction for
                    theft may be libelled and proved as aggravation of robbery, and a <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n251/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0251-0234"/> previous conviction for robbery as
                    aggravation of theft. Stolen goods are always taken subject to the inherent <hi
                        rend="italic">vitium reale</hi> of their acquisition, and the true owner may
                    recover them from any one in whose possession they are. The protection given by
                    market overt is unknown in Scotland. See Macdonald, <hi rend="italic">Criminal
                        Law,</hi> p. 18.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">United States.—</hi> The law depends almost entirely upon State
                    legislation, and is in general accordance with that of England. The only Acts of
                    Congress bearing on the subject deal with theft in the army and navy, and with
                    theft and receiving on the high seas or in any place under the exclusive
                    jurisdiction of the United States. The doctrine of market overt is not
                    acknowledged by any State. (J. w+.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
