<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0418-0399-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">TIMUR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 399</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:829774">Bees</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1084263">Purchasing</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn2p">Bees</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w08wh24">Portraits</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jq8p">Purchasers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n418/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TIMUR</label>. <hi rend="smallcaps">Timur Bey</hi> or <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Timur Lang</hi><hi rend="italic">lfTimur i Leng</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">∖</hi> “the lame Timur’’—vulgarized into <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Tamerlane</hi> —the renowned Oriental conqueror, was born in 1336 at Kesh,
                    better known as Shahr-i-Sabz, “the green city,” situated some 50 miles south of
                    Samarkand in Transoxiana. His father Teragai was head of the tribe of Berlas.
                    Great-grandson of Karachar Nevian (minister of Jagatai, son of Jenghiz Khan, and
                    commander-in-chief of his forces), and distinguished among his fellow-clansmen
                    as the first convert to Islamism, Teragai might have assumed the high military
                    rank which fell to him by right of inheritance; but like his father Burkul he
                    preferred a life of retirement and study. Under the paternal eye the education
                    of young Timúr was such that at the age of twenty he had not only become an
                    adept in manly outdoor exercises but had earned the reputation of being an
                    attentive reader of the Koran. At this period, if we may credit the <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs (Malfúzáfj,</hi> he exhibited proofs of a tender and
                    sympathetic nature.</p>
                <p>About 1358, however, he came before the world as a leader of armies. His career
                    for the next ten or eleven years may be thus briefly summarized from the <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoirs.</hi> Allying himself both in cause and by family
                    connexion with Kurgan, the dethroner and destroyer of Kezan, chief of the
                    Jagatai, he was deputed to invade Khorasan at the head of a thousand horse. This
                    was the second warlike expedition in which he was the chief actor, and the
                    accomplishment of its objects led to further operations, among them the
                    subjection of Khwarizm and Urganj. After the murder of Kurgan the contentions
                    which arose among the many claimants to sovereign power were arrested by the
                    invasion of Tughlak Timúr of Kashgar, a descendant of Jenghiz. Timúr was
                    despatched on a mission to the invader’s camp, the result of which was his own
                    appointment to the government of Máwará’lnahr (Transoxiana). By the death of his
                    father he was also left hereditary head of the Berlas. The exigencies of his
                    quasi-sovereign position compelled him to have recourse to his formidable
                    patron, whose reappearance on the banks of the Sihon created a consternation not
                    easily allayed. Máwará’lnahr was taken from Timúr and entrusted to a son of
                    Tughlak; but he was defeated in battle by the bold warrior he had replaced at
                    the head of a numerically far inferior force. Tughlak’s death facilitated the
                    work of reconquest, and a few years of perseverance and energy sufficed for its
                    accomplishment, as well as for the addition of a vast extent of territory.
                    During this period Timúr and his brother-in-law, Hosain—at first
                    fellow-fugitives and wanderers in joint adventures full of interest and romance—
                    became rivals and antagonists. At the close of 1369 Hosain was assassinated and
                    Timúr, having been formally proclaimed sovereign at Balkh, mounted the throne at
                    Samarkand, the capital of his dominions.</p>
                <p>The next thirty years or so were spent in various wars and expeditions. He not
                    only consolidated his rule at home by the subjection of intestine foes, but
                    sought extension of territory by encroachments upon the lands of contemporary
                    potentates. His conquests to the west and north-west led him among the Mongols
                    of the Caspian, and to the banks of the Ural and the Volga; those to the south
                    and south-west comprehended almost every province in Persia, including Baghdad,
                    Kerbela, and Kurdistan. To this time belong the vestiges of his presence that
                    still remain, such as the ruined monastery at Keghut near the Aras (Araxes), the
                    cleft stone in the church at Dayiru Ί-Omar (M’ar Jibráil) near Mardin, and the
                    ruinless sites of such ancient cities as Zaranj in Sistan. In 1398, when Timúr
                    was more than sixty years of age, Farishta tells us that, “informed of the
                    commotions and civil wars of India,” he “began his expedition into that
                    country,” and on 12th September “arrived on the banks of the Indus.” His passage
                    of the river and upward march along the left bank, the reinforcement he provided
                    for his grandson Pir Mohammed (who was invested in Multán), the capture of towns
                    or villages accompanied, it might be, with destruction of the houses and the
                    massacre of the inhabitants, the battle before Delhi and the easy victory, the
                    triumphal entry into the doomed city, with its outcome of horrors,— all these
                    circumstances belong to the annals of India. In April 1399, some three months
                    after quitting the capital of Mahmúd Tughla⅛, Timúr was back in his own capital
                    beyond the Oxus. It need scarcely be added that an immense quantity of spoil was
                    conveyed away. According to Clavijo, ninety captured elephants were employed
                    merely to carry stones from certain quarries to enable the conqueror to erect a
                    mosque at Samarkand. The war with the Turks which succeeded the return from
                    India was rendered notable by the capture of Baghdad, Aleppo, and Damascus, and
                    especially by the defeat and imprisonment of Sultan Bayazid. This was Timúr’s
                    last campaign. Another was projected against China, but the old warrior was
                    attacked by fever and ague when encamped on the further side of the Sihon
                    (Syr-Daria) and died at Atrár (Otrar) on the 17th February 1405. Markham, in his
                    introduction to the narrative of Clavijo’s embassy, states that his body “was
                    embalmed with musk and rose water, wrapped in linen, laid in an ebony coffin,
                    and sent to Samarkand, where it was buried.” Timur had carried his victorious
                    arms on one side from the Irtish and the Volga to the Persian Gulf and on the
                    other from the Hellespont to the Ganges.</p>
                <p>Timúr’s generally recognized biographers are—'Alí Yazdí, commonly called Sharifu
                    ’ d-Din, author of the Persian <hi rend="italic">Zafarnáma,</hi> translated by
                    Petis de la Croix in 1722, and from French into English by J. Darby in the
                    following year; and Ahmed ibn Mohammed ibn Abdallah, al Dimashki, al ’ Ajmi,
                    commonly called Ibn 'Arabsháh, author of the Arabic <hi rend="italic"
                    >'Ajaibu</hi><hi rend="italic">Ί</hi><hi rend="italic">ΜakhlnkAt,</hi>
                    translated by the Dutch Orientalist Golius in 1636. In the work of the former,
                    as Sir William Jones remarks, “the Tartarian conqueror is represented as a
                    liberal, benevolent, and illustrious prince”; in that of the latter he is
                    “deformed and impious, of a low birth and detestable principles.” But the
                    favourable account was written.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n419/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0419-0400"/>
                <p>under the personal supervision of Tinrúr’s grandson, Ibráhim, while the other was
                    the production of his direst enemy. Few indeed, if any, original annals of this
                    class are written otherwise than to order, under patronage, or to serve a
                    purpose to which truth is secondary. Among less reputed biographies or materials
                    for biography may be mentioned a second <hi rend="italic">Zafarnáma,</hi> by
                    Mauláná Nizámu ’ d-Din Shanab Gházáni (Nizam Shámí), stated to be “the earliest
                    known history of Timúr, and the only one written in his lifetime”; and vol. i.
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Matla'u’s·Sa'dain—</hi> a choice Persian MS. work of
                    1495—introduced to Orientalists in Europe by Hammer, Jahrbücher, Dorn, and
                    (notably) Quatremère. There are also the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs
                    {Malfúzát)</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Institutes (Tuzukát'),</hi> of which an
                    important section is styled <hi rend="italic">Designs and Enterprises ( Tadbírát
                    wa Kangàshaháj</hi> Upon the genuineness of these doubt has been thrown. The
                    circumstance of their alleged discovery and presentation to Shah Jahán in 1637
                    was of itself open to suspicion. Alhazen, quoted by Purchas in his quaint notice
                    of Timúr, and referred to by Sir John Malcolm, can hardly be accepted as a
                    serious authority. His assumed memoir was printed for English readers in 1597 by
                    William Ponsonby under the title of a <hi rend="italic">Historie</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">of the Great Emperor Tamerlan, drawn from the ancient monuments by
                    Messire Jean du Bee, Abbot of Mortimer;</hi> and another version of the same
                    book is to be found in the <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">du
                    Grand Tamerlan,</hi> by De Sainctyon, published at Amsterdam in 1678. But,
                    although the existence of this Alhazen of Jean de Bee has been believed by many,
                    the more trustworthy critics consider the history and historian to be equally
                    fictitious.</p>
                <p>Reference may be made to two more sources of information. (1) Supposed likenesses
                    of Timúr are to be found in books and in the splendid collection of Oriental
                    manuscripts and drawings in the British Museum. One contained in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Shah Jahán Náma—</hi> a gorgeous specimen of illuminated Persian
                    manuscript and exquisite caligraphy—represents a most ordinary, middle-aged
                    Oriental, with narrow black whisker fringing the cheek and meeting the tip of
                    the chin in a scanty, pointed beard; a thin moustache sweeps in a semicircle
                    from above the upper lip; the eyebrow over the almond-shaped eye is marked but
                    not bushy. But it were vain to seek for an expression of genius in the
                    countenance. Another portrait is included in a set of sketches by native
                    artists, some of which, taken probably from life, show great care and
                    cleverness. Timúr is here displayed as a stoutish, long-bodied man, below the
                    middle-height, in age and feature not unlike the first portrait, but with
                    thicker and more straggling hair, and distincter, though not more agreeable
                    character in the facial expression, yet not a sign of power, genius, or any
                    elements of grandeur or celebrity. The uncomfortable figure in the Bodleian
                    Library does not give much help. Sir John Malcolm has been at some pains to
                    invest his portrait of Timúr with individuality. But an analysis of his results
                    leaves the reader in more perplexity than satisfaction at the kind of
                    information imparted, and he reverts insensibly to the sources from which his
                    instructor has himself been instructed. (2) As regards plays, in Marlowe’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Tamburlaine</hi> Timúr is described as tall of stature, straightly
                    fashioned, large of limb, haring joints strongly knit, long and sinewy arms, a
                    breadth of shoulders to “bear old Atlas’s burden,” pale of complexion, and with
                    “amber hair wrapp’d in curls.” The outline of this description might be from
                    Sharifu ’d-Dín, while the colours are the poet’s own. A Latin memoir of
                    Tamerlane by Perendinus, printed in 1600, entitled <hi rend="italic">Magni
                    Tamerlanis Scytharum</hi><hi rend="italic">Imperatoris</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Vita,</hi> describes Timúr as tall and bearded, broad-chested and
                    broad-shouldered, well-built but lame, of a fierce countenance, and with
                    receding eyes, which express cruelty and strike terror into the lookers-on. But
                    Jean du Bee’s account of Timúr’s appearance is quite different. Now <hi
                    rend="italic">Tamburlaine</hi> was written in 1586. The first English
                    translation of Jean du Bee is dated in 1595, the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> by
                    Perendinus in 1600, and Petis de la Croix did not introduce Sharifu ’d-Dín or
                    'Ali Yazdí to European readers till 1722. The dramatist must have heard of Timúr
                    in other quarters, equally reliable it may be with those available in the
                    present stage of Oriental research. At the beginning of the 18th century Timúr
                    was represented in Rowe’s <hi rend="italic">Tamerlane</hi> as a model of valour
                    and virtue. The plot, however, has little to do with history, and is improbable
                    and void of interest. By Matthew Gregory Lewis again “Timour” is depicted as the
                    conventional tyrant of a gorgeous melodrama, slaying, burning, slaughtering, and
                    committing every possible atrocity until checked by violent death and a poetical
                    climax.</p>
                <p>Apart from modern European <hi rend="italic">savants</hi> and historians, and the
                    more strictly Oriental chroniclers who have written in Persian, Turkish, or
                    Arabic, the following authorities may be cited—Laonicus Chalcondylas, Joannes
                    Leunclavius, Joachimus Camerarius, Petrus Perondinus, Lazaro Soranzo, Simon
                    Mairlus, Matthew Michiovius. A score or so of other names are given by Samuel
                    Purchas. See also Clements Markham’s <hi rend="italic">Claνijo,</hi> in the
                    Hakluyt Society’s publications; White’s edition of Davy’s translation of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Institutes</hi> (1783); Stewart’s translation of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Malfúzát</hi>; Malcolm’s <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Persia·,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Trans. Roy. Soc.,</hi> 1885. (F. J. G.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
