<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0346-0329-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THUNDERSTORM (9th edition, volume 23, page 329)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:899352">Dues</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150494">Thunderstorms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864856">Clouds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139938">Swans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cr5nn0v">Swan</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gg1n">Clouds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n346/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THUNDERSTORM</label>. All the more ordinary phenomena of
                    thunderstorms had, about 1750, been conclusively traced to electrical charges
                    and discharges <hi rend="smallcaps">(Electricity,</hi> vol viii. p. 6), so that
                    they could easily be reproduced on a small scale in the laboratory. To the
                    article cited we therefore refer for their explanation. Some of the laws of
                    relative frequency of thunderstorms, in different places at the same season or
                    in the same place at different seasons, will be found in <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Meteorology</hi> (vol. xvi. p. 128). A discussion of the cause of thunder,
                    and of the circumstances which give rise to a crash, a roll, or a peal of
                    thunder is given under <hi rend="smallcaps">Acoustics</hi> (vol. i. p. 107). In
                    what follows, therefore, the rarer phenomena of thunderstorms, and the possible
                    sources of the atmospheric electricity, will be the chief points treated.</p>
                <p>There can be little doubt that atmospheric electricity, at least in the great
                    developments which characterize a thunderstorm, is due in some way to water.
                    Before a great thunderstorm the lower air is usually at an abnormally high
                    temperature, and fully saturated with water vapour, so that it is in a
                    thoroughly unstable condition. Immense cloud masses, often miles in vertical
                    thickness, which produce almost midnight darkness by day in the region of the
                    storm, and which appear, when seen from a distance, as if boiling upwards, are
                    always a notable feature of great thunderstorms. These are usually accompanied
                    by torrents of rain, or by violent hail-showers. And it is commonly observed
                    that each flash of lightning is followed, after a brief interval, by a sudden
                    but temporary increase in the rate of rainfall. At what stage of its
                    transformations the electrification is developed by water-substance is, as yet,
                    only guessed at,—though it seems most reasonable to conclude that it is anterior
                    to the formation of cloud, <hi rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> to the condensation of
                    vapour. And, though the idea was at one time very generally held and still has
                    many upholders, it seems unlikely to be the direct result of evaporation. For,
                    were it due directly either to evaporation or to condensation, it is almost
                    impossible to doubt that proof would long since have been furnished by careful
                    experiment, even if made on a scale so limited as that afforded by our
                    laboratories. No trace of electrical effect has been found to attend the
                    precipitation of moisture; and the electrical effects, sometimes considerable,
                    which have been found associated with evaporation have always been accompanied
                    by relatively violent physical and mechanical actions which are not observed in
                    conjunction with atmospheric electricity. It has been suggested by some
                    authorities that the electricity of a thunderstorm is developed during the
                    formation of hail, by others that it is due to the molecular actions which
                    accompany the diminution of total surface when two or more drops of water
                    coalesce into a single one. It has been ascribed to the friction of moist
                    against dry air, and to the dust-particles which appear to be necessary for the
                    condensation of vapour. Again, it has been suggested that it may be a mere
                    phenomenon of contact electricity, due to the impact of uncondensed vapour
                    particles on particles of air. It is almost unnecessary to observe that,
                    whatever hypothesis we adopt, some explanation must be given of two important
                    points :—(1) What becomes of the electricity equal and opposite to that in each
                    drop, which must be produced simultaneously with it <hi rend="italic">Ί</hi> (2)
                    By what means is the attraction between the drops and the recipient of the
                    opposite charge of electricity overcome so that the drops may be enabled to part
                    with their charge? It is to be presumed that gravity satisfies the second of
                    these questions. As to the first, it seems to necessitate the presence of
                    something besides water, in order that the electric separation may be commenced,
                    and thus appears to be fatal to the capillary theory indicated above. Whatever
                    be the true source of the charge, it is easy to see, by known properties of
                    electricity, that even an exceedingly small charge on each vapour particle would
                    lead to a very high potential as soon as a visible drop is formed, and that as a
                    drop increases in size its potential is proportional to its surface. That drops
                    of rain are often individually electrified to a very high potential is proved by
                    the frequent occurrence of “luminous rain,” when the ground is feebly lit up by
                    the multitude of tiny sparks given out by the drops as they come near it. The
                    flakes of falling snow, also, are often strongly electrified, so that smart
                    sparks have been drawn from an umbrella on which the snow was falling. But the
                    law of electric repulsion shows us at once that, as soon as the drops in a cloud
                    are sufficiently electrified, at least the greater part of their charge must
                    pass to the boundary of the cloud. When this occurs, the nature of the further
                    behaviour of the charge presents no difficulty. The reason for our singularly
                    complete ignorance of the source of atmospheric electricity seems to lie in the
                    fact that it can only be discovered by means of experiments made on a scale very
                    much larger than is attainable with the ordinary resources of a laboratory. The
                    difficulties will probably be easily overcome by the first nation which will go
                    to the expense of providing the necessary means.</p>
                <p>Numberless other explanations of the origin of thunderstorms have been suggested;
                    but the more reasonable of these do little more than shift the difficulty, for
                    they begin by assuming (without any hint as to its source) an electrification of
                    the earth as a whole, or of the lower (sometimes the upper) layers of the
                    atmosphere. Induction, convection, &amp;c., are then supposed to effect the
                    rest.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n347/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0347-0330"/>
                <p>Another and much less reasonable class of explanations depends upon
                    magneto-electricity. Some of these introduce the so-called “unipolar” induction
                    supposed to be due to the rotation of the earth, which behaves like a gigantic
                    magnet. Of this nature is the suggestion of Edlund, which was recently crowned
                    by the Academy of Sciences of Paris. That rapid variations in the earth’s
                    magnetic elements, such as often occur on a large scale, as in a “magnetic
                    storm,” have at least a share in the production of the aurora is a perfectly
                    reasonable and even plausible hypothesis, long ago brought forward by Balfour
                    Stewart. But we have yet to seek the source of these variations.</p>
                <p>The brightness of a flash of lightning is usually much underrated. It is true
                    that it rarely gives even at night an illumination greater than that due to
                    moonlight. But it must be remembered that Swan has proved that the impression of
                    a flash on the eye depends upon the duration, being nearly proportional to it,
                    and steadily increasing for about a tenth of a second. Now the duration of a
                    lightning-flash is (roughly speaking) only about one millionth of a second. This
                    is proved by the fact that the most rapidly rotating bodies appear to be
                    absolutely steady when illuminated by it. Hence, if it could be made to last for
                    a tenth of a second, it would give near objects an illumination one hundred
                    thousand times more brilliant than that of moonlight. It must be remembered that
                    the flash is not a mere line, but a column, of intensely heated air, driven
                    outwards from the track of the discharge at a rate initially far greater than
                    that of sound.</p>
                <p>What is called “summer lightning” or “wild-fire” is sometimes a rather puzzling
                    phenomenon. In the majority of cases it is merely the effect of a distant
                    thunderstorm. It is also often due to a thunderstorm in the higher strata of the
                    atmosphere overhead,—the reason why we hear no thunder being not so much the
                    distance from the spectator as the fact that sounds generated in rarer air lose
                    rapidly in intensity as they are propagated into denser air. But, besides these
                    more common forms of the phenomenon, there is certainly a form of sheet
                    lightning which occurs, without either sound or cloud, often close to the
                    spectator. The cause of this is not at all obvious.</p>
                <p>But the most mysterious phenomenon is what goes by the name of “globe lightning”
                    or “fire-ball,” a phenomenon lasting sometimes for several seconds, and
                    therefore of a totally different character from that of any other form of
                    lightning. The fire-ball is almost incomparably less brilliant than forked
                    lightning, because, though it lasts long enough to give the full impression of
                    its brightness, it is rarely brighter than iron in the state which we call
                    “red-hot.” It is always spherical, often more than a foot in diameter, and
                    appears to fall from a thunder-cloud by its own gravity, sometimes rebounding
                    after striking the ground. It usually bursts with a bright flash and a loud
                    explosion, occasionally discharging flashes of lightning. No experimenter has
                    yet succeeded in producing artificially anything resembling these natural and
                    intensely charged Leyden jars.</p>
                <p>The term “thunderbolt,” which is nowadays rarely used except by poets (and by the
                    penny-a-liners), preserves the old notion that something solid and intensely hot
                    passed along the track of a lightning flash and buried itself in the ground. Two
                    distinct classes of phenomena probably gave rise to this notion. When lightning
                    strikes the ground it often bores a hole of considerable depth, which is found
                    to be lined in its interior with vitrified sand. T <hi rend="underline">his</hi>
                    presents no difficulty. But <hi rend="smallcaps">Aerolites</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >{q.v.</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> y</hi><hi rend="italic">}</hi> are
                    often found, in the holes which they have made, still intensely hot, in
                    consequence of their rapid passage through the air. A hasty generalization seems
                    to have connected these two entirely independent phenomena, and thus given rise
                    to the notion of the thunderbolt. The ancient notion that a lightning flash
                    could occur in a clear sky is probably to be accounted for by the occasional
                    appearance of these ultramundane visitors.</p>
                <p>The sulphurous smell of lightning, which is vividly described in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Odyssey,</hi> is now known to be due to the formation of <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Ozone</hi> (g.v.).</p>
                <p>For the precautions necessary to prevent danger from a thunderstorm, see <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Lightning Conductor.</hi></p>
                <p>A whole volume of Arago’s collected works is devoted to thunderstorms, and many
                    important observations are to be found in the writings of Μ. D’Abbadie and other
                    scientific travellers. (P. G. T.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
