<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0090-0079-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">TASTE (9th edition, volume 23, page 79)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mh3x">Organ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40c4sr84">Smell</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nt76">Touch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047771">Organisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047777">Organization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1121562">Smell</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n90/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">TASTE</label> is the sensation referred to the mouth when
                    certain soluble substances are brought into contact with the mucous membrane of
                    that cavity. The sense is located almost entirely in the tongue. Three distinct
                    sensations are referable to the tongue—(1) taste, (2) touch, and (3)
                    temperature. The posterior part of its surface, where there is a Λ-shaped group
                    of large papillae, called circumvallate papillae, supplied by the
                    glosso-pharyngeal nerve, and the tip and margins of the tongue, covered with
                    filiform (touch) papillae and fungiform papillae, are the chief localities where
                    taste is manifested, but it also exists in the glosso-palatine arch and the
                    lateral part of the soft palate. The middle of the tongue and the surface of the
                    hard palate are devoid of taste. The terminal organs of taste consist of
                    peculiar bodies named taste-bulbs or tastegoblets, discovered by Schwalbe and
                    Lovèn in 1867. They can be most easily demonstrated in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >papiUae foliatae,</hi> large oval prominences found on each side near the
                    base of the tongue in the rabbit. Each papilla consists of a series of laminae
                    or folds, in the sides of which the tastebodies are readily displayed in a
                    transverse section. Tastebodies are also found on the lateral aspects of the
                    circumvallate papillae (see fig. 1), in the fungiform papillae, in the papillae
                    of the soft palate and uvula, the under surface of the epiglottis, the upper
                    part of the posterior surface of the epiglottis, the inner sides of the
                    arytenoid cartilages, and even in the vocal cords.</p>
                <p>The taste-bulbs are minute oval bodies, somewhat like an old-fashioned Florence
                    flask, about <hi rend="subscript"> π</hi> ⅞- <hi rend="subscript"> σ</hi> ∙ inch
                    in length by <hi rend="subscript"> κ</hi> ⅜ <hi rend="subscript"> γj</hi> ∙ in
                    breadth. Each consists of two sets of cells,—an <hi rend="italic">outer</hi>
                    set, nucleated, fusiform, bent like the staves of a barrel, and arranged side by
                    side so as to leave a small opening at the apex (the mouth of the barrel),
                    called the gustatory pore; and an <hi rend="italic">inner</hi> set, five to ten
                    in number, lying in the centre, pointed at the end next the gustatory pore, and
                    branched at the other extremity. The branched ends are continuous with
                    non-medullated nerve fibres from the gustatory nerve. These taste-bodies are
                    found in immense numbers: as many as 1760 have been counted on one circumvallate
                    papilla in the ox. They are absent in reptiles and birds. F. E. Schultze states
                    that they exist in the mouth of the tadpole, whilst the tongue of the frog is
                    covered with epithelium resembling that of the gustatory bodies. Leydig has
                    described organs having a similar structure in the skins of freshwater fishes
                    and the tadpole: these may possibly be widely distributed taste-organs. The
                    proofs that these are the terminal organs of taste rest on careful observations
                    which have shown (1) that taste is only experienced when the sapid substance is
                    allowed to come into contact with the taste-body, and that the sense <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n91/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0091-0080"/> is absent or much weakened in those areas of
                    mucous membrane where these are deficient; (2) that they are most abundant where
                    the sense is most acute; and (3) that section of the glosso-pharyngeal nerve
                    which is known to be distributed to the areas of mucous membrane where taste is
                    present is followed by degeneration of the tastebodies. At the same time it
                    cannot be asserted that they are absolutely essential to taste, as we can hardly
                    suppose that those animals which have no special taste-bodies are devoid of the
                    sense.</p>
                <p>Taste is no doubt closely allied to smell; hence in invertebrates organs are
                    found that may be referred to either of the senses (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Smell).</hi> Tastes have been variously classified. One of the most useful
                    classifications is into sweet, bitter, acid, and saline tastes. To excite the
                    sensation, substances must be soluble in the fluid of the mouth. Insoluble
                    substances, when brought into contact with the tongue, give rise to feelings of
                    touch or of temperature, but excite no taste. The specific mode of action of
                    sapid substances is quite unknown. The extent of surface acted on increases the
                    massiveness of the sensation, whilst the intensity is affected by the degree of
                    concentration of the solution of the sapid substance. If solutions of various
                    substances are gradually diluted with water until no taste is experienced,
                    Valentine found that the sensations of taste disappeared in the following order—
                    syrup, sugar, common salt, aloes, quinine, sulphuric acid; and Camerer found
                    that the taste of quinine still continued although diluted with twenty times
                    more water than common salt. Von Vintschgau found that the time required to
                    excite taste after the sapid substance was placed on the tongue varied. Thus
                    saline matters are tasted most rapidly (’ 17 second), then sweet, acid, and
                    bitter (’ 258 second). This is probably due to the activity of diffusion of the
                    substance. No relation between the chemical constitution of the substance and
                    the nature of the taste excited by it has yet been discovered, and there are
                    many curious examples of substances of very different chemical constitutions
                    having similar tastes. For example, sugar, acetate of lead, and the vapour of
                    chloroform have all a sweetish taste. A temperature of from 50° to 90° F. is the
                    most favourable to the sense, water above or below this temperature either
                    masking or temporarily paralysing it. Taste is often associated with smell,
                    giving rise to a sensation of flavour, and we are frequently in the habit of
                    confounding the one sensation with the other. Chloroform excites taste alone,
                    whilst garlic, asafoetida, and vanilla excite only smell. This is illustrated by
                    the familiar experiment of blindfolding a person and touching the tongue
                    successively with slices of an apple and of an onion. In these circumstances the
                    one cannot be distinguished from the other when the nose is firmly closed. No
                    doubt also experience aids in detecting slight differences of taste by
                    suggesting to the mind what may be expected; it is not easy, for instance, to
                    distinguish the tastes of red and white wine when the eyes are blindfolded.
                    Taste may be educated to a remarkable extent; and careful observation—along with
                    the practice of avoiding all substances having a very pronounced taste or having
                    an irritating effect—enables tea-tasters and winetasters to detect slight
                    differences of taste, more especially when combined with odour so as to produce
                    flavour, which would be quite inappreciable to an ordinary palate. As to the
                    action of electrical currents on taste, observers have arrived at uncertain
                    results. So long ago as 1752 Sulzer stated that a constant current caused, more
                    especially at the moments of opening and of closing the current, a sensation of
                    acidity at the anode ( + pole) and of alkalinity at the katode ( - pole). This
                    is in all probability due to electrolysis, the decomposition products exciting
                    the tastebodies. Grünhagen found that rapidly interrupted currents fail to
                    excite the sense; Von Vintschgau, who has directed much attention to the sense
                    of taste, says that when the tip of his tongue is traversed by a current there
                    is only a tactile sensation. Again Honigschmied, on the contrary, found that a
                    current excited the metallic or acid taste at the anode placed on the tip of the
                    tongue, whilst the alkaline taste of the katode was absent. The writer of this
                    article has found that this is the experience of most persons examined by
                    him.</p>
                <p>Disease of the tongue causing unnatural dryness may interfere with taste.
                    Substances circulating in the blood may give rise to subjective sensations of
                    taste. Thus santonine, morphia, and biliary products (as in jaundice) usually
                    cause a bitter sensation, whilst the sufferer from diabetes is distressed by a
                    persistent sweetish taste. The insane frequently have subjective tastes, which
                    are real to the patient, and frequently cause much distress. In such cases, the
                    sensation is excited by changes in the taste-centres of the brain. Increase in
                    the sense of taste is called <hi rend="italic">hypergeusia,</hi> diminution of
                    it <hi rend="italic">hypogeusia,</hi> and its entire loss <hi rend="italic"
                        >ageusia.</hi> Rare cases occur where there is a subjective taste not
                    associated with insanity nor with the circulation of any known sweetish matters
                    in the blood, possibly caused by irritation of the gustatory nerves or by
                    changes in the nerve centres.</p>
                <p>As to the comparative anatomy of the tongue, see Owen’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Comparative Anatomy and Physiology of Vertebrates</hi> (London, 1868). For
                    a full account of the physiology of taste, see Von Vintschgau’s article
                    “Geschmackssinn,” in <hi rend="italic">Hermann's Handbuch der Physiologie,</hi>
                    vol. iii. part ii. (J. G. Μ. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
