<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0923-0328-0311-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">THOMSON, James</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 23, page 311</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110447">Seasons</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1176048">Winter</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1006755">Mallets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:824216">Autumn</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1138503">Summer</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96094w">Seasons</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785p59">Autumn</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b46688q84">Odes</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n328/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THOMSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">James</hi></label> (1700-1748),
                    author of <hi rend="italic">The Seasons,</hi> was a native of the Scottish
                    Border country, his father being successively minister of the parishes of Ednam
                    and Southdean, in Roxburghshire. He was born at Ednam on September 11, 1700, and
                    was reared at a distance from the social influences and literary fashions that
                    helped to form and fix the manner of the “classical” school, the monotony of
                    which he was the first to break. Amidst the bare breezy hills and glens of a
                    Border parish, his youth was safe against the ascendency of the taste
                    established in the metropolis. Jedburgh school and Edinburgh university gave him
                    his book learning of the ordinary type; and he was fortunate enough to have
                    neighbours of extraordinary accomplishment, who opened his eyes to the poetic
                    side of nature, and encouraged him in verse-making. The teacher from whom he
                    learnt most was a Mr Riccalton, or Riccaulton, a graduate of Edinburgh, who had
                    taken to farming, but was afterwards persuaded to enter the church, and made
                    some contributions to theological literature. This scholarly enthusiast taught
                    Latin to the boys of Jedburgh in an aisle of the church, and encouraged Thomson
                    in his poetical turn by example as well as precept. We have the poet’s own
                    acknowledgment that the first hint of the <hi rend="italic">Seasons</hi> came
                    from a striking dramatic poem by Riccaulton entitled <hi rend="italic">A
                    Winter's Day.</hi> As a schoolboy Thomson wrote verses, and at the university he
                    continued the practice, but his early efforts were not particularly promising.
                    He was intended for the ministry, and was for five years a student of divinity;
                    but in 1725 he determined to follow his friend and classfellow David Mallet to
                    London, and seek his fortune there. Through the influence of Lady Grizel
                    Baillie, herself a song-writer, he obtained a tutorship in the family of Lord
                    Binning; but the plain-looking and plain-mannered poet had not the adroitness of
                    his friend Mallet, and he gave up the post after a few months. It was while he
                    lingered in the neighbourhood of Barnet, without employment, without money, with
                    few friends, saddened by the loss of his mother (his father had died when he was
                    eighteen), that Thomson conceived the idea of the first of his poems on the
                    Seasons, <hi rend="italic">Winter.</hi> The lines—</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> Welcome, kindred glooms, </l>
                    <l part="N"> Congenial horrors, hail! </l>
                </lg>
                <p>came from the heart; they expressed his own forlorn mood on the approach of the
                    winter of 1725. <hi rend="italic">Winter</hi> appeared in the spring of 1726. A
                    publisher, Millan,—not Millar, who afterwards published for him,—gave him three
                    guineas for the poem. The tradition is that it attracted no notice for a month,
                    but that, at the end of that time, a literary clergyman, Whatley, chanced to
                    take it up from a bookseller’s counter, and at once rushed off to the
                    coffeehouses to proclaim the discovery of a new poet. The town received the
                    discovery with acclamation; in another month a second edition was called for. No
                    time could have been better suited for the appreciation of Thomson’s striking
                    qualities; they were so entirely unlike what the public had for many years been
                    accustomed to. The fresh treatment of a simple theme, the warm poetical
                    colouring of commonplace incidents, the freedom and irregularity of the plan,
                    the boldness of the descriptions, the manly and sincere sentiment, the rough
                    vigour of the verse, took by surprise a generation accustomed to witty satire
                    and burlesque, refined diction, translations from the classics, themes valued in
                    proportion to their remoteness from vulgar life. Thomson at once became famous,
                    and, his naturally easy temper roused to full exertion, vigorously followed up
                    his success with <hi rend="italic">Summer</hi> and an <hi rend="italic">Ode to
                    the Memory of Sir Isaac Λ</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> r</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">eιvton. Spring</hi> was completed and published in 1728. A longer
                    interval elapsed before the appearance of <hi rend="italic">Autumn</hi>; it was
                    published in 1730, and followed presently by a handsome edition of the whole
                    four <hi rend="italic">Seasons.</hi> Meantime, drawn into the ardent political
                    strife of the time, he had produced, in 1729, his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Britannia,</hi> and early in 1730 had made his first attempt as a dramatist
                    with <hi rend="italic">Sophonisba.</hi> From this time there was a manifest
                    slackening either in his will or in his power to produce. He was appointed
                    travelling tutor to the son of Sir Charles Talbot, travelled with his pupil on
                    the Continent, and in 1733 obtained a small sinecure in the Court of Chancery.
                    It may have been this removal of the spur of necessity that made him take longer
                    over his poems. But it is a fair theory that the rigid taste of the time for
                    finish, which he had unconsciously defied with triumphant results, began to make
                    good an ascendency over him, and that he wrote less because he was cramped by
                    fear of the critics. None of the Qther <hi rend="italic">Seasons</hi> have the
                    same large and careless freedom as <hi rend="italic">Winter; Autumn</hi>
                    especially, the last of them, is much more laboured, and his revisions and
                    enlargements in successive editions show an anxious ambition after the finish of
                    the classical school. However this may be, he hesitated long over his next poem,
                    <hi rend="italic">Liberty·,</hi> the first part was published in 1734 and the
                    conclusion in 1736. He intended it to be his masterpiece, but with all his care
                    and pains it has fallen into deserved oblivion. In 1737 he lost his sinecure by
                    the death of his patron, but was recompensed by a pension from the prince.
                    Poverty, rather than natural fitness or inclination, drove him again to dramatic
                    composition. <hi rend="italic">Agamemnon</hi>-was produced in 1738, with
                    indifferent success. Next year a play, written in the interest of the prince and
                    the opposition, was interdicted by the lord chamberlain. The masque of <hi
                    rend="italic">Alfred,</hi> written by Thomson in conjunction with Mallet, and
                    containing the song <hi rend="italic">Pule Britannia,</hi> was produced in 1740,
                    <hi rend="italic">Tancred and Sigismunda</hi> in 1745. A year before this last
                    event the “poetical posture” of the poet’s income was improved by his
                    appointment to the sinecure office of surveyor-general of the Leeward Islands.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Castle of Indolence</hi> was his last work. It was not
                    published till the year of his death (1748), but he had been long engaged upon
                    it. The poem is full of character and humour, with here and there passages of
                    elaborately rich description; it is fuller than any other of the personality of
                    the poet, of the good-nature, generosity, and solid wisdom which gained him the
                    affection of so many friends; but still it is in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Seasons,</hi> and especially in the first of them, that Thomson is seen at his
                    best and strongest.</p>
                <p>Till the advent of Scott and Byron, Thomson was the most widely popular poet in
                    our language; and as late as the middle of this century a sumptuous edition,
                    illustrated by the Etching Club, was printed three times within ten years
                    (1842-52). The popular verdict on Thomson has been unanimously justified by
                    critics. (W. Μ.) <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n329/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0923-0329-0312"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
