<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0923-0347-0330-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">THURGAU, or Thurgovia (9th edition, volume 23, page
                    330)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6rb7d">Voting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vt81">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139996">Swedes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:932562">Foresters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115271">Sharing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881354">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1169232">Voting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n347/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">THURGAU, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Thurgovia</hi></label>, a
                    canton of Switzerland (ranking as seventeenth in the Confederation), takes its
                    name from the river Thur. It is bounded on the N. by the Rhine, on the E. by the
                    Lake of Constance (the cantonal frontier being so drawn as to leave the town of
                    Constance to Baden), on the S. by a line running from Arbon on the lake west and
                    south-west to Hörnli, and on the W. by a line drawn from Hörnli passing east of
                    Winterthur and west of Frauenfeld to the Rhine, a little west of Diessen-hofen
                    and opposite Schaffhausen. It is thus shaped like a triangle, of which the
                    Hörnli (3274 feet, the highest point in the canton) is the apex, and comprises
                    the middle basin of the Thur. Its total area is 381 ’ 4 square miles, of which
                    322 ’ 6 (or 84 ’ 6 per cent.) is reckoned as “productive land,” 69 <hi
                        rend="superscript"> -</hi> 8 being covered by forests, and 6*9 by vineyards.
                    Of the “unproductive” portion no less than 50 ’ 5 square miles consists of the
                    cantonal share of the Lake of Constance. According to the census of 1880, the
                    population amounted to 99,552 (females being in a majority of 1000), an increase
                    of 6252 on the census of 1870; of these, 99,026 are German-speaking. In religion
                    the inhabitants are divided, there being 71,821 Protestants to 27,123 Roman
                    Catholics; the canton till 1815 was in the diocese of Constance, and since 1828
                    has been in the reconstructed diocese of Basel, though for some time after 1873
                    the Government would not recognize the authority of Bishop Lachat, in
                    consequence of his support of the dogma of <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit23newyrich/page/n348/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0923-0348-0331"/> infallibility at the Vatican council The
                    capital is Frauen feld (5811 inhabitants), and Romanshorn (population 3647) is
                    an important railway centre on the lake. The canton has many small villages, and
                    the population is chiefly employed in agricultural pursuits, though
                    cotton-spinning is rapidly increasing. The orchards are so splendid that Thurgau
                    has been called “the garden of Helvetia.” A network of well-made roads traverses
                    it in every direction.</p>
                <p>The Thurgau originally took in all the country, roughly speaking, between the
                    Reuss, the Lake of Lucerne, the Rhine, and the Lake of Constance; but many
                    smaller districts (Zürichgau, Toggenburg, Appenzell, St Gall) were gradually
                    carved out of it, and the county was reduced to about the size of the present
                    canton when in 1264 it passed by the gift of the last count of Kyburg to his
                    nephew Rudolph of Hapsburg, chosen emperor in 1273. In 1415 the count, Duke
                    Frederick of Austria (a Hapsburg), was put under the ban of the empire by the
                    emperor Sigismund for having aided Pope John XXIII. to escape from Constance,
                    and the county was overrun, Sigismund in 1417 mortgaging to the city of
                    Constance the appellate jurisdiction in all civil and criminal matters
                    (“landgericht” and “blutbann”) arising within the county, which he had declared
                    to be forfeited in consequence of Frederick’s conduct. In 1460 some of the
                    Confederates, now becoming very eager for conquests, overran and seized the
                    county. Winterthur was saved, but in 1461 Frederick's son, Duke Sigismund, had
                    perforce to cede the county to the Confederates. Henceforth it was ruled as a
                    “subject district” by seven members of the League,—Bern, occupied in the west,
                    not being admitted to a share in the government till 1712, after one of the wars
                    of religion. It was only in 1499 that the Confederation (then consisting of ten
                    members) obtained from Constance her supreme jurisdiction, through the mediation
                    of the duke of Milan, but there were still forty-two minor jurisdictions
                    belonging to various lords, spiritual and temporal, which went on till 1798 and
                    greatly limited the power of the Confederates. Thurgau had hoped, but in vain,
                    to be admitted in 1499 a full member of the Confederation.</p>
                <p>At the time of the Reformation many of the inhabitants became Protestants, and
                    bitter quarrels ensued between the Protestant and Catholic (the latter having a
                    large majority) members of the Confederation who had rights over Thurgau, with
                    regard to the toleration of the new doctrines in the “subject districts” such as
                    Thurgau. By the first peace of Kappel (1529) the majority in each “commune” was
                    to settle the religion of that “commune,” but by the second (1531, after
                    Zwingli’s death) both religions were to be allowed side by side in each
                    “commune.” Thurgau thus became a “canton of parity,” as it is to this day. Its
                    rulers, however, continued to watch each other very closely, and Kilian
                    Kesselring, one of the chief military commanders in Thurgau, was in 1633, on
                    suspicion of having connived at the advance of the Swedes through Thurgau on
                    Constance, seized by the Catholic cantons and severely punished. In 1798 Thurgau
                    became free, and was one of the nineteen cantons of the Helvetic republic, being
                    formally received (like the other “subject lands ”) as a full member of the
                    Swiss Confederation in 1803 by the Act of Mediation. It was one of the very
                    first cantons to revise, in 1830, after the July revolution in Paris, its
                    constitution in a very liberal sense, and in 1831 proposed a revision of the
                    federal pact of 1815. This failed, but the new federal constitutions of 1848 (of
                    which one of the two drafters was Kern of Thurgau) and 1874 were approved by
                    very large majorities. In 1849 the cantonal constitution was revised and the
                    veto introduced, by which the people might reject a bill passed by the cantonal
                    assembly. Finally, in 1869, the existing constitution was drawn up, by which the
                    “initiative” (or right of 2500 electors to compel the cantonal assembly to take
                    any subject into consideration) and the “obligatory <hi rend="italic"
                        >referendum”</hi> (by which all laws passed by the cantonal assembly, and
                    all financial resolutions involving a capital expenditure of 50,000 francs or an
                    annual one of 10,000, must be submitted to a popular vote) were introduced. The
                    cantonal government consists of a legislative assembly (now of ninety-seven
                    members, one to every 250 electors) and an executive council of five members,
                    both elected directly by the people; 5000 electors can at any time call for a
                    popular vote on the question of the dismissal of either one or the other.
                    Further, to show the very democratic character of the constitution, it may be
                    added that members of both houses of the federal assembly are in Thurgau elected
                    direct by the people. The “communes” in Thurgau are of no less than eleven or
                    twelve varieties. The division of the lands, &amp;c., of the old “burgher
                    communes” between them and the new communes, consisting of all residents (with
                    whom political power rests), was carried out (1872) in all of the 214 communes;
                    but there are still thirty-eight guilds or corporations with special rights over
                    certain forests, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>The best history of the canton is that by J. A. Pupikofer, of which a second and
                    very much enlarged edition is now (1887) being published.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
