<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0918-0878-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WICKLOW</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 878</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk98">Devil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:891974">Devil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=918" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WICKLOW</label>, a maritime county in the province of
                    Leinster, in Ireland, is bounded on the north by Dublin county, on the east by
                    St George’s Channel, on the south by Wexford, and on the west by Carlow, a
                    detached portion of Dublin, and Kildare. It lies between 52° 40', and 53° 14'
                    north latitude, and 5° 57' and 6° 46' west longitude, extending forty miles in
                    its greatest length from north to south, and thirty-three in its greatest
                    breadth from cast to west, and comprehending an area of 781 square miles, or
                    500,178 acres, of which 405,039 are cultivated land, 94,100 uncultivated
                    mountain or bog, and 1039 covered with water. It ranks as the eighteenth county
                    in superficial extent, and the seventeenth in that of cultivated land.</p>
                <p>According to Ptolemy the geographer, the northern part of the county was the
                    residence of the tribe of the Cauci, and the southern that of the Menapii. It
                    was afterwards occupied by the Irish septs of the Byrnes and O’Tooles, who,
                    though the district was claimed by the English after their settlement, as part
                    of the county of Dublin, maintained their independence, and carried on an almost
                    continual war against the new settlers, until the end of the reign of Elizabeth,
                    after whose death the district was made shireground by her successor James I. in
                    1605, and placed under the jurisdiction of English magistrates. The inha∙</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=919"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0919-0879"/>
                <p>bitants adhered to the royal cause during the war of 1641, until the arrival of
                    Cromwell, to whose superior force they submitted without opposition. No other
                    occurrences of historical importance took place until the year 1798, when
                    several bands of insurgents sought refuge in the mountainous fastnesses here,
                    after the dispersion of their main body in Wexford, and continued’ to harass the
                    neighbouring counties, until tranquillity was restored, partly by making terms
                    with their leaders, and partly by cutting roads and establishing military posts
                    through the interior of the country, which till then had been nearly
                    impassable.</p>
                <p>The county forms one of the four great mountain groups of Ireland. The land rises
                    from the valley of the Liffey and Dublin Bay on the north, by successive ridges,
                    increasing in height, and occasionally intersected by deep glens, to the middle
                    of the county, whence it again subsides to the borders of Wexford and Carlow.
                    The direction of the range is from north-east at Bray, to south-west, the
                    central part of the line being usually the most elevated, and the surface
                    declining to the sea on the east, and the level country of Kildare and Carlow on
                    the west. Lugnaquilla, to the east of Baltinglas, is the most elevated point of
                    the range: its summit is 3039 feet above the sea-level. To the north, on the
                    verge of Dublin county, are the Butter Mountain, 1459, Kippure, 2473, and the
                    Three-rock Mountain, 1763 feet high; more southerly, Djouce, 2384 feet, and
                    Sugar-loaf, 1126. In the centre are Thonalagee, 2683; Comaderry, 2296; Lugduff,
                    2148; Knockreagh, 1559; and Croghan, 2175. The glens form very striking and
                    picturesque features of this romantic district, being deep, narrow, and several
                    of them densely covered with wood. The most celebrated are the Dargle, near the
                    county of Dublin; Glencullen, Glencree, the Glen of the Downs, the Devil’s Glen,
                    Glenmalur, the Glen of Imail, and the Vale of Ovoca. The rivers are few and
                    small, all having their sources in the central group. The Liffey, which rises in
                    Djouce Mountain, and after a circuitous course through Kildare, discharging
                    itself into Dublin Bay, is known chiefly as having the metropolitan city on its
                    banks. The Slaney, which rises near Glendalough, is not navigable until it has
                    traversed the greater part of Wexford county. The Ovoca is formed by the
                    junction of the Awenmore and Awenbeg at the meeting of the waters in the
                    romantic Vale of Ovoca. It is afterwards joined by the Daragh or Aghrim from the
                    west, and empties itself into St George’s Channel at Arklow. The Vartrey, a
                    small stream, falls into the sea north of Wicklow Head. Numerous lakes lie in
                    the valleys between the central mountain-ridges. They are small, but generally
                    surrounded by very picturesque scenery. The most remarkable are Lough Bray, in
                    Glencree, near the borders of Dublin; Lough Dan, Lough Tay, Luggelagh, and the
                    lakes of Glendalough. The last form an object of peculiar interest, from their
                    romantic situation, the remains of ancient ecclesiastical structures in their
                    neighbourhood, and the popular legends connected with them. The coast presents a
                    succession of fine prospects, but is much dreaded by mariners, in consequence of
                    the sand-banks that skirt it. These are, the Kish Bank, each extremity of which
                    is marked by a floating light; Bray Bank, the Codling, South Ridge, Wicklow, and
                    Arklow Banks. The southern extremity of the last named is also marked by a
                    floating light. The only harbours in this line of coast are those of Wicklow and
                    Arklow, both fit only for small vessels. The projecting point of Wicklow Head is
                    marked by two fixed lights. A few creeks afford shelter for fishing-craft.
                    Herrings and round fish are taken off Wicklow Bank, where also oysters and
                    lobsters are caught; but the business is carried on with so little spirit,
                    owing, it is said, to the want of capital, that fish is brought from Dublin for
                    sale. The state of the fisheries in 1836 was as follows:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> No. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Tonnage. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Men. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"><p>Decked vessels 39 1174
                            156</p><p>Half-decked ditto 153 1425 858</p><p>Open sail-boats 57 —
                            246</p><p>Row-boats 14 — 38</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"> Total of fishermen 1298 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The western side of the county presents one of the great granite formations of
                    Ireland, extending from Kingstown Harbour to the south-western extremity of the
                    county. Each side is bordered by a range of clay-slate rock, passing into
                    greenstone or a greenstone-slate. The rest of the county consists of clay-slate,
                    graywacke, and graywacke-slate, interspersed in various places with small
                    patches of granite, quartz-rock, and greenstone-trap protrusions, with
                    whindykes. The eastern side of the granitic range abounds with metalliferous
                    veins, while the western is totally destitute of them. Lead has been raised near
                    Lough Dan, at Luganure in Comaderry Mountain, at Glendalough, and at
                    Ballyfinshogue; copper at Ballymurtagh and elsewhere. The annual produce of the
                    lead-mines now in operation is estimated at 2500 tons, valued at L.38,000; and
                    of copper and lead in other mines at 12,500 tons, value L.35,000. The granite
                    supplies inexhaustible quantities of stone for building and flagging. Slates for
                    roofing are procured at Dunganstown and Carnew. The climate, though moist, is
                    healthy; the lower lands near the sea produce the arbutus, myrtle, and
                    laurestinus, which flourish in the open air, seldom requiring artificial
                    protection during winter. The character of the soil is very various; near the
                    sea, and along the banks of the larger rivers, it is rich, abounding with
                    limestone, limestone-gravel, and marl. The mountainous tracts have generally a
                    deep thick covering of heath and turf, based upon disintegrated granite. This
                    part contains large tracts of bog. Along the verge of Dublin boundary, a
                    substratum, lying within a few inches of the surface, forms a crust impenetrable
                    to water, thus rendering the upper soil wholly unprofitable until this layer be
                    broken up with the axe, for it resists the action of the spade or plough; after
                    which, when blended with the subjacent clays, it forms a productive soil. Much
                    of the natural timber with which the county was at a former period nearly
                    covered, is still preserved, forming an important feature in the landscape; and
                    young plantations are yearly rising around the mansions and villas with which
                    this district, the chosen pleasure-ground of Ireland, is thickly studded.</p>
                <p>The progress of the population, as far as it can be ascertained from authorities
                    worthy of notice, is as follows:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Year. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Authority. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> No. of Inhabitants. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>1760 De Burgo 43,872</p><p>1792
                            Beaufort. 58,000</p><p>1812 Parliamentary census 83,109</p><p>1821 Ditto
                            110,767</p><p>1831 Ditto 121,557</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The latest of these returns gives an average of one inhabitant to ever}’ four
                    acres. The return of the Commissioners of Public Instruction in J 834, which,
                    being arranged according to dioceses instead of counties, cannot be deemed
                    strictly accurate, gives a gross population of 118,661, of whom 25,005 were
                    members of the established church, 322 Protestant dissenters, and 93,334 Roman
                    Catholics. The number of children receiving instruction in the public schools at
                    the under-named periods was,</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Males. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Females. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Sex not ascertained. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Total. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="5" role="data" rows="1"><p>1821 5597 3108 8,705</p><p>1824-6
                            6377 4671 285 11,333</p><p>1836- 7 1151 1012 2,163</p><p>1837- 8 1232
                            1042 2,274</p><p>1838- 9 1549 1351 2,900</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=920"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0920-0880"/>
                <p>The number of the children of each religious denomination, as stated in the
                    return of 1824—6, being the only one in which this point is noticed, was,
                    members of the established church, 3666; dissenters, 31; Roman Catholics, 7270;
                    besides 366 whose religion could not be ascertained. The number of schools,
                    according to the same return, was 258, of which forty-four, having 3526 pupils,
                    were supported by grants of public money; thirty-eight, with 1619 pupils, by
                    voluntary subscriptions; and 176, with 6188 pupils, wholly by the fees paid by
                    the pupils.</p>
                <p>The county is divided into the seven baronies of Arklow, Ballinacor, Newcastle,
                    Rathdrum, Shillelagh, Upper and Lower Talbotstown. These are subdivided into
                    fifty-eight parishes, of which forty-nine are in the diocese of Dublin, two in
                    Ferns, and seven in Leighlin. The diocese of Glen-dalough, which anciently
                    comprehended the greater part of the county, having been united to that of
                    Dublin in 1497, has been so intimately amalgamated with it that their respective
                    boundaries cannot now be ascertained. The county returned ten members to the
                    Irish parliament, two for the county at large, and two each for the boroughs of
                    Baltinglas, thessington, Carysfort, and Wicklow. All the boroughs were
                    disfranchised at the time of the Union, and those of Wicklow and Baltinglas are
                    the only two to which corporate privileges are to be granted under the municipal
                    corporation act. The number of electors was, in</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Year. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> No. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1831 1013 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1832 695 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1833 1566 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Year. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> No. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1834 1670 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1835 1670 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1836 1679 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Year. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> No. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1837 1679 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1838 1679 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1839 1380 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The number of electors is to that of the inhabitants as one to eighty-eight, and
                    to that of the heads of families as one to fifteen. The county is in the
                    Leinster circuit. The assizes are held in the town of Wicklow, where the county
                    court-house, prison, and infirmary, arc built. General sessions of the peace are
                    also held there and at Baltinglas. The local magistracy consists of a
                    lieutenant, sixteen deputy-lieutenants, fifty-nine other unsalaried magistrates,
                    and a stipendiary. Under these is a constabulary force, consisting of a county
                    inspector, five sub-inspectors, six head constables, and 199 constables and
                    sub-constables. There is a second infirmary at Baltinglas, and four
                    feverhospitals, with a number of dispensaries in different parts. Lunatics are
                    sent to the district asylum in Dublin, into which twenty-two cases from this
                    county are admissible; but several patients are still kept in the county prison.
                    Baltinglas, Rathdrum, and Shillelagh, have been fixed on as sites for workhouses
                    for unions under the poor-law act.</p>
                <p>The rich low' lands near the sea, and along the banks of the Slaney and Ovoca,
                    are under tillage, all the operations of which are carried on according to the
                    most approved systems. Much of the mountain district is adapted for pasturage,
                    particularly for feeding a small breed of sheep, whose meat is much prized in
                    the Dublin market. The mountain of Lugnaquilla has a fine sheep-walk on its
                    summit. Lime and marl are the chief manures: the former is brought by sea from
                    Howth to the districts near the coast; it is also drawn in large quantities from
                    Carlow to the inland parts. Butter is made in large quantities in the dairies,
                    which are generally attached to the farm-houses. The fences in the most highly
                    improved districts are of white thorn; in other parts earthen mounds, and in the
                    rocky mountainous heights dry stone-walls</p>
                <p>The manufacture of flannels was here carried on extensively, and a market-house
                    for their sale was erected at Rathdrum; but it has declined greatly, and the
                    woollen manufacture is now nearly confined to the fabrication of friezes and
                    coarse cloths for home-consumption. Some coarse linen is also wrought for the
                    same purpose. But the county owes its wealth wholly to its agriculture. Most of
                    the produce is sent to Dublin; but some is exported from Wicklow and Arklow, and
                    the quantities are annually increasing. The annual average of the exports and
                    imports through these places is estimated as follows:</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> Exports. </cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> Imports. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> Tons. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> L. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Tons. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> L. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="6" role="data" rows="1"><p>Wicklow 16,000 85,000 8,000
                            15,000</p><p>Arklow 900 8,500 4,000 6,500</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="6" role="data" rows="1"> Total 16,900 93,500 12,000 21,500
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>This is the only county in Ireland in which there is no banking establishment,
                    either private or joint-stock; yet it is the most thriving in proportion to its
                    population and extent of productive land. There are loan-societies in eight
                    places: the sums in the hands of borrowers at the close of 1839 amounted to
                    L.9315, the number of borrowers during the same year to 9100.</p>
                <p>Though the high state of prosperity this county displays is mainly attributable
                    to the well-directed efforts of agricultural industry, yet some portion of it
                    must be allowed to arise from the number of men of landed property whom the
                    extraordinary beauty of the country has induced to make it their chosen place of
                    residence, thus heightening its natural advantages of scenery by the
                    adventitious ornaments of splendid mansions and villas, surrounded by demesnes
                    laid out in the most refined style. Two main lines of road conduct the stranger
                    through it. The one on the eastern side, and mostly near the sea-coast, presents
                    an almost uninterrupted succession of splendid prospects, through a highly
                    cultivated country. Proceeding from the city of Dublin, through the Scalp, the
                    lands of Powerscourt, the Dargle, the Glen of the Downs, Delgany, the Devil’s
                    Glen, Luggelagh, Glendalough, and the Vale of Ovoca, to Arklow, the eye finds
                    nothing to rest upon but scenes of rural beauty. The other main road, along the
                    western side, chiefly through the rich valley of the Slaney, presents a similar
                    succession of scenery of a less romantic character. Even the intermediate space,
                    though wholly composed of mountain tracts little capable of high cultivation,
                    presents several wild landscapes of combined cliff and glen, to which an easy
                    access is found through the military road already noticed.</p>
                <p>The peasantry, notwithstanding the proximity of the metropolis, resembles that of
                    the more remote agricultural districts in habits, dwellings, and mode of life;
                    the chief article of food being the potato, and the fuel turf, though coal
                    imported from England is in general use among the wealthier classes, especially
                    near the sea.</p>
                <p>There are several cromlechs still existing, and many raths. Ruins of monastic
                    buildings are to be seen at Baltinglas, Wicklow, Rathdrum, and Glendalough or
                    “the Glen of the Two Lakes,” where there is a pillar-tower, and the remains of
                    several places of religious worship, one of them being the cathedral of the
                    ancient diocese, from which it has acquired the name of “the Seven Churches.” It
                    had been the site of a city, the metropolis of the sept of the O’Tooles, and is
                    now a place of great resort for visitors, from its picturesque scenery. Several
                    castles were built in this county by the English, the sites of most of which can
                    still be ascertained by what is left of their structures.</p>
                <p>Wicklow, the assize-town, is built on an elevated spot projecting into the sea
                    near the mouth of the Vartrey. It was originally the site of a castle erected by
                    Maurice Fitzgerald, and was long maintained as a post of importance, under the
                    superintendence of a constable. The town is small and irregularly built, owing
                    most of its support to the assizes and sessions. It was a borough by
                    prescription, but its corporate rights were confirmed by a charter of James I.,
                    granted in 1613, to be enjoyed under a portreeve, burgesses, and freemen, who
                    had a right of exemption<pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=921" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0921-0881"/>
                    from harbour-dues, and of pasturage on the common. The corporate landed property
                    is about 300 acres. The portreeve held a weekly court for the recovery of debts
                    to the amount of five marks. By the municipal corporation act, the old
                    corporation has been dissolved, and, under certain conditions, power is to be
                    given to create a new one, styled “the portreeve, free burgesses, and commonalty
                    of the town of Wicklow.” There is a Saturday market, and four fairs annually.
                    Races are held every year at the Mur-ragh, a border of dry sandy land, extending
                    for several miles along the sea-shore to the north of the town, forming a
                    peninsula, which encloses a long narrow basin, in which vessels drawing less
                    than eight feet of water can enter at spring tides. The population in 1821
                    amounted to 2146, and in 1831 to 2472. The population of the other towns having
                    each upwards of 1000 inhabitants was, in 1831, as follows: Bray, 3656; Arklow,
                    4383; Baltinglas, 1699; and Rathdrum, 1054. (c. P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
