<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0762-0722-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WALLACE, Sir William</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 722</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q37b">Prisons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1009087">Marching</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=762" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WALLACE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir William</hi></label>, the
                    name of one well known to the readers of British history, as the heroic defender
                    of Scotish independence against the aggressions of Edward I. of England. He was
                    the second of three sons of Sir Malcolm Wallace (or Walays) of Elderslie and
                    Auchin-bothic, in the county of Renfrew, and not far from the town of Paisley.
                    The earlier years of Wallace appear to have been spent at Dunipace, in
                    Stirlingshire, in the society of his uncle, a wealthy priest, who gave him an
                    education far above what was usual in those times, and whose strong love of
                    liberty fostered his nephew’s youthful enmity against the English. The early
                    rudiments of education thus acquired were afterwards strengthened by the
                    instruction which he received at Dundee. At this period of life he also acquired
                    those hardy and warlike accomplishments, which inured his frame to fatigue, and
                    gave him a ready command of the weapons of war. His early hatred of the English
                    led him into many brawls and adventures;<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See Henry’s Wallace, by Dr Jamieson; and Carrick’s Life <hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi> Wallace.</p></note> but it was not till after the battle
                    of Dunbar, when Scotland was completely overrun, that he first came prominently
                    before his countrymen. In 1297, in a skirmish, in which several were killed, he
                    slew with his dagger William de Hesilridge, the sheriff of Clydesdale. For this
                    deed he was proclaimed a traitor, outlawed, and driven from home to the wilds
                    and fastnesses of the country, where he joined himself to men whose fortunes
                    were as desperate as his own, and his courage and higher rank made them choose
                    him for their chief. From this time he was constantly engaged against the enemy
                    with various results, but ultimately, as his adherents increased, and his plans
                    became more matured, with decided advantage. This kind of guerilla warfare was
                    of the utmost importance in his future proceedings. By it he became acquainted
                    with the strongest passes and the best positions for defence in the country; his
                    men were inured to a life of fatigue and privation, to feel the benefits of
                    discipline and obedience, and to rest with the most perfect confidence in the
                    abilities, courage, and great strength of their intrepid commander.</p>
                <p>The success which attended his efforts induced him to undertake an enterprise of
                    greater importance. By a forced march he surprised Ormesby, the English
                    justiciary, at Scone, defeated his troops, nearly captured him, and took a rich
                    booty. This exploit led Bruce and a number of the nobility to join him with
                    their vassals; and the united forces, led by Wallace, cleared the country of the
                    English. This intelligence reached Edward when about to embark for Flanders. An
                    army of 40,000 foot and 300 horse was despatched into Scotland, under the
                    command of Henry Percy, which on the 9th of July 1297 came up with that of the
                    Scots, encamped at Irvine, consisting of nearly the same strength, and commanded
                    by Wallace. Dissensions had however broken out among the leaders: the feudal
                    barons, from pride and jealousy, would not submit to his orders, and they
                    therefore entered into negociations with Percy, which ended in their submission
                    to Edward. Sir Andrew Murray of Bothwell was the only man of rank who adhered to
                    Wallace; and with a large body of tried and veteran followers, they retired
                    indignantly to the north. Percy, considering that he had put an end to the
                    revolt, retired to England; but Wallace and Murray, dividing their forces,
                    carried on their operations against the English, and with such vigour, that in a
                    short time all the strongholds north of the river Forth, except the castle of
                    Dundee, were retaken. Wallace had just laid siege to that fortress, when his
                    scouts informed him of the approach of a powerful force, under the command of
                    the earl of Surrey, and Cressingham the treasurer. He instantly left the siege,
                    to be continued by the citizens, and by a forced march took possession of the
                    high ground on the river Forth, above Cambuskenneth, at Stirling, before the
                    English forces reached the south side of the river. The Scotish army, <pb
                    break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=763"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0763-0723"/> consisted of 40,000 foot and 180 horse, while
                    that of the English amounted to 50,000 foot and 1000 heavy armed horse. On the
                    morning of September 11, 1297, against the advice of those who knew the nature
                    of the ground, Surrey ordered his troops to deploy over the narrow bridge; but
                    when only half their number had passed, and before their ranks could be arrayed
                    on the narrow peninsula which formed the field of battle, Wallace attacked them
                    with his whole force, and nearly every soldier that crossed the bridge was
                    either slain or drowned. This decisive defeat was followed by the expulsion of
                    the English from the kingdom. To lessen the severity of a dreadful dearth and
                    famine which now spread over Scotland, Wallace resolved on an expedition into
                    England, not only to procure subsistence for his numerous army, but also to
                    retaliate on that country the injuries which Scotland had received. He therefore
                    proceeded as far as Newcastle, wasting the northern counties with fire and
                    sword, sparing neither age nor sex, and carrying off a large and valuable booty.
                    Soon after his return from this successful expedition, he was elected governor
                    of Scotland, and, strengthened by this high title, he proceeded to regulate the
                    affairs of the kingdom, which its exigencies required. So firm and determined
                    was his rule, so beneficial his measures, that the powerful nobility were
                    compelled to submit to his authority, while the lesser barons willingly
                    supported him. This state did not long continue. Edward, in July 1298, at the
                    head of an army of nearly 100,000 foot and 8000 horsemen, entered Scotland,
                    while Wallace retired before him as he advanced, wasting the country, so as to
                    make Edward depend on his own supplies. This plan of warfare reduced the English
                    army to such straits that the king had to order an inglorious retreat. At this
                    critical moment, when the military skill of Wallace predicted the most complete
                    success, the treachery of two Scotish nobles, Patrick earl of Dunbar, and the
                    earl of Angus, revealed to the English monarch the dispositions of Wallace.
                    Edward immediately ordered his army to advance, and by a rapid night-march, came
                    up to the Scotish army at Falkirk; and Wallace, with not one third the number of
                    soldiers, was compelled by his position to fight at disadvantage, and was
                    defeated with great loss. Shortly after this defeat, he resigned his high office
                    as governor, and proceeded to France, apparently with the consent of the
                    regents, with the expectation of obtaining assistance for Scotland from its
                    sovereign. In this he was deceived, as, on arriving at Amiens, he was thrown
                    into prison, and a letter was written by Philip to Edward, offering to send him
                    to London. In this however there was more policy than sincerity; for Wallace was
                    secretly released from prison, and furnished with letters, dated November 3,
                    1298, to the French agents at the court of Rome, ordering them to solicit Pope
                    Boniface to give Wallace an attentive hearing regarding the affairs of Scotland.
                    There is no proof that Wallace was at Rome, but certain it is that Boniface, in
                    his bull to Edward, exhibited a knowledge of its history and affairs which he
                    could only have derived from such a source as Wallace. This noble-minded patriot
                    remained on the continent until late in the year 1303, when he returned into
                    Scotland, and immediately commenced active operations in assisting those who
                    still defended the liberties of their country. By his resolute career, he
                    rendered himself so obnoxious to Edward, that when mercy was extended to the few
                    remaining patriots on certain conditions, Edward excluded this great man, and
                    set a reward of 300 merks on his head. By the treachery of a servant who waited
                    on him, of the name of Jack Short, he was at length betrayed to Sir John
                    Monteith, a Scotish baron, who captured him at night in bed in the house of a
                    certain Ralph Rae, at Robroyston, in the neighbourhood of Glasgow, and for which
                    he received from the English privy council a grant of land of the annual value
                    of one hundred pounds. Wallace was conveyed to London, where he arrived upon
                    Sunday the 22d of August 1305. On the following day he was tried in Westminster
                    Hall, with mock splendour and ceremony, by the form of English law, but without
                    the least regard to its justice. In accordance with the predetermined resolution
                    of Edward, he was condemned to suffer death, and the sentence was executed the
                    same day, with disgraceful and revolting cruelty.</p>
                <p>Thus ended the career of this noble-minded patriot, but not without leaving a
                    name which will ever be revered. He found his country overpowered and
                    disorganized, her people disheartened, her nobles and leaders in prison, or in
                    the pay of one of the ablest monarchs that ever swayed the English sceptre,
                    himself without wealth or influence, and an outlaw; yet under all these
                    disadvantages, his love of freedom and hatred of oppression, his fearless
                    courage and perseverance, which nothing could subdue, his military skill, his
                    political sagacity, his natural eloquence, and the ardour with which he animated
                    his companions and followers, all conspired to restore confidence in his
                    countrymen, and to free them from the invaders; and had it not been for the
                    pride, jealousy, and treachery of her nobles, the measures that he pursued for
                    organizing the strength and extending the commerce of the kingdom would have
                    given it a stability, which the warlike power of the English, aided by the
                    experience, military tactics, and judgment of her monarch, would not have been
                    able to overpower. As it was, both he and his country suffered from the venality
                    of those who by birth and power were her natural protectors.</p>
                <p>His person was of the most perfect form, and of a stature approaching the
                    gigantic. In strength he was superior to the strongest men of his day; and his
                    frame was such, that it was capable of bearing the greatest fatigue. At his
                    execution it is probable that he was not above thirty-five years of age.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
