<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0904-0864-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WESTMORELAND</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 864</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:950637">Halls</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=904" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WESTMORELAND</label>, one of the most northern English
                    counties. It is separated from the sea-shore by a narrow strip of the county of
                    Lancaster, which bounds it on the south and south-west, as do Cumberland on the
                    north and north-west, and Yorkshire on the east. It is of very irregular shape.
                    Its greatest length is forty, and its greatest breadth thirty-five miles.
                    According to the best estimate, it contains 762 square miles, or 489,680 British
                    statute acres. It is divided into four wards, distinguished by the prefixes of
                    East, Kendal, Lonsdale, and West, which are again divided into thirty
                    parishes.</p>
                <p>The population of the several wards in 1831 was found to be, of the West Ward,
                    7884; of the East Ward, 14,455; of Kendal Ward and Kendal Town, 27,252; and of
                    Lonsdale Ward, 5448.</p>
                <p>The population of the whole county amounted in 1801 to 41,617, in 1811 to 45,922,
                    in 1821 to 51,350, and in 1831 to 55,041. At the last-mentioned period the males
                    were 27,576, and the females 27,465. The dwelling-houses were 10,353, inhabited
                    by 10,984 families.. Of the families, 4454 were chiefly employed in agriculture;
                    4116 were chiefly employed in trade, manufactures, and handicraft; and the
                    remaining 2414 were comprised in neither of the preceding classes. By the census
                    of the same year, the number of males twenty years of age was 14,020; the
                    occupiers of land employing labourers, 1435; the occupiers of land not
                    employing*labourers, 1685; the labourers employed in agriculture, 3474; persons
                    employed in manufactures or making manufacturing machinery were 1074; in retail
                    trade or handicraft as masters or workmen, 3621; the capitalists, bankers,
                    professional, and other educated men were 602; the labourers in labour not
                    agricultural were 1195; the other males twenty years of age (except servants),
                    746; male servants twenty years of age 188, and under twenty years 66; and the
                    female servants 2576. This county is the least densely peopled of any in
                    England.</p>
                <p>The greater part of the county consists of bleak and barren moors, and groups of
                    lofty and naked mountains. The valleys between these mountains, through which
                    the rivers wind, are of moderate fertility, and when well cultivated yield good
                    crops of oats, and in some few instances of wheat and barley. The better parts
                    of these valleys are appropriated to feed cattle or produce hay. The acreable
                    value of the land, in the whole of this county, is much lower than that in any
                    other part of England. According to the returns under the income-tax, the
                    average annual rent and tithes together did not exceed 8s. 7d. per acre, being
                    about half the average value of the rest of the kingdom. The romantic prospects,
                    however, which are afforded by the contrast between the mountains and the lakes,
                    more than repay the traveller for rambling at his leisure through the fine
                    scenery. The lakes of Winandermere and Ulleswater are partly in this county, and
                    those of Grasmere and Hause Water, with several smaller lakes, provincially
                    called Tarns, wholly so. Besides the char (a fish almost peculiar to these
                    lakes), trouts, pikes, perch, and eels, are taken abundantly in these
                    waters.</p>
                <p>The cattle of Westmoreland are of the long-horned kind, and attain a large size
                    when well fed. The butter they afford is highly valued, and supplies to some
                    extent the markets of the metropolis. Large flocks of sheep are fed on the
                    mountains, which yield a coarse wool; but by crossing the breed the wool of late
                    years has been much improved. Numbers of geese are fed on the moors, and these,
                    with hams, form a part of the exports of the county. Westmoreland is nearly
                    destitute of coals, and the metallic ores lie so deep, or are in so remote
                    situations, that there is none of them worked. Slates of the finest quality are
                    abundant, and large quantities of them are exported. Limestone is also very
                    plentiful.</p>
                <p>The principal manufactures of the county are chiefly carried on at Kendal, a
                    place early celebrated for the woollen cloth which bore its name. This
                    manufacture, and that of linsey-woolsey, as well as of coarse worsted stockings,
                    are still continued; and considerable progress has recently been made in
                    introducing the making of cotton goods. It appears by the parliamentary returns,
                    that in 1831 the town of Kendal was in a state of such activity as to employ
                    between 500 and 600 males, upwards of twenty years of age, in making cotton
                    checks, kerseys, linseys, blanketing, and other goods. Woollen goods are made at
                    Kirkland and some other places, and gunpowder at Sedgwick and Long-dales, while
                    the cotton trade of Kendal and its vicinity has been remarkably extended.</p>
                <p>The principal rivers are the Eden, the Lune, the Ken or Kent, and the Lowther,
                    which are more remarkable for the beauties displayed on their borders, and for
                    the abundance of fish they contain, than for any facilities they afford to
                    intercourse. None of them is navigable, nor are there any artificial canals.</p>
                <p>The county gives the title of earl to the family of the Fanes, and that of
                    Lonsdale to the Lowthers, and recently the title of Baron Brougham to the head
                    of the family of that name, and of Langdale to the Master of the Rolls. Two
                    members of the House of Commons are returned for the county. The town of Kendal
                    with its townships, and those of Kirkland and Nether Graveship, have been
                    created a borough by the reform law, and elect one member; and by the same law
                    the ancient borough of Appleby has been disfranchised.</p>
                <p>The most remarkable seats of noblemen and gentlemen are the following: Lowther
                    Castle, earl of Lonsdale; Appleby Castle, earl of Thanet; Abbot Hall,
                    Christopher Wilson, Esq.; Mint House, J. H. Long, Esq.; Netherdale Hall, John
                    Mounsey, Esq.; Brougham Hall, Lord Brougham; Carlton Hall, Lord Wallace.</p>
                <p>The town of Kendal contains 10,015 inhabitants, and Kirby Lonsdale 1686. No other
                    town in the county has a population of 1500.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>See Button’s Beauties of England. England Delineated.
                    Parliamentary Population Returns.</p></note> '</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
