<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0947-0907-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">WITCHCRAFT</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 907</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4222r65v">Witchcraft</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795d31">Demonomania</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jp12">Prayer</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756s76">Prayers</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fk98">Devil</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4b56d40f">Confession</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46t0gw81">Belief</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1109125">Scots</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1176327">Witchcraft</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859760">Christians</term><term n="12" ref="fasttopic:1176346">Witches</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:891974">Devil</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058667">Personality</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=947" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">WITCHCRAFT</label>, a supernatural power of which persons
                    were formerly supposed to obtain the possession by entering into a compact with
                    the devil. They gave themselves up to him body and soul; and he engaged that
                    they should want for nothing, and that he would avenge them upon all their
                    enemies. As soon as the bargain was concluded, the devil delivered to the witch
                    an imp, or familiar spirit, to be ready at a call, and do whatever it was
                    directed. By the assistance of this imp and the devil together, the witch, who
                    was almost always an old woman, was enabled to transport herself in the air on a
                    broomstick or a spit to distant places to attend the meetings of the witches. At
                    these meetings the devil always presided. They were also enabled to transform
                    themselves into various shapes, particularly to assume the forms of cats and
                    hares, in which they most delighted; to inflict diseases on whomsoever they
                    thought proper, and to punish their enemies in a variety of ways.</p><p>The belief that certain persons were endowed with supernatural power, and that
                    they were assisted by invisible spirits, is very ancient. The <hi rend="italic">sagoe</hi> of the Romans seem rather to have been sorcerers than witches; and
                    indeed the idea of a witch, as above described, could not have been prevalent
                    till after the propagation of Christianity, as the heathens had no knowledge of
                    the Christian <hi rend="italic">devil.</hi> Witchcraft was universally believed
                    in Europe till the sixteenth century, and even maintained its ground with
                    tolerable firmness till the middle of the seventeenth. Vast numbers of reputed
                    witches were convicted and condemned to be burnt every year. The methods of
                    discovering them were various. One was, to weigh the supposed criminal against
                    the church Bible, which, if she was guilty, would preponderate: another, by
                    making her attempt to say the Lord’s Prayer. This no witch was able to repeat
                    entirely, but would omit some part or sentence of it. It is remarkable, that all
                    witches did not hesitate at the same place, some leaving out one part, and some
                    another. Teats, through which the imps sucked, were indubitable marks of a
                    witch: these were always raw, and also insensible, and if squeezed, sometimes
                    yielded a drop of blood. A witch could not weep more than three tears, and that
                    only out of the left eye. This want of tears was, by the witch-finders, and even
                    by some judges, considered as a very substantial proof of guilt. Swimming a
                    witch was another kind of popular ordeal generally practised. For this she was
                    stripped naked, and cross-bound, the right thumb to the left toe, and the left
                    thumb to the right toe. Thus prepared, she was thrown into a pond or river, in
                    which, if guilty, she could not sink; for having, by her compact with the devil,
                    renounced the benefit of the water of baptism, that element, in its turn,
                    renounced her, and refused to receive her into its bosom. Sir Robert Filmer
                    mentions two others by fire: the first, by burning the thatch of the house of
                    the suspected witch; the other, burning any animal supposed to be bewitched by
                    her, as a hog or ox. These, it was held, would force a witch to confess. The
                    trial by the stool was another method used for the discovery of witches. It was
                    thus managed: having taken the suspected witch, she was placed in the middle of
                    a room upon a stool or table, cross-legged, or in some other uneasy posture; to
                    which, if she submitted not, she was then bound with cords; there she was
                    watched, and kept without meat or sleep for the space of twenty-four hours; for,
                    they said, within that time they should see her imp come and suck. A little hole
                    was likewise made in the door for imps to come in at; and lest it should come in
                    some less discernible shape, they that watched were taught to be ever and anon
                    sweeping the room, and if they saw any spiders or flies, to kill them: if they
                    could not kill them, then they might be sure they were imps. If witches, under
                    examination or torture, would not confess, all their apparel was changed, and
                    every hair of their body shaven off with a sharp razor, lest they should secrete
                    magical charms to prevent their confessing. Witches were most apt to confess on
                    Friday. By such trials as these, and by the accusation of children, old women,
                    and fools, were thousands of unhappy women condemned for witchcraft, and burnt
                    at the stake.</p><p>For a considerable time after the inquisition was erected, the trials of witches,
                    as heretics, were confined to that tribunal; but the goods of those who were
                    condemned being confiscated to the holy office, its ministers were so active in
                    discovering sorcerers, that the different governments found it necessary to
                    deprive them of the cognizance of this crime. On the continent, commissioners
                    were then appointed for the discovery and conviction of witches, who, though
                    less active than the inquisitors, were but too zealous in prosecuting their
                    function. In 1494, Sprenger and institor, two persons employed in this
                    commission, published a collection of trials, most of which had come before
                    themselves, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Malleus Maleficarum.</hi> This
                    served as a kind of institute for their successors.</p><p>∣ The first writers against witchcraft were stigmatized as atheists, though they
                    only endeavoured to prove the imbecility of the persons accused, and the
                    infatuation or the knavery of their accusers. Such were the epithets bestowed by
                    Dr More. Wierus, the disciple of the celebrated Agrippa, gave rise to the first
                    great controversy on this subject. His master had taught him humanity; and he
                    endeavoured, but with too feeble a hand, to stop the bloody proceedings of the
                    judges. Wierus appears to have been a well-disposed, weak man, with extensive
                    reading on this subject, but too narrow-minded to comprehend it thoroughly. He
                    involved himself in unspeakable difficulties, by admitting the action of
                    supernatural powers in certain diseases, and in possessions, while he denied
                    that witches had any concurrence in them. These appearances, said he, are
                    illusions of the devil, who persuades simple and melancholy persons that the
                    mischief he himself performs is done by them, and at their pleasure. He was weak
                    enough to attempt the explanation of every story alleged by his antagonists,
                    without questioning the truth of the facts.</p><p>Bodin, a French lawyer of eminence, who had assisted at several trials of
                    witches, wrote against Wierus, in his <hi rend="italic">Demonomania.</hi> He
                    urged the concurrent testimonies of sufficient witnesses, and the confessions of
                    the witches themselves, to establish the existence of sorcery. Wierus owned that
                    the unhappy persons believed themselves to be guilty of the crimes alleged
                    against them, but that they were deceived by the devil. But what do you make of
                    the witches’ meetings, cried Bodin? The witches, replied his antagonist, are
                    atrabilious. This explanation was so unsatisfactory, that Wierus passed for a
                    magician, whom the devil had furnished with specious arguments to save others
                    from punishment. Lerchemer,Godelmann, Ewichius, Ewal-dus, and some others,
                    followed him, notwithstanding this stigma; but they were opposed by men of more
                    acuteness and consistency than themselves; by Remigius, who had condemned
                    several hundreds of sorcerers to the flames; Delrio, whose book is a complete
                    Corpus Magiae; Cujacius, Erastus, Scribonius, Camerarius, and a crowd of
                    others.</p><p>In this country, while the belief in witchcraft was supported by royal authority
                    (for James I. is universally known to have written on demonology), countenanced
                    by Bacon, and generally adopted among the people, only one writer was hardy
                    enough to oppose it. This was Reginald Scot, who published a collection of
                    impostures detected, under the title of “Discoveries of Witchcraft.” James
                    ordered the book to be burnt by the common executioner, and the judges continued
                    to burn witches as usual. During the civil wars, upwards of eighty were hanged
                    in Suffolk, on <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=948" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0948-0908"/>the accusations of Hopkins the witch-finder.
                    Webster was the next writer against witchcraft, but he had a different fate from
                    that of Scot, for most of his arguments were refuted by Glanville. This very
                    acute writer was induced to publish his Philosophical Considerations about
                    Witchcraft, by the apprehension that the increasing disbelief of witches and
                    apparitions tended to affect the evidences of religion, and even of a Deity. In
                    respect of argument he was certainly superior to his adversaries; his reasoning
                    is perspicuous, though sometimes subtile, placed on the most specious
                    foundations of evidence, and arranged with great skill.</p><p>On the continent, this controversy seemed almost forgotten, till Bekker published
                    <hi rend="italic">his Monde Enchantée.,</hi> in which he denied the existence of
                    witches, on the Cartesian principle that the Deity is the source of all action,
                    consequently actions so opposite to his nature and attributes cannot be supposed
                    to exist. He was answered by Frederick Hoffmann, the father of the modern theory
                    and practice of medicine, in his dissertation <hi rend="italic">De Diaboli
                    Potentia in Corpora.</hi></p><p>The latest witchcraft phrensy was in New England about the year 1692, when the
                    execution of witches became a calamity more dreadful than the sword or the
                    pestilence. The accusers became so daring, that neither civil nor religious
                    authority would have proved a security against their attacks, if all the
                    prosecutions had not been suddenly dropped, and the prisoners set at liberty. So
                    far did those wretches proceed in absurdity, that a dog was accused of throwing
                    persons into fits by looking at them. As soon as the prosecutions were stopped,
                    all reports of witchcraft ceased.</p><p>It would be ridiculous to attempt a serious refutation of the existence of
                    witches; and the task has long been unnecessary. In this country, at least, the
                    discouragement long given to all suspicion of witchcraft, and the repeal of the
                    statutes against that crime, have very much weakened, though perhaps they have
                    not entirely eradicated, the persuasion. On the continent, too, it is evidently
                    on the decline; and notwithstanding the exertions of Dr de Haen, and of the
                    celebrated Lavater, we have little doubt that in a short time posterity will
                    everywhere wonder at the credulity of their ancestors. That there ever were
                    witches, is an opinion which cannot for a moment be admitted by a thinking man.
                    The actions imputed to them were either absurd or impossible; the witnesses by
                    whose evidence they were condemned, either weak enthusiasts or downright
                    villains; and the confessions ascribed to the witches themselves, effects of a
                    disordered imagination produced by cruel treatment and excessive watchings. As
                    to the nightly meetings, demonologists themselves have been obliged to confess
                    that they were nothing else but uneasy dreams, often produced by soporific
                    compositions. The facts which have been brought forward by the advocates for
                    witchcraft bear in their front the most evident marks of trick and imposture;
                    and this has constantly been detected whenever these facts have been properly
                    examined.</p></div></body></text></TEI>