<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0749-0709-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WALACHIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 709</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1159574">Turks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:964057">Hungarians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1734394">Peasants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028366">Mountains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p26qc7r">Turks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=749" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WALACHIA</label>, a principality situated between the Danube,
                    the Moldau, and the Hungarian province of Siebenburgen, the capital of which is
                    Bucharest. In the time of the Romans it was a part of Dacia. In the twelfth and
                    thirteenth centuries, it received from the court of Byzantium princes who were
                    tributary to it. After the fall of that government, Walachia became dependent
                    first on Hungary and afterwards on Poland, which was the period of its greatest
                    prosperity; but it terminated in 1421, when the country submitted to the Turks.
                    This submission was voluntary; and in return the princes nominated from
                    Constantinople were allowed to enjoy their ancient constitution, religion, and
                    privileges. These grants however benefited only the princes or hospodars, and
                    the nobility or bojares; for the peasants and the rest of the inhabitants were
                    retained in a state of severe feudal slavery’. In consequence of this
                    aristocratical oppression under the hospodars and bojares, the country rapidly
                    declined both in numbers and in cultivation. Those who obtained power paid large
                    sums for it at Constantinople, and extorted from the inhabitants the means of
                    reimbursement during their temporary and dependent exercise of sovereignty.
                    During this period, the Turks retained in their own hands Brahilow, Giurgewo,
                    and Thurnut, the strong places which protect the navigation of the Danube.</p>
                <p>In 1716 the first Greek was appointed hospodar; his name was Nicholas
                    Maurokordatus. When he attained the sovereign power, the country was in the most
                    depressed condition, the larger portion of the land uncultivated, and the people
                    almost in a state of savage ignorance. Though no degree of freedom was
                    introduced by the accession of a Greek prince, yet many improvements were
                    introduced which advanced civilization. By this prince a printing-press was
                    established, and some schools founded, in which the ancient Greek and Latin
                    languages were taught, as well as the Sclavonic. Under his brother and successor
                    Constantine, the peasants were lightened of a great part of their slavish
                    burdens. He introduced a better course of agriculture, and first brought in the
                    cultivation of maize, which has gradually become the chief aliment of the
                    people. His successor caused the Bible and the liturgical books of the Greek
                    church to be translated into the vernacular language. The hospodars Alexander
                    Ypsilante, Ghika, Kallimachi, and Karadza, attended to education, or affected to
                    do so, and during their rule books embodying the ancient laws were printed and
                    generally circulated. As the rulers however had unlimited power, subject only to
                    the payment of an annual sum of 300,000 thalers, great oppression, and
                    frequently great cruelty, were exercised towards all under their authority.
                    These hospodars were sometimes suddenly deposed, and in some cases suffered
                    violent deaths, under charges of treachery, which commonly consisted of
                    negociations, real or pretended, with Russia or with Austria. After wars between
                    Turkey and Russia, followed by the successive treaties of Kancardschi, Jassy,
                    and Bucharest, the hospodars were declared to be under the protection of Russia,
                    to which nation the Walachians were much attached, from similarity of religion.
                    When hospodars were appointed, however, the Turkish pacha in command of the
                    fortresses on the Danube put up to auction the revenues paid on the trade by the
                    river, and thus sold a monopoly of the whole commerce in the pro <pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=750" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0750-0710"
                    />ducts of Walachia and Moldavia. This led to great internal distress, which was
                    augmented by the contemporaneous demands made by the bojares or landed
                    proprietors on the peasants. Amidst this unfortunate concurrence of evils, the
                    hospodar Prince Karadza, under apprehension of being deposed, or perhaps of
                    being executed, withdrew himself with his family and his treasure, and passing
                    through Hungary, took refuge in Geneva and Genoa in October 1818. In January
                    1819, the Porte nominated as his successor Prince Alexander Suzzo, who died two
                    years after. His death seemed to be the signal of a general insurrection, which,
                    though it broke out first in Walachia and Moldavia, speedily extended to the
                    whole of European Greece, as well as to the islands, and produced those
                    transactions which more properly belong to the history of that country than of
                    Walachia.</p>
                <p>The insurrection in Walachia was first commenced by a native bojar, Theodore
                    Wladimirsko, who had in the Russian service acquired the reputation of a brave
                    and skilful officer. He had retired from the army, and carried on an extensive
                    trade in corn, by which he had acquired considerable wealth, and had formed
                    connections and obtained confidence among the peasantry’ and smaller
                    proprietors. The interregnum appeared a favourable moment, and he at first
                    collected fifty adherents in Little Walachia, where he was soon joined by more
                    than 1000 peasants. In the mean time the Porte had nominated a new hospodar,
                    Kallimachi, who sought to form an alliance with Wladimirsko, by means of which
                    he expected to be enabled to raise the sum necessary to be paid at
                    Constantinople as the purchase of his dignity. The negociation was proceeding,
                    and might have been concluded, if not to the honour, to the advantage of the two
                    aspirants; but Alexander Ypsilante, a descendant of him who had been hospodar in
                    1806, and who had obtained the rank of general in the Russian army, appeared on
                    the scene with a body of Greeks, and took possession of Jassy. This caused a
                    most bloody civil war, by which Walachia and Moldavia were dreadfully ravaged
                    and wasted by alternate victors. The Turks at length sent an army sufficiently
                    strong to suppress the several contending parties, when submission was thus
                    enforced. The sultan, instead of a Greek, nominated a native as viceroy, and in
                    1822 placed Gregory Ghika on the throne, who, surrounded by Turkish guards, had
                    little or no power, and felt that his dignity was of very uncertain duration. He
                    continued to hold it, such as it was, till 1828, when a new war between Russia
                    and Turkey broke out, and the former took possession of both the principalities,
                    and established in Bucharest a plan of Russian civil organization.</p>
                <p>In its present state, Walachia extends in north latitude from 43° 44' to 46° 17',
                    and in east longitude from 22° 52' to 27° 51', and is in extent 24,640 square
                    miles. It is divided into two portions, viz. Eastern or Little Walachia, and
                    Western or Great Walachia, and these are again subdivided into circles, of which
                    the number in the former is five, and in the latter twelve. In the whole are
                    comprehended twenty-two cities or fortified places, twenty-five markettowns, and
                    2548 villages and hamlets. The number of the inhabitants is very doubtful; some
                    accounts make them amount to more than 1,000,000, while others state them not to
                    exceed 600,000. Nearly the whole of them adhere rigidly to the Greek church, and
                    are under the ecclesiastical authority of the archbishop of Bucharest, and of
                    the bishops of Rimnik and of Buseo. There are numerous monasteries, but the
                    occupants of them are very few. The people are strict in observing the great
                    number of holidays which the Greek church enjoins, and which are said to exceed
                    200 in each year, and on which no one works. There are a few Roman Catholics,
                    who own as their suffragan the bishop of Nicoolis. The people are of mixed
                    races, Walachians, Greeks, Armenians, Jews, and Gipsies. The latter, amounting
                    to 50,000 persons, are chiefly employed in the more servile occupations. These
                    mixed races have formed a common language, composed partly of Greek, somewhat
                    more of Latin, and abounding in words of original derivation. It has been seldom
                    acquired by any foreigner, nor has it been much studied or grammatically
                    analysed.</p>
                <p>A portion of the Carpathian Mountains, through which are several passages leading
                    to the Austrian territories, surrounds Walachia on the west and north-west
                    sides. From these, mountains project towards the Danube, and between them are
                    beautiful and fruitful vales, containing soils capable of producing most
                    abundant crops. From the termination of these spurs from the mountains there is
                    a level district, declining gradually to the great stream, and on its border
                    becoming marshes and morasses, in some parts covered with wood.</p>
                <p>If the inhabitants were industrious, the government protective, many of the
                    holidays abolished, and capital could be accumulated, few parts of Europe would
                    produce so much of all that contributes to life and comfort as this
                    principality. With its ignorant and inactive occupation, the land yields great
                    crops of maize, wheat, and barley. The first two are the exclusive food of man,
                    and the latter of the cattle. Hemp and flax are flourishing products. Fruit of
                    every kind is plentiful; the sides of the hills are covered with vines, and the
                    wine made from them is equal to that of Hungary. The land is watered by numerous
                    brooks, and the meadows yield excellent pasture for black cattle, while there
                    are plains well adapted for the breeding of horses. The export of horses and
                    cows is the chief trade between the principality and the surrounding countries.
                    The climate is temperate, though colder in winter than in the districts to the
                    south of the Balkan Mountains, but the winter scarcely endures more than two
                    months. There are no mines at work, and no manufactures except those of the
                    domestic kind.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
