<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0900-0860-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WESTMEATH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 860</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4736m682">Lakes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=900" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WESTMEATH</label>, an inland county in the province of
                    Leinster, in Ireland, is bounded on the north by Longford and Meath, on the east
                    by Meath and Kildare, on the south by the King’s county, and on the west by
                    Roscommon. It lies between 53° 20' and 53° 47' N. lat., and 7° and 7° 55' W.
                    long., extending forty miles in its greatest length from north to south, and
                    forty-five in its greatest breadth from west to east, and comprehending an area
                    of 708 square miles, or 453,468 acres, of which 431,041 are land, and the
                    remaining 22,427 are covered with water. It ranks as the twenty-sixth county in
                    superficial extent, and the twenty-fourth in that of its cultivated land.</p>
                <p>The county originally formed part of the central kingdom of Meath, when it was
                    distinguished by the name of Eircamhoin, or the western division. Nor was it
                    till the reign of Henry VIII. that it was formed into a separate county,
                    including within it the district of Longford, which continued to form part of it
                    till the reign of Elizabeth. Before the English invasion, the M‘Geoghegans,
                    chieftains of Moycashel, the Malones, and the Magardleys, were the principal
                    families. When the palatinate of Meath was granted to Hugh de Lacy by Henry II.,
                    the former proprietors were supplanted by English settlers, the principal of
                    whom were the families of Petit, Tuite, Hussey, Dalton, Delamaine, Nugent,
                    Geneville, Nangle, Ledwich, and Constantine. The confiscations consequent on the
                    wars of 1641 and 1688, in both of which the landed gentry took an active part,
                    made very great alterations in the state of property. The landing of a French
                    force in the west of Ireland in 1798 occasioned a partial insurrection in this
                    county, in the course of which the armed peasantry seized <pb break="no"
                    facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=901" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0901-0861"
                    />and fortified Wilson’s Hospital, but were quickly dispossessed of it by a
                    detachment of the royal forces.</p>
                <p>This district forms the most elevated portion of the great central plain of
                    Ireland, which is here 274 feet above the sea-level; but no part of it is
                    mountainous. The highest elevations are Knocklayde in the north, 795 feet high,
                    and the Hill of Ben, 710. All the hills are suited, even to their summit, for
                    pasturage, and some for tillage; many are richly clothed with timber. Lakes are
                    numerous: the largest lie in a direction nearly north and south along the middle
                    of the county. Lough Shillin, the most northern, is a border lake on the side of
                    Cavan, and near it is the smaller border lake of Lough Kinnail or Kinully. Lough
                    Dereveragh is a winding expanse of water, eleven miles long and three broad,
                    bordered in some parts by steep hills richly clothed with trees. Farther south
                    is Lough Owell or Hoyle, studded with islands, and Lough Tron or Hiern, of
                    smaller dimensions. The most southern, and also the largest lake of the chain,
                    is Lough Ennell, equally admirable for its scenic beauties and for its extent of
                    surface. A number of smaller lakes are scattered throughout the county. Loughs
                    Lene, Bawn, Glyde, and Fore, are in the northern part; the small but romantic
                    lake of Loughsewdy in the western. Lough Drin is remarkable only for its great
                    depth; it covers but an acre of land. Lough Ree or Reagh, which is in reality a
                    portion of the Shannon, forms part of the western boundary of the county,
                    separating it from that of Roscommon. It is twenty miles in length, and contains
                    several islands, two of which were the sites of religious foundations.</p>
                <p>Though no large rivers traverse this portion of the island, it may be considered
                    to be the source of several. The Inny, which rises in Lough Ramor in Cavan, and
                    enters Westmeath through Lough Shillin, through the most part of its course
                    forms the boundary line on the side of Longford, but in one part traverses the
                    county, and after dividing two of its baronies, ultimately joins the Shannon.
                    Two small rivers, the Golden and Silver Arms, which issued from the northern and
                    southern extremities of Lough Owell, have been closed up, so as to increase the
                    quantity of water in the parent lake, which is the main feeder of the Royal
                    Canal. The Brosna flows from Lough Ennell into the Shannon, which forms part of
                    the western boundary of the county. Lough Lene also gives rise to two streams of
                    some notoriety. The northern, after sinking into the ground near the village of
                    Fore, and re-appearing, empties itself, under the name of the Glore, into the
                    Inny, and the united streams pass through the Shannon into the Atlantic. The
                    southern forms the Deel, which joins the Boyne, and falls into the Irish Sea.
                    Hence this little lake, with its two perennial branches, may be said to divide
                    Ireland into two islands.</p>
                <p>The county forms part of the great limestone field that traverses the island
                    across its centre. This substratum is interrupted in two places only, the one at
                    Moat-a-Grenogue, and the other near Ballymahon, at each of which places the
                    sandstone rises from under the limestone bed, and forms insulated protuberances
                    of some elevation. In some places the limestone is wrought up for architectural
                    and domestic purposes, but in others its quality is such as to render it nearly
                    unfit for the farmer’s use, in consequence of the quantity of fuel required for
                    its calcination. Traces of lead and copper have been discovered, but not in
                    quantities sufficient to hold out a fair prospect of pecuniary remuneration by
                    exploring them farther. Coal is also said to have been raised in small
                    quantities. A chalybeate spring rises at Grangemore, near Kinnegad, bursting
                    forth with force, and forming a copious stream; but in consequence of the
                    difficulty of access to it, few take advantage of its medicinal virtues. The
                    soil is in general a deep rich loam resting on the limestone, but in the flat
                    lands in the west it is light. The centre is intersected with numerous eskers
                    formed of calcareous gravel. There is much bog: that of Allen covers a large
                    portion of the western baronies. Many parts are well timbered; and traces of the
                    old forests show themselves by the spontaneous growth of indigenous trees of
                    various kinds in places where the young shoots are protected from the
                    depredations of cattle.</p>
                <p>The progress of the population, and its actual state, according to the latest
                    census, appear in the following table.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Year. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Authority. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> No. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="3" role="data" rows="1"><p>1760 De Burgo 50,340</p><p>1792
                            Beaufort 69,000</p><p>1812 Parliamentary census...112,000</p><p>1821
                            Ditto 128,819</p><p>1831 Ditto 148,161</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The last of these returns gives a population of one inhabitant to every 3∙06
                    acres. The return of the Commissioners of Public Instruction in 1834, taken
                    according to dioceses, gives a population to the county of about 138,560 souls,
                    of whom 10,175 are of the established church, 251 Protestant dissenters, and
                    128,133 Roman Catholics. The number of children receiving instruction in the
                    public schools, at the periods stated beneath, is as follows, according to
                    returns made to parliament.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Boys. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Girls. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Sex not ascertained. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Total </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="5" role="data" rows="1"> 1821 4952 2374 7326 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="5" role="data" rows="1"> 1824-6 5740 3820 359 9919 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="5" role="data" rows="1"> 1836-7 1717 1656 3373 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="5" role="data" rows="1"> 1837-8 1881 1664 3545 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="5" role="data" rows="1"> 1838-9 2126 1925 4051 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>According to the return of 1824-6, the number of Catholic children educated in
                    the public schools was 8249, of Protestants 1533, and of dissenters six; that of
                    those whose religious persuasion could not be ascertained amounting to 131. The
                    total number of schools was 216, out of which number twenty-six, containing 1532
                    pupils, were maintained wholly by grants of public money; twenty-five, with 1542
                    pupils, by voluntary subscriptions; all the remaining schools, in number 165,
                    and educating 6845 children, being supported wholly by the fees of the pupils.
                    An establishment for the maintenance and education of 160 boys, the sons of
                    Protestant parents, natives of Westmeath, who are afterwards apprenticed to
                    Protestant artificers, with a fee of L.10 each, was founded under the will of
                    Andrew-Wilson of Piercefield, Esq. and still exists. The estate bequeathed for
                    this purpose amounts to L.4000 per annum. Under the incorporated society for
                    erecting charter schools, there is a school situate at Leney, six miles from
                    Mullingar, intended for the maintenance and education of sixty children.</p>
                <p>The county is divided into the twelve baronies of Braw-ney, called also the
                    territory of Brawney, Clonlonan, Cork-aree, Delvin, Demifore, Farbill,
                    Fartullagh, Kilkenny-west, Moyashel and Magheradernon, Moycashel, Moygoish, and
                    Rathconrath. These are subdivided into sixty-two parishes, of which fifty-nine
                    are in the diocese of Meath, and three in that of Ardagh. It was represented in
                    the Irish parliament by ten members, two for the county, and two for each of the
                    boroughs of Athlone, Fore, Kilbeggan, and Mullingar. By the arrangements under
                    the union act, all the boroughs were disfranchised, except the first, which
                    belongs only partially to this county, one half of it being in Roscommon; it now
                    returns one member. The constituency for the county was as follows in the
                    under-named years.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Date. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> No. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1829 2601 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1830 641 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1831 921 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1832 1395 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Date. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> No. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1833 1395 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1834 1395 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1835 1395 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1836 1526 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Date. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> No. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1837 1525 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1838 1525 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> 1839 1300 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=902"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0902-0862"/>
                <p>The number of electors in the last of these returns gives an average of one
                    elector to every 106 individuals, or of one to every eighteen heads of families
                    of six individuals each.</p>
                <p>The county is in the home circuit. The assizes are held at Mullingar. General
                    sessions of the peace are held alternately in that town and in Moate. The local
                    government consists of a lieutenant, fifteen deputy-lieutenants, sixty-nine
                    unpaid magistrates, and a stipendiary, under whom there is a constabulary force,
                    consisting of a county inspector, six sub-inspectors, seven head constables, and
                    272 constables and sub-constables. The county infirmary is in Mullingar, a fever
                    hospital at Castlepollard, and fifteen dispensaries in various places. Lunatics
                    are sent to the district asylum at Maryborough, where forty patients from the
                    county are received. Mullingar and Athlone have been fixed on as sites for the
                    workhouses of poor-law unions.</p>
                <p>All kinds of grain thrive well in this productive soil. The English system of
                    tillage is adopted by all except the poorer farmers and cottagers. Wheat forms a
                    part of every succession of crops, and green crops are very frequent. Limestone
                    gravel, which is to be had in abundance in most parts, is the usual manure. The
                    fences are bad, except in the demesnes of the gentry. The low lands and valleys
                    produce abundance of rich grass; from which cause, and as the management of
                    cattle has been found more profitable and less laborious than tillage, most of
                    the land in the county is assigned to the former department of rural economy.
                    Great attention is paid to the breeds of cattle, which, both great and small,
                    are purchased chiefly at the fairs of Ballinasloe. The long-homed cows are
                    preferred, as being large, and good milkers. The breed of horses is excellent.
                    Many are brought young from Connaught, and reared here till fit for the market.
                    Dairies are frequent, and butter is made in large quantities. The method of
                    haymaking is bad, the hay being allowed to stand in small stacks in the field
                    till late in the season, in consequence of which it is much injured both by the
                    heat and the rains. Like most other parts of the island, timber was abundant,
                    until destroyed by a lavish and improvident use of it, which made no provision
                    for a fresh supply. The deficiency is severely felt; but here, as elsewhere,
                    great exertions are making to remedy it by young plantations, which are now
                    rising in many parts.</p>
                <p>The manufactures are not, nor were they ever, of any magnitude; the making of
                    woollen and linen cloths being almost wholly confined to the domestic demand,
                    and the operations carried on in the farmers’ houses. Fish is abundant in the
                    lakes and rivers. Bream, trout, pike, and eels, are taken in the Inny; salmon in
                    the same river and in the Brosna. The goaske, a fish about the size of the
                    herring, is found in Lough Dereveragh; a thin-shelled mussel in some of the
                    bogs. The Royal Canal passes through the central part of the county from east to
                    west; a branch of the Grand Canal proceeds from near Philipstown in King’s
                    county to Kilbeggan. There are three banking establishments, one a branch of the
                    Provincial, the other two of the National Bank of Ireland. There are nine loan
                    societies, in which the total amount of the loans in the hands of borrowers at
                    the close of 1839 was L.10,675, and the total number of borrowers during the
                    year 9071. Under the direction of the late Commissioners for Railroads in
                    Ireland, a survey has been made of a line from Dublin, to enter the county near
                    Killucan, and to proceed to Mullingar, whence it is to diverge in two branches,
                    the one north-west through Longford to Sligo, the other westward through Athlone
                    to Galway; but no steps have yet been taken to carry the plan into
                    execution.</p>
                <p>A considerable number of the landed proprietors reside on their own property;
                    hence the county contains many elegant mansions and villas, surrounded by
                    well-planted demesnes, which add very much to the natural beauties of the
                    landscape. In the demesne of Mount d’Alton is an obelisk fifty feet high,
                    erected in honour of the empress Maria Theresa, the Emperor Joseph, and King
                    George III., by a late member of the D’Alton family, a retired officer in the
                    Austrian service. An obelisk of similar dimensions stands on the estate of
                    Lowville, near Kilkenny-west. The character of the middling and lower classes is
                    superior to that of those in the adjoining county of Meath. The peasantry are
                    described as being lively, intelligent, and quick-witted; hasty in their
                    tempers, and prone to litigation; unwilling to deviate from the habits and
                    customs of their forefathers; lax in their ideas of morality towards their
                    superiors, but rigidly observant of the engagements voluntarily entered into
                    with one another, and of the religious observances imposed on them by their
                    clergy. They are also much addicted to superstitious practices. The horses are
                    bathed in one of the lakes on the second Sunday in August, called Garlic Sunday,
                    from a belief that they will thus be secured from injury during the rest of the
                    year. Fish taken out of the stream that sinks into the ground near Fore will not
                    be eaten, in consequence of the religious respect with which the water of it is
                    honoured. A disinclination to improvement in their farms, and to domestic
                    neatness, is also observable. The cottages are ill constructed and badly
                    furnished, the roofs being made of boughs of trees with the leaves on, covered
                    with sods of turf or peat called scraws, and thatched with straw. Many are
                    without chimneys, the place of which is supplied by a hole in the roof. The
                    furniture consists of a deal table, a few stools, an iron pot, and a dresser,
                    with a few plates and dairy utensils. Yet their clothing is comfortable, usually
                    of home-made gray or drab frieze. The use of linen has of late been almost
                    universally superseded by cotton. The favourite garment of the men is a large
                    loose coat, wrapped up in which they go to the fairs and markets even during the
                    heat of summer, followed by their wives, who transact most of the business
                    there. The women spin the wool and flax for their clothing, perform the
                    household work, and take a large share in the labours of the field. When
                    married, they still retain their maiden names. English and Irish are spoken, but
                    the use of the latter is more general in their intercourse with one another.</p>
                <p>Many remains of antiquity still exist. The parish of Rathconrath takes its name
                    from a rath or moat of large dimensions and peculiar construction; besides
                    which, nine of smaller size have been discovered within its boundaries. A still
                    more remarkable pile of the same kind exists at Ballymore. It had originally
                    been a Danish fort, and its position was so well chosen for military purposes,
                    that it was strongly fortified by the Irish in the wars of 1641 and 1688; and
                    after its capture by the English in the latter period, it was made the
                    head-quarters of General Ginckell when preparing to besiege Athlone. A third,
                    called the Fort of Turgesius, as being the reputed place of residence of that
                    monarch during his reign in Ireland, is to be seen near Lough Lene. Those of
                    inferior note are too numerous to be particularized. The ruins of ancient
                    castles are also visible in many places. The origin of several of them can be
                    traced back to Hugh de Lacy, the first lord palatine of the county. His chief
                    place of residence was at Kilbixy, where he had a large and well-fortified
                    castle, and where also stood a town of such importance as to be governed by a
                    mayor or sovereign, and burgesses, with their usual appendages of inferior
                    officers. The site of the former is now merely matter of conjecture; and the
                    privileges, and consequently the importance, of the latter have been transferred
                    to Mullingar. Another of this nobleman’s castles was at Ardnurcher, better known
                    by the name of Horseleap, from the romantic tradition of an extraordinary bound
                    made by a horse across a cleft between two steep hills, in effecting <pb
                    break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=903"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0721-0903-0863"/> which the animal is said to have left the marks
                    of its hoofs on the rock whence it started, and their traces are supposed to be
                    visible to the present day; or from a leap over the drawbridge, made by a knight
                    in effecting his escape from the castle. The castle is also noted in history as
                    being the place where the same De Lacy was treacherously killed by one of his
                    own menials. The castles of Sonnagh, Rath-wire, and Killare, were built by the
                    same nobleman. In the barony of Moycashel are the remains of several castles
                    formerly possessed by the M‘Geoghegans, the ancient proprietors of the soil.
                    Some of the old monastic buildings have been converted into parochial places of
                    worship, both Protestant and Roman Catholic. The ruins of a few are still in
                    existence, but the locality of many others is now a subject tending rather to
                    excite than to satisfy curiosity. The ruins of Tristernagh Abbey, called also
                    the Priory of Kilbixy, and founded by one of Hugh de Lacy’s immediate
                    successors, were visible till the year 1783, when they were totally destroyed.
                    Near them are the remains of the chapel of Templecross, which, though of
                    inferior note as a structure of monastic celebrity, is memorable from being the
                    place where the corp-naomh, or blessed body, a relic of extraordinary sanctity,
                    was found. The relic consists of a wooden box about the size of a small Bible,
                    clasped with bands of brass, studded with valuable stones, and marked with a
                    crucifix. Its contents, if any, are unknown, for no hand has yet been found of
                    nerve sufficient to venture to force it open. It is used as a test of evidence.
                    An oath on the corp-naomh is considered as an act of peculiar solemnity; a
                    pledge which, if given in support of a falsehood, is supposed to bring down on
                    the guilty person some visitation of dreadful consequence. Such is the respect
                    paid even to its name, that if any one asserts what he wishes to be received
                    with implicit credit, he avers its truth “by the corp-naomh that arose at
                    Templecross.” The site of the Abbey of Multifernan can still be traced by its
                    ruins. It lies about four miles north of Tristernagh, and is singularly
                    remarkable as being in possession of the Franciscan friars till the commencement
                    of the year 1641, notwithstanding the total suppression of the monasteries by
                    Henry VIII. upwards of a century before. For some years previous to the breaking
                    out of the civil wars at the above-mentioned period, it had been much frequented
                    by visitors of every description, who went thither, as was said, to arrange the
                    plans of the ensuing insurrection. The unusual assemblage of strangers is also
                    said to have excited such apprehensions in the mind of the then bishop of
                    Ardagh, that he removed with all his property to England, and thus escaped the
                    calamities with which so many who continued to reside in the country were
                    visited. There were three religious houses at Mullingar, belonging respectively
                    to the Dominicans, Franciscans, and Augustinians. At Kilkenny-west are the
                    reliques of a preceptory of the Knights of St John. It is also remarkable for a
                    noted holy well.</p>
                <p>The population of Westmeath is so exclusively rural, that Mullingar, where the
                    assizes are held, is the only town containing more than 2000 inhabitants. It is
                    situate nearly in the centre of the county and of Ireland, at the junction of
                    the barony of Fertullagh with that of Moyashel and Magheradernon, on the stream
                    of the Golden Arm, about midway between Loughs Owell and Ennell. It was one of
                    the ancient palatinate towns of the county, and suffered much by the ravages
                    committed during the petty wars with the Irish. In the war of 1688, it was
                    fortified by General Ginckcll, and was for some time the head-quarters of the
                    English army. Though it obtained a charter, it enjoyed none of the usual
                    corporate rights, except that of returning two members to parliament, a
                    privilege of which its proprietor or patron availed himself till the union. Four
                    general sessions of the peace are held here. It is the site of the county
                    court-house, prison, and infirmary, and has a large church, and a Roman Catholic
                    chapel capable of holding 6000 persons, which is considered to be the cathedral
                    of the diocese; the parish, with two others and a part of a third, being the
                    mensal of the bishop, who resides in the town. The vicinity of the Royal Canal,
                    which passes close to the northern side of the town, and on which steamers ply
                    regularly to Shannon harbour, has made the place the centre of an increasing
                    inland trade, which is also aided by the mail-road to Sligo passing through it.
                    It holds a weekly market, and four fairs during the year. Large quantities of
                    butter are brought to the former, and the latter are great marts for wool, homed
                    cattle, and pigs; the November fair is for horses. One half of the town of
                    Athlone is in this county, and is connected with the other half, lying on the
                    Roscommon side, by a long bridge over the Shannon, so narrow that two carriages
                    can with difficulty pass each other; but this check upon the communication
                    between the two provinces of Leinster and Connaught is about to be obviated by
                    the erection of a new bridge. The town is governed by a sovereign, two bailifs,
                    and a recorder. It returned two members to the Irish parliament, and since the
                    union one to the imperial parliament. The number of electors in 1832 was 243; in
                    1834, 274; and in 1839, 275. It is a place of great antiquity, being known as
                    such before the settlement of the English; and after their arrival a castle was
                    erected here by King John, to secure the main pass of the Shannon, which was
                    deemed of such importance, that in a grant of the whole of Ireland by Henry III.
                    to his son Edward, Athlone was specially excepted. It afterwards was the seat of
                    government for the lord president of Connaught. In the war of 1642 it was taken
                    by the Irish after a stubborn and protracted resistance, but subsequently
                    retaken by the parliamentary army. In the war of 1688 it was invested by King
                    William’s forces under General Douglas, who was forced to raise the siege by
                    means of the gallant defence of Colonel Grace; but it was soon after taken by
                    storm by General Ginckell, in the face of the Irish army commanded by St Ruth.
                    In 1697, the magazine was struck by lightning, and the castle and town nearly
                    destroyed. It is still considered of such importance in a military point of
                    view, that large works have been thrown up on its western side, in which a
                    garrison is maintained. The population of Mullingar amounted in 1831 to 4295,
                    that of the eastern portion of Athlone to 5655. The population of the other
                    towns whose number of inhabitants exceed 1000 each is, Kilbeggan, 1985; Moate,
                    1785; Castlepollard, 1618. (c. p.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
