<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0853-0813-06" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">WATSON, Robert</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 21, page 813</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:821653">Authority</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1113216">Sermons</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:942527">Gibbons</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94h10">Sermons</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dq72">Salt</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=853" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">WATSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Robert</hi></label>, LL.D., an
                    elegant historian, was born at St Andrews, about the year 1730. He was the son
                    of an apothecary of that place, who was also a brewer. Having gone through the
                    usual course of languages and philosophy at the school and university of his
                    native city, and also entered on the study of divinity, a desire of being
                    acquainted with a larger circle of literati, and of improving himself in every
                    branch of knowledge, carried him, first to the university of Glasgow, and
                    afterwards to that of Edinburgh. The period of theological studies at the
                    universities of Scotland is four years; but during that period, young men of
                    ingenious minds find sufficient leisure to carry on and advance the pursuits of
                    general knowledge. Mr Watson pursued his studies with ardour. Few men ever
                    studied more constantly. It was a rule with him to study eight hours every day;
                    and this rule he observed during the whole course of his life. An acquaintance
                    with the polite writers of England, after the union of the two kingdoms, became
                    general in Scotland; and in Watson’s younger years, an emulation began to
                    prevail of writing pure and elegant English. He applied himself with great
                    industry to the principles of philosophical or universal grammar; and by a
                    combination of these with the authority of the best English writers, formed a
                    course of lectures on style or language. He proceeded to the study of rhetoric
                    or eloquence, the principles of which he endeavoured to trace to the nature of
                    tile human mind. He delivered a course of lectures in Edinburgh on these
                    subjects, and met with the countenance, approbation, and friendship of Lord
                    Kames, Mr Hume, with other men of genius and learning.</p><p>At this time he had become a licentiate; and a vacancy having happened in one of
                    the churches of St Andrews, he offered himself a candidate for that living, but
                    was disappointed. Soon after he was appointed professor of logic; and he also
                    obtained a patent from the crown, constituting him professor of rhetoric and
                    belles lettres. The study of logic in St Andrews, as in most other places, was
                    at this time confined to syllogisms, modes, and figures. Watson, whose mind had
                    been opened by conversation, and by reading the writings of the wits that had
                    begun to flourish in the Scotish capital, prepared and read to his students a
                    course of metaphysics and logics on the most enlightened plan; in which he
                    analysed the powers of the mind, and entered deeply into the nature of the
                    different species of evidence of truth or knowledge. By his History of the Reign
                    of Philip II. King of Spain, published at London in 1777, in 2 vols. 4to, Dr
                    Watson attained in his lifetime a considerable degree of celebrity; and his
                    History of the Reign of Philip III., published after his death, added to his
                    fame. Of this last performance, however, he has only completed the first four
                    books; the two last were written by Dr Thomson, at the desire of the guardians
                    of his children. Lond. 1783, 4to.</p><p>Dr Watson was appointed principal of United College on the death of Dr Tulideph,
                    but he only enjoyed this preferment for a few years. He married a lady of
                    singular beauty and virtue, the daughter of Dr Shaw, professor of divinity in St
                    Mary’s College. By this lady he had five daughters, who survived him. He died in
                    the year 1780.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Watson,</hi><hi rend="italic">Richard,</hi> Bishop of
                    Landaff, celebrated as an able theologian, and as a professor of chemistry, was
                    born in August 1737, at Heversham near Kendal, in Westmoreland. His ancestors
                    had been farmers of their own estates for several generations; and his father
                    had for forty years been master of the free school at Heversham, but was become
                    infirm, and had resigned it a little before his birth. He was however educated
                    at this school, and continued there till 1754, when he was sent as a sizer to
                    Trinity College, Cambridge. He applied without intermission to his studies, and
                    in 1757 he obtained a scholarship, with particular expressions of approbation
                    from Dr Smith, who was then master. He had made it a constant practice in his
                    mathematical pursuits, to think over the demonstration of every proposition that
                    he studied, in his solitary walks; a habit which must certainly have been very
                    conducive to the improvement of geometrical talent, though it could scarcely be
                    adopted without great labour by those who follow the algebraical mode of
                    analysis in all their investigations. After this period he passed many hours
                    daily, for a considerable portion of his life, in the occupation of instructing
                    others, without much enlarging the scale of his own information, though
                    certainly not without adding to the solidity and precision of his knowledge of
                    the most important elementary truths of science; and when he graduated in 1759,
                    he was classed as the second wrangler, which he seems to have considered, not
                    without reason, as the place of honour for the year, the senior wrangler, who
                    was a Johnian, having, as it was generally believed, been unfairly preferred to
                    him. In October 1760, he became a fellow of Trinity, and in November, assistant
                    tutor of the college. Having taken <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=854" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0854-0814"/>his degree of M. A. in 1762, he was soon afterwards made moderator of the
                    scholastic exercises of the university, an arduous and honourable office, which
                    he also filled in several subsequent years.</p><p>In 1764, he undertook a journey to Paris, though without being able to speak the
                    language, in order to take charge of his young friend and pupil Mr Luther, who
                    returned to England with him soon after. He was elected in the same year
                    professor of chemistry, though he had never devoted any portion of his attention
                    to that science; but he soon rendered himself sufficiently master of all that
                    was then known of the science, to give a very popular course of lectures on the
                    subject about a year after his election, with the assistance of an operator whom
                    he had brought from Paris, and to become the author of a series of essays, which
                    served for many years as the most agreeable introduction to the elementary
                    doctrines and the ordinary processes of chemistry. He obtained from the
                    government, by proper representations, a salary of L.100 a year for himself, and
                    for all future professors. He also paid some attention to theoretical and
                    practical anatomy, as having some relation to the science of chemistry. In 1767,
                    he became one of the principal tutors of Trinity College; in 1769, he was
                    elected a fellow of the Royal Society, and in October 1771, he unexpectedly
                    obtained the important and lucrative appointment of regius professor of
                    divinity, upon the premature death of Dr Rutherforth, and in that capacity he
                    held the rectory of Somersham in Huntingdonshire. He had been little accustomed
                    to the study of the divinity of the schools, or even of the fathers; but his
                    eloquence and ingenuity supplied the want of theological learning, though he
                    gave some offence to his more orthodox colleagues, by confining his arguments
                    more strictly to the text of the scripture than they thought perfectly
                    consistent with the duty of a champion of the church of England, which they
                    considered to be the description of a professor of divinity in an English
                    university. He attracted, however, as long as he officiated in person, audiences
                    as numerous, to the exercises in the schools at which he presided, as had
                    attended his chemical lectures.</p><p>He married, in December 1773, Miss Wilson of Dallam Tower in Westmoreland. Their
                    union continued uninterrupted for more than forty years. In 1774 he obtained a
                    prebend of Ely, in exchange for a rectory in Wales, which the duke of Grafton
                    had procured for him; and he became archdeacon of Ely in January 1780: in the
                    same year Bishop Keene presented him with the rectory of Northwold in Norfolk;
                    and in 1782, his pupil, the duke of Rutland, gave him the rectory of Knaptoft in
                    Leicestershire: the same interest obtained him also from Lord Shelburne the
                    bishopric of Landaff. Here his episcopal preferment rested. He generally joined
                    the politics of the opposition, and especially on the question of the unlimited
                    regency; but he was too independent in his sentiments to become a very useful
                    member of any administration; and he retired, before the end of the year 1789,
                    without books, and with somewhat more of disgust than he ought in justice to
                    have felt, to an estate which he had bought at Calgarth, on the banks of
                    Winandermere, and occupied himself entirely, besides the education of his
                    family, in agricultural improvements, especially in planting, for which he
                    received a medal from the Society of Arts in 1789. His pupil, Mr Luther of Ongar
                    in Essex, had died in 1786, and left him an estate, which he afterwards sold for
                    something more than L.20,000.</p><p>He considered as one of the best practical results of his chemical studies, the
                    suggestion which he made to the duke of Richmond, then master of the ordnance,
                    respecting the preparation of charcoal for gunpowder, by burning the wood in
                    close vessels, which, it seems, very materially improved the quality of the
                    powder.</p><p>He had the liberality to confer, in 1804, a small living, as a reward for
                    literary merit only, on Mr Davies, the author of the Celtic Researches. The next
                    year, he applied with success to the duke of York for the promotion of his son,
                    who had then the rank of a major; and his royal highness speedily complied with
                    his solicitation, as a personal favour only, without waiting for any ministerial
                    influence.</p><p>His health had been seriously impaired by an illness which attacked him in 1781,
                    and which his friends attributed, though perhaps without sufficient reason, to
                    excessive study. In October 1809, he had a slight paralytic affection, and
                    another in 1811; but it was in 1813 that his last illness might be said to
                    begin, and he sunk gradually till the 4th of July 1816. The elder of his two
                    sons was in the army, the younger in the church: he left also several daughters.
                    His writings are as miscellaneous as they are numerous, but none of them are
                    bulky.</p><p>1. Institutionum Chemicarum pars Metallurgica. Cambr. 1768, 8vo. Repr. Ess. vol.
                    v.</p><p>2. Experiments and Observations on the Solution of Salts. Phil. Trans. 1770, p.
                    325, Ess. v. Especially on the specific gravities of salts and their solutions.
                    3. Remarks on the Effects of Cold in February 1771. Phil. Trans. 1771, p. 213,
                    Ess. v. With some experiments on congelation. 4. Experiment with a Thermometer
                    having its bulb blackened. Phil. Trans. 1773, p. 40, Ess. v. Raised 10°. 5.
                    Chemical Experiments and Observations on Lead Ore. Phil. Trans. 1778, p∙ 863,
                    Ess. v. 6. Observations on the Sulphur Wells at Harrowgate. Phil. Trans. 1786,
                    p. 171, Ess. v.</p><p>7∙ An Essay on the Subjects of Chemistry, and their General Division.</p><p>8. Assize Sermon, preached at Cambridge. 17G9, 4to.</p><p>9. Letters to the Members of the House of Commons, by a Christian Whig, 1772.</p><p>10. 11. Two Sermons. Cambr. 1776, 4to. On the Revolution, and on the King’s
                    Accession.</p><p>12. A brief State of the Principles of Church Authority, 1773. Reprinted in 1813
                    as a charge.</p><p>13. A Fast Sermon, Feb. 1780.</p><p>14. A Sermon addressed to the Clergy of Ely, 1780. Recommending oriental
                    literature.</p><p>15. An Apology for Christianitv, in a series of Letters addressed to Edward
                    Gibbon, Esq. Lond. 1778, 12mo. Often reprinted, and considered as very
                    satisfactory, though the author confesses, with more of the courtier than of the
                    orthodox divine, in a letter to Mr Gibbon, that the essay “derives its chief
                    merit from the elegance and importance of the work it attempts to oppose.”</p><p>16. Chemical Essays. Lond. 1781-7,5 vols. 12mo. Addressed to his pupil the duke
                    of Rutland. The work was intended for general information, and became extremely
                    popular as a first introduction. The first volume relates to salts, sulphurs,
                    vitriols, and gunpowder; the second to common salt, distillation, lime, clay,
                    and pit coal; the third to bitumens, charcoal, evaporation, lead, and lead ores;
                    and the fourth to zinc, gum, metal, tin, copper, iron, and stones; the fifth is
                    a republication of the author’s earlier chemical tracts. After the completion of
                    these volumes, he had the resolution to burn all his chemical papers.</p><p>17. A Letter to Archbishop Cornwallis on the Church Revenues, 1782. A plan for
                    equalizing the bishoprics.</p><p>18. A Sermon preached the 30th Jan. before the Lords. 1784, 4to.</p><p>19. Visitation Articles, for the Diocese of Landaff.</p><p>20. Theological Tracts. Lond. 1785, 6 vols. 8vo. Collected from various authors,
                    not excluding many works of dissenters from the church.</p><p>21. A Sermon on the Wisdom and Goodness of God, in having made Rich and Poor,
                    1785, 1793. Adapted to allay the discontents which were then prevalent among the
                    lower classes.</p><p>22. Sermons and Tracts. Lond. 1788, 8vo. Chiefly republications.</p><p>23. An Address to Young Persons after Confirmation. 1789, 12mo.</p><p>24. Considerations on the Expediency of Revising the Liturgy. 1790, 8vo.
                    Anonymous.</p><p>25. A Sermon preached for the Westminster Dispensary in 1785, with an Appendix.
                    1792.</p><p>26. A Charge to the Clergy of his Diocese. 1792, 4to.</p><p>27. Two Sermons and a Charge. 1795, 4to. The first sermon is entitled Atheism
                    refuted; the second, The Christian Religion no Imposture.</p><pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=855" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0855-0815"/><p>28. An Apology for the Bible, in a series of Letters addressed to Thomas Paine.
                    Lond. 1796, 12mo. An able and judicious answer to the contemptible work of a
                    mischievous incendiary: it seems to have been singularly successful in producing
                    clear and rapid conviction. Thanks were returned to the author from Ireland and
                    from America, and he gained L. 1000 by the sale of the book, besides allowing it
                    to be often reprinted gratuitously.</p><p>29. An Address to the People of Great Britain. 1700, 8vo. Enforcing the necessity
                    of submission to the exigencies of the times. It went through fourteen editions,
                    besides several piracies; and it was reprinted in Ireland by order of Lord
                    Camden, then Lord Lieutenant. Mr Wakefield answered it somewhat intemperately,
                    and the bishop attempted ineffectually, out of respect for his classical
                    acquirements, to lighten the punishment which was allotted to him.</p><p>30. Charge to the Clergy of Landaff. 31. Second Charge, 1802. On similar
                    subjects.</p><p>32. A Charge relating to Ecclesiastical Reform, 1802.</p><p>33. A Sermon preached at the London Hospital, 1802. Against the principles of
                    Paine.</p><p>34. Thoughts on the intended Invasion, 8vo.</p><p>35. Substance of a Speech intended to have been delivered, 1804. In favour of
                    Catholic Emancipation.</p><p>36. Sermon preached before the Society for the Suppression of Vice, 1804.</p><p>37. A Charge to the Clergy, 1805. 38. Another Charge, on the Catholic Question,
                    1803.</p><p>39. Two Apologies, two Sermons, and a Charge. 1806, 8vo. Reprinted.</p><p>40. A second Defence of Revealed Religion, 1807. In two sermons, preached in the
                    Chapel Royal.</p><p>41. A Paper on Planting and on Waste Land. Communications to the Board of
                    Agriculture, vol. vii. 1808, 4to. 42. He had also written some Preliminary
                    Observations in the Agricultural Report of Westmoreland.</p><p>43. Miscellaneous Tracts. Lond. 1815, 2 vols. 8vo. Religious, political, and
                    agricultural. “His discourse on the first and second Adam, and the nature of
                    death as affected by each, is almost unequalled in originality of thought and
                    vigour of expression.” Quarterly Review.</p><p>(44). It has been said that he published some papers in the Manchester Memoirs;
                    but they do not appear in the indices.</p><p>45. Anecdotes of the Life of Richard Watson, Bishop of Landaft; written by
                    himself at different times, and revised in 1814. Published by his son Richard
                    Watson, LL. B. Prebendary of Landaff and Weils. Lond. 1817, 4to. Lond. 1818, 2
                    vols. 8vo. Quarterly Review, xviii. p. 229. Treated with great ability, but with
                    too much severity. His chief mistake indeed seems to have been, that he expected
                    his literary merits alone to secure him political advancement; further than
                    this, there is nothing disgusting, to a candid reader, in the sincerity with
                    which he displays the consciousness of his own merits. The praises of the
                    reviewer himself are at least as energetic as those of the friends whose
                    language he has occasionally copied; his censures are not less impressive; but
                    tor an author’s censure of himself, it would be idle to look in a work of
                    autobiography.</p><p>Though somewhat reserved, Dr Watson is said to have been remarkable for the
                    simplicity of his manners and the equality of his temper. With respect to his
                    conduct in the school of divinity, the reviewer confesses that “he ascended the
                    chair with many eminent qualifications for his difficult and distinguished
                    functions. The exercise of four years, as moderator of the philosophical
                    schools, had rendered his faculty of speaking Latin perfectly easy; by great
                    assiduity, the vices of his early education had been so far corrected that a
                    false quantity was never heard to escape him; all the tricks and shifts of
                    school logic were familiar to his mind, in addition to which, his acuteness and
                    ingenuity were admirable. His majestic and commanding figure, his terrific
                    countenance, his deep sonorous voice, the uninterrupted tenor of his sentences,
                    which, though far from classical, were never either barbarous or soloecistic,
                    and, above all, the boldness and originality of his sentiments, seldom left the
                    under graduates’ places unoccupied in the theological school. It was sport to
                    see how the grave professor would glide over the surface of the subject with
                    every appearance of profundity, or when pinned, as his opponent hoped, into a
                    corner, would wind himself out with all the lubricity of an eel. Still he had a
                    large mind; he endured, he encouraged, <hi rend="italic">he delighted</hi> In
                    <hi rend="italic">the opposition of able men; he never flinched from the strokes
                    of those who had more information than himself,</hi> secure in the consciousness
                    of his own ability to encounter learning by invention. The same tolerance of
                    contradiction, the same dexterity in parrying attacks, he brought with him into
                    private conversation, which rendered him, when the poison of politics did not
                    operate on his constitution, a most agreeable and amusing debater. In these
                    happier hours, and they were not few, he would even smile at the pomp and
                    magnificence of his own manner, and relax into all the <hi rend="italic">playfulness</hi> and pleasantry which are almost inseparable from <hi rend="italic">real genius.”</hi></p><p>Our critic appears, however, to have exceeded the limits of candour and of
                    charity, when he asserts that “he was governed through life by the two leading
                    principles of interest and ambition, both of which were thwarted in his
                    political conduct, by a temper so wayward, and a presumption so overweening,
                    that the disappointment produced by their collision embittered his mind, and
                    exasperated his latter days to a very high degree of malignity. Accomplished as
                    he was in academical learning, he had no ingenuous or disinterested love of
                    knowledge: he read only that he might teach, and he taught only that he might
                    rise.”</p><p>“When he felt himself neglected, he avowedly and professedly abandoned all study,
                    because, says be, 'eagerness in the pursuit of knowledge was a part of my temper
                    till,' and only till, ‘ the acquisition of knowledge was attended with nothing
                    but the neglect of the king and his ministers.’ Disgusted, therefore, and
                    disappointed, as much as broken in constitution, he withdrew into the wilds of
                    Westmoreland without a library, and to this privation he voluntarily submitted
                    almost thirty years. From taste he derived neither amusement nor occupation, for
                    of taste he never had a tincture; placed amidst the most delicious scenes of
                    England, he thought of nothing but turning his own portion of them to emolument
                    !” Thus “this violent deciaimer against sinecures and nonresidence was the first
                    who converted the regius professorship of divinity into a sinecure: this enemy
                    of pluralities held at least <hi rend="italic">fourteen</hi> places of
                    preferment; this man of moderation in his wishes, and calm contentment, under
                    the shade of retirement, spent the last twenty-nine years of his life in ‘
                    execrating’ [complaining of] those who, for his factious obstinacy, had left him
                    to that retirement, while he was occupied in nursing up a fortune, till,
                    according to his own boast, with the poorest bishopric in the kingdom, he became
                    the richest bishop upon the bench.”</p><p>With respect to the merits of the question between him and the administration of
                    his early friend Mr Pitt, there will probably be as many different opinions as
                    there are readers of different political parties; but he had surely no right to
                    expect that a ministry determined to support every minute article of the
                    established constitution of the country, both in church and in state, should
                    voluntarily add to the power and authority of a person who had repeatedly
                    declared himself rather hostile than indifferent to many points which they
                    thought essential to both; or even of one who felt so decided a conviction of
                    the importance of every single opinion which he had himself adopted, as to
                    refuse his concurrence in such measures of legislation as they might deem of
                    vital importance to the good of the country, and such as had been sanctioned by
                    the concurrent determination of the majority of a cabinet taking on themselves
                    the whole responsibility of their proceedings. He must have been aware that a
                    house divided against itself cannot stand, and that the members of every
                    administration, in a country not despotic, must consent to give up something to
                    each other’s feelings, and to make a small sacrifice of private conviction for
                    the great objects of public energy and unanimity. (L L.)</p></div></body></text></TEI>