<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0697-0657-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VIRGINIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j6857x">Railroads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fb4wm7s">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9h942">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vp1v">Dollar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865087">Coal</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865671">Coaling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1744651">Dollarization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:896433">Dollar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204598">Pennsylvania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205075">Ohio</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204739">Maryland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=697" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">VIRGINIA</label>, the largest and most central state
                    in the American Union, perhaps the most varied in its productions, and the
                    richest in natural resources, blessed with a happy climate and a fruitful soil,
                    exhibiting a pleasant interchange of the most romantic and lovely scenes. The
                    state borders upon the Atlantic ocean and the river Ohio, extending from 75° 10'
                    to 83° 25' W. Long., having Maryland on the east, and Ohio and Kentucky on the
                    west: on the north are Maryland and Pennsylvania, and on the south Tennessee and
                    North Carolina. Its general breadth from north to <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=698" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0698-0658"
                    />south is about 200 miles. Its length in the southern part is from 400 to 430
                    miles, and, north of 38°, about half that extent; its area is about 70,000
                    square miles, being but little inferior to Scotland and England united.</p>
                <p part="N">With the exception of Pennsylvania, Virginia is the only state that
                    extends quite across the great Appalachian chains, and it is traversed from
                    north to south by several well-defined mountain ranges. Our knowledge of the
                    course and connections of these chains, which have not been accurately laid down
                    in maps, is yet very imperfect, but some of them have been traced with tolerable
                    precision. The Blue Ridge, although pierced by the Potomac, James, and Staunton
                    rivers, constitutes a well-marked and continuous chain of 260 miles in length.
                    In general it forms rounded, swelling masses, about 2000 feet above the level of
                    the sea, or about 1500 feet above the valleys at its eastern base; but the Peaks
                    of Otter shoot up in projecting summits to the height of 4260 feet. The
                    prolongation of the Kittutinny mountain of Pennsylvania, enters the state in
                    Morgan county, under the name of the Great Ridge, or North mountain, and passes
                    into North Carolina under the name of the Iron mountain. Its height is generally
                    from 2100 to 2500 feet, but the White Top peak reaches the height of 6000 feet.
                    The Great valley, which lies between these two ridges, sometimes called the
                    German valley, is a continuation of the Cumberland and Tulpehocken valleys of
                    Pennsylvania. Through this ridge the New river passes westward, and the James
                    and Potomac eastward. West of this are numerous mountain masses, which are
                    probably prolongations of those which traverse central Pennsylvania.</p>
                <p part="N">Every portion of Virginia is traversed by fine rivers and streams,
                    useful either as channels of navigation or for manufacturing purposes. The chief
                    of these is the main trunk of the Potomac, which has already been described
                    under the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Maryland.</hi> Its principal tributaries
                    are from this state. The Rappahannock rises on the eastern side of the Blue
                    Ridge, and is navigable for small vessels to Fredericksburg, 110 miles. James
                    river is by far the largest and most important of the streams which have their
                    whole course in Virginia, and is not inferior to the Potomac and the Kanhawa in
                    utility and the varied beauties of its scenery. Rising in the Alleghany
                    mountain. It first bears the name of Jackson’s river, and after having received
                    the Cow Pasture river, a considerable stream. It takes the name of King James,
                    passes through the Kittutinny, and several other mountain chains, enters the
                    great valley, and, gathering the waters of that fruitful region, emerges from
                    the Blue Ridge over the Irish Falls. Above Richmond it descends by a fall of
                    seventy feet, in the distance of eight miles, into the low country. Below
                    Richmond it gradually becomes wider and deeper, and in the lower part of its
                    course expands into a long, spacious bay, with sufficient depth for the largest
                    ships. Vessels of 600 tons ascend to City Point, seventy-five miles from the
                    bay, although there are some bars and shoals which obstruct the navigation; and
                    vessels drawing fifteen feet of water proceed thirty miles higher, to Warwick,
                    which is within five miles of Richmond, the capital of the state. The
                    Blackwater, Nottoway, and Meherrin, unite in North Carolina to form the Chowan,
                    which enters Albemarle sound. They are all navigable for small coasting vessels.
                    The Great Renawha, and the other rivers of the western section, all reach the
                    Ohio.</p>
                <p part="N">The geological formations of this vast region have as yet been but very
                    partially explored. The mineral wealth of Virginia is almost boundless; gold,
                    copper, lead, iron, coal, salt, limestone, marls, gypsum, magnesian, copperas,
                    and alum earths, excellent marbles, granites, soapstones, freestones, &amp;c.,
                    are among its subterraneous treasures. The first coalfield is that of the
                    primary region, the extent of which has not been determined, but indications of
                    coal have been traced from the South Anna, near its mouth, to Prince Edward,
                    south of the Appomattax. The thickness of the coal-seams is very variable,
                    ranging from four or five to thirty, forty, and even sixty feet; the coal is
                    bituminous, and of an excellent quality. On the north branch of the Potomac
                    there is a remarkable bituminous coalfield. Upon a stratum of valuable iron-ore,
                    not less than fifteen feet in thickness, there rests a bed of sandstone, upon
                    which reposes a coal-seam three feet thick; upon this, another bed of sandstone,
                    then a two feet vein of coal; next sandstone, then another coal-seam of four
                    feet; again a stratum of sandstone, and over it a seven feet vein of coal; over
                    this a heavy bed of iron-ore, and crowning the scries an enormous coal-seam from
                    fifteen to twenty feet in thickness. West of the Alleghany, there are some of
                    the most extensive and valuable deposits of coal in the world. At Wheeling, on
                    the Ohio, and for fourteen miles down the river, the bank presents an
                    uninterrupted bed of highly bituminous coal, upwards of sixteen feet thick. Salt
                    springs occur in various places. But the most important works are on the Great
                    and Little Kanawha. Gold is at present the most important of the metallic
                    minerals of Virginia. It occurs throughout a belt on the western side of the
                    primary district, stretching from beyond the Rappahannock to the Appomattax.
                    Most of the gold hitherto obtained has been procured by washings from the
                    deposit-mines, but several veins have yielded rich returns. In 1803, at Reid’s
                    mine, a negro found one lump that weighed twenty-eight pounds avoirdupois, worth
                    eight thousand dollars. The largest piece of gold in one mass, ever found in
                    Europe, weighed only twenty-two ounces; and this was found in Wicklow in
                    Ireland. But the mines in Virginia are neither extensively worked, nor fully
                    developed. For several years they have been left to the enterprise of the
                    farmers, or owners of the soil, who occupy themselves with mining when not
                    engaged on their farms; and it is calculated that the product of the mines in
                    this section of the country, will amount to about L.80,000 annually.</p>
                <p part="N">Iron will probably at some future day prove to be a more precious
                    deposit; but, although the ore of several varieties is lavished in profusion on
                    different sections of the state, it is at present but little worked. Copper-ores
                    are found among the altered rocks cast of the Blue Ridge; and numerous openings
                    have been made in Orange, Amherst, Campbell, and Buckingham, for procuring the
                    cupreous rock, which at an early period was ground on the spot, and sent to
                    England to be smelted. Lead occurs in the southwestern part of the state, in the
                    forms of the sulphuret (galena) and carbonate, both of which are wrought,
                    yielding a large per centage of valuable metal.</p>
                <p part="N">A continuous line of railway is nearly completed across the state, from
                    the Potomac to the Roanoke. The Richmond and Potomac railroad extends from
                    Potomac creek in Stafford, through Fredericksburg, to Richmond, seventy miles,
                    having been completed in 1836. Railroads and canals cross the state in every
                    direction, affording ready and convenient means of communication for all
                    purposes.</p>
                <p part="N">Agriculture has always been the chief occupation of the inhabitants, but
                    not to the exclusion of other branches of industry. “There is a great diversity
                    in the agriculture of the state, but it is seldom well managed. On both sides of
                    the Blue Ridge, maize, or Indian corn, wheat, rye, oats, and buckwheat, are the
                    principal grain crops. Tobacco is the principal staple of most of eastern
                    Virginia, but in the valley it is cultivated only in the southern portion, and
                    not at all beyond the Alleghany. In the eastern and southern counties cotton is
                    planted to a considerable extent. On the shores of the Chesapeake, barley and
                    the castor oil bean are cultivated; and on some of the best lands above
                    tide-water, hemp is raised to advantage. The Trans-Alleghany county, being
                    exceedingly mountainous and remote<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=699" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0699-0659"
                    /> from market, is chiefly devoted to raising live stock. No more grain is
                    raised than is sufficient to supply the county itself. The culture of tobacco
                    was begun as early as 1616, and that plant soon formed the staple production of
                    the colony. During the latter half of the last century, the annual export
                    amounted to 60,000 or 70,000 hogsheads; of late years the amount produced in
                    eastern Virginia has fallen off considerably, on account of the exhaustion of
                    much of the land suited to this crop; but its cultivation has been much extended
                    beyond the Blue Ridge. The manufactures of Virginia are by no means
                    inconsiderable in value and extent, but they are not in general of the class
                    which involves the nicer and more complicated processes of art, consisting
                    rather of those simpler operations, which convert the native growth of the
                    forest, the products of the mineral kingdom, or the fruits of agricultural
                    labour, into articles of home consumption or commerce. The forests and the
                    coal-beds furnish a cheap and easy supply of fuel, and the numerous water-falls
                    offer an almost unlimited motive power for economical purposes; and within the
                    last few years several cotton mills have been erected for spinning and weaving,
                    in which white operatives have sought employment. The exports of Virginia
                    consist chiefly of agricultural products; lumber, salt, castor oil, ginseng,
                    coal, gold, some furs, &amp;c. The value of the direct exports to foreign
                    countries in 1836, was 6,192,040 dollars, but the internal American trade must
                    exceed that sum. The imports from foreign ports amounted in the same year to
                    only 1,106,814; but Virginia receives her supplies of manufactured goods and
                    foreign productions chiefly from northern ports. The fisheries of the Chesapeake
                    and its tributaries are valuable. The shipping owned in the state amounts to
                    50,000 tons.”</p>
                <p part="N">The first white settlers in Virginia were English; and the emigration
                    from England continued to be pretty active during a great part of the
                    seventeenth century, particularly from the time of the civil wars to the
                    Restoration, in 1660, and toward the close of the century, both before and after
                    the Revolution. Many victims of the political disturbances of those periods were
                    also sent to Virginia as servants; and the captives at Worcester, the followers
                    of Penruddoc, the Irish catholics, and the soldiers of the duke of Monmouth,
                    were sold into servitude in the colony. In the following century, many German
                    emigrants, chiefly from Maryland and Pennsylvania, occupied the valley in the
                    rear of the Blue Ridge, which thence received the name of the German Valley; and
                    in the more western part of the state, great numbers of Irish settlers fixed
                    themselves; and some felons were transported to Virginia, as to other colonies.
                    Negroes and mulattose constitute a large proportion of the population of
                    Virginia, and these are mostly field in slavery. The first negroes were brought
                    into the harbours of the Chesapeake by a Dutch ship in 1620, when twenty were
                    sold to the colonists; but the importation was for a long time so
                    inconsiderable, that at the end of fifty years their number was only 2000. The
                    inhabitants indeed endeavoured to discourage the traffic, and the Assembly made
                    repeated attempts to prevent the further introduction of negroes, but failed in
                    obtaining the requisite sanction of the crown; and up to the time of the
                    revolution-war, from 5000 to 6000 were annually brought into the province by the
                    English slave-traders. It is one of the grievances recited in the constitution
                    of 1776, and reaffirmed in the new instrument adopted in 1830, that George III.
                    had prompted the rising in arms of “those very negroes whom, by an inhuman use
                    of his negative, he had refused us permission to exclude by law ;” and in 1778
                    the new state prohibited their importation under heavy penalties. The existing
                    black population of Virginia is probably altogether native.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Population ar different periods.</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Whites. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Slaves. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Free Blacks. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Total Blacks. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Total. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1642 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> ... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> ... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> ... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> ... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 20,000 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1670 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 38,000 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2,000 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> ... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2,000 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 40,000 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1790 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 442,115 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 293,427 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 12,766 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 306,193 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 748,308 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1800 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 514,280 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 345,796 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 20,124 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 365,920 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 880,200 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1810 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 551,534 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 392,518 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 30,570 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 423,088 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 974,622 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1820 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 603,074 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 425,153 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 37,139 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 462,292 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1,065,366 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1830 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 694,300 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 469,757 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 47,348 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 517,105 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1,211,405 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">Besides the loss of population, occasioned by the removal of free
                    labourers and of planters with their forces, the sale and exportation of slaves
                    to other states have been a constant drain to this class of the population,
                    especially during the last ten years. Virginia has the unenviable distinction of
                    being a slave-breeding state, not only supporting slavery within its own limits,
                    but contributing to extend it in other states of the Union. This unnatural and
                    disgusting trade must infallibly demoralize both the white and coloured
                    population; and as a proof of the suffering which it entails upon its wretched
                    victims, no less a sum than 14,412 dollars is stated in the account of the
                    public expenditure of the state for 1833 for <hi rend="italic">transported and
                        executed slaves;</hi> while the next item, the public guard, amounts only to
                    19,225 dollars.</p>
                <p part="N">A few families of Indians of the Nottoway tribe, a branch of the great
                    Iroquois family, are still found on the river of that name, but they have lost
                    the language of their fathers, and have become much mixed with negroes. Of the
                    thirty Powhatan clans found here by the first colonists, not one is believed to
                    survive.</p>
                <p part="N">Richmond, the capital of the state, and its principal city, is
                    pleasantly situated on the left bank of the James, below the lower falls,
                    standing on several eminences, which command fine views of the surrounding
                    country, and give to the city an air of singular beauty. Richmond was declared
                    the capital of the state in 1779, and incorporated as a city in 1782, when
                    however it was merely a small village. In 1800 the population was 5,737, and in
                    1830 it was 16,060, more than one half blacks; at present, inclusive of
                    Manchester, which is united with it by a bridge, it exceeds 20,000. Richmond is
                    110 miles from the mouth of the river, which carries fourteen feet of water to
                    Warwick, five miles below the city, and is navigable for boats 220 miles above
                    the falls.</p>
                <p part="N">Such was the state of education in the colony, that one of the early
                    governors thanked God that there were no free schools or printing in Virginia.
                    In 1796, an act was passed for the establishment of primary schools; but in 1809
                    the governor complained that the law had in no instance been complied with. In
                    that year a literary fund was created by the appropriation of fines, escheats,
                    and forfeitures, to this object; and the money received by the state from the
                    federal government in 1816, for military services rendered during the late war,
                    was afterwards appropriated to the same purpose. In 1833 the fund amounted to
                    1,551,837 dollars, and the income to 78,340 dollars. In 1817 a permanent
                    appropriation was made of 45,000 dollars a-year from this revenue, to be
                    distributed among the several counties and towns, in proportion to their free
                    white population, for the instruction of poor children, and an additional sum
                    was granted for the same object in 1836. In 1833, by returns from one hundred
                    counties, there were 2833 common schools, attended by 17,081 poor children. In
                    order to extend the benefits of this system to all classes of whites, the
                    school-commissioners of any county are authorised to lay off the county into
                    school-districts, and, whenever any district shall have raised three-fifths of
                    the <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=700"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0700-0660"/>sum necessary to build a school-house, to
                    contribute the remaining two-fifths. They are also empowered to pay a sum not
                    exceeding one hundred dollars towards a teacher’s salary, provided the
                    inhabitants of the district contribute an equal sum towards the same object; and
                    every white child in such district is to be gratuitously taught in such school.
                    There are about fifty-five academies in the state. The higher educational
                    institutions are the university of Virginia at Charlottesville; the college of
                    William and Mary at Williamsburg; Washington college at Lexington, Bockbridge
                    county; Hampden-Sydney college in Prince Edward county; Randolph-Macon college
                    at Boydton, Mecklenburg county; the Union theological seminary in Prince Edward
                    county; the Episcopal theological seminary near Alexandria; and the Virginia
                    Baptist seminary near Richmond. In 1839 there were fifty-two newspapers
                    published in Virginia.</p>
                <p part="N">The legislature, styled the General Assembly, consists of two houses; a
                    house of delegates of 134 members, chosen annually; and a senate of thirty-two
                    members, chosen for the term of thirty-four years. Senators and delegates must
                    be resident freeholders; the latter of the age of twenty-five years, the former
                    of thirty. All laws must originate in the house of delegates. The governor and
                    the council of state, of three members, are chosen by the joint vote of both
                    houses of the assembly, for the term of three years, the senior councillor being
                    lieutenant-governor. The superior judges are chosen by the same bodies, and hold
                    office during good behaviour. The justices of the peace are appointed by the
                    governor on nomination, by the existing justices of the respective counties, and
                    one of their number performs the duties of sheriff. A small property
                    qualification is required to confer the right of suffrage on white male
                    citizens; and at all elections “the votes must be given openly, or <hi
                        rend="italic">viva voce,</hi> and not by ballot.”</p>
                <p part="N">The revenue of the state for the year 1834, was 403,335 dollars, of
                    which 291,581 dollars were derived from taxes on land, slaves, horses, and
                    carriages, and 101,283 from licences, making, with the balance of 185,221
                    dollars in the treasury at the close of 1833, a total of 588,556 dollars. The
                    expenditure, during the same year, amounted to 472,337 dollars; some of the
                    principal items, exclusive of payments from literary and other funds, being as
                    follows:</p>
                <p part="N">General assembly...90,141</p>
                <p part="N">Officers’ salaries .78,815</p>
                <p part="N">Judiciary 22,625</p>
                <p part="N">Criminal charges....32,240</p>
                <p part="N">Revolutionary half-pay officers...12,166</p>
                <p part="N">Transported and executed slaves...14,412</p>
                <p part="N">Public guard 19,225</p>
                <p part="N">Penitentiaries 23,911</p>
                <p part="N">Lunatic asylum 34,500</p>
                <p part="N">General appropriations...24,417</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
