<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0691-0651-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VIN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881354">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:961111">Hospitalers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1116352">Shipping</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cs62">Hoods</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ng4gw65">Gunning</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=691" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">VIN</label> cent. JoHN <hi rend="smallcaps">Jervis,
                        Earl of</hi> ST, a distinguished naval officer, was born at Meaford, in
                    Staffordshire, on the 9th of January 1734, old style. His father, Lwynfen
                    Jervis, Esq., was counsel and solicitor to the admiralty, and treasurer of
                    Greenwich Hospital. Young Jervis was destined for the law, but having contracted
                    a dislike to that profession, and a strong predilection for the sea, he ran away
                    from school, and expressed his determination to be a sailor. He was therefore
                    placed under Commodore Townsend, who was at that time going out in the
                    Gloucester as commander-in-chief to Jamaica. This was in the year 1748. In 1754
                    he was made a lieutenant out of the Prince into the Royal Anne; and in the year
                    1759 he distinguished himself very much at the siege and capture of Quebec, when
                    General Wolfe was killed. He was in consequence promoted by Sir Charles
                    Saunders, the commander-in-chief, to the rank of commander into the Porcupine
                    sloop of war. In the following year he was made a post-captain. He commanded the
                    Foudroyant in July 1788, when the memorable rencontre took place between Admiral
                    Keppel and Count d’Orvilliers, and bore a very distinguished part in that
                    action. In 1782, Captain Jervis fell in off Brest harbour with the French ship
                    Pegase, of seventy-four guns and 700 men, and took her after an engagement which
                    lasted three-quarters of an hour. The Pegase had eighty men killed and wounded,
                    while Captain Jervis and four men only were wounded on board the Foudroyant. In
                    consequence of this action, which at once raised his renown to the highest
                    pitch, he was created a knight companion of the Bath. In 1784 he was elected
                    member of parliament for Launceston, and he afterwards sat for North Yarmouth.
                    In 1787 he was advanced to the rank of rear-admiral of the blue, in 1793 to that
                    of vice-admiral, and in 1795 he became admiral.</p>
                <p part="N">In November 1793 an expedition was fitted out to attack the French
                    Carribee islands, and Sir Charles Grey and Sir John Jervis were nominated
                    respectively to command the land and sea forces to be employed on the occasion.
                    The expedition was at first completely successful, and Martinique, St Lucia, and
                    Guadaloupe, were surrendered to the British arms. The French however succeeded
                    in retaking Guadaloupe, and the rainy season and the yellow fever frustrated all
                    the efforts of the British to regain possession of it. In 1795, on the
                    resignation of Admiral Hood, Jervis was appointed to the command of the British
                    fleet in the Mediterranean, and was employed in blockading the French fleet in
                    Toulon, and protecting our trade in the Levant, a service which he performed
                    with consummate skill and success.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1797 Admiral Jervis, with only fifteen ships of the line, gained his
                    celebrated victory over the Spanish fleet, consisting of twenty-seven ships of
                    the line. The engagement, which took place off Cape St Vincent. on the 14th of
                    February, lasted about ten hours. The Spaniards were completely defeated, and
                    four sail of the line, two of 112, one of 84, and one of 74 guns, were taken.
                    The thanks of both houses of Parliament were voted to the fleet, and <pb
                        break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=692"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0692-0652"/> the commander-in-chief was created a peer, by
                    the title of Earl of St Vincent. This victory was much more important in its
                    consequences than might be supposed from the mere numerical loss which it caused
                    to the enemy. It paralyzed the power of Spain, gave encouragement to our allies,
                    and added fresh vigour to the efforts of the government in prosecuting the war.
                    The battle of Cape St Vincent was followed by the mutiny of the British fleet at
                    Spithead; and in the month of May and June following its effects were felt in
                    the fleet which was cruizing before Cadiz under the command of Lord St Vincent.
                    But the ringleaders were executed, and the mutiny speedily repressed by the
                    resolute and determined conduct of the commander-in-chief, with a combination of
                    humanity and ingenuity eminently characteristic of the man: he contrived to make
                    one execution produce the effect of many, by ordering it on an unusual day,
                    Sunday morning. It was the practice to dispatch mutinous vessels to serve under
                    his orders; and by his masterly operations of combined mercy and justice, he
                    soon reduced them to order, restoring discipline by such examples as should be
                    most striking, without being more numerous than absolute necessity required. In
                    June 1799 he resigned the command of the fleet, in consequence of ill health,
                    and returned to England in the month of August following. On the resignation of
                    Lord Bridport, and his final retirement from active service, he was appointed to
                    the command of the Channel fleet, and in the spring of 1800 hoisted his flag in
                    the Ville de Paris. In the following year, on the formation of the Addington
                    ministry, he was made first lord of the admiralty, and in that important office
                    the great capacity for business with which he was endowed by nature shone forth
                    in all its lustre. He instituted the celebrated Commission of Naval Inquiry,
                    which not only led to numberless discoveries of abuse and extravagance, but laid
                    the foundation of a system of economical administration, which has since been
                    extended from the navy to all the departments of the state. The extent of
                    corruption brought to light by the Commissioners of Naval Inquiry almost exceeds
                    belief. From the dockyard only the government was plundered at the rate of a
                    million sterling annually, and the same nefarious practices prevailed in all the
                    other departments. Lord St Vincent grappled boldly with these monstrous and
                    deep-rooted abuses, and by his unsparing rigour, inflexible honesty, and
                    resistless energy, succeeded in putting them down. “It is impossible,” says Lord
                    Brougham “to calculate what would have been the saving effected to the revenues
                    of this country, had Lord St Vincent presided over any great department of
                    national affairs from the beginning of the war, instead of coming to our
                    assistance after its close.” The resignation of Mr Addington in 1804 put an end
                    to the naval administration of St Vincent. as first lord of the admiralty; but
                    the exigencies of the state caused him in 1806 to be called from his well-earned
                    retirement, and from the enjoyment of his domestic comforts, at the age of
                    seventy-two, to take the command of the Channel fleet. He was at the head of the
                    expedition, and the commission sent to the court of Portugal in 1806; and his
                    conduct in that delicate and important affair displayed great talents and
                    address. In the spring of 1807, advanced age and impaired health compelled him
                    finally to resign his command. The remainder of his life was spent in retirement
                    at his beautiful seat of Rochetts, where he died on the 14th of March 1823, in
                    the eighty-eighth year of his age. The character of Lord St Vincent presented an
                    admirable union of the brightest qualities which can adorn both civil and
                    military life. As a statesman, he was distinguished for his sagacity and
                    foresight, and the profoundness of his views. He was a steady and consistent
                    supporter of liberal principles, ever preferring the side of humanity and
                    freedom. He was not more distinguished for his great talents than for his
                    magnanimity and complete freedom from every feeling of jealousy or envy. And it
                    has been justly said by one who knew him well, that “all good officers, all men
                    employed under him, whether in civil or military service, spoke of him as they
                    felt, with admiration of his genius approaching to enthusiasm.” (Captain
                    Brenton’s Life of Earl St Vincent. Lord Brougham’s Statesmen of the Times of
                    George III.) <hi rend="smallcaps">b. q.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
