<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0599-0561-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VARNISH</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04032">Alcohol</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41s37">Alcoholates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40z70w4g">Alcohols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1245970">Sun</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804631">Alcohols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804414">Alcoholics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804361">Alcoholates</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804461">Alcoholism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=599" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">VARNISH</label>, a clear limpid fluid, capable of
                    hardening without losing its transparency, used by painters, gilders, &amp;c. to
                    give a lustre to their works, in order to preserve them and defend them from the
                    air.</p>
                <p part="N">A coat of varnish ought to possess the following properties. 1st. It
                    must exclude the action of the air; because wood and metals are varnished to
                    defend them from decay and rust. 2d. It must resist water; for otherwise the
                    effect of the varnish could not be permanent. 3d. It ought not to alter such
                    colours as are intended to be preserved by this means. It is necessary therefore
                    that a varnish should be easily extended or spread over the surface, without
                    leaving pores or cavities; that it should not crack or scale; and that it should
                    resist water. Now resins are the only bodies that possess these properties.
                    Resins consequently must be used as the bases of varnish. The question which of
                    course presents itself must then be, how to dispose them for this use; and for
                    this purpose they must be dissolved, as minutely divided as possible, and
                    combined in such a manner that the imperfections of those which might be
                    disposed to scale may be corrected by others.</p>
                <p part="N">Resins may be dissolved by three agents, 1st, By fixed oil. 2d, By
                    volatile oil. 3d, By alcohol. And accordingly we have three kinds of varnish;
                    the fat or oily varnish, essential varnish, and spirit varnish. Before a resin
                    is dissolved in a fixed oil. It is necessary to render the oil drying. For this
                    purpose the oil is boiled with metallic oxides; in which operation the mucilage
                    of the oil combines with the metal, while the oil itself unites with the oxygen
                    of the oxide. To accelerate the drying of this varnish. It is necessary to add
                    oil of turpentine. The essential varnishes consist of a solution of resin in oil
                    of turpentine. The varnish being applied, the essential oil flies off, and
                    leaves the resin. This is used only for paintings. When resins are dissolved in
                    alcohol, the varnish dries very speedily, and is subject to crack; but this
                    fault is corrected by adding a small quantity of turpentine to the mixture,
                    which renders it brighter, and less brittle when dry.</p>
                <p part="N">We shall now give the method of preparing a number pf varnishes for
                    different purposes.</p>
                <p part="N">4 <hi rend="italic">Varnish for Toilet-boxes, Cases, Fans,</hi>
                    &amp;c.—Dissolve two ounces of gum mastich and eight ounces gum sandarach in a
                    quart of alcohol; then add four ounces of Venice turpentine.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">A Varnish for Wainscots, cane chairs, Iron chairs,
                        Grates.—</hi> Dissolve in a quart of alcohol eight ounces of gum sandarach,
                    two ounces of seed lac, four ounces of rosin; then add six ounces of Venice
                    turpentine. If the varnish is wished to produce a red colour, more of the lac
                    and less of sandarach should be used, and a little dragon's blood should be
                    added. This varnish is so thick that two layers of it are equal to four or five
                    of another.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">A Varnish for Fiddles, and other Musical
                        Instruments—</hi> Put four ounces of gum sandarach, two ounces of lac, two
                    ounces of gum mastich, an ounce of gum elemi, into a quart of alcohol, and hang
                    them over a slow fire till they are dissolved; then add two ounces of
                    turpentine.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Varnish in order to employ Vermilion for painting
                        Equipages—</hi> Dissolve in a quart of alcohol six ounces of sandarach,
                    three ounces of gum lac, and four ounces of rosin; afterwards add six ounces of
                    the cheapest kind of turpentine; mix with it a proper quantity of vermilion when
                    it is io be used <hi rend="italic">Gold-coloured Varnish—</hi> Pound separately
                    four ounces of stick lac, four ounces of gamboge, four ounces of dragon’s blood,
                    four ounces of anotta, and one ounce of saffron: put each of them separately
                    into a quart of alcohol, and expose them for five days in a narrow-mouthed
                    bottle to the sun, or keep them during that time in a very warm room, shaking
                    them every now and then to hasten the solution. When they are melted, mix them
                    together. More or less of each of these ingredients will give the different
                    tints of gold according as they are combined. In order to make silver imitate
                    gold exactly when covered with this varnish, the quantity of ingredients must be
                    somewhat greater. The method of gilding silver leaf, &amp;c. with this varnish,
                    is as follows: The silver leaf being fixed, in the same manner as gold leaf, by
                    the interposition of proper glutinous matters, the varnish is spread upon the
                    piece with a brush or pencil. The first coat being dry, the piece is again and
                    again washed over with the varnish till the colour appears sufficiently deep.
                    What is called <hi rend="italic">gilt leather,</hi> and many picture frames,
                    have no other than this counterfeit gilding. Washing them with a little
                    rectified spirit of wine affords a proof of this; the spirit dissolving the
                    varnish, and leaving the silver leaf of its own whiteness. For plain frames,
                    thick tinfoil may be used instead of silver. The tin leaf, fixed on the piece
                    with glue, is to be burnished, then polished with emery and a fine linen cloth,
                    and afterwards with putty applied in the same manner: being then lacquered over
                    with the varnish five or six times. It looks very nearly like burnished gold.
                    The same varnish, macle with a less proportion of the colouring materials, is
                    also applied on works of brass; both for heightening the colour of the metal to
                    a resemblance with that of gold, and for preserving it from being tarnished or
                    corroded by the air.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Oil Varnishes</hi> Gum copal and amber are the
                    substances principally employed in oil varnishes. They possess the properties
                    necessary for varnishes, solidity and transparency. The copal being whitest, is
                    used for varnishing light, the amber for dark colours. It is best to dissolve
                    them before mixing them with the oil, because by this means they are in less
                    danger of being scorched, and at the same time the varnish is more beautiful.
                    They should be melted in a pot on the fire; they are in a proper state for
                    receiving the oil when they give no resistance to the iron spatula, and when
                    they run off from it drop by drop. The oil employed should be a drying oil, and
                    perfectly free from grease. It should be poured into the copal or amber by
                    little and little, constantly stirring the ingredients at the same time with the
                    spatula. When the oil is well mixed with the copal or amber, take it off the
                    fire; and when it is pretty cool, pour in a greater quantity of the essence of
                    turpentine than the oil that was used. After the varnish is made. It should be
                    passed through a linen cloth. Oil varnishes become thick by keeping; but when
                    they are to be used, it is only necessary to pour in a little essence of
                    turpentine, and to put them for a little on the fire. The turpentine is
                    necessary in oil varnishes to make them dry properly; generally twice as much of
                    it is used as of oil. Less is necessary in summer than in winter. Too much oil
                    hinders the varnish from drying; but when too little is used. It cracks and does
                    not spread properly. We shall subjoin the most useful oil varnishes.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">White copal Varnish.</hi> —On sixteen ounces of melted
                    copal pour four, six, or eight ounces of linseed oil, boiled and quite free from
                    grease. When they are well mixed, take them off the fire (not forgetting to stir
                    them properly); and when pretty cool, pour in sixteen ounces of the essence of
                    Venice turpentine. Pass the varnish through a cloth. Amber varnish is made in
                    the same way.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Black Varnish for coaches and Iron Work.—</hi> This
                    varnish is composed of bitumen of Palestine, rosin, and amber, melted
                    separately, and afterwards mixed: the oil is then <pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=600" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0600-0562"
                    />added, and afterwards the turpentine, as directed above. The usual proportions
                    are, twelve ounces of amber, two ounces of rosin, two ounces of bitumen, six of
                    oil, and twelve of the essence of turpentine. Golden coloured varnish may be
                    made also by substituting linseed oil for alcohol.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Essential Oil Varnishes.—</hi> The only essential oil
                    varnishes used are for pictures. Picture varnishes should be white, light, and
                    quite transparent, which will preserve the colours without giving them any
                    disagreeable tint; and it should be possible to take them off the picture
                    without injuring it. They are usually made of gum mastich and turpentine
                    dissolved together in some essential oil. The varnish is passed through a cloth,
                    and allowed to clarify. It is applied cold to the picture.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Varnish for Glass in order to preserve it from the
                        rays of the Sun.—</hi> Pulverize a quantity of gum adragant.</p>
                <p part="N">and let it dissolve for twenty-four hours in the white of eggs well beat
                    up; then rub it gently on the glass with a brush.</p>
                <p part="N">Varnishes, before they are used, should be carefully kept from dust,
                    which would spoil them; and they should be kept in a vessel quite clean and dry.
                    When used, they should be lifted lightly with a brush, and spread upon a ground
                    altogether free from dirt and moisture. The substance, after being varnished,
                    should be exposed to the beat of the sun, or placed in a warm room covered with
                    a glass case, to keep out all filth. Oil varnishes require more heat than
                    alcohol varnishes. The varnish should be put on very quickly, making great
                    strokes with the pencil or brush, taking care that these strokes never cross one
                    another; it should be spread equally, and never thicker than a leaf of paper; a
                    second coat should never be put on till the first is quite dry. If the varnish,
                    after being put on, becomes dull and uneven. It must be taken off entirely, and
                    new varnish applied.</p>
                <p part="N">When wainscot is to be varnished. It is first painted of a wooden
                    colour. This colour is made by infusing in water either red or yellow ochre
                    (according to the colour wished for), terra ombria (a kind of ochre) and white
                    lead; into this as much as necessary is put of <hi rend="italic">parchment
                        paste.</hi> Two thin coats of this are to be put on, and, after they are
                    quite dry, the varnish.</p>
                <p part="N">Varnishes are polished with pumice-stone and Tripoli earth. The
                    pumice-stone must be reduced to an impalpable powder, and put upon a piece of
                    serge moistened with water; with this the varnished substance is to be rubbed
                    lightly and equally. The Tripoli must also be reduced to a very fine powder, and
                    put upon a clean woollen cloth moistened with olive oil, with which the
                    polishing is to be performed. The varnish is then to be wiped with soft linen,
                    and, when quite dry, cleaned with starch or Spanish white, and rubbed with the
                    palm of the hand or with a linen cloth.</p>
                <p part="N">To recover colours or varnish, and to take off the dirt and filth which
                    may adhere to them, a ley is used made of potash and the ashes of lees of wine.
                    Take forty-eight ounces of potash, and sixteen of the above mentioned ashes, put
                    them into six quarts of water, and the ley is made. Instead of the ashes an
                    equal quantity of potash would probably do as well. To clean dirty colours,
                    dilute some of this ley with four times its quantity of water, and rub the
                    picture with it; then wash it with river water; and when dry, give it a coat or
                    two of varnish. In order to take off a varnish, wash it with the above mentioned
                    ley, then with water, and then lift it off the substance on which it was with
                    any iron instrument.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
