<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0641-0603-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">VERMONT</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204305">Vermont</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205688">Connecticut</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:844698">Camels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844686">Cameleers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:837146">Bouquets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:955558">Heroes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:932562">Foresters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pq59">Camel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46d5pd23">Heroes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=641" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">VERMONT</label>, one of the United States of
                    America. It lies between the river Connecticut and the long tapering basin of
                    Lake Champlain; stretching from 42° <hi rend="italic">44' to</hi> 45° north
                    lat., a distance of nearly 160 miles, and from 71° 30' to 73° 20' west long.,
                    with a breadth expanding pretty regularly from forty-five miles in the south to
                    ninety in the north. It has an area of 10,200 square miles.</p>
                <p part="N">The most striking natural feature of this tract is the mountainous range
                    called the Green Mountains, which traverse the state from north to south, and,
                    passing into Massachusetts, there take the name of the Hoosic Mountains. In the
                    centre of the state this ridge is divided into two, of which the one called the
                    Height of Land runs north-east to Canada, and the other, taking a north-westerly
                    direction, sinks down in the northern part of the state. The Green Mountains,
                    from whose verdure this state derives its name, are from ten to fifteen miles
                    wide, and are much intersected by valleys; they are watered by numerous springs
                    and brooks, and are covered with evergreen trees and shrubs nearly to their
                    summits. There are many good farms among the mountains, and much of the land
                    upon them is suitable for grazing. The highest points are Mansfield Mountain,
                    rising to 4280 feet; Camel’s Rump, 4190 feet, both in the north-western ridge;
                    and Killington Peak, further south, 3675 feet in height. Ascutney, a detached
                    elevation near Windsor, rises to the height of 3320 feet above the level of the
                    sea.</p>
                <p part="N">The Connecticut forms the eastern boundary of the state. Oniou river
                    passes through Montpellier, the capital, into Lake Champlain at Burlington.
                    Otter creek is a principal branch of Oniou river. Lamoile and Missique are
                    considerable streams north of the Oniou. In the Green Mountains rise many
                    smaller rivers, which at once beautify the country by the picturesque scenery of
                    their banks, and promote its manufactures by the mills which they turn in their
                    course. Those which run towards the east are tributaries to the Connecticut, and
                    those whose course is towards the west discharge their waters into Lake
                    Champlain.</p>
                <p part="N">Lake Champlain, between the west shore of this state and New York, is a
                    beautiful sheet of water, 128 miles long, and from one to twenty wide. It
                    discharges at its northern extremity by the river Sorel into the St. Lawrence,
                    and contains upwards of sixty islands, of which Motte, and North and South Hero,
                    are of considerable size. Besides the rivers which flow into it from the Green
                    Mountains, it receives the Chazy, Saranac, Sable, Bouquet, and Wood rivers, from
                    New York, on the western shore. The Champlain canal connects it with Hudson
                    river and the New York and Erie canal. Lying extremely convenient to facilitate
                    the commerce of the state both with New York and Montreal. It is navigated by a
                    number of steam-boats and lake vessels. Memphremagog is a considerable lake,
                    twenty-five miles long and three broad, lying partly in Vermont and partly in
                    Canada, receiving a number of streams from this state, and communicating by the
                    St. Francis with the St. Lawrence.</p>
                <p part="N">The prevailing rocks belong to the stratified primary group, embracing
                    mica and talcose slates, gneiss, primary limestone, argillite, &amp;c. On the
                    western border there is a narrow strip of transition limestone. These rocks
                    afford good building materials, and marble is quarried and carried out of the
                    state. The magnetic oxide of iron abounds at Somerset, and the brown hematite,
                    associated <pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=642"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0642-0604"/>with oxide of manganese, occurs at Bennington,
                    Pittsford, and Manleton. Pyrites, or sulphuret of iron, is found in Strafford
                    and Shrewsbury; and about three million pounds of copperas, of the value of
                    70,000 to 75,000 dollars, are made here annually.</p>
                <p part="N">Vermont was originally covered with a dense forest, a large part of
                    which still remains, although considerable encroachments have been made on it in
                    clearing land for cultivation, and in felling trees for timber. The mountains
                    produce hemlock, spruce, and fir; the lower grounds, various species of oak,
                    pine, maple, elm, hickory, beech, birch, ash, buttonwood or sycamore, and lime
                    or basswood, and the cedar grows in wet places. Ginseng, sarsaparilla,
                    sassafras, snakeroot, lobelias, &amp;c., are also among the products of the
                    forest. Maple-sugar is made in large quantities for domestic use and
                    exportation, and pot and pearl ashes, and lumber, are also exported.</p>
                <p part="N">Vermont is divided into fourteen counties, which are subdivided into
                    townships. There are no large towns in the state, but Vergennes has the name of
                    a city.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Population in</hi> 1830.</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Counties. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Population. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> County Towns. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Population. </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Addison, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 24,940 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Middleburgh,.. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3468 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 17,468 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Bennington,</p><p part="N"
                                >Manchester,</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3419 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1525 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Caledonia, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 20,967 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Danville, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2631 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Chittenden, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 21,765 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Burlington,.... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3526 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Essex </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3981 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Guildhall, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 481 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Franklin, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 24,525 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> St. Albans, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2375 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Grand Isle, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3696 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> North Hero,... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 638 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> La Moelle, established in 1837,} </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> ... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Hydepark,...... </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 823 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Orange, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 27,285 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Chelsea </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1958 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Orleans, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 13,890 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Irasburgh, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 860 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Rutland </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 31,294 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Rutland, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2753 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Washington, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 21,378 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Montpelier </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1792 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Windham </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 28,746 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Newfane, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1441 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Windsor, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 40,625 </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Windsor,....</p><p part="N"
                                >Woodstock,.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3134 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3044 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">Vermont is not a slave-holding state. The number of newspapers published
                    in this state in 1839 was thirty-one.</p>
                <p part="N">The senate established in 1836 consists of thirty members, each county
                    being entitled to at least one, and the rest apportioned according to
                    population; and the House of Representatives is composed of one member from each
                    town.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
