<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-4099-0329-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAURICE, St</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qh7s">Arminianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65f63">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1125233">Soldiers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194204099?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">MAURICE, <hi rend="smallcaps">St</hi></label>,
                    commander of the Theban legion, was i Christian, as were also the officers and
                    soldiers of that egion, amounting to six thousand six hundred men. This egion
                    received its name from the city Thebes in Egypt, flιere it was raised. It was
                    sent by Diocletian to check he Bagaudae, who had excited some disturbances in
                    Gaul, laurice having carried his troops over the Alps, the Em-eror Maximinian
                    commanded him to employ his utmost xertions to extirpate Christianity. This
                    proposal was ≡ceived with horror both by the commander and by the )ldiers. The
                    emperor, enraged at their opposition, com- ∣anded the legion to be decimated;
                    and when they still eclared that they would sooner die than do any thing
                    rejudicial to the Christian faith, every tenth man of those ho remained was put
                    to death. Their perseverance exted the emperor to still greater cruelty; for
                    when he saw ∣at nothing could induce them to relinquish their relion, he
                    commanded his troops to surround them and cut .em in pieces. Maurice, the
                    commander of these Chris- 'ιn heroes, and Exuperus and Candidus, officers of the
                    gion, who had chiefly instigated the soldiers to this noble sistance, signalized
                    themselves by their patience and eir attachment to the doctrines of the
                    Christian religion, ιey were massacred at Agaune in Chablais, on the 22d
                    September 286. Notwithstanding many proofs in sup-rt of this transaction,
                    Dubordier, lĭottinger, Moyle, ιrnet, and Mosheim, are disposed to deny the fact.
                    But, the other hand, it is defended by Hicks, an English iter, and by Dorn
                    Joseph de Lisle, a Benedictine monk the congregation of Saint Vannes, in a work
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">De-pxedelα</hi><hi rend="italic">Vérité du
                        Martyre</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Legion Thebenne,</hi> 1737.</p>
                <p part="N">defence of the same fact, the reader may consult <hi rend="italic"
                        >His-re de S. Mauritie,</hi> by Rossignole, a Jesuit, and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Acta f ∙ηxtorum</hi> for the month of September. The martyrdom
                    ( this legion, written by St Eucherius, bishop of Lyons, was transmitted to
                    posterity in a very imperfect manner by Surius. Chifflat, a Jesuit, discovered
                    and gave to the public an accurate copy of this work; and Don Ruinart maintains
                    that it has every mark of authenticity. St Maurice is the patron of a celebrated
                    order in the dominions of the king of Sardinia, created by Emanuel Philibert,
                    duke of Savoy, to reward military merit, and approved by Gregory XIII. in 1572.
                    But the commander of the Theban legion must not be confounded with another St
                    Maurice, mentioned by Theodoret, who suffered martyrdom at Apamea in Syria.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Maurice,</hi><hi rend="italic">St,</hi> a small
                    city in Switzerland, in the canton of Valais. It is remarkable as a pass between
                    lofty rocks through which the river Rhone has wrought a passage, and over which
                    there is a bridge of one arch. It was deemed by the Romans an important pass,
                    and was therefore strongly fortified by them; and many of their antiquities are
                    now found there. The name is taken from the leader of the Theban legion, who,
                    according to tradition, here destroyed the idols of the heathen inhabitants. It
                    now contains 1250 inhabitants.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Maurice</hi><hi rend="italic">de Nassau,</hi>
                    Prince of Orange, succeeded to the government of the Low Countries after the
                    death of his father William, who was killed in 1584 by the fanatic Gérard. The
                    young prince was then only eighteen years of age, but his courage and abilities
                    were above his years. He was appointed captain-general of the United Provinces,
                    and he reared that edifice of liberty of which his father had laid the
                    foundations. Breda submitted to him in 1590; Zutphen, Deventer, Hulst, Nimeguen,
                    in 1591. He gained several important advantages in 1592, and in the following
                    year he made himself master of Gertruydenburg. When he had performed these
                    splendid services, he returned to the Low Countries by the way of Zealand. His
                    fleet was attacked by a dreadful tempest, in which he lost forty vessels, and he
                    himself had very nearly perished. His death would have been considered by the
                    Hollanders as a much greater calamity than the loss of their vessels. They
                    watched over his safety with exceeding care. In 1594, one of his guards was
                    accused of an intention to take away his life, and it was generally believed
                    that he had been bribed to do this service by the enemies of the republic; but
                    he fell a sacrifice at Bruges, either to his own fanaticism, or to the jealous
                    anxiety of the friends of Maurice. The Prince of Orange defeated the troops of
                    the Archduke Albert in 1597, and drove the Spaniards entirely out of Holland. In
                    1600 he was obliged to raise the siege of Dunkirk; but he took ample vengeance
                    upon Albert, whom he again defeated in a pitched battle near Nieuport. Before
                    the action, this great general sent back the ships which had brought his troops
                    into Flanders. “My brethren,” said he to his army, “we must conquer the enemy or
                    drink up the waters of the sea. Determine for yourselves; 1 have resolved I
                    shall either conquer by your bravery, or never survive the disgrace of being
                    conquered by men in every respect our inferiors.” This speech elevated the
                    soldiers to the highest pitch of enthusiasm, and the victory was complete.
                    Rhinberg, Grave, and Ecluse, cities in Flanders, submitted in the following year
                    to the conqueror. Maurice, however, not only laboured for the commonwealth, but
                    also for himself. He coveted the sovereignty of Holland, but in the prosecution
                    of his design was opposed by the pensioner Barneveldt. But the zeal and activity
                    of this wise republican cost him his life. He was an Arminian; and at this time
                    Maurice defended Gomar against Arminius. In 1619, the prince, taking advantage
                    of the general odium under which the Arminians lay, found means to get
                    Barneveldt condemned. His death, which was wholly owing to the ambition of the
                    Prince of Orange, made a deep impression on the minds of the Hollanders. The
                    truce with Spain having expired, Spinola laid siege to Breda in 1624; and in <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:194204112?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0714-4112-0330"/>
                    six months he took the place, though with great slaughter , of his troops. The
                    Prince of Orange, having proved unsuccessful in every attempt to raise the
                    siege, died of vexation in 1625, at the age of fifty-five, being reputed the
                    greatest warrior of his time. “The life of this stadtholder,” says the Abbé
                    Raynal, “was almost an uninterrupted series of battles, of sieges, and of
                    victories. Of moderate abilities in everything else, he shone conspicuous in his
                    military capacity. His camp was the school of Europe; and those who received
                    their military education in his armies augmented, perhaps, the glory of their
                    master. Like Montecuculi, he discovered inimitable skill in his marches and
                    encampments; like Vauban, he possessed the talent of fortifying places, and of
                    rendering them impregnable; like Eugene, the address to find subsistence for
                    great armies in countries barren by nature, or ravaged by war; like Vendôme, the
                    happy talent of calling forth, in the moment when they became necessary, greater
                    exertions from his soldiers than could reasonably be expected; like Condé, that
                    infallible quickness of eye which usually decides the fortune of battles; like
                    Charles XII. the art of rendering his troops almost invincible to cold, hunger,
                    and fatigue; like Turenne, the secret of making war with the least possible
                    expense of human blood.” The Chevalier Folard maintains that Maurice was the
                    greatest commander of infantry since the time of the Romans. He studied the
                    military art of the ancients, and applied their rules with great exactness in
                    the various occurrences of war. He not only took advantage of the inventions of
                    others, but he also enriched the science of war with several improvements.
                    Telescopes were first used by him for military purposes; and, besides a kind of
                    gallery in conducting a siege, and the plan of blockading a strong place, which
                    were of his invention, he greatly improved the art by his method of pushing an
                    attack with great vigour, and of defending, for the greatest length of time, and
                    in the best manner, a place besieged. In short, the many useful things which he
                    practised or invented placed him in the highest rank amongst military men. On
                    one occasion, a lady of quality asked him, “Who was the first general of the
                    age? Spinola,” replied he, “is the second.” It was his constant practice, during
                    sleep, to have two guards placed by his bed-side, not only to defend him in case
                    of danger, but to awake him if there should be the least occasion. The war
                    between Spain and Holland was never carried on with greater vigour and animosity
                    than during his administration. The grand signior, hearing of the quantity of
                    blood shed in this contest, thought that a great empire must be depending on the
                    decision. When the object of so many battles was pointed out to him on a map, he
                    said coldly, “If it were my business, I would send my pioneers, and order them
                    to cast this little corner of earth into the sea.” Maurice was succeeded by
                    Frederick Henry, his brother.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
