<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-3735-0301-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MASORA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163204">Ushers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828168">Basil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1169292">Vowels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194203735?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">MASORA</label>, a term in the Jewish theology,
                    signifying a work on the Bible, performed by several learned rabbin, in order to
                    secure it from any alterations which might otherwise happen.</p>
                <p part="N">The work of the Masorites regards merely the letter of the Hebrew text,
                    in which they have, first, fixed the true reading by vowels and accents;
                    secondly, they have numbered not only the chapters and sections, but the verses,
                    words, and letters of the text, finding in the Pentateuch 5245 verses, and in
                    the whole Bible 23,206. The Masora is called by the Jews the <hi rend="italic"
                        >hedge or fence of the law,</hi> because this enumeration of the verses,
                    words, and letters, is a means of preserving it from being corrupted and
                    altered. They have also marked whatever irregularities occur in any of the
                    letters of the Hebrew text; such as the different size of the letters, their
                    various positions and inversions, &amp;c. and they have been fruitful in finding
                    reasons for these irregularities, as well as in discovering mysteries in them.
                    They are further supposed to be the authors of the Keri and Chetib, or the
                    marginal corrections of the text in our Hebrew Bibles.</p>
                <p part="N">The text of the sacred books, it is to be observed, was originally
                    written, like an inscription, without any breaks or divisions into chapters or
                    verses, or even into words; so that a whole book, in the ancient manner, was but
                    one continued word. Of this kind we have still several ancient manuscripts, both
                    Greek and Latin. As, therefore, the sacred writings had undergone an infinite
                    number of alterations, whence various readings had arisen, and the original had
                    become much mangled and disguised, the Jews had recourse to a canon, which they
                    judged infallible, to fix and ascertain the reading of the Hebrew text; and this
                    rule they call <hi rend="italic">Masora,</hi> or tradition, as if this criticism
                    were nothing but a tradition which had been handed down to them from their
                    forefathers. Accordingly they say, that when God gave the law to Moses upon
                    Mount Sinai, he taught him, first, the true reading of it, and, secondly, its
                    true interpretation; and that both these were handed down by oral tradition,
                    from generation to generation, until at length they were committed to writing.
                    The former of these, or the true reading, forms the subject of the Masora; the
                    latter, or true interpretation, is that of the Mishni and Ge mar a.</p>
                <p part="N">According to Elias Levita, the Jews of a famous school at Tiberias,
                    about five hundred years after Christ, were the persons who composed, or at
                    least began, the Masora, whence they are called <hi rend="italic">Masorites</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">Masoretic Doctors.</hi> Aben Ezra makes them the authors
                    of the points and accents in the Hebrew text, as we now find it, the former of
                    which serve as vowels.</p>
                <p part="N">The ageof the Masorites has been much disputed. Archbishop Usher places
                    them before Jerome, Capel at the end of the fifth century, and Father Morin in
                    the tenth century. Basnage says that they were not a society, but a succession
                    of men; and that the Masora is the work of many grammarians, who, without
                    associating and communicating their notions, composed this collection of
                    criticisms on the Hebrew text. It is urged that there were Masorites from the
                    time of Ezra and the men of the great synagogue, till about the year of Christ
                    1030; and that Ben Asher and Ben Naphtali, who were the best of the profession,
                    and who, according to Basnage, were the inventors of the Masora, flourished at
                    this time. Each of these published a copy of the whole Hebrew text, as correct
                    as they could make it. The eastern Jews have followed that of Ben Naphtali, and
                    the western that of Ben Asher; and all that has been done since is to copy after
                    them, without making any more corrections or Masoretic criticisms.</p>
                <p part="N">The Arabs have done the same thing with the Koran that the Masorites did
                    with the Bible; nor indeed do the Jews deny having borrowed this expedient from
                    the Arabians, who first put it in practice in the seventh century.</p>
                <p part="N">There is a great and little Masora printed at Venice and at Basil, with
                    the Hebrew text in a different character. Buxtorf has written a Masoretic
                    commentary, which he calls <hi rend="italic">Tiberias.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
