<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0714-0459-0049-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MALABAR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c552">Nestorians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20j3f">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wm1410b">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032276">Nairs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028364">Mountaineers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028366">Mountains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1213323">Aden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194200459?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">MALABAR</label>. This tract of country extends along
                    the western coast of India, from Cape Comorin to the river Chandragiri, in lat.
                    12. 30. north. The British province of Malabar is a particular portion of this
                    tract, which is situated between the 10th and 13th degrees of north latitude. Io
                    the north it is bounded by the province of Canara, to the south by the rajah of
                    Cochin’s territories, to the west by the ocean, and to the east by the chain <hi
                        rend="italic">of</hi> the Western Ghauts, below which the country lies,
                    extending about 200 miles along the sea-coast. The country may be divided into
                    two portions, the first of which borders the seacoast, and consists of a poor
                    sandy soil, seldom above three miles wide, and in general not so much. Low
                    branches of hills extend from the Ghauts to a considerable distance’ to the
                    westward, and sometimes even to the sea. The strip of country bordering upon the
                    sea is well adapted for the cultivation of rice; and it is remarkably
                    intersected by inlets of the sea, which often run for great lengths parallel to
                    the line of coast, receiving the various mountainstreams, and communicating with
                    the ocean by different narrow and shallow openings. In other places, the fresh
                    water, as it descends from the mountains into the low lands within the downs
                    upon the sea-coast, in the rainy season, totally overflows them, as the water
                    has no issue, and must consequently stagnate until it evaporates. By this
                    natural irrigation the lands are fitted for some particular qualities of rice.
                    There are a few mountain streams and rivers; and the distance of the mountains
                    from the sea is too inconsiderable for the formation of any large river. By far
                    the most extensive portion of Malabar lies in the vicinity of the Ghaut
                    Mountains, and consists of low hills separated by narrow valleys, which are in
                    general extremely fertile, being the receptacles of the fine particles of mould
                    carried down from the hills, and which stop when they can be carried no farther.
                    The hills have mostly level summits, which are bare in many parts, especially
                    towards the north, and expose to the view large surfaces of naked rock, with
                    remarkably steep sides; but they are seldom of any considerable height. They are
                    in general very industriously cultivated; their sides, which possess the best
                    soil, being formed into terraces. The valleys are in most cases watered by
                    rivulets which carry off the superfluous water; and where there is no issue, it
                    overflows the adjacent lands. The upland is barren, and the cultivation much
                    neglected; and it is in the valleys and extensive ravines, and upon the banks of
                    the rivers, that the inhabitants chiefly reside. Dr Buchanan mentions that some
                    parts of the country which he passed through in this province were the most
                    beautiful he had ever seen, being equal to the finest parts of Bengal, but the
                    trees were loftier, and the palms more numerous. In many places the rice-grounds
                    are interspersed with high swells, that are crowded with <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:194200472?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0714-0472-0050"/>houses;
                    whilst the view to the north is bounded by naked rocky mountains, and to the
                    south by the lofty forests of the Travancore hills.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">See <hi rend="italic">Journey
                                from Madras, through Μya e, Canara, and Malabar,</hi> by F.
                            Buchanan, Μ. D. vol. ii. p. 347∙</p></note> The climate is moist; the
                    low country of Malabar, as well as the whole region which lies under the Western
                    Ghauts, becomes excessively hot in the month of February; and the vapours and
                    exhalations are so thick, that it is difficult to distinguish objects at the
                    distance even of five miles. These vapours may be viewed from the mountains,
                    where the cold is very severe. The moisture collected increases with the heat;
                    and in March and April a prodigious quantity is accumulated, and floats in the
                    atmosphere, sometimes ascending nearly to the tops of the mountains, where it is
                    checked or condensed by the cold; but, descending immediately after, it is again
                    rarefied by the heat of the lower atmosphere, into vapour, before it reaches the
                    earth. At the setting in of the western monsoon, the whole is condensed into
                    rain, which falls very heavily, partly in the low country, and partly in the
                    mountains; and a small portion escapes and is blown across Mysore. These heavy
                    rains serve to bear away the soil, and leave nothing but loose stones and sand
                    upon the hills. The country abounds in lofty forests, which are sometimes
                    intermixed with cornfields and plantations of fruit-trees. The teak is produced
                    in great abundance, mostly about Manarghaut; but it is too remote from any
                    navigable river to be transported with a profit from the place of its growth.
                    Sandal-wood is also exported from Malabar, though it is not the produce of the
                    country; at least such as is found within the limits of Malabar is not of a good
                    quality, being entirely devoid of smell; but, growing as it does immediately to
                    the eastward of the Western Ghauts, all that is produced towards the sources of
                    the Cavery naturally comes to Malabar, which affords the nearest ports that can
                    be found for its exportation. The palm is produced in the greatest abundance
                    about Palighaut, and with proper care an excellent spirit might be extracted
                    from it. These forests, unlike those in India, are the private property of the
                    landholders, who have exercised the right of selling and mortgaging the trees to
                    Moplay merchants. This right is interfered with in a manner equally oppressive
                    and impolitic by the surveyor of forests, an officer appointed with a view to
                    preserve them. Sir Thomas Munro, with his usual enlightened views, remonstrated
                    against his interference with the proprietors of the forests, and pointed out
                    its prejudicial effects upon the interests of all parties concerned, and the
                    grievance was to a certain extent redressed. Cocoa-nut trees abound in the
                    province. Black pepper is produced abundantly in Malabar, and forms the chief
                    export by Europeans, who usually purchase about five eighths of all that is
                    produced, and carry it principally to Europe directly, or to Bombay and China.
                    The remainder is chiefly exported by native traders to the Bay of Bengal, Surat,
                    Cutch, Sinde, and other countries in the north-west of India; and a considerable
                    quantity finds its way to the Arabian ports of Muscat, Mocha, Hodeida, and Aden.
                    They use scarcely any horses, asses, swine, sheep, or goats, in Malabar; and
                    such as arc required for the use of the inhabitants are imported from the east.
                    They have a small breed of cattle and buffaloes; but even these are but little
                    used in the transportation of goods, which arc usually carried by porters.
                    Poultry have been introduced into the country by the Europeans; and common fowl
                    may be had in abundance. In many parts field labour is performed by slaves, who
                    are the absolute property of their lords, and may be sold at pleasure. But. a
                    husband and wife cannot be separated, though parents may be taken from their
                    children. The country is distinguished by the neatness of its villages, which
                    are superior to any in India. They are built of mud, which is neatly smoothed,
                    and are either white-washed or painted; and are much embellished by the beauty
                    and elegant dresses of the Brahmin girls. The villages, as well as the bazars,
                    are the work of foreigners, the aboriginal natives of Malabar living in detached
                    houses surrounded with gardens. The higher ranks use little clothing, but are
                    remarkably clean in their persons; and all ranks are free from cutaneous
                    distempers, excepting the very lowest castes of slaves.</p>
                <p part="N">The country being intersected by many rivers, and bounded by a high wall
                    of mountains, was protected by these natural obstacles against the torrent of
                    Mahommedan invasion which desolated other parts of India; and it was not till
                    1766, when it was invaded by Hyder Ali, that it was subjected to a foreign yoke.
                    Hence the original manners and peculiar customs of the Hindus have been
                    preserved here in much greater purity than in other parts of India. Besides the
                    Hindus, who form the great proportion of the inhabitants, the population
                    consists of Moplays or Mahommedans, Christians, and Jews. The Hindus are divided
                    into the following castes; namely, Nam-buries, or Brahmins; the Nairs of various
                    denominations; the Teers or Tiars, who are cultivators of the land, and freemen;
                    the Malears, who are musicians and conjurors, and also freemen; and, lastly, the
                    Patiars, who are slaves or bondmen. Of these castes, the most remarkable are the
                    Nairs, the pure Sudras of Malabar, who all lay claim to be born soldiers, though
                    they are of various ranks and professions. There are altogether eleven ranks of
                    Nairs, who form the militia of Malabar, under the Brahmins and rajahs. They are
                    proud and arrogant to their inferiors; and, in former times, a Nair was expected
                    instantly to cut down a cultivator or fisherman who presumed to defile him by
                    touching his person, or a Patiar who did not turn out of his road as a Nair
                    passed. It is a remarkable custom amongst this class, that a Nair never cohabits
                    with the person whom he calls his wife. He gives her all proper allowances of
                    clothing and food; but she remains in her mother’s or brother’s house, and
                    cohabits with any person or persons she chooses, of equal rank; so that no Nair
                    knows his own father; and the children all belong to the mother, whose claim to
                    them admits of no doubt. This state of manners also prevails in the neighbouring
                    countries of Travancore, Bednore, and Canara.</p>
                <p part="N">As in Malabar, the ancient Hindu state of property and manners prevails,
                    almost the whole land, cultivated and uncultivated, belongs to individuals, and
                    is held by a right which conveys a full and absolute property in the soil. There
                    are many traditions and conjectures respecting the origin of landed property in
                    those countries; and upon this subject a very full detail will be found in Mr
                    Thackeray’s report on the land tenures and assessments in Malabar,<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">See <hi
                                rend="italic">Fifth Report of the Select Committee on India
                                Affairs,</hi> p. 799.</p></note> in which he, along with Colonel
                    Munro and others, strongly contends, that in the southern parts of India,
                    namely, in Malabar, Tanjore, Trichinopoly, &amp;c. the private right of property
                    in the soil has been established from time immemorial. “The occupants of the
                    land,” says one of the collectors of the revenue in Southern India, “by whatever
                    name distinguished, have the right of selling, bestowing, devising, and
                    bequeathing their lands, in the manner which to them is most agreeable.”<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N"><hi
                                rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> p. 831. Extract from the Report of the
                            principal Collector of Tanjore and Trichinopoly.</p></note> The
                    succession to property, in consequence of the extraordinary customs of the
                    Nairs, depends on the mother, about whom there can be no mistake, though the
                    father is frequently uncertain.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194200485?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0714-0485-0051"/>
                <p part="N">Christianity appears at a very early period to have made considerable
                    progress on the Malabar coast; and there is a greater proportion of persons
                    professing that religion in this than in any other part of India. Three
                    ecclesiastical chiefs, two appointed by the Portuguese church at Goa, and one by
                    the see of Rome, ruled over this establishment, besides the Babylonish bishops
                    who preside over the Nestorian community. Forty-four churches compose at present
                    the Nestorian communion, which has been reduced from 200,000 souls, its amount
                    before the arrival of Vasco de Gama, to about 40,000. The total number of
                    Christians on the Malabar coast, including the Syrians or Nestorians, is
                    computed to amount to 200,000, of whom 90,000 are settled in Travancore. The
                    Jews are estimated at 30,000.</p>
                <p part="N">It is supposed that Malabar was, at a very early period, conquered by a
                    king from above the Ghauts. The Nairs may have been established at the same time
                    by the conqueror, or called in by the Brahmins, as a military body, to support
                    the government. In process of time they obtained settlements in the land; and
                    the chiefs, taking every opportunity to aggrandize themselves, became rajahs,
                    and from a remote period continued to govern Malabar like independent princes,
                    until Hyder’s invasion in 1760. Tradition, and the general opinion of the
                    inhabitants, contradict the notion that any land-tax existed in Malabar prior to
                    that event. No conclusive evidence is supplied on this subject by the doubtful
                    analogies of the neighbouring states; in some of which, such as Travancore, no
                    land-tax was said to exist, whilst in Canara a regular land-tax has been imposed
                    for centuries. There does not seem to have been any urgent necessity for the
                    establishment of a general land-tax, as there was no army besides the militia,
                    nor indeed any expensive establishments. Hyder subdued the country in 1761, and
                    expelled all the rajahs, except such as conciliated him by immediate submission.
                    Disturbances λvere occasioned by these proceedings; but he succeeded in
                    establishing his authority, and in 1782 appointed a deputy, who made still
                    further progress in subduing and settling the country. In 1788 Tippoo, his son,
                    proposed to the Hindus to embrace the true faith, and began by levying
                    contributions on his infidel subjects, and forcibly circumcising many of the
                    Brahmins, Nairs, and others. This produced a serious rebellion, which, however,
                    was soon quelled by his vigorous administration; and in the mean time the
                    country was laid waste by these tyrannical proceedings. On the breaking out of
                    the war between Tippoo and the British in 1790, the refractory rajahs and Nairs,
                    who were leading a predatory life in the jungles, were encouraged to join the
                    Company’s army. After the war, they were re-instated in their authority; but
                    they made such large claims to independence, whilst they failed at the same time
                    to fulfil their engagements for the payment of the revenue, and were also so
                    tyrannical in their proceedings, that they were finally deprived of all
                    authority, and allowed one fifth of their revenues for the support of their
                    dignity. Many of them, in consequence, had recourse to rebellion; but they were
                    put down by a military force, and some of them punished. Since this period,
                    under the management of the British collectors of revenue, the country exhibits
                    comparative tranquillity, and is said to be advancing in prosperity; though the
                    heavy assessments imposed by the British tend to obstruct its progress.</p>
                <p part="N">Under the name of Malabar is distinguished a large tract of country
                    extending along the western coast of India, from Cape Comorin to the river
                    Chandragiri, in lat. 12.30. north; and the term is frequently erroneously
                    applied to the whole country from Bombay to the southern extremity. The above
                    account applies only to the British province of that name.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Malabar</hi><hi rend="italic">Point,</hi> a
                    remarkable promontory of Hindustan, on the island of Bombay, remarkable for a
                    cleft rock, in great repute for its sanctity amongst the numerous Hindus who
                    resort thither for the purpose of being purified from their sins, which is
                    effected by passing through the aperture, which is of considerable elevation,
                    being situated amongst rocks of difficult access, that, in the stormy season,
                    are incessantly washed by the billows. In the vicinity are the ruins of a
                    temple, said to have been blown <hi rend="superscript"> u</hi> p by the
                    Portuguese; and a beautiful Brahmin village, built round a fine tank of
                    considerable extent, with broad flights of steps down to the water.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
