<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0588-0553-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WHITETHROAT (9th edition, volume 24, page 553)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126120">Songs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1138503">Summer</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176048">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1181567">Wrens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:854204">Chiffchaff</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175501">Willows</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128737">Sparrows</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44b2xd0k">Willows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4736mb9b">Wrens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15v25">Sparrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4416t316">Hay</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1215269">Gibraltar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n588/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WHITETHROAT</label>, a name commonly given to two species of
                    little birds, one of which, the <hi rend="italic">Motacilla</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Sylvia</hi> of Linnaeus and <hi rend="italic">Sylvia
                    rufa</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This specific
                    term has been very constantly but most inaccurately, not to say absurdly, used
                    for a very different bird, the Chiffchaff (cf. [Willow] <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Wren).</hi> Its only proper application is to the Whitethroat.</p></note> or
                    <hi rend="italic">S.</hi><hi rend="italic">cinerea</hi> of some recent authors,
                    is regarded as the type, not only of the genus <hi rend="italic">Sylvia,</hi>
                    but of the so-called Family <hi rend="italic">Sylviidae (cf.</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Warbler).</hi></p>
                <p>Very widely spread over Great Britain, in some places tolerably common, and by
                    its gesticulations and song rather conspicuous, it is one of those birds which
                    has gained a familiar nickname, and “Peggy Whitethroat” is the anthropomorphic
                    appellation of schoolboys and milkmaids, though it shares “Nettle-creeper” and
                    other homely names with perhaps more than one congener, while to the writers and
                    readers of books it is by way of distinction the Greater Whitethroat. The song
                    of this bird, except by association with the season at which it is uttered, can
                    scarcely be called agreeable, some of its notes being very harsh; but the
                    performer may be seen to be always in earnest, erecting the feathers of his
                    crown, puffing out those of his throat, shaking his wings, and making other
                    rapid movements expressive of his feelings. Occasionally he will deliver his
                    song as he flies up in a peculiar fashion, describing small circles in the air,
                    stopping with a jerk, and then returning to the spot whence he arose.</p>
                <p>The Lesser Whitethroat, <hi rend="italic">Sylvia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >curruca,</hi><note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Of course
                    this is not the <hi rend="italic">curruca</hi> of ancient writers, that being
                    almost certainly the Hedge-Sparrow (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Sparrow),</hi> the
                    ordinary dupe of the Cuckow.</p></note> is both in habits and plumage a much
                    less sightly bird: the predominant reddish brown of the upper surface, and
                    especially the rufous edging of the wingfeathers, that are so distinctive of its
                    larger congener, are wanting, and the whole plumage above is of a smoky-grey,
                    while the bird in its movements is never obtrusive, and it rather shuns than
                    courts observation, generally keeping among the thickest foliage, whence its
                    rather monotonous song, uttered especially in sultry weather, may be continually
                    heard without a glimpse of the vocalist being presented. The nests of each of
                    these species are very pretty works of art, firmly built of bents or other
                    plant-stalks, and usually lined with horsehair; but the sides and bottom are
                    often so finely woven as to be like open basket-work, and the eggs, splashed,
                    spotted, or streaked with olive-brown, are frequently visible from beneath
                    through the interstices of the fabric. This style of nest-building seems to be
                    common to all the species of the genus <hi rend="italic">Sylvia,</hi> as now
                    restricted, and in many districts has obtained for the builders the name of
                    “Hay-Jack,” quite without reference to the kind of bird which puts the nests
                    together, and thus is also applied to the Blackcap, <hi rend="italic">S.
                    atricapilla,</hi> and the Garden-Warbler—this last being merely a book-name— <hi
                    rend="italic">S. salicaria (S.</hi><hi rend="italic">hortensis</hi> of some
                    writers).<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This bird, if
                    it has any true English name at all, should perhaps be called the “Pettichaps,”
                    that being applied to it, though not exclusively, in Lancashire and Yorkshire,
                    but not, it would seem, in Northamptonshire or Hampshire (c∕. YarrelΓs <hi
                    rend="italic">Br. Birds,</hi> 4th ed. pp. 415, 416).</p></note> The former of
                    these deserves mention as one of the sweetest songsters of Great Britain, and
                    fortunately it is very generally distributed in summer. To quote the praise
                    bestowed upon it, in more than one passage, by Gilbert White would here be
                    superfluous. The name Blackcap is applicable only to the cock bird, who further
                    differs from his brown-capped mate by the purity of his ashy-grey upper plumage;
                    but, notwithstanding the marked sexual difference in appearance, he takes on
                    himself a considerable share of the duties of incubation, and has been declared
                    by more than one writer to sing while so employed—a statement that seems hardly
                    credible. All these four birds, as a rule, leave Great Britain at the end of
                    summer to winter in the south.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The Blackcap is recorded as having occurred several times in
                    England in winter: but its tarrying was doubtless involuntary.</p><p/></note>
                    Two other species, one certainly belonging to the same genus, <hi rend="italic"
                    >S. orphea,</hi> and the other, <hi rend="italic">S. nisoria,</hi> a somewhat
                    aberrant form, have occurred two or three times in Great Britain. The rest,
                    numbering perhaps a dozen, must be passed over.</p>
                <p>Nearly allied to <hi rend="italic">Sylvia,</hi> if indeed it can be properly
                    separated, is <hi rend="italic">MelizoρhUus,</hi> which consists of two species,
                    one of them the curious Dartford Warbler of English writers, <hi rend="italic"
                    >M.</hi><hi rend="italic">undatus</hi> or <hi rend="italic">provincialis.</hi>
                    This is on many accounts a very interesting bird, for it is one of the few of
                    its family that winter in England,—a fact the more remarkable when it is known
                    to be migratory in most parts of the Continent. Its distribution in England is
                    very local, and chiefly confined to the southern counties, where through causes
                    very insufficiently known it has of late years become so scarce that its
                    extermination seems probable. It is a pretty little dark-coloured bird, which
                    here and there may be seen on furze-grown heaths from Kent to Cornwall. In
                    spasmodic gesticulations the cock surpasses the Whitethroat; but these feats are
                    almost confined to the pairing-season, and at other times of the year the bird’s
                    habits are retiring. For a species with wings so feebly formed it has a wide
                    range, inhabiting nearly all the countries of the Mediterranean seaboard, from
                    Palestine to the Strait of Gibraltar, and thence along the west coast of Europe
                    to the English Channel; but everywhere else it seems to be very local.</p>
                <p>This may be the most convenient place for noticing the small group of Warblers
                    belonging to the well-marked genus <hi rend="italic">Hyρolais,</hi> which,
                    though in general appearance and certain habits resembling the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Phylloscopi (cf.</hi> [Willow] <hi rend="smallcaps">Wren),</hi> would seem
                    usually to have little to do with those birds, and to be rather allied to the
                    <hi rend="italic">Sylviinae,</hi> if not to the <hi rend="italic">Acrocephalinae
                    (cf.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Warbler).</hi> They have a remarkably loud song,
                    and in consequence are highly valued on the continent of Europe, where two
                    species at least spend the summer. One of them, <hi rend="italic">H.
                    icterina,</hi> has occurred more than once in the British Islands, and their
                    absence as regular visitors is to be regretted. Among the minor characteristics
                    of this little group is one afforded by their eggs, which are of a deeper or
                    paler brownish pink, spotted with purplish black. Their nests are beautiful
                    structures, combining warmth with lightness in a way that cannot be fully
                    appreciated by any description.</p>
                <p>A great number of other more or less allied forms, interesting as they are in
                    various ways, cannot for want of space be here mentioned. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
