<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0727-0686-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WRASSE (9th edition, volume 24, page 686)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1129919">Spine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925154">Fins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1145710">Teeth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926650">Fishing</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx3570p">Spines</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xd3v">Spine</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cf9j97x">Fins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd22">Teething</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c56c">Teeth</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n727/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WRASSE</label>. This name is applied to the fishes of the
                    family <hi rend="italic">Labridae</hi> generally, and more especially to certain
                    members of the family to be mentioned hereafter. They are without exception
                    inhabitants of the sea, very abundant in the tropical zone, less so in the
                    temperate, and disappearing altogether on the confines of the Arctic and
                    Antarctic Circles. Their body is generally compressed, like that of a carp,
                    covered with smooth (cycloid) scales; they possess one dorsal fin only, the
                    anterior portion of which consists of numerous spines. Many wrasses are readily
                    recognized by their thick lips, the inside of which is sometimes curiously
                    folded, a peculiarity which has given to them the German name of “lip-fishes.”
                    The dentition of their jaws consists of strong conical teeth, of which some in
                    front, and often one at the hinder end of the upper jaw, are larger than the
                    others.</p>
                <p>But the principal organs with which they crush shell-fish, crustaceans, and other
                    hard substances are the solid and strongly-toothed pharyngeal bones, of which
                    the lower are coalesced into a single flat triangular plate. The majority of
                    wrasses are beautifully coloured, exhibiting extraordinarily varied patterns of
                    permanent pigmentary colours, as well as evanescent reflexions of the scales.
                    All of them are surface fishes, living close to the shore or coralbanks. Rocky
                    parts of the coast overgrown with seaweed are their favourite haunts in the
                    temperate, and coral-reefs in the tropical seas. Some 450 species of wrasses
                    (including Parrot-Wrasses) are known, chiefly from the tropics; some grow to a
                    large size and are esteemed as food, whilst others, like the British species,
                    are small and but rarely eaten.</p>
                <p>Of the British wrasses the Ballan Wrasse <hi rend="italic">(Labrus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">maculatus)</hi> and the Striped or Red Wrasse or Cook <hi
                    rend="italic">(Labrus</hi><hi rend="italic">mixtus)</hi> are the most common.
                    Both belong to the genus <hi rend="italic">Labrus,</hi> in which the teeth stand
                    in a single series, and which has a smooth edge of the praeoperculum and only
                    three spines in the anal fin. The ballan wrasse is the larger, attaining to a
                    length of 18 inches, and, it is said, to a weight of 8 ïb; its colours are
                    singularly variegated, green or brownish, with red and blue lines and spots; the
                    dorsal spines are twenty in number. The cook wrasse offers an instance of
                    well-marked secondary sexual difference,—the male being ornamented with blue
                    streaks or a blackish band along the side of the body, whilst the female has two
                    or three large black spots across the back of the tail. This species possesses
                    only from sixteen to eighteen spines in the dorsal fin. The Goldsinny or
                    Corkwing <hi rend="italic">(Crenilabrus melops)</hi> is much more frequent on
                    the southern coasts of England and Ireland than farther north, and rarely
                    exceeds a length of 10 inches. As in other wrasses, its colours are beautiful,
                    but variable; but it may be readily distinguished from the two preceding species
                    by the toothed edge of the praeoperculum. The three other British wrasses are
                    much scarcer and more local, viz., Jago’s Goldsinny <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Ctenolabrus ruρestris),</hi> with a large black spot on the anterior dorsal
                    spines, and another on the base of the upper caudal rays; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Acantholabrus pallowi,</hi> which is so rarely captured that it lacks a
                    vernacular name, but may be easily recognized by its five anal spines and by the
                    teeth in the jaws forming a band; and the Rock-Cook <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Centrolabrus</hi><hi rend="italic">exoletus),</hi> which also has five anal
                    spines, but has the jaws armed with a single series of teeth.</p>
                <p>On the Atlantic coasts of the Northern States of North America the wrasses are
                    represented by the genus <hi rend="italic">Tautoga,</hi> which is distinct from
                    the European forms. The only species of this genus, known by the names of Tautog
                    or Blackfish, is a fish of considerable economic value, being much esteemed as
                    food. It is caught in great numbers, and generally sold of a weight of about 2
                    lb.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
