<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0635-0598-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WINDHAM, William (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    598)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933481">Foxes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:869839">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46h4ct7t">Fox</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hv69">Nonconformists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n635/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WINDHAM, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>
                    (1750-1810), English politician, came from an ancient family long resident at
                    Felbrigg near Cromer in Norfolk. His father, Colonel William Windham, was an
                    adventurous soldier with a taste for languages, both ancient and modern; William
                    Windham, the statesman, was born in Golden Square, London, on 3d May 1750. At
                    the age of seven he went to Eton, which he quitted in 1766 for the university of
                    Glasgow, and under the care of Dr Simson he acquired the taste for mathematics
                    which always distinguished him. In 1767 he matriculated as gentleman commoner at
                    University College, Oxford, where he remained until 1771. He never took the
                    degree of B.A., but qualified as Μ. A. on 7th October 1782, and received the
                    degree of D.C.L. on 3d July 1793. He made a tour in Norway in 1773 and visited
                    Switzerland and Italy between 1778 and 1780. His maiden speech on the political
                    platform was delivered at Norwich on 28th January 1778, when he vehemently
                    opposed the prosecution of the American War. On his return to England in 1780 he
                    contested the representation of the city of Norwich, but was not successful. His
                    entrance into public life took place in April 1783, when he went to Ireland as
                    chief secretary to Lord Northington, the lord-lieutenant under the coalition
                    ministry of Fox and Lord North. Windham was his own keenest critic, his distrust
                    in his own powers and his disappointment at his own achievements being
                    conspicuous on every page of his <hi rend="italic">Diary.</hi> Sickness
                    compelled his return to England early in July 1783; but change of scene and
                    constant exercise restored him to health before the end of that year. In April
                    1784 he again contested Norwich and was returned by a majority of 64 votes, thus
                    scoring one of the few triumphs attained by the adherents of the coalition
                    cabinet. This seat he retained until 1802, when he was beaten by William Smith,
                    one of the leaders of the Nonconformists. Though he strenuously opposed all
                    proposals for parliamentary reform, to which most of the Whigs were deeply
                    committed, Windham remained in alliance with that party until after the outbreak
                    of the French Revolution, when he and several of his chief allies joined Pitt.
                    The place of secretary-at-war was conferred upon him in July 1794, and he was at
                    the same time created a privy councillor and admitted to a seat in the cabinet.
                    Windham discharged the duties of his office with unflagging zeal, his efforts
                    being particularly directed towards ameliorating the condition of the inferior
                    grades of the army. In the autumn of 1794 he was despatched to the duke of
                    York’s camp in Flanders with the views of his ministerial colleagues, but their
                    advice could not counteract the military incapacity of the royal duke. When Pitt
                    was frustrated in his intention of freeing the Catholics from their political
                    disabilities, Windham, who in religious matters always inclined to liberal
                    opinions, took his place among the ministers who retired from office (February
                    1801). He was a constant opponent of all negotiations for peace with France,
                    preferring to prosecute the campaign at whatever cost until some decisive
                    victory had been gained, and the temporary peace of Amiens, which was carried
                    through under Addington’s administration, did not meet with his approval. When
                    he was ousted from the representation of Norwich (July 1802), a seat for the
                    pocket borough of St Mawes in Cornwall was found for him by its patron, the
                    marquis of Buckingham, whose opinions coincided with Windham’s on the leading
                    political questions of the day. He declined a place in Pitt’s new cabinet (May
                    1802) on the ground that the exclusion of Fox, who had joined with them in
                    opposition to the weak ministry of Addington, prevented the formation of an
                    administration sufficiently strong in parliament and the country to cope with
                    the dangers which threatened the safety of the nation, and he offered a general
                    opposition to the measures which the prime minister proposed. On Pitt’s death in
                    January 1806 the ministry of “All the Talents” was formed under the leadership
                    of Lord Grenville, and Windham accepted the seals as secretary of state for war
                    and the colonies. Fox’s death necessitated several official changes; and a
                    peerage was proposed for Windham, but he declined the proffered honour, and
                    remained in office as long as the ministry existed. A general election took
                    place in October 1806 and Windham was elected for the county of Norfolk; but the
                    election was declared void on petition, and he was compelled to sit for the
                    Treasury borough of New Romney, for which he had also been elected. In 1807,
                    when the House was dissolved under the influence of the “No Popery” cry of
                    Spencer Perceval, a seat was found for Windham by Lord Fitzwilliam in his close
                    constituency of Higham Ferrers. Liberty of religious opinion he uniformly
                    supported at all periods of his life, and with equal consistency he opposed all
                    outbreaks of religious fanaticism; hence with these convictions in his mind few
                    of the domestic measures of the new ministers met with his approbation.
                    Moreover, he disapproved of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n636/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0636-0599"/> the expedition to the Scheldt, and thought the
                    charges brought against the duke of York, as commander-in-chief, required his
                    retirement from office. At the same time he actively opposed the bill of Sir
                    Samuel Romilly, his colleague on most political questions, for reducing the
                    number of offences visited with the punishment of death. In July 1809 he
                    received a blow on the hip whilst rendering assistance at a fire, which he
                    thought little of at the time; but a tumour subsequently formed on the spot and
                    an operation became necessary. This brought on a fever, and Windham rapidly
                    sank. He died on 4th June 1810, and was buried in the family vault at
                    Felbrigg.</p>
                <p>Windham was tall and well-proportioned; and the impressiveness of his speeches
                    was heightened by the excellence of his address. Exercise of all kinds had
                    charms for him. He attended all the celebrated prize-fights of his day, and he
                    more than once spoke in the House of Commons against the prevention of
                    bull-baiting. Nor did he neglect the pleasures of literature and science. His
                    speeches were published in three volumes in 1806, with a memoir by Thomas Amyot,
                    his private secretary while he was in office in 1806, and his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Diary</hi> was edited by Mrs Henry Baring in 1866. The passages in the latter
                    -work relative to Dr Johnson’s declining days have been of considerable use to
                    the later editors of Boswell.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
