<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0599-0564-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WILBERFORCE, Samuel (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    564)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n599/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WILBERFORCE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel</hi></label>
                    (1805-1873), bishop of Oxford and afterwards of Winchester, was the third son of
                    William <hi rend="smallcaps">Wilberforce</hi> (see below), and was born at
                    Clapham Common near London on 7th September 1805. Until he entered Oriel
                    College, Oxford, in 1823 he was educated privately. In the “United Debating
                    Society,” which afterwards developed into the “Union,” Wilberforce distinguished
                    himself as a zealous advocate of liberalism. The set of friends with whom he
                    chiefly associated at Oxford were sometimes named, on account of their
                    exceptionally decorous conduct, the “Bethel Union”; but he was by no means
                    averse to amusements, and specially delighted in hurdle jumping and hunting. He
                    graduated in 1826; and the summer and autumn of 1827 were spent in a Continental
                    tour. After his marriage on 11th June 1828 to Emily Sargent, he was in December
                    ordained and appointed curate-in-charge at Checkenden near Henley-on-Thames. In
                    1830 he was presented by Bishop Sumner of Winchester to the rectory of
                    Brightstone in the Isle of Wight. In this comparatively retired sphere he soon
                    found scope for that manifold activity which so prominently characterized his
                    subsequent career. In 1831 he published a tract on tithes, “to correct the
                    prejudices of the lower order of farmers,” and in the following year a
                    collection of hymns for use in his parish, which had a large general
                    circulation; a small volume of stories entitled the <hi rend="italic">Note Book
                    of a Country Clergyman</hi>; and a sermon, <hi rend="italic">The Apostolical
                    Ministry.</hi> He now began to be sought for as a preacher and declined several
                    offers of appointments. In February 1836 he was made a rural dean. At the close
                    of 1837 he published the <hi rend="italic">Letters and Journals</hi> of Henry
                    Martyn. Although a High Churchman Wilberforce held aloof from the Oxford
                    movement, and in 1838 his divergence from the “Tract” writers became so marked
                    that J. H. Newman declined further contributions from him to the <hi
                    rend="italic">British Critic,</hi> not deeming it advisable that they should
                    longer “co-operate very closely.” In 1838 Wilberforce published, with his elder
                    brother Robert, the <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of his father and two years
                    later his father’s <hi rend="italic">Correspondence.</hi> In 1839 he also
                    published <hi rend="italic">Eucharistica</hi> (from the old English divines), to
                    which he wrote an introduction, <hi rend="italic">Agathos and other Sunday
                    Stories,</hi> and a volume of <hi rend="italic">University Sermems,</hi> and in
                    the following year <hi rend="italic">Rocky Island and other Parables.</hi> In
                    November 1839 he was installed archdeacon of Surrey, in August 1840 collated
                    canon of Winchester, and in October he accepted the rectory of Alverstoke. In
                    1841 he was chosen Bampton lecturer, and shortly afterwards made chaplain to the
                    Prince Consort, an appointment he owed to the impression produced by a speech at
                    an antislavery meeting some months previously. In October 1843 he was appointed
                    by the archbishop of York to be sub-almoner to the queen. In 1844 appeared his
                    <hi rend="italic">History of the American Church.</hi> In March of the following
                    year he accepted the deanery of Westminster, and in October the bishopric of
                    Oxford.</p>
                <p>The bishop in 1847 became involved in the Hampden controversy, and signed the
                    remonstrance of the thirteen bishops to Lord John Russell against Dr Hampden’s
                    appointment to the bishopric of Hereford. He also endeavoured to obtain
                    satisfactory assurances from Dr Hampden; but, though unsuccessful in this, he
                    withdrew from the suit against him. The publication of a papal bull in 1850
                    establishing a Roman hierarchy in England brought the High Church party, of whom
                    Wilberforce was the most prominent member, into temporary disrepute. The
                    secession to the Church of Rome of his brother-in-law, Archdeacon (now Cardinal)
                    Manning, and afterwards of his two brothers, brought him under further
                    suspicion, and his revival of the powers of convocation lessened his influence
                    at court; but his unfailing tact and wide sympathies, his marvellous energy in
                    church organization, the magnetism of his personality, and his eloquence, both
                    on the platform and in the pulpit, gradually won for him recognition as without
                    a rival on the episcopal bench. In the House of Lords he took a prominent part
                    in the discussion of social and ecclesiastical questions. He has been styled the
                    “bishop of society”; but society occupied only a fraction of his time. The great
                    bent of his energies was ceaselessly directed to the better organization of his
                    diocese and to the furtherance of schemes for increasing the influence and
                    efficiency of the church. In 1854 he opened a theological college at Cuddesdon,
                    which was afterwards the subject of some controversy on account of its alleged
                    Romanist tendencies. His attitude towards <hi rend="italic">Essays and
                    Reviews</hi> in 1861, against which he wrote an article in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Quarterly,</hi> won him the special gratitude of the Low Church party, and
                    latterly he enjoyed the full confidence and esteem of all except the extreme men
                    of either side and party. On the publication of Colenso’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Commentary on the Romans</hi> in 1861 Wilberforce endeavoured to induce the
                    author to hold a private conference with him; but after the publication of the
                    first two parts of the <hi rend="italic">Pentateuch Critically Examined</hi> he
                    drew up the address of the bishops which called on Colenso to resign his
                    bishopric. In 1867 he framed the first <hi rend="italic">Report</hi> of the
                    Ritualistic Commission, in which coercive measures against ritualism were
                    discountenanced by the use of the word “restrain” instead of “abolish” or
                    “prohibit.” He also endeavoured to take the sting out of some resolutions of the
                    second Ritualistic Commission in 1868, and was one of the four who signed the
                    <hi rend="italic">Report</hi> with qualifications. Though strongly opposed to
                    the disestablishment of the Irish Church, yet, when the constituencies decided
                    for it, he prudently advised that no opposition should be made to it by the
                    House of Lords. After twenty-four years’ labour in the diocese of Oxford, he was
                    named by Mr Gladstone for the bishopric of Winchester. His unremitting labours
                    had, however, seriously told on his constitution, and the change to a new
                    diocese, entailing a repetition of the work of organization which he had
                    completed in the old one, proved too much for his health. The result was a
                    severe affection of the heart, which on more than one occasion threatened to
                    prove fatal. He was killed on 19th July 1873 by the shock of a fall from his
                    horse near Dorking, Surrey.</p>
                <p>Besides the works already mentioned, Wilberforce wrote <hi rend="italic">Heroes
                    of Hebrew History</hi> (1870), originally contributed to <hi rend="italic">Good
                    Words,</hi> and several volumes of sermons. See <hi rend="italic">Life of Samuel
                    Wilberforce, with</hi><pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n600/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0600-0565"/><hi rend="italic">Selections from his Diary and
                    Correspondence,</hi> vol. i., ed. by Ashwell, and vols. ii. and iii., ed. by his
                    son Reginald G. Wilberforce.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
