<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0649-0612-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WINKELRIED, Arnold von (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    612)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p84445x">Spear</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43775w28">Books</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836401">Books</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128817">Spears</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n649/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WINKELRIED, <hi rend="smallcaps">Arnold von</hi></label>. The
                    incident with which this name is connected is, after the feat of Tell, the best
                    known and most popular in the early history of the Swiss Confederation. We are
                    told how, at a critical moment in the great battle of Sempach, when the Swiss
                    had failed to break the serried ranks of the Austrian knights, a man of
                    Unterwalden, Arnold von Winkelried by name, came to the rescue. Commending his
                    wife and children to the care of his comrades, he rushed towards the Austrians,
                    gathered a number of their spears together against his breast, and fell pierced
                    through and through, having opened a way into the hostile ranks for his
                    fellow-countrymen, though at the price of his own life. But the Tell and
                    Winkelried stories stand in a very different position when looked at in the dry
                    light of history, for, while in the former case imaginary and impossible men
                    (bearing now and then a real historical name) do imaginary and impossible deeds
                    at a very uncertain period, in the latter we have some solid ground to rest on,
                    and Winkelried’s act might very well have been performed, though, as yet, the
                    amount of genuine and early evidence in support of it is very far from being
                    sufficient.</p>
                <p>The Winkelrieds of Stanz<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Their history from 1248 to 1534 has been minutely worked out from the
                    documents by Herr Hermann von Liebenau, in a paper published in 1854, and
                    reprinted at Aarau in 1862, with much other matter, in his book, <hi
                    rend="italic">Arnold</hi><hi rend="italic">von Winkelried,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >seine</hi><hi rend="italic">Zeit und</hi><hi rend="italic">seine
                    That.</hi></p><p/></note> were a knightly family when we first hear of
                    them,though towards the end of the 14th century they seem to have been but
                    simple men without the honours of knighthood, and not always using their prefix
                    “von.” Among its members we find an Erni Winkelried acting as a witness to a
                    contract of sale on May 1, 1367, while the same man, or perhaps another member
                    of the family, Erni von Winkelried, is plaintiff in a suit at Stanz on September
                    29, 1389, and in 1417 is the landamman (or head man) of Unterwalden, being then
                    called Arnold Winkelriet. We have, therefore, a real man named Arnold Winkelried
                    living at Stanz about the time of the battle of Sempach. The question is thus
                    narrowed to the points, Was he present at the battle, and did he then perform
                    the deed commonly attributed to him? involving a minute investigation of the
                    history of that battle, to ascertain if there are any authentic traces of this
                    incident, or any opportunity for it to have taken place.</p>
                <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Evidence</hi><hi rend="italic">of Chronicles.—</hi> The
                    earliest known mention of the incident is found in a Zurich chronicle
                    (discovered in 1862 by Herr G. von Wyss), which is a copy, made in 1476, of a
                    chronicle written in or at any rate not earlier than 1438, though it is wanting
                    in the 16th-century transcript of another chronicle written in 1466, which up to
                    1389 closely agrees with the former. It appears in the well-known form, but the
                    hero is stated to be “ein getrüwer man under den Eidgenozen,” no name being
                    given, and it seems clear that his death did not take place at that time. No
                    other mention has been found in any of the numerous Swiss or Austrian chronicles
                    till we come to the book <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Helvetiae</hi><hi rend="italic">Origine,</hi> written in 1538 by Rudolph
                    Gwalther (Zwingli’s son-in-law), when the hero is still nameless, being compared
                    to Decius or Codrus, but is said to have been killed by his brave act. Finally,
                    we read the full story in the original draft of Giles Tschudi’s chronicle, where
                    the hero is described as “a man of Unterwalden, of the Winkelried family,” this
                    being expanded in the final recension of the chronicle (1564) into “a man of
                    Unterwalden, Arnold von Winckelried by name, a brave knight,” while he is
                    entered (in the same book, on the authority of the “Anniversary Book” of Stanz,
                    now lost) on the list of those who fell at Sempach at the head of the Nidwald
                    (or Stanz) men as “Herr Arnold von Winckelriet, ritter,” this being in the first
                    draft “Arnold Winckelriet.”</p>
                <p>(2) <hi rend="italic">Ballads.—</hi> There are several war songs on the battle of
                    Sempach which have come down to us, but in one only is there mention of
                    Winkelried and his deed. This is a long ballad of 67 four-line stanzas, part of
                    which (including the Winkelried section) is found in the additions made between
                    1531 and 1545 to Etterlin’s chronicle by H. Berlinger of Basel, and the whole in
                    Werner Steiner’s chronicle (written 1532). It is agreed on all sides that the
                    last stanza, attributing the authorship to Halbsuter of Lucerne, “as he came
                    back from the battle,” is a very late addition. Many authorities regard it as
                    made up of three distinct songs (one of which refers to the battle and
                    Winkelried), possibly put together by the younger Halbsuter (citizen of Lucerne
                    in 1435, died between 1470 and 1480), though others contend that the
                    Sempach-Winkel-ried section bears clear traces of having been composed after the
                    Reformation began, that is, about 1520 or 1530. Some recent discoveries have
                    proved that certain statements in the song usually regarded as anachronisms are
                    quite accurate; but no nearer approach has been made towards fixing its exact
                    date, or that of any of the three bits into which it has been cut up. In this
                    song the story appears in its full-blown shape, the name of Winckelriet being
                    given.</p>
                <p>(3) <hi rend="italic">Lists of Those who Fell at</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sempach.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> We find in the “Anniversary Book” of
                    Emmetten in Unterwalden (drawn up in 1560) the name of “der Winkelriedt” at the
                    head of the Nidwald men; and in a book by Horolanus, a pastor at Lucerne (about
                    1563), that of “Erni Winckelried” occurs some way down the list of Unterwalden
                    men.</p>
                <p>(4) <hi rend="italic">Pictures and Drawings.—</hi> In the MS. of the chronicle of
                    Diebold Schilling of Bern (c. 1480) there is in the picture of the battle of
                    Sempach a warrior pierced with spears falling to the ground, which may possibly
                    be meant for Winkelried; while in that of Diebold Schilling of Lucerne (1511),
                    though in the text no allusion is made to any such incident, there is a similar
                    picture of a man who has accomplished Winkelried’s feat, but he is dressed in
                    the colours of Lucerne. Then there is an engraving in Stumpfs chronicle (1548),
                    and, finally, the celebrated one by Hans Rudolph Manuel (1551), which follows
                    the chronicle of 1476 rather than the ballad.</p>
                <p>The story seems to have been first questioned about 1850 by Moritz von Stürler of
                    Bern, but the public discussion of the subject originated with a lecture by
                    Prof. O. Lorenz on “Leopold III. und die Schweizer Bünde,” which he delivered in
                    Vienna on March 21, 1860. This began the lively paper war humorously called “the
                    second war of Sempach,” in which the Swiss (with but rare exceptions) maintained
                    the historical character of the feat against various foreigners—Austrians and
                    others.</p>
                <p>Most of the arguments against the genuineness of the story have been already more
                    or less directly indicated. (1) There is the total silence of all the old Swiss
                    and Austrian chroniclers until 1538, with the solitary exception of the Zurich
                    chronicle of 1476 (and this while they nearly all describe the battle in more or
                    less detail). The tale, as told in the 1476 chronicle, is clearly an
                    interpolation, for it comes immediately after a distinct statement that “God had
                    helped the Confederates, and that with great labour they had defeated the
                    knights and Duke Leopold,” while the passage immediately following joins on to
                    the former quite naturally if we strike out the episode of the “true man,” who
                    is not even called Winkelried. (2) The date of the ballad is extremely
                    uncertain, but cannot be placed earlier than at least 60 or 70 years after the
                    battle, possibly 130 or 140, so that its claims to be regarded as embodying an
                    oral contemporary tradition are of the slightest. (3) Similar feats have been
                    frequently recorded, but in each case they are supported by authentic evidence
                    which is lacking in this case. Five cases at least are known: a follower of the
                    count of Hapsburg, in a skirmish with the Bernese in 1271; Stülinger of Ratisbon
                    in 1332, in the war of the count of Kyburg against the men of Bern and
                    Solothurn; Conrad Royt of Lucerne, at Nancy in 1477; Herni Wolleben, at Frastenz
                    in 1499, in the course of the Swabian war; and a man at the battle of Kappel in
                    1531. (4) It is argued that the course of the battle was such that there was
                    little or no chance of such an act being performed, or, if performed, of having
                    turned the day. This argument rests on the careful critical narrative of the
                    fight constructed by Herr Kleissner and Herr Hartmann from the contemporary
                    accounts which have come down to us, in which the pride of the knights, their
                    heavy armour, the heat of the July sun, the panic which befell a sudden part of
                    the Austrian army, added to the valour of the Swiss, fully explain the complete
                    rout. Herr Hartmann, too, points out that, even if the knights (on foot) had
                    been ranged in serried ranks, there must have been sufficient space left between
                    them to allow them to move their arms, and therefore that no man, however
                    gigantic he might have been, could have seized hold of more than half a dozen
                    spears at once.</p>
                <p>Herr K. Bürkli <hi rend="italic">(Der Wahre Winkelried,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—die</hi><hi rend="italic">Taktik der alten Urschweizer,</hi> Zurich, 1886) has
                    put forth a theory of the battle which is, he allows, opposed to all modern
                    accounts, but entirely agrees, he strongly maintains, with the contemporary
                    authorities. According to this the fight was not a pitched battle but a
                    surprise, the Austrians not having had time to form up into ranks. Assuming
                    this, and rejecting the evidence of the 1476 chronicle as an interpolation and
                    full of mistakes, and that of the song as not proved to have been in existence
                    before 1531, Herr Bürkli comes to the startling conclusion that the phalanx
                    formation of the Austrians, as well as the name and act of Winkelried, have been
                    transferred to Sempach from the fight of Bicocca, near Milan (April 27, 1522),
                    where a real leader of the Swiss mercenaries in the pay of France, Arnold
                    Winkelried, really met his death in very much the way <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n650/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0650-0613"/> that his namesake perished according to the
                    story. Herr Bürkli confines his criticism to the first struggle, in which alone
                    mention is made of the driving back of the Swiss, pointing out also that the
                    chronicle of 1476 and other later accounts attribute to the Austrians the manner
                    of attack and the long spears which were the special characteristics of <hi
                    rend="italic">Swiss</hi> warriors, and that if Winkelried were a knight (as is
                    asserted by Tschudi) he would have been clad in a coat of mail, or at least had
                    a breastplate, neither of which could have been pierced by hostile lances.</p>
                <p>Whatever may be thought of this daring theory, it seems clear that, while there
                    is some doubt as to whether such an act as Winkelried’s was possible at Sempach,
                    taking into account the known details of the battle, there can be none as to the
                    utter lack of any early and trustworthy evidence in support of his having
                    performed that act in that battle. It is quite conceivable that such evidence
                    may later come to light; for the present it is wanting.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> See in particular Theodor von Liebenau’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic">Schlacht bei Sempach</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic">Gedenkbuch zur fünften Säcularfeier</hi>
                    (1886), published at the expense of the Government of Lucerne. This contains
                    every mention or description of the battle or of anything relating to it,
                    published or unpublished, in prose or in verse, composed within 300 years after
                    the battle, and is a most marvellous and invaluable collection of original
                    materials, in which all the evidence for winkelried’s deed has been brought
                    together in a handy shape. Besides the works mentioned in the text, the
                    following are the most noteworthy pamphlets relating to this controversy. Ip
                    support of winkelried’s act: G. v. Wyss, <hi rend="italic">Ueber</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">eine Zürcher-Chronik aus dem löten Jahrhundert,</hi> Zurich, 1862;
                    A. Daguet, “La Question de Winkel-ried,” in <hi rend="italic">Musée
                    Neuchâtelois</hi> for Dec. 1883; G. H. Qchsenbein, “Die Winkelried-frage,” in
                    <hi rend="italic">Sonntagsblatt</hi> of the <hi rend="italic">Bund</hi>
                    newspaper for Jan. and Feb. 1879; A. Bernoulli!, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Winkelrieds</hi><hi rend="italic">That</hi><hi rend="italic">bei Sempach,</hi>
                    Basel, 1886; W. Oechsli, <hi rend="italic">Zur</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Sempacher</hi><hi rend="italic">Schlachtfeier,</hi> Zurich, 1886; E. Secretan,
                    <hi rend="italic">Sempach et Winkelried,</hi> Lausanne, 1886; and the summary in
                    K. Dändliker’s larger <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Schweiz,</hi> i. 510-525, Zurich, 1884. Against winkelried’s claims we have the
                    remarkable study of O. Kleissner, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Quellen zur</hi><hi rend="italic">Sempacher</hi><hi rend="italic">Schlacht
                    und</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic">Winkelriedsage,</hi>
                    Göttingen, 1873; Ο. Hartmann, <hi rend="italic">Die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Schlacht bei Sempach,</hi> Frauenfeld, 1886; and the concise summary of the
                    evidence given by Μ. v. Stiirler (the first to suspect the story) in the <hi
                    rend="italic">Anzeiger für</hi><hi rend="italic">Schweiz.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Geschichte,</hi> 1881, 392-394. (W. A. B. C.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
