<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0528-0503-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WESLEY (9th edition, volume 24, page 503)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49k45v4z">Hymns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn1111w">Scholars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:965486">Hymns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018703">Methodists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106878">Scholars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n528/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WESLEY</label>, an English family of special ecclesiastical
                    distinction, claims descent from the ancient De Wellesleys, one of whom, Guy,
                    was made a thane by Athelstan about 938, the family seat being at Welswe, near
                    Wells, in Somerset. Two brothers, John and Bartholomew, were among the ministers
                    ejected for nonconformity in 1662.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel</hi> (1662-1735), son of the above John, was born
                    17th December 1662. He was educated at an academy at Stepney, London, and in
                    August 1683 entered Exeter College, Oxford, as a <hi rend="italic">pauper
                    scholaris,</hi> shortly after which he joined the Church of England, a step
                    which so deeply offended his family that they left him henceforth to his own
                    resources. While still an undergraduate he published <hi rend="italic">Maggots,
                    or Poems on Several Subjects never before Handled,</hi> 1685. He graduated B.A.
                    1688, was ordained priest 24th February 1689, and the following year was
                    presented to the living of South Ormsby, Lincolnshire. In 1697 he removed to
                    Epworth, Lincolnshire, where he died 25th April 1735. Among other works he was
                    the author of <hi rend="italic">Life of Christ</hi> (1693), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Elegies on Queen Mary and Archbishop Tillotson</hi> (1695), <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of the Old and New Testaments in Verse</hi> (1704), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pious Communicant Rightly Prepared 1700)</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Latin
                    Commentary on the Book of Job</hi> (1733). After the battle of Blenheim he
                    published (1705) a long poem on <hi rend="italic">Marlborough, or the Fate of
                    Europe,</hi> for which Marlborough made him chaplain of a regiment. He had
                    nineteen children, of whom three sons, Samuel, John, and Charles, acquired
                    eminence.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel</hi> (1690-1739) was born in London 10th February
                    1690, and educated at Westminster school, where he was <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n529/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0529-0504"/> nominated king’s scholar. In 1711 he entered
                    Christ Church, Oxford, and on taking his M.A. degree returned to Westminster as
                    tutor. He lived on intimate terms with Harley, earl of Oxford, Pope, Swift, and
                    Prior, and wrote somewhat clever squibs against Sir Robert Walpole, the Whigs,
                    and the Low Church divines. They were collected and published 1736, reached a
                    second edition 1743, and were reprinted, with notes by James Nicholls and life
                    by W. Nicholls, in 1862. Wesley became master of Tiverton grammar-school in
                    1732, and died there 6th November 1739.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi> (1703-1791), brother of the preceding and founder
                    of Methodism, was born, probably at Epworth, 17th June (O.S., 28th N.S.) 1703.
                    There was a tradition in the family that he was christened John Benjamin, but he
                    never made use of the second name. When his father’s rectory was burnt down in
                    1709 he was for a time left in the building, and narrowly escaped death. He
                    entered Charterhouse in 1714, whence in 1720 he was elected to Christ Church,
                    Oxford. In 1726 he became fellow of Lincoln, and in 1727 graduated M.A. After
                    acting for some time as his father’s curate he settled in November 1729 at
                    Oxford, and began to take pupils. About the same time, along with his brother
                    Charles and others, he commenced that systematic course of religious life which
                    led to their being termed by the Oxonians Methodists. A full record of the
                    religious labours of Wesley is given under <hi rend="smallcaps">Methodism</hi>
                    (vol. xvi. pp. 185-189). In the organization of Methodism he displayed not only
                    extraordinary energy and capacity for work but remarkable administrative powers.
                    His oratory was colloquial, terse, and homely, but never vulgar, while his
                    expressive and refined features and intense yet reasoned earnestness enabled him
                    to acquire among his followers a personal influence of an unrivalled kind.
                    Although from overwork or exposure he had one or two serious illnesses, he
                    generally enjoyed robust health, an experience probably partly accounted for by
                    his constant journeys on horseback. In 1790 he said, “I do not remember to have
                    felt lowness of spirits for a quarter of an hour since I was born.” He preached
                    usually at 5 o’clock in the morning, and frequently twice again in the same day,
                    the number of sermons he delivered in a year being over 800. He continued his
                    labours almost to the last, but wrote, 1st January 1790, “I am now an old man
                    decayed from head to foot.” He died 2d March 1791. Wesley translated several
                    hymns from the German for the collections edited by him and his brother Charles,
                    but is not known to have been the author of any original hymns (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Hymns,</hi> vol. xii. p. 594). The first collection of <hi
                    rend="italic">Psalms and Hymns</hi> edited by the brothers appeared anonymously
                    in 1738, and a <hi rend="italic">Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems, from the
                    Most Celebrated Authors,</hi> in 1744. Wesley has no claims to rank as a thinker
                    or even as a theologian, but within certain narrow limits was a skilful
                    controversialist. He was the author of <hi rend="italic">Primitive Physic</hi>
                    (1747), <hi rend="italic">Explanatory Notes on the New Testament (1755), Notes
                    on the Old and New Testaments</hi> (1764), <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of
                    Original Sin</hi> (1757), <hi rend="italic">Survey of the Wisdom of God in
                    Creation</hi> (1763), <hi rend="italic">Preservative against Unsettled Notions
                    in Religion</hi> (1770), and <hi rend="italic">A Calm Address to our American
                    Colonies (1775).</hi> He also edited the <hi rend="italic">Christian
                    Library,</hi> in fifty volumes. His <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> appeared in
                    1818, and an eleventh edition, with life by J. Beecham and preface by T.
                    Jackson, was published in 15 vols., 1856-57.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Charles</hi> (1708-1788), brother of the preceding, was born
                    prematurely at Epworth, 18th December 1708. He entered Westminster school in
                    1716, was admitted a king’s scholar in 1721, and entered Christ Church, Oxford,
                    in 1726. He accompanied his brother John to Georgia in 1735 as secretary to the
                    managing committee, having been ordained priest a few days before leaving
                    England; but on account of a strong feeling of opposition manifested against him
                    in the religious communities of Frederica he left Georgia for England five
                    months after landing. To a serious illness which happened to him in February
                    1738 he attributed a moral change which he associated with conversion and a
                    conscious sense of pardon. He seconded his brother in his evangelizing labours
                    in England with unceasing diligence, and, although not possessing his brother’s
                    gifts of oratory and personal magnetism, contributed by his hymns an element of
                    success to the movement of prime and permanent importance. He published no fewer
                    than 4100 hymns of his own composition, and left about 2000 in manuscript.
                    Numerous editions both of the special and general collections of his hymns have
                    been published. Both as regards the number of his compositions and their various
                    excellences, he is entitled to the chief place among Methodist hymn writers (see
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Hymns,</hi><hi rend="italic">ut supra).</hi> He died 29th
                    March 1788. His <hi rend="italic">Sermons,</hi> with memoir, appeared in 1816; a
                    <hi rend="italic">Life,</hi> by Rev. Thomas Jackson, in 1841; and his <hi
                    rend="italic">Journal,</hi> with notes by Rev. Thomas Jackson, 1849.</p>
                <p>Two sons of Charles Wesley attained eminence as musicians :— <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Charles</hi> (1757-1815), organist of St George’s, Hanover Square, London, who
                    in 1778 published <hi rend="italic">Six Concertos for the Organ and Harp·,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="smallcaps">Samuel</hi> (1766-1837), organist of the Chapel Royal,
                    noticed below.</p>
                <p>See, in addition to the authorities already mentioned, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lives</hi> by Hampson (1791), Coke and Moore (1792), Whitehead (1793-96),
                    Southey (1820), Moore (1824), Watson (1831), Miss Wedgwood (1870), and Tyerman
                    (exhaustive and complete) (1870); J. Dove, <hi rend="italic">Biographical
                    History of the Wesleys</hi> (1833); and G. J. Stevenson, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Memorials of the Wesley Family</hi> (1876).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
