<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0651-0614-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WIRE (9th edition, volume 24, page 614)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198483">Brown</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897725">Drawing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176150">Wire</term>
                    <term ref="fast:958715">Holes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1017914">Metallizing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018047">Metals</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rp5c">Drawings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m9198r">Drawing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4251fv6s">Wire</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tm72270">Metals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4t727j1r">Copper</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n651/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WIRE</label>. The physical properties requisite to make
                    useful wire are possessed by only a limited number of metals and metallic
                    alloys. The metals must in the first place be ductile; and, further, the wire
                    when drawn out <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n652/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0652-0615"/> must possess a certain amount of tenacity, the
                    quality on which the utility of wire principally depends. The metals suitable
                    for wire, possessing almost equal ductility, are platinum, silver, iron, copper,
                    and gold; and it is only from these and certain of their alloys with other
                    metals, principally brass and bronze, that wire is prepared. By careful
                    treatment wire of excessive tenuity can be produced. Dr Wollaston first
                    succeeded in drawing a platinum wire ∙ <hi rend="subscript"> 3lι</hi> ⅞ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> oσ</hi> inch in diameter by encasing a fine platinum wire
                    within silver to ten times its diameter. The cored wire he then reduced to ∙ <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 57</hi> ⅛- <hi rend="subscript"> σ</hi> ∙ inch, and by
                    dissolving away the silver coating the platinum wire <hi rend="italic smallcaps"
                    > -</hi><hi rend="italic subscript smallcaps"> s</hi><hi rend="italic
                    smallcaps"> ^s⅛wq</hi> ineh thick only remained. By continued treatment in this
                    way wires of platinum used for spider-lines of telescopes are now obtained of
                    such extreme tenuity that a mile length of the wire weighs not more than a
                    grain; and it is said that platinum wire has been made which measures not more
                    than <hi rend="subscript"> a 0</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 0 0</hi> mm., equal to less than the fifty-thousandth part of
                    an inch. The accompanying table shows the comparative tenacity of the wire of
                    metals and metallic alloys.</p>
                <p>Wire was originally made by beating the metal out into plates, which were then
                    cut into continuous strips, and afterwards rounded by beating. The art of
                    wire-drawing does not appear to have been known till the 14th century, and it
                    was not introduced into England before the second half of the 17th century. Wire
                    is usually drawn of cylindrical form; but it may be made of any desired section
                    by varying the outline of the holes in the draw-plate through which it is passed
                    in the process of manufacture. The draw-plate is a disk of hard steel pierced
                    with a series of holes corresponding in aperture with the size and section of
                    the wire to be made. The holes are funnel-shaped, being widest at the side where
                    the metal enters, and tapering to their small diameter at the face where the
                    wire is drawn away. The excessive friction, which is partly relieved by
                    lubricants, causes a rapid enlargement of the holes; and where great uniformity
                    of size is required, as in the case of fine gold, silver, and platinum wire,
                    perforated rubies or similar hard stones are fitted in the draw-plate. The
                    draw-plate is mounted in the draw-bench, which is provided with a reel on which
                    the wire is wound, and in drawing down to smaller dimensions it passes through
                    successive smaller holes in the draw-plate—one at a time—and is wound on another
                    reel or frame on the bench. During the drawing the wire requires to be annealed
                    more or less frequently according to the nature of the metal under treatment.
                    The ductility of the metal and the diameter of the wire operated on determine
                    the rapidity with which the wire can be drawn: iron and brass travel at rates
                    varying from 12 to 45 inches per second, while gold and silver wires of fine
                    section may be drawn through at 60 to 70 inches per second. Stout iron wire down
                    to a section of ∣ inch or thereby is made by rolling bars of fine fibrous metal
                    in a rolling mill, in the same way as nail rods, small bars, and angles are
                    rolled. The thinner wires are drawn from these stout wires by the ordinary
                    process of drawing. Iron requires repeated annealing in the process of
                    attenuation, and to preserve it from oxidation it is treated with a scour-bath,
                    consisting of dilute sulphuric acid and a proportion of sulphate of copper. The
                    minute film of copper thus deposited on the wire not only prevents oxidation,
                    but also favours the drawing by lessening the friction in passing through the
                    draw-plate. Much of the iron wire which is to be used in exposed situations is
                    further protected from oxidation by a covering of zinc in the so-called
                    galvanizing process.</p>
                <p>In commerce the sizes of wire are estimated by certain more or less recognized
                    standard wire gauges. The most commonly quoted is the Birmingham wire gauge. It
                    gives forty measurements, which bear no definite relation to each other, ranging
                    from the largest No. 0000=‘454 inch to No. 36=‘004 inch. Sir Joseph Whitworth in
                    1857 proposed a standard wire gauge which is coming to be generally recognized.
                    His measurements range from half an inch to one-thousandth of an inch by regular
                    gradations of one-thousandth. Beginning at the smallest, No. 1 is <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> 001 inch, 2= 002 inch, 10= ’ 010 inch, and so on,
                    larger breaks being made in the scale as the size increases, but the number and
                    ratio continuing the same till it ends at No. 500= <hi rend="superscript">
                    -</hi> 500 inch. In America a standard wire gauge, proposed in 1864 by Messrs
                    Brown and Sharpe, of Providence, R.I., is now extensively recognized. In it the
                    gradations are uniform, increasing in geometric ratio, so that the size of each
                    successive number is found by multiplying the preceding by</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Diameter.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Strain.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Gold 1</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•0162 inches.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>5∙61- 542 lb</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Platinum i</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0161 „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>6∙70- 659 ,,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Silver</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•0157 „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>7∙86- 7·78 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Copper</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•0177 „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10∙11-10∙20 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Iron</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•0169 „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>H∙12-10∙89 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Copper</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•0605 „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2331b</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Brass</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>•0640 „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>203 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Steel ...„</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0600 „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>342 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Phosphor Bronze</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Ό630 „</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>394 „</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>1 ’ 123. The standard is calculated from wire No. 36, which in the American gauge
                    represents a diameter of ’ 005, while in the Birmingham gauge No. 36 is equal to
                    ’ 004 inch.</p>
                <p>It must be obvious that the uses of wire are multifarious and diverse beyond all
                    enumeration. It forms the raw material of important manufactures, such as the
                    wire-net industry, wire-cloth making, and wire-rope spinning, in which it
                    occupies a place analogous to a textile fibre. Wire-cloth of all degrees of
                    strength and fineness of mesh is used for sifting and screening machinery, for
                    draining paper pulp, for window screens, and for many other purposes. Vast
                    quantities of copper and iron wire are employed for telegraph and telephone
                    wires and cables, and as conductors in electric lighting. It is in no less
                    demand for fencing, and much is consumed in the construction of suspension
                    bridges, and cages, &amp;c. In the manufacture of stringed musical instruments
                    and philosophical apparatus wire is again largely used. Among its other sources
                    of consumption it is sufficient to mention pin and hair-pin making, the needle
                    and fish-hook industries, nail, peg, and rivet making, and carding machinery;
                    but indeed there are few industries into which wire does not more or less
                    enter.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
