<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0592-0557-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WICKLOW (9th edition, volume 24, page 557)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914304">Episcopalians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075567">Presbyterians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075562">Presbyterianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163841">Valleys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n592/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WICKLOW</label>, a maritime county of Ireland, in the
                    province of Leinster, is bounded on the E. by St George’s Channel, N. by the
                    county of Dublin, S. by Wexford, and W. by Carlow and detached portions of
                    Kildare. The area is 500,178 acres or about 781 square miles.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Physical Features.—</hi> The coast is precipitous and
                    picturesque, but very dangerous of approach owing to sandbanks. There are no
                    inlets that can be properly termed bays. The harbour at Wicklow has lately been
                    improved; but that of Arklow is suitable only for small vessels. To the north of
                    the town of Wicklow there is a remarkable shingle beach, partly piled up by the
                    waves and currents. The central portion of the county is occupied by a granite
                    mountain range, forming one of the four principal mountain groups of Ireland.
                    The direction of the range is from north-east to south-west, and the highest
                    elevations are generally attained along the central line. The range consists of
                    long sweeping moorlands, rising occasionally by precipitous escarpments into
                    culminating points, tlιe highest summits being Kippure (2473 feet), Duff Hill
                    (2369), Douce Hill (2384), and Lugnaquilla (3039). The range rises from the
                    north by a succession of ridges intersected by deep glens, and subsides towards
                    the borders of Wexford and Carlow. Though the range is metamorphic, it is also
                    in part intrusive, and its formation has been accompanied by a considerable
                    elevation of Silurian rocks, beyond which it does not penetrate, notwithstanding
                    that the Cambrian rocks occupy a large tract along the sea coast. In the valleys
                    there are many instances of old river terraces, the more remarkable being those
                    at the lower end of Glenmalure and the lower end of Glendalough. It is in its
                    deep glens that much of the peculiar charm of Wicklow scenery is to be found,
                    the frequently rugged natural features contrasting finely with the rich and
                    luxuriant foliage of the extensive woods which line their banks. Among the more
                    famous of these glens are the Dargle, Glencree, Glen of the Downs, Devil’s Glen,
                    Glenmalure, Glen of Ismail, and the beautiful vale of Ovoca. The eastern
                    districts of the county are occupied by clay slate or quartzite, the latter of
                    which presents frequently a smooth polished surface and shows indications of
                    Glacial erosion. Evidences of Glacial action also appear in the moraines of
                    Glenmalure and Glendalough. The principal rivers are the Liffey, on the
                    north-western border; the Vartry, which passes through Devil’s Glen to the sea
                    north of Wicklow Head; the Avonmore and the Avonbeg, which unite at the “meeting
                    of the waters” to form the Ovoca, which is afterwards joined by the Aughrim and
                    falls into the sea at Arklow; and the Slaney, in the west of the county, passing
                    southwards into Carlow. There are a number of small but romantic lakes in the
                    valleys, the principal being Loughs Dan, Bray, and Tay or Luggelaw, and the
                    loughs of Glendalough.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Minerals.—</hi> Lead is raised at Lugganure (near Rathdrum),
                    the principal lead mine in Ireland. In 1796 gold was discovered near Croghan
                    Kinshela, but not in quantities to render working remunerative. Auriferous
                    silver occurs in the slaty strata. There are important copper mines at Ovoca,
                    where sulphur and iron are also dug. Slates for roofing are quarried at
                    Dunganstown and elsewhere. Limestone, limestone gravel, and marl are obtained
                    near the sea and in the river valleys.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Agriculture.—</hi> According to the latest landowners’ return,
                    Wicklow was divided among 1041 proprietors, possessing 497,656 acres, at an
                    annual valuation of £254,800, or about 10s. 2gd. per acre. There were also about
                    2500 acres of waste land. Of the proprietors 534, or rather more than a half,
                    possessed less than 1 acre each. The following possessed over 8000 acres each
                    :—William Kemmis, 8042; J. S. Moore, 8731; R. A. G. Cunninghame, 10,479; earl of
                    Meath, 14,718; marquis of Downshire, 15,766; earl of Carysfort, 16,292; J.
                    Mandeville Hugo, 17,937; earl of Wicklow, 22,104; marquis of Waterford, 26,035;
                    Viscount Powerscourt, 36,693; and earl Fitzwilliam, 89,891. The climate near the
                    sea is remarkably mild, and permits the myrtle and arbutus to grow. The land in
                    the lower grounds is fertile; and, although the greater part of the higher
                    districts is covered with heath and turf, it affords good pasturage for sheep.
                    There is a considerable extent of natural timber, as well as artificial
                    plantations. Out of a total area of 499,894 acres in 1886 105,642 or 21 1 per
                    cent, were under crops, 234,890 or 47 per cent, under grass, 175 acres fallow,
                    19,479 or 3 ’ 9 per cent, woods and plantations, 29,028 or 5'8 per cent, bog and
                    marsh, 94,347 or 18 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 9 per cent, barren mountain
                    land, and 16,333 or 3 ’ 3 per cent, water, roads, fences, &amp;c. The total
                    number of holdings in 1886 was only 8072 and their size is much above the
                    average for Ireland, 70 being above 500 acres in extent, 973 between 100 and 500
                    acres, 2615 between 30 and 100 acres, 2646 between 5 and 30 acres, 855 between 1
                    and 5 acres, and 913 not exceeding 1 acre each. Between 1849 and 1886 the area
                    under crops decreased from 126,251 to 105,642 acres; but within the last ten
                    years the decrease was not so marked, the area in 1876 being 111, 488 acres. The
                    area under meadow and clover has been gradually increasing: in 1849 it was
                    50,793 acres, and, while in 1876 it was 60,086 acres, in 1886 it was 60,390. The
                    area under green crops shows very slight fluctuations: in 1849 it was 18,837 and
                    in 1886 it was 18,114. Potatoes and turnips, which occupied respectively 10,847
                    and 5304 acres in 1886, have not perceptibly altered in the proportions of the
                    areas. The decrease in the area under corn crops has, on the other hand, been
                    remarkable; from 56,616 acres in 1849 it fell to 31,361 in 1876 and to 27,129 in
                    1886. The area under wheat in 1849 was 7817 acres, but between 1876 and 1886 it
                    decreased from 3639 to 814 acres. The area under oats has decreased from 44,527
                    acres in 1849 to 26,920 in 1876 and 25,344 in 1886; the area under barley, bere,
                    and other corn crops being in these years 4272,1480, and 971 acres respectively.
                    The number of horses in 1886 was 11,300 (of which 7206 were used for
                    agricultural purposes), asses 3465, mules 351, cattle 81,577 (of which 24,523
                    were milch cows), sheep 169,334, pigs 22,329, and goats 6278.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Communication.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> The Dublin,
                    Wicklow, and Wexford Railway skirts the coast from Bray to the town of Wicklow,
                    after which it bends westward to Rathdrum, and then passes by the vale of Ovoca
                    to Arklow. At Wooden Bridge a branch goes off south-westwards to Shillelagh.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures and Trade. —</hi> Except in the Ovoca district,
                    where the mining industry is of some importance, the occupations are chiefly
                    agricultural. The manufacture of flannel, which formerly gave employment to a
                    considerable number of people, is now in a very depressed condition. Herring and
                    round fish are caught off the coast, but these fisheries are much neglected.
                    There, is, however, a rather prosperous oyster fishery at Arklow. Of late years
                    the harbour at Wicklow has been improved, the bed of the river deepened, and a
                    steam-packet pier erected.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Administration and Population.—</hi> According to De Burgo <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> s estimate, the population of Wicklow in 1760
                    amounted to 43,872; the parliamentary census of 1812 placed it at 83,109; by
                    1821 it had increased to 110,767, and by 1841 to 126,143, but by 1861 it had
                    diminished to 86,451, by 1871 to 78,697, and by 1881 to 70,386 (males 35,101,
                    females 35,285). Roman Catholics in 1881 numbered 79 ’ 9 per cent, of the
                    population, Protestant Episcopalians 18 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 3 (an
                    unusually large proportion for the south of Ireland), Presbyterians 0 ’ 4,
                    Methodists Γ0, and other denominations 0 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 4. The
                    number of persons who could read and write numbered 57 ’ 4 of the population,
                    able to read only 12 ’ 8 per cent., illiterate 29 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi>
                    8. There were none who could speak Irish only, and the number who could speak
                    Irish and English was 243. Wicklow, which formerly returned two members to
                    parliament, was ⅛ 1885 formed into two parliamentary divisions, an eastern and
                    awestern, each returning one member. The principal towns are part of Bray
                    (4387), a fashionable watering-place, the other part (2148) being in Dublin;
                    Wicklow (3391), the county town; and Arklow (4777), a fishingstation of some
                    importance. The county is divided into eight baronies and contains fifty-nine
                    parishes. According to the Protestant Episcopal arrangements, it is in the
                    dioceses of Dublin and Glendalough, with portions in those of Leighlin and
                    Ferns. It is in the home or Leinster circuit; and assizes are held at Wicklow
                    and quarter-sessions at Bray, Baltinglass, Tinahely, Arklow, and Wicklow. There
                    are ten petty sessions districts within the county, and portions of four others.
                    It includes two poor-law unions and portions of the unions of Naas, Rathdown,
                    and Shillelagh. It is in the Dublin military district.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities.—</hi> On the division of the district
                    of the Pale by King John into twelve counties Wicklow was included in Dublin
                    county. It was made a separate county by James I. in 1605. It sided with the
                    royal cause during the Cromwellian wars, but on Cromwell’s advance submitted to
                    him without striking a blow. During the rebellion of 1798 some of the insurgents
                    took refuge within its mountain fastnesses. An engagement took place <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n593/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0593-0558"/> between them and General Holt near Aughrim, which
                    was speedily decided in Holt’s favour; a second was fought at Arklow between
                    them and General Needham with a similar result. Of the ancient cromlechs there
                    are three of some interest, one near Enniskerry, another on the summit of
                    Lugnaquilla, and a third, with a druidical circle, at Donoughmore. There are
                    comparatively unimportant monastic remains at Rathdrum, Baltinglass, and
                    Wicklow. The ruins in the vale of Glendalough, known as the “seven churches,”
                    are, with the doubtful exception of Clonmacnoise, the most remarkable
                    ecclesiastical remains in Ireland. They owe their origin to St Kevin, who lived
                    in the vale as a hermit, and is reputed to have died on 3d June 618. On the site
                    of St Kevin’s cell an extensive monastic establishment was founded, and around
                    it a town sprang up, which was long famed as a seat of learning. The buildings
                    which constitute the “seven churches” are the round tower, one of the finest in
                    Ireland, 110 feet in height and 51 in circumference; St Kevin’s kitchen or
                    church, of which the nave, 25 feet by 15, with a curious high-pitched roof and a
                    round belfry (supposed to be the earliest example of a round belfry springing
                    from the roof or gable), still remains; a structure within the cemetery called
                    the cathedral, in a state of great dilapidation, but from its position and
                    dimensions seemingly well entitled to its name; the lady chapel, chiefly
                    remarkable for its doorway of wrought granite, in a style of architecture allied
                    to the Greek; Trinity church, consisting of nave (29 feet 6 inches by 17 feet 6
                    inches), chancel (13 feet 6 inches by 9 feet), and a basement story, and
                    presenting some of the finest characteristics of the ancient architecture of
                    Ireland, including a very beautiful specimen of the square-headed doorway; the
                    monastery, or St Saviour’s abbey, with peculiar ornamental sculpture, and
                    supposed to contain the tomb of St Kevin; and the Refeart or cemetery church. In
                    the cemetery and all along the valley there are a large number of monuments and
                    stone crosses of various size and style. The cave known as St Kevin’s bed shows
                    evidence of having been artificially constructed, but is probably only an
                    enlarged natural cavity. Of the old fortalices or strongholds associated with
                    the early wars those of special interest are Black Castle, near Wicklow,
                    originally founded by the Norse invaders, but taken by the Irish in 1301, and
                    afterwards rebuilt by William FitzWilliam; the scattered remains of Castle
                    Kevin, the ancient stronghold of the O’Tooles, by whom it was probably
                    originally built in the 12th century; and the ruins of the old castle of the
                    Ormondes at Arklow, founded by Theobald FitzWalter (died 1285), the scene of
                    frequent conflicts up to the time of Cromwell, by whom it was demolished in
                    1649, and now containing within the interior of its ruined walls a constabulary
                    barrack. The fine mansion of Powerscourt occupies the site of an old fortalice
                    founded by De la Poer, one of the knights who landed with Strongbow; in the
                    reign of Henry VIII. it was taken by the O’Tooles and O’Brynes. (T. F. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
