<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0574-0539-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WHEWELL, William (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    539)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w64d">Barrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825145">Bacon</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018631">Methodism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n574/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WHEWELL, <hi rend="smallcaps">William</hi></label>
                    (1794-1866), philosopher and historian of science, was born on 24th May 1794 at
                    Lancaster, where his father was a house-carpenter. He was educated at the blue
                    school and the grammar school of Lancaster, and afterwards at Heversham grammar
                    school, where he obtained the exhibition which enabled him to enter Trinity
                    College, Cambridge, in October 1812. For the remainder of his life his home was
                    within the walls of Trinity. He graduated as second wrangler in 1816, was
                    elected fellow in 1817, appointed a mathematical lecturer in the following year,
                    and in due course became one of the college tutors. From 1828 to 1832 he held
                    the professorship of mineralogy and from 1838 to 1855 that of moral philosophy,
                    or (as it was then called) moral theology and casuistical divinity. In 1841 he
                    was appointed master of the college on the resignation of Dr Wordsworth. He died
                    on 6th March 1866 from the effects of a fall from his horse.</p>
                <p>Soon after taking his degree Whewell began to lay the foundation of his
                    reputation by great and varied activity as an author, as well as by the
                    prominent part he took in all matters educational and constitutional concerning
                    the college and university. His first work, <hi rend="italic">An Elementary
                    Treatise on Mechanics</hi> (1819), was influential—along with the works of
                    Peacock and Herschel—in reforming the traditional method of mathematical
                    teaching in Cambridge; and it was also largely due to him that, at a later
                    period (1856), the circle of Cambridge studies was widened by the admission of
                    the moral and natural sciences to an academic position. On the other hand, his
                    attitude with respect to questions of university and college reform was
                    (especially in later life) conservative. Claiming to be a reformer, he had yet
                    no sympathy with the constitutional changes proposed at the time, and since
                    commonly accepted as desirable and necessary. He upheld strenuously the tutorial
                    system, while endeavouring to improve its efficiency; he opposed the admission
                    of Dissenters to the university in a controversy with Thirl wall (1834); he
                    defended the system of clerical fellowships, the custom which admitted a
                    privileged class of students under the name of “fellow-commoners,” and the large
                    powers which the “caput” or head of a college then possessed in university
                    government. The appointment of the University Commission in 1850 encountered his
                    opposition, and the proposed reform of the university in 1855 called forth from
                    him two pamphlets of hostile <hi rend="italic">Pemarks.</hi> The reform really
                    wanted was, he contended, to encourage scientific and professorial work, and to
                    utilize the college funds, not to put elections in the hands of the members of
                    senate.</p>
                <p>In the summer of 1826, and again in 1828, Whewell was engaged along with Airy in
                    conducting experiments in Dolcoath mine, Cornwall, in order to determine the
                    density of the earth. Their united labours were unsuccessful, and Whewell did
                    little more in the way of experimental science. He was the author, however, of
                    an <hi rend="italic">Essay on Mineralogical Classification,</hi> published in
                    1828, and contributed various memoirs on the tides to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Philosophic,al Transactions</hi> of the Royal Society between 1833 and 1850.
                    But it is on his <hi rend="italic">History</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Philosophy
                    of the Sciences</hi> that his claim to an enduring reputation mainly rests. The
                    <hi rend="italic">History of the Inductive Sciences, from the Earliest to the
                    Present</hi><hi rend="italic">Time</hi> appeared originally in 1837. Whewell’s
                    wide acquaintance with various branches of science—though he cannot be said to
                    have been a specialist in any department —enabled him to write a comprehensive
                    account of their development, which has not yet been superseded, although it may
                    want the thoroughness, and even in many respects the accuracy, of various
                    subsequent histories of the special sciences. In his own opinion, moreover, the
                    <hi rend="italic">History</hi> was to be regarded as an introduction to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophy of the Inductive Sciences</hi> (1840). The latter
                    treatise<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Afterwards
                    broken up into three parts published separately: (1) the <hi rend="italic"
                    >History of Scientific Ideas</hi> (1858), substantially a reproduction of the
                    first part of the <hi rend="italic">Philosophy</hi>; (2) the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Novum</hi><hi rend="italic">Organum Renovatum</hi> (1858), containing the
                    second part of the same work, but without the historical review of opinions,
                    which was issued with large additions as (3) the <hi rend="italic">Philosophy of
                    Discovery</hi> (1860).</p></note> analyses the method exemplified in the
                    formation of ideas, in the new inductions of science, and in the applications
                    and systematization of these inductions, all exhibited by the <hi rend="italic"
                    >History</hi> in the process of development.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Philosophy</hi> is described by the author as “an
                    application of the plan of Bacon’s <hi rend="italic">Novum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Organum</hi> to the present condition of physical science,” and as an attempt
                    “to extract from the actual past progress of science the elements of a more
                    effectual and substantial method of discovery” than Bacon’s. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophy</hi> is divided into two parts, treating respectively
                    of ideas and of knowledge. The first part begins with an investigation of ideas
                    in general, analysing the fundamental nature of scientific truths, the grounds
                    of our knowledge of them, and the mental processes by which they are
                    ascertained, and then applies these general principles to the philosophy of each
                    of the subdivisions of science adopted in the <hi rend="italic">History.</hi>
                    The second part discusses knowledge or the construction of science, the
                    processes by which our conceptions are brought to bear on facts, binding them
                    together into ideal combinations. By the “explication of conceptions” the ideas
                    appropriate to particular classes of facts are brought forward and explained;
                    and by the “colligation of facts” the conceptions involving those ideas are
                    united to the facts for the construction of science. But no art of discovery,
                    such as Bacon anticipated, follows from the analysis of the method of scientific
                    discovery; for the elements of “invention, sagacity, genius,” are needed at each
                    forward step in scientific progress. At the same time Whewell claimed that the
                    methods exhibited in his analysis were, not only the methods by which
                    discoveries had actually been made, but also as definite and practical as any
                    that had been put forward. The process of induction (or colligation of
                    ascertained facts into general propositions) is analysed into three steps,—(1)
                    the selection of the (fundamental) idea, such as space, number, cause, or
                    likeness; (2) the formation of the conception, or more special modification of
                    those ideas, as a circle, a uniform force, &amp;c.; and (3) the determination of
                    magnitudes. Upon these follow special methods of induction applicable to
                    quantity, viz., the method of curves, the method of means, the method of least
                    squares, and the method of residues, and special methods depending on
                    resemblance (to which the transition is made through the law of continuity),
                    viz., the method of gradation and the method of natural classification.</p>
                <p>Whewell’s philosophy of science, as well as his ethical doctrine, was conditioned
                    by opposition to the empirical tendency then prevalent amongst English thinkers.
                    In this he was influenced by the results of the Kantian philosophy. He
                    maintained the distinction between necessary and contingent truths,—the former
                    involved in the innate constitution of the mind, the latter coming from
                    experience. It is on this reference to the mind of what the current English
                    philosophy attempted to derive from impressions of sense that the leading
                    positions of his philosophy depend, and on it hinges the controversy between
                    himself and J. S. Mill. He defended the <hi rend="italic">a priori</hi>
                    necessity of axioms attacked by the latter, and in his inductive theory
                    attributed more importance to the function of the mental idea in the colligation
                    of facts than Mill did, while he would have dispensed with the inductive methods
                    of Mill by his rules for the constructioií of conceptions.</p>
                <p>Between 1835 and 1861 Whewell was the author of various works on the philosophy
                    of morals and politics, the chief of which, <hi rend="italic">Elements of
                    Morality, including Polity,</hi> was published in 1845. The peculiarity of this
                    work—written, of course, from what is known as the intuitional point of view—is
                    its fivefold division of the springs of action and of their objects, of the
                    primary and universal rights of man (personal security, property, contrast,
                    family rights, and government), and of the cardinal virtues (benevolence,
                    justice, truth, purity, and order). Among Whewell’s other works—too numerous to
                    mention—reference must be made to writings popular in their day, such as the
                    Bridgewater Treatise on <hi rend="italic">Astronomy</hi> (1833), and the essay,
                    <hi rend="italic">Of the Plurality of Worlds</hi> (1854), in which he argued <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n575/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0575-0540"/> against the probability of planetary life, and
                    also to the <hi rend="italic">Platonic Dialogues for English Readers</hi>
                    (1859-61), to the <hi rend="italic">Lectures on the History of Moral Philosophy
                    in England</hi> (1852), to the essay, <hi rend="italic">Of a Liberal Education
                    in General, with particular reference to the Leading Studies of the University
                    of Cambridge</hi> (1845), to the important edition and abridged translation of
                    Grotius, <hi rend="italic">De Jure Belli</hi><hi rend="italic">et Pacis</hi>
                    (1853), and to the edition of the <hi rend="italic">Mathematical Works</hi> of
                    Isaac Barrow (1860).</p>
                <p>Full bibliographical details are given by Isaac Todhunter, <hi rend="italic">W.
                    WΙιewell: αη Account of h is Writings,</hi> 2 vols. (1876). The <hi
                    rend="italic">Life of W. Wħewell</hi> has been written by Mrs Stair Douglas
                    (1881).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
