<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0597-0552-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NORRIS, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 552</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1091272">Reason</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1091282">Reasoning</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xg9fj36">Platonists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n597/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NORRIS, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1657-1711),
                    the disciple of Plato and Malebranche, was born in 1657 at
                    Collingbourne-Kingston in Wiltshire, where his father was then incumbent. He was
                    educated at Winchester School, and entered at Exeter College, Oxford, in 1676.
                    In 1680 he took his degree and was elected to a fellowship at All Souls’
                    College. He first made himself known in the university, Anthony Wood tells us,
                    by a translation of Robert Waryng’s philosophical poem, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Effigies</hi><hi rend="italic">Amoris,</hi> entitled <hi rend="italic">The
                    Picture of Love Unveiled.</hi> This appeared in 1682, and was followed in 1683
                    by his first original work, <hi rend="italic">An Idea of Happiness.</hi> With
                    Plato, he places the highest happiness or fruition of the soul in the
                    contemplative love of God— <hi rend="superscript"> ti</hi> that primitive and
                    original Beauty, Perfection, and Harmony.” Norris’s poems, mostly composed about
                    this time, are, in the main, expressions of his habitual mood of devout but
                    somewhat abstract contemplation. They have little poetic richness, but their
                    grave style is often not without impressiveness, and works itself out at
                    intervals into a felicitous stanza or a memorable line. A few pieces (such, for
                    instance, as <hi rend="italic">The Parting}</hi> might claim even a higher
                    praise. The poems appeared in 1684 as the first part of a volume of <hi
                    rend="italic">Poems and Discourses occasionally written.</hi> Three years later
                    a new and enlarged edition was published with the title, <hi rend="italic">A
                    Collection of Miscellanies·,</hi> and in this form the volume was popular enough
                    to go through nine editions. In the midst of these graver productions Norris
                    found leisure to give vent to his hereditary Tory and High-Church feeling in a
                    satire on the Whigs and a Latin tractate aimed at the Calvinistic dissenters.
                    All through his life his intense intellectual activity seemed to make it almost
                    a necessity for him to mingle in whatever controversy was going on. But
                    philosophy and philosophical theology formed his central interest. Malebranche’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Recherche</hi><hi rend="italic">de la Vérité,</hi> which had
                    appeared in 1674, made an easy conquest of the Oxford fellow, to whom its
                    doctrine appeared no more than the consistent and clarified modern expression of
                    that Platonized Christianity which met him alike in St John, in Plotinus, and in
                    Augustine, the father whom he “loved to speak after.” Perhaps it would be more
                    correct to say that Norris reads his favourite authors in the light of the
                    theory derived from Malebranche. It is at least doubtful whether he would have
                    reached any definiteness of philosophic theory for himself without the aid of
                    the French thinker. He makes no secret of his discipleship. Malebranche, he
                    says, “is indeed the great Galileo of the intellectual world. He has given us
                    the point of view, and. whatever further detections are made, it must be through
                    his telescope.” Norris’s readings in modern philosophy were not confined,
                    however, to Malebranche; he had studied the works of Descartes himself, and most
                    of what had been written for and against Cartesianism on the Continent. Of
                    English thinkers, More and Cudworth, the so-called Cambridge Platonists, had
                    influenced him most; and in 1685 his study of their works had ripened into a
                    correspondence with the former. After More’s death Norris published the
                    correspondence between them as an appendix to his Platonically conceived essay
                    on <hi rend="italic">The Theory and Regulation of Love</hi> (1688).</p>
                <p>Some time before this Norris had taken orders, and in 1689, on being presented to
                    the living of Newton St Loe, in Somersetshire, he married, and resigned his
                    fellowship. In the same year he published <hi rend="italic">Reason and
                    Religion,</hi> the first of his riper works. The <hi rend="italic">Reflections
                    upon the Conduct of Human Life,</hi> which he wrote (also in 1689) “by way of
                    letter to an excellent lady, the Lady Masham,” did not advance his interests in
                    that quarter; for the lady, whose eyes were only weak, was nettled at being set
                    down in the preface as blind. In 1690 Norris published a volume of <hi
                    rend="italic">Discourses upon the Beatitudes,</hi> which proved decidedly
                    popular, and induced the author to follow it up by three more volumes of <hi
                    rend="italic">Practical Discourses</hi> between 1690 and 1698. The year 1690 is
                    memorable as the year of the publication of Locke’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Essay,</hi> and the book came into Norris’s hands just as his volume of <hi
                    rend="italic">Discourses</hi> was passing through the press. He at once
                    appreciated its importance, but its whole temper was alien from the modes of
                    thought in which he had been reared, and its main conclusions moved him to keen
                    dissent. He hastened to “review” it in an appendix to his sermons. These <hi
                    rend="italic">Cursory Reflections</hi> constitute Norris the first critic of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Essay,</hi> and they anticipate some of the arguments that
                    have since been persistently urged against Locke from the transcendental side.
                    Though holding to the “grey-headed, venerable doctrine” of innate ideas as
                    little as Locke himself, Norris finds the criticism in the first book of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Essay</hi> entirely inconclusive, and points out its inconsistency
                    with Locke’s own doctrine of evident or intuitively perceived truths. He also
                    suggests the possibility of subconscious ideation, on which Leibnitz laid so
                    much stress in the same connexion. He next complains that Locke neglects to tell
                    us “what kind of things these ideas are which are let in at the gate of the
                    senses.” In other words, while giving a metaphorical account of how we come by
                    our ideas, Locke leaves unconsidered the intellectual nature of the ideas or of
                    thought in itself. Unless we come to some conclusion on this point, Norris
                    argues, we have little chance of being right in our theory of how ideas “come to
                    be united to our mind.” He also puts his finger upon the weakness <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n598/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0598-0553"/> of Locke’s doctrine of nominal essences, showing
                    how it ignores the relation of the human mind to objective truth, and instancing
                    mathematical figures as a case “where the nominal essence and the real essence
                    are all one.”</p>
                <p>In 1691 Norris was transferred to Bemerton, a pleasant rural charge near
                    Salisbury, where George Herbert had been parish priest in the earlier part of
                    the century. A few miles distant is Langford Magna, where from 170-4 onwards
                    Norris had a congenial metaphysical neighbour in the person of Arthur Collier,
                    the future author of <hi rend="italic">Clavis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Universalis.</hi> The remaining twenty years of Norris’s life were spent at
                    Bemerton, the flight of time marked only by the works that still came in rapid
                    succession from his pen. In 1691-92 he was engaged in controversy with his old
                    enemies the “Separatists,” and with the Quakers, his Malebranchian theory of the
                    divine illumination having been confounded by some with the Quaker doctrine of
                    the light within. In 1697 he wrote <hi rend="italic">An Account of Reason and
                    Faith,</hi> one of the best of the many answers to Toland’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Christianity not Mysterious.</hi> Norris adopts the distinction between things
                    contrary to reason and things above reason, and maintains that the human mind is
                    not the measure of truth. In 1701 appeared the first volume of the systematic
                    philosophical work by which he is remembered, <hi rend="italic">An Essay towards
                    the Theory of the Ideal or Intelligible World.</hi> The first volume treats the
                    intelligible world absolutely; the second, which appeared in 1704, considers it
                    in relation to human understanding. In 1708 Norris wrote J. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Philosophical Discourse concerning the Natural Immortality of the Soul,</hi>
                    defending that doctrine against the assaults of Dodwell. But after the
                    completion of his <hi rend="italic">magnum opus</hi> his appearances in print
                    became less frequent. His health was not robust, and perhaps he was a little
                    disappointed at his failure to reach the larger public. Norris died in 1711 at
                    the comparatively early age of 54.</p>
                <p>It will hardly be claimed for Norris that he was either an original thinker or a
                    master of style. As Molyneux writes to Locke, he is “overrun with Malebranche
                    and Plato his philosophy is hardly more than an English version of Malebranche,
                    enriched by wide reading of “Platonic” thinkers of every age and country. His
                    style is too scholastic and self-involved. Nevertheless he was an acute and
                    strenuous thinker. His <hi rend="italic">Theory of the Intelligible World</hi>
                    is an attempt to explain the objective nature of truth, which he blamed Locke
                    for leaving out of regard. By the intelligible world Norris understands the
                    system of ideas eternally existent in the mind of God, according to which the
                    material creation was formed. This ideal system he identifies with the Logos—the
                    second person of the Trinity, the light that lighteth every man that cometh into
                    the world. For it is these ideas and their relations that are alone the
                    object-matter of science; whenever we know, it is because they are present to
                    our mind; or, as Malebranche says, we see all things in God. Material things are
                    wholly dark to us, except so far as the fact of their existence is revealed in
                    sensation. The matter which we say that we know is the idea of matter, and
                    belongs, like other ideas, to the intelligible world. When stripped of its
                    semi-mythical form of statement, Norris’s emphatic assertion of the ideal nature
                    of thought and its complete distinction from sense as such may be seen to
                    contain an important truth. He stands somewhat aside from the main course of
                    English philosophical thought. But, as the disciple and correspondent of More,
                    he is, in a sense, the heir of the Cambridge Platonists, while, as the first
                    critic of Locke’s <hi rend="italic">Essay,</hi> he may be said to open the
                    protest of the church against the implicit tendencies of that work. He occupies
                    a place, therefore, in the succession of churchly and mystical thinkers of whom
                    Coleridge is the last eminent example. (A. SE. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
