<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0576-0533-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NONCONFORMITY, Law relating to</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 533</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gf8v">Quakers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bg0t">Worship</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1181450">Worship</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1084913">Quakers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n576/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NONCONFORMITY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Law relating
                    to</hi></label>. The history of the gradual relief of nonconformists in England
                    from their disabilities will be found under <hi rend="smallcaps">England,</hi>
                    and under the heads of the various denominations, <hi rend="italic"
                    >e.g.,</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Baptists, Independents, Methodism, Quakers,
                    &amp;c.</hi> See also <hi rend="smallcaps">Oaths.</hi> It is proposed here to
                    note simply the present legal aspects of nonconformity apart from its history,
                    that is, the matters in which the law as to nonconformists still differs from
                    that applicable to members of the Church of England. The differences may be
                    conveniently grouped under six heads.</p>
                <p>(1) <hi rend="italic">Judicial notice.</hi> The courts, both temporal and
                    spiritual, take judicial notice of the tenets and authorities of the Church of
                    England, the crown being head of the law and of the church. Where the tenets and
                    authorities of a nonconformist body come in question, they must be proved by
                    evidence. By Lord Lyndhurst’s Act, 7 and 8 Vict., c. 45, where no particular
                    religious doctrine or mode of worship has been prescribed by the deed or
                    instrument of trust the usage of the congregation for twenty-five years is to be
                    taken as conclusive evidence of the doctrine and worship which may be properly
                    observed in such meeting-houses. (2) <hi rend="italic">Tribunal.</hi> Offences
                    against the law ecclesiastical (not being crimes) committed by clergy of the
                    Church of England as a rule come by letters of request from the bishop of the
                    diocese before the Arches Court of Canterbury or the Chancery Court of York (of
                    both of which the same person is now judge). Similar matters arising in
                    nonconformist bodies can only be tried by the ordinary secular courts, and
                    generally depend upon the question whether a minister has done any act which is
                    not in accordance with the rules governing the particular body of which he is a
                    minister. A nonconformist body is in law nothing more than a voluntary
                    association, whose members may enforce discipline by any tribunal assented to by
                    them, but must be subject in the last degree to the courts of the realm.
                    Brawling in a church by a person in holy orders is an offence within the Church
                    Discipline Act, 3 and 4 Vict., c. 86, and falls under the cognizance of the
                    spiritual courts; similar conduct by a nonconformist minister in his own place
                    of worship can only be punished as an offence under 9 and 10 Vict., c. 59. (3)
                    <hi rend="italic">Status of ministers.</hi> A nonconformist minister is not in
                    holy orders, and his chapel is not a consecrated building. His status is,
                    however, recognized to a limited extent. By the Toleration Act, 1 Will, and Μ.,
                    c. 18, a minister, preacher, or teacher of a nonconformist congregation is
                    exempt from certain parochial offices, as that of churchwarden. He is also
                    exempt from serving in the militia or on a jury. These privileges only attach
                    where the place of worship of which he is a minister has been duly registered,
                    18 and 19 Vict., c. 81, unless in the case of bodies subject to special
                    legislation, as Quakers. Registration is not required in the case of consecrated
                    buildings. By 45 and 46 Vict., c. 50, s. 12, a nonconformist minister cannot be
                    elected an aiderman or councillor. He cannot take a degree in divinity at
                    Oxford, Cambridge, or Durham, 34 and 35 Vict., c. 26, and so is debarred from
                    holding any professorship of divinity in those universities. (4) <hi
                    rend="italic">Marriage.</hi> Marriage by a person in holy orders was probably
                    necessary at common law, at any rate from the Reformation up to 1836. (See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Marriage.)</hi> And from the date of Lord Hardwicke’s Marriage
                    Act, 26 Geo. II., c. 33 (1753), up to 1836 the ceremony must have been performed
                    in a consecrated building. The first Act of Parliament that relieved dissenters
                    (other than Jews and Quakers) from these restrictions was the Marriage Act of
                    1836, 6 and 7 Will. IV., c. 85. Since that Act the ceremony of marriage may be
                    performed in a nonconformist place of worship, but it must be after due notice
                    to the superintendent registrar and in his presence or in that of a registrar,
                    and the building must be one that is duly certified for marriages. These
                    preliminaries (except the first, and that only where the marriage is not by
                    banns, licence, or special licence) are not necessary where the marriage takes
                    place in a church. Marriage by banns, licence, or special licence cannot take
                    place except in a church. (5) <hi rend="italic">Burial.</hi> By the Burial Laws
                    Amendment Act, 1880, 43 and 44 Vict., c. 41, burial may take place in a
                    churchyard without the rites of the Church of England. But in such a case notice
                    must be given in a specified form, which is unnecessary where the burial service
                    is conducted by a clergyman of the Church of England. (6) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Parish offices.</hi> By 1 Will, and Μ., c. 18, s. 5, a dissenter chosen
                    churchwarden and scrupling to take the oaths may execute his office by deputy.
                    His acceptance of office is made optional by the Act; there is nothing to
                    prevent his discharging it if he see fit to do so. This seems to be still the
                    law, although a declaration was substituted for the oath by 5 and 6 Will IV., c.
                    62, s. 9.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">The Colonies.—</hi> In crown colonies ecclesiastical
                    jurisdiction may be conferred by the sole authority of the crown. In colonies
                    which have parliamentary representation the crown cannot give to a metropolitan
                    bishop jurisdiction or coercive legal authority over suffragan bishops or over
                    any other person. In colonies of the former kind the Church of England may still
                    preserve the privileges which attach to her in the mother country; in colonies
                    of the latter kind she is in the same position as any other religious body,
                    simply a voluntary association. Since the Irish Church Act, 1869, 32 and 33
                    Vict., c. 42, the Church of Ireland has been practically in the same position as
                    the Church of England in colonies which have representative government.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
