<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0250-0239-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NATAL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 239</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4m03xx9x">Boers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n250/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NATAL</label>, a British colony on the south-east coast of
                    Africa, situated nearly between 29° and 31° S. lat. and 29° and 32° E. long., is
                    bounded on the N.E. by Zululand and the Transvaal, on the S.E. by the Indian
                    Ocean, on the N.W. by the Orange Free State and the Transvaal, and on the S.W.
                    by Basutoland, Griqualand East, and the country of the Pondas. It is of an
                    irregular diam&lt;md shape, with a length of about 270 miles from north to
                    south, and a breadth of 170 miles from east to west. The extent of sea-coast is
                    about 150 miles, and its area is about 17,000 square miles, or 11,000,000 acres
                    (one-third of the size of England).</p>
                <p>For several miles northward from the Bluff at Durban the coast is low, but well
                    wooded, and broken in several places by the mouths of rivers and streams; to the
                    south of the Bluff it is of moderate elevation near the sea, the hills rising
                    inland to a considerable height. Rich in verdure, and in the wet season clothed
                    with bright green grass and clumps of trees and bushes, and diversified by
                    numerous streams, the landscape indicates a country of great fertility of soil.
                    From the coast to the western boundary of the colony the land rises by terraces
                    or plateaus to an elevation of at least 4000 feet above the sea-level. For about
                    15 miles inland it is broken and hilly, and thickly covered with long grass, and
                    in some parts studded with jungly bush and clumps of palm, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n251/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0251-0240"/> euphorbia, and mimosa. For some 30 miles farther
                    inland the more elevated but less broken land loses all tropical character, and
                    presents large tracts of good pasturage, but with scarcely any bush or wood.
                    Beyond this district, at an ever-increasing elevation, the country, still hilly
                    and undulating, opens out in many places into more extensive grass plains,
                    generally denuded of bush or wood, although in some localities and in the
                    “kloofs” with a south-eastern aspect are dense clumps of forest trees netted
                    over in many instances with ferns; the western boundary of these rising lands is
                    the Drakensberg mountain-range, which has an altitude of some 3000 or 4000 feet
                    above the country at its base, and an absolute maximum altitude of 10,350 feet
                    above sea-level. Apart from the Drakensberg range, the country, though hilly and
                    much broken, has no mountains of note; many large hills, however, with flattened
                    tops (table mountains) stand out singularly high above the surrounding country,
                    presenting a peculiar appearance to one unaccustomed to South-African
                    scenery.</p>
                <p>The colony is well watered throughout, but none of the streams are navigable, and
                    all have bars at their entrances; attempts are being made to form harbours at
                    the mouths of the Umkomanzi and the Umzimkulu to the south of Durban. The
                    Umgeni, about 12 miles from Pietermaritzburg, has a sheer fall of about 360
                    feet, and when it is flooded the rush of its waters is a magnificent spectacle.
                    The harbour or port of Natal at Durban (strictly D’Urban), the only natural one
                    in the colony, consists of an outer bay or roadstead, which has a fair
                    anchorage, and an inner bay; at the entrance of the latter is a deepwater
                    channel, where ships of large tonnage can be safely moored, but a sand bar at
                    its entrance restricts the passage of large ships to the highest tides, and in
                    rough weather renders communication with the outer bay quite impracticable. This
                    bar varies constantly throughout the year, and probably is influenced by the
                    Agulhas stream and other oceanic currents. Much money has been spent on works
                    for the removal of the bar, without any good result, but other plans are now
                    being adopted, with every hope of success. When this obstacle is removed Natal
                    will possess one of the best harbours on the south-east coast of Africa.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Climate.—</hi> The summer or hot rainy season lasts from
                    October to March inclusive, and the six remaining months form the winter or cold
                    dry season. The following are the average temperatures for the three hottest and
                    three coldest months of the year, taken from observations at Durban,
                    Pietermaritzburg, and Byrne extending over ten years:—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Highest.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Lowest.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mean.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>December, January, and
                            February...</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>..' 97∙5</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>53 ∙3</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>7Γ2</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>June, July, and August</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>.. 83∙4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>31 ∙9</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>56 ∙7</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In the summer months cloudy afternoons with thunderstorms are frequent, and the
                    accompanying rains are very cool and refreshing. Within 30 miles of the coast
                    fires in dwellings are seldom required throughout the coldest months of the
                    year. The rainfall averages 33 ’ 50 inches; it is heaviest in the summer months,
                    but in June and July it frequently happens that there is no rain at all over a
                    large portion of the colony. From July to December the upper districts are
                    occasionally subject to hot winds, during which all vegetation droops as if
                    dying, and languor and depression affect all animal life; but these seldom reach
                    to within 20 miles of the coast. Violent hailstorms are not frequent, but
                    hailstones have occasionally killed fowls, dogs, and goats, and in some
                    instances have cut through iron roofing.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Geology.—</hi> Along the coast belt there are evidences of
                    comparatively recent upheaval. The high land of the colony rests on granite,
                    trap, and sandstone, the last of the Old Silurian type. Sandstone of a more
                    recent epoch, well suited for building purposes, is sometimes met with. As a
                    rule these fundamental rocks are found under thick beds of shale, the surface
                    being of the most varied description, and never of the same quality over any
                    very extensive area. The soil on the coast is mostly sandy loam, except where
                    the valleys have alluvial deposits from disintegrated shales and erupted rocks.
                    In the uplands the deep light, heavy black, and fine red loams are distributed
                    over beds of clay, ironstone, or granite in areas of varying extent. Ironstone
                    is to be met with in great quantities. Coal of several qualities exists in the
                    Klip River county, with seams varying from 4 to 10 feet in thickness; analysis
                    and experiment have shown it to be very suitable for locomotive and general
                    steam purposes. Some descriptions of it are well suited for gas, and nearly all
                    of it will make good household coal. The area of the available coal-field is
                    some 1350 square miles, and at a moderate computation the mines contain
                    2,000,000,000 tons of serviceable coal. In association with these seams of coal
                    very valuable iron ore has been discovered. Vast deposits of fine white and
                    yellow crystalline marbles have recently been found about 6 miles inland from
                    the mouth of the Umzimkulu river. Slight indications of copper have been met
                    with. In the extreme north are some mineral springs which have a temperature of
                    about 130° Fahr., and are considered to possess medicinal qualities.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Flora.—</hi> The chief forms of plants peculiar to Natal are
                    the liane and mimosa along the coast, and the orchid, aloe, pothos, liliaceous,
                    and fern forms in the upland districts. The heaths and proteads common at the
                    Cape of Good Hope are seldom if ever found in Natal, but almost any varieties of
                    the flora of semi-tropical and temperate countries that are introduced attain
                    perfection. The indigenous timber trees, mostly found in isolated clumps and in
                    somewhat inaccessible situations, are principally the yellow wood <hi
                    rend="italic">(Podocarpus elongatus),</hi> sneezewood <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Pteroxylon utile),</hi> stinkwood <hi rend="italic">(Oreodapħne</hi><pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n252/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0252-0241"/><hi rend="italic">bullata),</hi> black ironwood
                    <hi rend="italic">(Olea laurifolia),</hi> white ironwood <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Vepris</hi><hi rend="italic">lanceolata),</hi> and the mangrove <hi
                    rend="italic">(Rhizophora)</hi>; all are very useful woods, and the yellow wood,
                    sneezewood, stinkwood, and ironwood when polished have grain and colour equal to
                    maple, walnut, and ebony. The “rooibesje,” red pear, and milkwood trees are used
                    for boatbuilding. The Australian <hi rend="italic">Eucalyptus</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Casτcarina</hi> in great variety, and many other imported trees,
                    including syringas, wattles, acacias, willows, pines, cypress, cork, and oak all
                    thrive when properly planted and protected from grass fires.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fauna.—</hi> The herds of elephants which roamed in the coast
                    bushes in 1837 have disappeared, and the roar of the lion is no longer to be
                    heard in the uplands. The hippopotamus is very scarce, and nearly all, if not
                    all, the buffalo and quagga have crossed over into Zululand. Leopards or tigers
                    and tiger cats (all called by the natives “ingwe”), and hyaenas and wild dogs
                    <hi rend="italic">(Canis pictus'}</hi> of different species, are still found in
                    or about bush jungles and forest clumps; elands <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Antilope</hi><hi rend="italic">or</hi><hi rend="italic">cas}</hi> are
                    preserved on some estates, and there are at least ten distinct species of
                    antelope. Ant-eaters <hi rend="italic">( Orycteropus capensis),</hi> porcupines,
                    rock rabbits, hares, and cane rats are common in different localities. Baboons
                    <hi rend="italic">(Cynocephalus</hi><hi rend="italic">porcarius)</hi> and
                    monkeys of different kinds frequent the mountains and rocky kloofs and bush and
                    timber lands. The birds of Natal are of many species; some have beautiful
                    plumage, but none of them, with the exception of the canary, are to be
                    considered as songsters. The crocodile is to be found at the mouths of all
                    rivers, and for a certain distance inland from the sea. Of snakes there are
                    about forty distinct species or varieties. The most dreaded by the natives are
                    called “imamba,” of which there are at least eight different kinds; these snakes
                    elevate and throw themselves forward, and have been known to pursue a horseman.
                    One sort of imamba, named by the natives “indhlondhlo,” is crested, and its body
                    is of a bright flame colour. The sluggish puff-adder <hi rend="italic">(Clotho
                    arietans}</hi> is common and very dangerous. A hooded snake <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Naja haemachates),</hi> the “imfezi” of the natives, is dangerous, and spits
                    or ejects its poison; and besides this there are a few other varieties of the
                    cobra species. The largest of the serpent tribe, however, is the python <hi
                    rend="italic">(Hortulia natalensis},</hi> called “iuhlwati” by the natives; its
                    usual haunts are by streams amongst rocky boulders and in jungles, and instances
                    are recorded of its strangling and crushing adult natives. Insects abound in
                    great numbers, the most troublesome and destructive being the tick <hi
                    rend="italic">(Ixodes natalensis),</hi> which infests the pasturage, and the
                    white ant <hi rend="italic">(Termes</hi><hi rend="italic">mordax).</hi>
                    Occasionally vast armies of caterpillars make a sudden appearance and advance
                    over large tracts of country, devouring all vegetation in their line of march.
                    The fish moth, a steel-grey slimy active fish-shaped insect, is found in every
                    house, and is very destructive in the wardrobe and library. Fish of excellent
                    quality and in great quantities abound on the coast. Prawns, crayfish, and
                    oysters are also obtainable, and turtle <hi rend="italic">(Chelonia my das)</hi>
                    are frequently captured. Little attention, however, has been given to deep-sea
                    fishing, and the only fishermen are the coolies, who use nets along the beach.
                    The natives (Zulus) as a rule will not touch fish. Freshwater scale-fish are
                    mostly full of bones, but fine eels and barbel are plentiful in the rivers.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Agriculture.—</hi> The chief crop is maize, known in South
                    Africa as “meallies,” its grain constituting the principal food of about
                    seveneighths of the population. Maize, indeed, and Kaffre corn <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Sorghum Caffrorum),</hi> with pumpkins and sweet potatoes <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Convolvulus Batatas),</hi> “imphee” or “imfi” <hi rend="italic">(Sorghum
                    saccharatum),</hi> and tobacco are about the only crops raised by the natives.
                    The European farmers in the uplands, by irrigating the land in the winter
                    months, produce wheat of very fair quality, but not in sufficient quantity to
                    supply the demands of the colony. Oats, barley, and other grains grow readily;
                    and nearly all European vegetables yield fair crops in suitable localities.
                    Arrowroot succeeds well on the coast, and is an article of export. Some years
                    ago coffee and cotton had the attention of the planter, but both are now
                    neglected. Rice has been cultivated by some farmers, but not to any great
                    extent. Tobacco flourishes luxuriantly wherever there is good soil, but the
                    difficulties in the way of curing and manufacturing it prevent its being at
                    present an article of export. The cultivation and manufacture of sugar have
                    attracted most attention of late; sugar, indeed, with its products is the
                    principal staple produced in and exported from Natal. The capsicum for cayenne
                    pepper, and ground-nuts <hi rend="italic">(Arachis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >hypogaea)</hi> for oil, are also grown for exportation. Tea has been cultivated
                    of late by some few planters on the coast, and promises ere long to be grown on
                    a much larger scale. There are but few indigenous fruits, the principal being
                    the Natal orange (a species of <hi rend="italic">Strychnos},</hi> the Natal plum
                    or “amatungula” <hi rend="italic">(Arduinia</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >grandi·</hi><hi rend="italic">flora),</hi> the Kei apple <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Aberia caffra),</hi> Cape gooseberry <hi rend="italic">(Physalis</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">pubescens),</hi> and the Kaffre fig, the fruit of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Urostigma natalensis.</hi> Many subtropical fruits, however, and
                    fruits of European culture thrive well in Natal.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Stock.</hi> —Previous to 1855 large and numerous herds of
                    cattle pastured over the whole country, but in that year “lung-sickness,” an
                    epidemic of the nature of pleuro-pneumonia, broke out with great virulence, and
                    scarcely 4 per cent, of the animals attacked recovered. Lung-sickness and “red
                    water” still claim many victims annually, and are the constant dread of the
                    stock farmer. “Horse sickness,” a form of anthrax, is very fatal to horses,
                    especially in wet summers. The following figures give approximately the number
                    of the several kinds of stock belonging to Europeans and natives respectively
                    in</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Stock.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Europeans.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Natives.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Horned cattle</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>140,716</p><p>17,261</p><p>1,121</p><p>70,589</p><p>6,159</p><p>10,809</p><p>410,353</p><p>1,821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>379,569 15,915 <hi rend="italic">nil.
                            nil.</hi></p><p>166,477 5,554 600</p><p>24,509</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Horses</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Mules and donkeys</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Angora goats</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Other goats</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Pigs...7.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sheep (wool-bearing)</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Sheep (not wool-bearing)</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The cattle consist principally of the Zulu, Africander, and Fatherland breeds,
                    but recently some English shorthorns and other improved stock have been
                    introduced. Ostriches also are farmed for the sake of their feathers, but as yet
                    this industry has not succeeded so well in Natal as in the Cape Colony.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Commerce.—</hi> The staple productions of Natal have increased
                    with the introduction of the sugar-cane, and sugar and rum are the principal
                    articles of native produce exported. Wool, arrowroot, and feathers are also the
                    outcome of local industry, but the exports of greatest value and importance are
                    the wool and hides of the Transvaal and the Orange Free State, and feathers,
                    ivory, and skins from the interior, which are shipped at Durban. The value of
                    Natal sugar produced in 1856 was stated at £483, and in 1881 at £172,237. The
                    principal imports in 1882 (total value £2,213,538) were clothing, cotton and
                    woollen goods, haberdashery, leather manufactures, iron and ironmongery,
                    spirits, oilman’s stores, and flour, and the chief exports (£731,809) were wool,
                    sugar, hides, ostrich feathers, and Angora hair,—by far the greater part of the
                    imports (£1,784,345) and exports (£595,744) being received from and shipped for
                    the United Kingdom.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Revenue and Expenditure.—</hi> The increase in the revenue and
                    expenditure in thirty vears is shown as follows;—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Year.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Revenue.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Expenditure.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1852</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>£27,158</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>£24,876</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1862</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>98,086</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>83,886</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1872</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>180,498</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>132,978</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1882</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>496,783</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>489,113</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The revenue is principally derived from customs duties, native hut taxes,
                    transfer dues on land sales, and excise. The public debt of the colony on the
                    31st December 1882 was £2,101,500, with a sinking fund towards its redemption of
                    £153,597.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Roads and Telegraphs. —</hi> Until very recently all goods and
                    produce were conveyed in ox-waggons carrying from 3 to 5 tons weight. These had
                    to travel on roads sometimes little better than tracks worn by traffic, and
                    frequently impassable during wet weather; and for some years before the breaking
                    out of the Zulu War (1879) the average cost of carriage was as high as
                    eighteen-pence per ton per mile. Now, however, three lines of railway have been
                    opened,—one of 78 miles from the port at Durban to Pietermaritzburg, another
                    from Durban 20 miles north to Verulam through the sugar lands in that district,
                    and a third 7 miles southward to the sugar estates by the Isipingo river. These
                    alone have cost the colony about £1,250,000. An additional line, of 118 miles,
                    to cost about £1,180,000, is in process of construction from Pietermaritzburg to
                    Ladysmith, and will no doubt be at once carried on to connect with the railways
                    of the Orange Free State. The telegraph between Natal and the Cape Colony was
                    opened in 1878, and in the following year telegraphic communication by way of
                    Lorenzo Marques was extended to England. Branches of telegraph are also carried
                    direct from Natal into the Transvaal and the Orange Free State.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Government.—</hi> The colony was annexed as a district to the
                    Cape Colony in August 1845, but in November of the same year it was made a
                    separate government, to be administered by a lieutenant-governor under the
                    general control of the governor of the Cape Colony. At first the
                    lieutenant-governor and an assistant council of four chief officials formed the
                    executive, while the legislative council consisted of the lieutenant-governor
                    and three principal officers. In 1856 Natal became wholly independent of the
                    Cape, and the legislative council was made to consist of sixteen members, twelve
                    elective and four non-elective. In 1869 the lieutenant-governor was empowered to
                    nominate two elective members of^the legislative council as members of the
                    executive council. In 1873 the number of members was increased to twenty,
                    fifteen being elective and five non-elective, and in 1875 eight nominee members
                    were added. The colony is now administered by a governor, the promotion from
                    lieutenant-governor being made 28th January 1882; and by law No. 1, 1883, the
                    legislative council consists of thirty members, twenty-three of whom are
                    elective and seven non-elective, two of the latter holding office during the
                    royal pleasure. The executive <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n253/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0253-0242"/> council has been further increased by two
                    nominees not officers of the Government. The qualification for voters is the
                    possession of freehold property worth £50, the occupation of property at an
                    annual rental of £10, or an income of £96 per annum after three years’ colonial
                    residence. All voters are legally eligible as members. Boroughs or towns having
                    1000 inhabitants or upwards can form themselves into corporations for the
                    supervision of their own municipal affairs, and townships or villages under
                    certain conditions can frame local bye-laws.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Law and Justice.—</hi> The Roman-Dutch law by special enactment
                    prevails within the colony, in addition to which are a number of ordinances and
                    laws enacted by the local legislature, mostly founded upon imperial statute law.
                    The law of evidence is the same as that of the courts of England. It has not
                    been thought practicable as yet to bring the native population under the same
                    laws as govern the colonists of European descent; but in 1848 the natives had
                    their own laws confirmed by letters patent, except so far as these might be
                    repugnant to the general principles of humanity as recognized throughout the
                    civilized world; and they were codified and reduced into writing in 1878. Crimes
                    amongst natives, with some few exceptions, are, however, tried by the ordinary
                    courts. Special laws also have been passed for the benefit of the coolie
                    immigrants. The administration of justice is conducted by a supreme court, and
                    by the courts of the resident magistrates. The three judges of the supreme
                    court, one of whom is chief-justice, sit in Pietermaritzburg <hi rend="italic"
                    >in banco</hi> every alternate month, and during the other months circuit courts
                    are held at Durban and in other towns. There is a vice-admiralty court, of which
                    the chief-justiceof the supreme court is judge and commissary. In addition to
                    these are courts for the adjudication of cases under native law with right of
                    appeal to the native high court, which sits under its own special judge assisted
                    by assessors if need be; and from this high court appeal can be had to a court
                    of which the chief-justice of the colony, the secretary for native affairs, and
                    the judge of the native high court are judges. An appeal lies from all inferior
                    courts to the supreme court, and in suits where the subject-matter in dispute is
                    of the value of £500 an appeal can be had from any final judgment of the supreme
                    court to the privy council.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Education and Religion.—</hi> In 1861 there were two collegiate
                    institutions endowed in Natal, the one for Pietermaritzburg and the other for
                    Durban, but little more was done as regards education until the education laws
                    came into force in 1878, when a council of education was created to administer
                    funds voted by the legislative council for scholastic purposes and to control
                    all matters connected with the establishment and working of the public schools
                    of the colony. Most of the religious bodies have good schools in their several
                    parishes or districts; and public libraries and other literary institutions are
                    to be found not only in Pietermaritzburg and Durban but in the principal towns
                    and villages. Natal was erected into a see in 1853, with its cathedral in
                    Pietermaritzburg. Proceedings were taken against Bishop Colenso (who died June
                    20, 1883) on certain charges of heresy, and judgment given against him by the
                    South-African bishops in 1863; and this led eventually to the formation of a
                    separate see in the colony. On the 25th January 1869 the bishop of Maritzburg
                    was consecrated at Cape Town; he is a suffragan of the bishop of Cape Town, and
                    has his cathedral church also in Pietermaritzburg. The Wesleyan Church has a
                    very strong staff of clergy and local preachers in the colony, whilst the
                    Congregational Church, the Dutch Reformed Church, the Presbyterian Church, and
                    the Roman Catholic Church are all represented. At the stations of the Berlin,
                    Free Church of Scotland, American Zulu, Hanoverian, Norwegian, and Trappist
                    missions, great efforts are made to evangelize and train the natives and
                    coolies.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Population.—</hi> The total population is about 380,000, of
                    whom about 30,000 are whites, 20,000 Indian coolies, and 330,000 natives, mostly
                    descendants of early refugees from Zululand. Of the white population about
                    one-fifth are of Dutch extraction, and are chiefly resident in the Umvoti,
                    Weenen, Klip River, and Newcastle divisions. Most of the coolies are located on
                    the coast lands amongst the planters, who without their assistance would find
                    all field and manufacturing operations impossible, as the natives cannot be
                    depended on for continuous or skilled work.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> The country was discovered by Vasco da Gama, who
                    sighted the Bluff headland at the entrance to the bay forming the present port
                    at Durban on Christmas Day in 1497, and so named the country Terra Natalis. From
                    that date little is recorded until the survivors of the crew of the Dutch ship
                    “Stavenisse,” wrecked on the coast in 1686, gave their report of the country and
                    its inhabitants. In 1721 the Dutch formed a settlement, but it was soon
                    abandoned. Subsequently, about 1810, it would, seem that Chaka, chief of the
                    Amazulu, swept with his warriors through the whole of Natal and the adjoining
                    territories, destroying all males, and making booty of the cattle and women. One
                    tribe, the Ama-tuli, however, after offering resistance to the invader,
                    retreated into the dense bush near the Bluff and were amongst the few aborigines
                    when the British took possession of the country. In 1824 Lieutenant Farewell and
                    about twenty companions landed in Natal with the view of colonizing it, and for
                    that purpose entered into a treaty with Chaka. Some four years after their
                    arrival, however, Chaka was murdered by his brother Dingaan, and the settlement
                    was broken up. In 1835 another British officer, Captain Allen Gardner, got
                    permission from Dingaan to introduce missionaries into the country, and at once
                    formed the township of Durban, at the port where there were still a few English
                    settlers. In 1837 several Dutch farmers made an exodus from the Cape Colony, and
                    one of their leaders, Pieter Retief, with the assistance of the Rev. Mr Owen,
                    who had been for some time a resident missionary at Dingaan’s own head kraal,
                    obtained from Dingaan a cession of the whole territory of Natal. Immediately
                    after the conclusion of the treaty Retief and his followers were treacherously
                    murdered, and the attempt was made to extirpate the Boers throughout the length
                    and breadth of the land. The latter with their firearms eventually proved more
                    than a match for their numerous assailants, and joining Mpanda, who had rebelled
                    against his brother Dingaan, utterly routed Dingaan’s army on the banks of
                    the.White Umvolozi in 1840, and drove him to the Amaswazi country, where he was
                    shortly after assassinated. Natal became a British colony on 8th August 1843,
                    and, owing no doubt <hi rend="subscript"> κ</hi> to the fame of the security and
                    protection to be found under the British flag, large accessions were at once
                    made to the native population by refugees from the several surrounding tribes.
                    Since 1843 the colony has made rapid progress; the native tribes as a rule have
                    been loyal, and, although occasional reports from Zululand have alarmed the
                    colonists, it has very seldom been found necessary to send out the volunteer
                    forces on <hi rend="italic">commando.</hi> Any tendency to insubordination on
                    the part of the resident natives has always been quickly suppressed, and a
                    spirit of disaffection has never become general. In 1879 the colony became the
                    base of operations against the Zulu king Cetywayo, and in 1881 it was for a
                    short time invaded by the Transvaal Boers in connexion with the fighting which
                    arose out of the annexation of the Transvaal in 1877.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> Holden, <hi rend="italic">History of Natal;
                    Reports of Grout and Fynn to Native Commission,</hi> 1853; Cloete, <hi
                    rend="italic">Lectures,</hi> 1856; Shepstone, <hi rend="italic">Historic Sketch
                    of Natal,</hi> 1864; Brook, <hi rend="italic">History of Natal,</hi> edited by
                    Mann; Johnston, <hi rend="italic">Health and Disease,</hi> Natal, 1860; Harvey
                    anil Sonder, <hi rend="italic">Flora Capensis;</hi> Layard, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Birds of South Africa;</hi> Smith, <hi rend="italic">Zoology of South
                    Africa</hi>; Drummond, <hi rend="italic">Large Game of South Africa; African
                    Pilot for South and East Coasts of Africa;</hi> Cadiz, <hi rend="italic">Laws of
                    Natal;</hi> Colenso, <hi rend="italic">The Zulu War;</hi> Statham, <hi
                    rend="italic">Boers, Blacks, and British;</hi> Bird, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Form‰&gt;f Government (Natal),</hi> 1869; Carter, <hi rend="italic">Narrative
                    of the Boer War.</hi> (J. W. T.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
