<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0171-0160-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NABATAeANS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 160</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tq5rg4g">Coins</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205669">Jordan</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:891230">Deserts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:866649">Coins</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1032123">Nabataeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:813061">Arches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n171/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NABATAeANS</label>, a famous people of ancient Arabia, whose
                    settlements in the time of Josephus <hi rend="italic">(Ant.,</hi> i. 12, § 4;
                    comp. Jerome, <hi rend="italic">Qu. in Gen.</hi> xxv.) gave the name of Nabatene
                    to the border-land between Syria and Arabia from the Euphrates to the Red Sea.
                    The language of Josephus suggests, and Jerome, apparently following him,
                    directly affirms, that the name is identical with that of the Ishmaelite tribe
                    of Nebaioth (<hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> &gt;T□}, Gen. xxv. 13; Isa. lx. 7),
                    which in later Old Testament times had a leading place among the northern Arabs,
                    and is associated with Kedar much as Pliny v. 11 (12) associates <hi
                    rend="italic">Nabataei</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cedrei.</hi> The
                    identification is still followed by many scholars, but is rendered uncertain by
                    the fact that the name Nabataean is properly spelled with <hi rend="italic"
                    >t</hi> not <hi rend="italic">t</hi> (non: on the inscriptions, Arabic <hi
                    rend="italic">Nabat, Nabit,</hi> &lt;fcc.). Thus the history of this remarkable
                    people cannot with certainty be carried back beyond 312 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.,</hi> at which date they were attacked without success by Antigonus in
                    their mountain fortress of Petra. They are described by Diodorus (xix. 94 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.)</hi> as being at this time a strong tribe of some 10,000
                    warriors, preeminent among the nomadic Arabs, eschewing agriculture, fixed
                    houses, and the use of wine (which were forbidden on pain of death), living on
                    flesh and milk, and drinking water sweetened with manna, but adding to pastoral
                    pursuits a considerable and profitable trade with the seaports in myrrh and
                    spices from Arabia Felix, as well as a trade with Egypt in bitumen from the Dead
                    Sea used in the preparation of mummies. Their arid country was the best
                    safeguard of their cherished liberty; for the bottle-shaped cisterns for
                    rain-water which they excavated in the rocky or argillaceous soil were carefully
                    concealed from invaders. Petra or Sela' was the ancient capital of Edom; the
                    Nabataeans must have occupied the old Edomite country, and succeeded to its
                    commerce, after the Edomites took advantage of the Babylonian captivity to press
                    forward into southern Judaea. This migration, the date of which cannot be
                    determined, also made them masters of the shores of the Gulf of'Akaba and the
                    important harbour of Elath. Here, according to Agatharchides <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Geog. Gr. Min.,</hi> i. 178), they were for a time very troublesome, as
                    wreckers and pirates, to the reopened commerce between Egypt and the East, till
                    they were chastised by the Greek sovereigns of Alexandria.</p>
                <p>Tenacious as they were of the nomad usages of their ancestors, the Nabataeans had
                    already some tincture of foreign culture when they first appear in history. That
                    culture was naturally Aramaic; they wrote a letter to Antigonus “in Syriac
                    letters,” and Syriac continued to be the language of their coins and
                    inscriptions when the tribe grew into a kingdom, and profited by the decay of
                    the Seleucids to extend its borders northward over the more fertile country east
                    of the Jordan. They occupied the Haurân, and about 85 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> their king Aretas (Hâritha) became lord of Damascus and Coele Syria.
                    Allies of the first Hasmonaeans in their struggles against the Greeks, they
                    became the rivals of the Judaean dynasty in the period of its splendour, and a
                    chief element in the disorders which invited Pompey’s intervention in Palestine.
                    The Roman arms were not Very successful against the sons of the desert
                    (expedition of Scaurus, 63 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi>); King Aretas retained
                    his whole possessions, including Damascus, as a Roman vassal.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Compare 2 Cor. xi. 32. The
                    Nabataean Aretas or Aeneas there mentioned reigned from 7 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> to 40 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> or thereby.</p></note></p>
                <p>As “allies” of the Romans the Nabataeans continued to flourish throughout the
                    first Christian century. Their power extended far into Arabia, particularly
                    along the coast of the Red Sea; and Petra was a meeting-place of many nations,
                    though the importance of its commerce was diminished by the rise of the Eastern
                    trade-route from Myoshormus to Coptus on the Nile. Under the Roman peace they
                    lost their warlike habits, and were a sober, acquisitive, orderly people, wholly
                    intent on trade. They had now agriculture and houses of stone, and were not
                    unacquainted with foreign luxuries and arts (Strabo, xvi. 4). Such a people
                    might have long been a valuable bulwark between Rome and the wild hordes of the
                    desert but for the short-sighted cupidity of Trajan, who reduced Petra and broke
                    up the Nabataean nationality (105 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.).</hi> The new Arab
                    invaders who soon pressed forward into their seats found the remnants of the
                    Nabataeans transformed into <hi rend="italic">fellahin,</hi> and speaking
                    Aramaic like their neighbours. Hence Nabataeans became the Arabic name for
                    Aramaeans, whether in Syria or'Irâk, a fact which was misinterpreted by
                    Quatremère into a theory that the Nabataeans were originally Aramaean immigrants
                    from Babylonia. More recent inquiry has shown this view to be quite false. The
                    Nabataeans were true Arabs—as the proper names on their inscriptions show—who
                    came under the influence of Aramaean civilization. See especially Nöldeke in <hi
                    rend="italic">Z.</hi><hi rend="italic">D. Μ. G.,</hi> xvii. 705 <hi
                    rend="italic">sq.,</hi> xxv. 122 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi></p>
                <p>For the inscriptions and coins of the Nabataeans consult De Luynes in <hi
                    rend="italic">Remιe Numism.,</hi> 1858; Levy in <hi rend="italic">Z. D. Μ.
                    G.,</hi> xiv. 363 <hi rend="italic">sq.;</hi> De Vogué, <hi rend="italic">Mil.
                    d'Arch. Or.,</hi> 1868, <hi rend="italic">Syrie Centrale,</hi> 1866-77, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Inscr.</hi><hi rend="italic">Sémitiques,</hi> 1868—77. The
                    character of De Vogué’s inscriptions from the Haurân appears to be the parent of
                    the Cufic Arabic. The so-called <hi rend="italic">Fdlcιha Nabatiya,</hi> or
                    “Nabataean agriculture,” which professes to be an Arabic translation by
                    Ibn-Wahshiya from an ancient Nabataean source (MSS. in Leyden and elsewhere), is
                    a forgery of the 10th century. See Gutschmid in <hi rend="italic">Z. D. Μ.
                    G.,</hi> XV. 1 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi>; and Nöldeke, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ibid.,</hi> xxix. 445 <hi rend="italic">sq.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
