<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0177-0166-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NAIRN (9th edition, volume 17, page 166)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104803">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109125">Scots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115719">Shells</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4bt5f">Shells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c4k">Marl</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t08d">Dykes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n177/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NAIRN</label>, a small maritime county in the north-east of
                    Scotland, is bounded W. and S. by Inverness, E. by Elgin, and N. by the Moray
                    Firth. Its greatest length from north to south is about 20 miles, and its
                    greatest breadth about 15 miles; the area is 114,400 acres, or about 179 square
                    miles.</p>
                <p>The coast is low and sandy, and is skirted by sandbanks which render navigation
                    dangerous. The eastern part of the seaboard district is formed of low sand-hills
                    which extend into Morayshire. Parallel with the coast-line there is a great
                    deposit of sand and gravel, which forms a terraced bank rising to the height of
                    about 90 feet, and extends from 4 to 5 miles inward; it rests on Old Red
                    Sandstone, which sometimes protrudes on the surface. This undulating plain is
                    bordered by a hilly region which occupies two-thirds of the county. Where it
                    joins the plain it is skirted by a strip of Devonian associated with coarse
                    conglomerate. The hills, some of which reach a height of about 1500 feet, are
                    formed of granite and grey gneiss, with occasional beds of primitive limestone.
                    Freestone is plentiful, and there is also a species of dark bluestone which is
                    greatly valued for ornamental building. Shell-marl is obtained from several of
                    the lochs. The only rivers are the Nairn and Findhorn, with their tributaries.
                    The Nairn, after entering the county, flows north-east for a distance of about
                    30 miles, and falls into the Moray Firth at the town of Nairn. The Findhorn,
                    which also rises in Inverness, flows north-east through the southern and hilly
                    district of the county into Morayshire. The soil of the alluvial plain on the
                    coast is light and porous, and has been rendered very fertile by careful
                    cultivation. There is also some rich land on the Findhorn. The most advanced
                    methods of agriculture are in operation, but only a small proportion of the
                    surface is capable of tillage, scarcely more than a fifth of the total area
                    being under crops. The hills are for the most part covered with heath or pasture
                    suitable for sheep, intermixed with fir and larch plantations.</p>
                <p>The number of holdings in 1880-was only 392, and of these 214 did not exceed 50
                    acres in extent, 92 were between 50 and 100 acres, and 86 above 100 acres.
                    According to the agricultural returns of 1882 there were 26,463 acres under
                    cultivation, of which 9359 were under corn crops, 4871 under green crops, 10,031
                    under rotation grasses, and 2124 permanent pasture; 12 acres were under
                    orchards, and 13,241 underwoods. Very little wheat is grown, the principal corn
                    crops being barley or here, 3156 acres, and oats, 5917 acres. Of the green crops
                    4201 acres were under turnips or swedes, and 617 under potatoes. Horses in 1832
                    numbered 1292, cattle 5992 (1801 being cows or heifers in milk or in calf),
                    sheep 17,442, and pigs 981.</p>
                <p>The valued rental of the county in 1674 was £15,162 Scots, or about £1263
                    sterling. Exclusive of railways, the valuation in 1881-82 was £36,217. According
                    to the latest return the number <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n178/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0178-0167"/> of proprietors was 537, possessing lands of a
                    gross annual value of £41,767. Of these 467 possessed less than 1 acre, and 5
                    more than 5000 acres, viz., earl of Cawdor, 46,176 acres; James C. G. Brodie,
                    22,378; N. J. M <hi rend="superscript"> 4</hi> Gillivray, 12,600; earl of Leven
                    and Melville, 7805; and Hugh Davidson, 6363. There are several fine mansions in
                    the county, in addition to a number of shooting lodges. The coast is skirted by
                    the Highland Bailway, and there is a good harbour at Nairn. The county possesses
                    no special trade or manufacture, but there is a large distillery at a short
                    distance from the county town.</p>
                <p>Nairn includes three entire parishes, Ardclach, Auldearn, and Nairn, and portions
                    of the parishes of Cawdor, Croy, Dyke, Moy, Petty, Daviot, and Urquhart,—the
                    last two being detached portions, lying within Inverness and Ross respectively,
                    at considerable distances from the rest of the county. Since 1801, when it was
                    8322, the population has been slowly but steadily increasing, and in 1881
                    nrunbered 10,455 (4979 males and 5476 females). There is one royal burgh, Nairn,
                    and a burgh of barony, Auldearn. The county is under the same sheriffdom as
                    Elgin and Banff, and unites with Elgin in returning a member to parliament.
                    Anciently Nairn was included under the province of Moray, which was governed by
                    a ri or mormaer. Roman coins have been found at a vitrified fort on the summit
                    of a hill in the parish of Cawdor. There are numerous stone circles, including a
                    very perfect one on the summit of Lethenbar Hill, one at Golford, and. one at
                    Moyness consisting of two concentric circles and a rocking stone. Cawdor Castle,
                    a fine baronial structure, in a very picturesque situation, 5 miles south of
                    Nairn, is associated in unauthentic legend with the murder of King Duncan by
                    Macbeth; but no part of the building is really older than the 15th century.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Nairn,</hi> a royal and parliamentary burgh and county town,
                    is pleasantly situated near the Moray Firth, on the left bank of the Nairn, and
                    on the Highland Railway, 93 miles west-north-west of Aberdeen and 15 north-east
                    of Inverness. The principal buildings are the town and county hall (1818)
                    surmounted by a spire, the hospital (1816) in the Italian style, the new public
                    hall erected at a cost of £12,000, and the academy. Nairn is much frequented in
                    summer for sea-bathing, and possesses very complete artificial baths. There is a
                    commodious harbour with breakwater and pier. The principal exports are corn,
                    eggs, potatoes, herrings, haddocks, freestone, and timber, and the principal
                    imports coal, lime, and provisions. There are freestone quarries in the
                    neighbourhood, and the town possesses rope and twine factories. There is also a
                    salmon fishery. The burgh unites with Fortrose, Forres, and Inverness in
                    returning a member to parliament. The population of the parliamentary burgh in
                    1881 was 4161, and that of the royal burgh 4665.</p>
                <p>The town, whose original name was Invernairn, stood at first at some distance
                    from its present site. Its earliest extant charter, which bears, however, to be
                    a renewal of one received from Alexander I. in the 12th century, was granted by
                    James VI. in 1589. At that time the inhabitants of the western half of the town
                    spoke only Gaelic, and until a late period the distinction between the two
                    sections of the town inhabited by different races was very clearly marked.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
