<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0553-0510-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NÎMES, or Nismes</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 510</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1167847">Visigoths</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:937895">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:937852">Gardening</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:938950">Gates</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:800130">Age</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:800293">Aging</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:813061">Arches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4j96091f">Arches</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n553/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NÎMES, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Nismes</hi></label>, a city of
                    France, chief town of the department of Gard, a bishop’s see and seat of a court
                    of appeal, lies 450 miles south-south-east of Paris by the Clermont-Ferrand
                    Railway, and 80 miles north-west of Marseilles. The importance of the place is
                    due to its central position between the Rhone, the Cevennes, and the sea, to the
                    richness of the surrounding district, which before the ravages of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Phylloxera</hi> was clothed with vines, to its commerce and
                    industry, and lastly to its archaeological treasures. No town in France can show
                    so many remains of the Roman period. The amphitheatre is still in a good state
                    of preservation. Occupied during the Middle Ages by a special quarter, with even
                    a church of its own, it was cleared in 1809, and since then has been well kept
                    in repair. It is built of large stones without mortar. In form it is elliptical,
                    measuring 437⅜ by 332∣ feet externally; the arena is 327 by 222 feet. The
                    elevation (70 feet in all) consists of a ground story of 60 arches, an upper
                    story of 60 arches, and an attic with consoles pierced with holes for sunnorting
                    the <hi rend="italic">velarium</hi> or awning. There are four main gates, one at
                    each of the cardinal points; and no fewer than one hundred and twenty-four
                    doorways gave exit from the tiers of the amphitheatre to the inner galleries.
                    Originally designed for gladiatorial shows, or stag or boar hunts, the area has
                    in recent times been sometimes used for bull-fights. The celebrated Maison
                    Carrée, a temple in the style of the Parthenon, but on a smaller scale, 82 feet
                    long by 40 wide, is one of the finest monuments of the Roman period, and
                    probably dates from the time of the Antonines. It contains a collection of
                    antique sculptures and inscriptions. The temple of Diana,—possibly a building
                    connected with the neighbouring baths,—is now overgrown with fig trees and
                    climbing plants, but preserves a few fragments of statues and some rustic
                    columns. The Tour Magne (Turris Magna), situated on the highest point in the
                    city, 375 feet above sea-level, is still 92 feet in height, and was formerly a
                    third higher. Admittedly the oldest monument of Nîmes, it has been variously
                    regarded as an old signal tower, a treasure-house, or the tomb of a Greek family
                    settled in Gaul along with the earliest Phoenician colonists. Attached to the
                    ramparts erected by Augustus, and turned into a fortress in the Middle Ages by
                    the counts of Toulouse, the Tour Magne was restored about 1840. From the top
                    there is a magnificent view extending from Canigou at the east end of the
                    Pyrenees to Mont Ventoux, an outpost of the Alps; northward it takes in the
                    vine-and olive-clad Garrigues and the Cevennes, eastward the valley of the Rhone
                    and the Vaucluse and Alpine ranges, and southward the Mediterranean and the
                    Aigues Mortes ramparts. Near the Tour Magne has been discovered the reservoir
                    from which the water conveyed by the Pont du Gard was distributed throughout the
                    city. Two gates, that of Augustus dating from 16 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi>
                    and the Porte de France, both semicircular arches, are preserved as historical
                    monuments. Many of the finest buildings known to have existed have disappeared.
                    When it still possessed its capitol, the temple of Augustus, the basilica of
                    Plotina erected under Hadrian, the temple of Apollo, the hot baths, the theatre,
                    the circus, constructed in the reign ot Nero, the Campus Martius, and the
                    fortifications built by Augustus, Nîmes must have been one of the richest of the
                    Roman cities of Gaul. The cathedral (St Castor), occupying, it is believed, the
                    site of the temple of Augustus, is partly Roman and partly Gothic in style. It
                    contains the tombs of Flèchier and Cardinal de Bernis. The church of St Paul, a
                    modern Romanesque building, is adorned with frescos by Flandrin; St Baudile
                    (modern Gothic) is of note for the two stone spires which adorn its façade; and
                    the court-house has a fine Corinthian colonnade and a pediment. Other buildings
                    and institutions of note are the hospitals, the barracks, the old citadel
                    (dating from 1687, and now used as a central house of detention), the picture
                    gallery in the old lycée, the public library (50,000 volumes), and the museum of
                    natural history.</p>
                <p>The esplanade in front of the court-house has in the centre a handsome fountain
                    with five marble statues by Pradier. The Fountain Gardens, in the north-west of
                    the town, owe their peculiar character as well as their name to a spring of
                    water which after heavy rains is copious enough not only to fill the ornamental
                    basins (constructed in the 18th century with balustrades and statues on ancient
                    foundations) but also to form a considerable stream. Neither the spring,
                    however, nor the Vistre into which it discharges, is sufficient for the wants of
                    the city, and water has consequently been brought from the Rhone, a distance of
                    17 miles. A beautiful avenue, the Cours Neuf, runs south for nearly a mile from
                    the middle walk of the garden.</p>
                <p>At the close of the Middle Ages the industries of Nîmes were raised to a state of
                    great prosperity by a colony from Lombardy and Tuscany; and, though the plague,
                    the wars of religion, and the revocation of the edict of Nantes were all
                    sufficiently disastrous in their effects, before the Revolution about half of
                    the whole community, or from 10,000 to 12,000 persons, had come to be engaged in
                    manufactures. Since then, however, the numbers of this class have hardly
                    increased, while the population of the city has been doubled. The silk
                    manufacture (reeling, spinning, weaving) no longer occupies all hands.
                    Upholstery materials (which have - almost displaced shawls), carpets,
                    handkerchiefs, tapes, braidings, hosiery, leather, clothes, and boots and shoes
                    are also produced; and, coal being worked in the neighbourhood, a number of
                    foundries have been established. Nîmes is, besides, one of the great southern
                    markets for wine and brandy, silks and cocoons; and there is a good trade in
                    grain, groceries, and colonial wares. The population of the city in 1881 was
                    61,210; that of the commune was 62,394 in 1871, and 63,552 in 1881.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n554/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0554-0511"/>
                <p>Nemausus, the ancient Nîmes, derived its name from the sacred wood in which the
                    Volcae Arecomici (who of their own accord surrendered to the Romans in 121 <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">b.c.)</hi> were wont to hold their assemblies. Constituted a
                    colony of veterans by Augustus, and endowed with numerous privileges, it built a
                    temple and struck a medal in honour of its founder. The medal, which afterwards
                    furnished the type for the coat of arms granted to the town by Francis I., bears
                    on one side the heads of Caesar Augustus and Vipsanius Agrippa (the former
                    crowned with laurel), while on the other there is a crocodile chained to a
                    palm-tree, with the legend <hi rend="smallcaps">Col. Nem.</hi> It was Agrippa
                    who built the public baths at Nîmes, the temple of Diana, and the aqueduct of
                    the Pont du Gard. The city-walls, erected by Augustus, were nearly 4 miles in
                    circuit, 30 feet high, and 10 feet broad, flanked by ninety towers, and pierced
                    by ten gates. Hadrian on his way back from Britain erected at Nîmes two
                    memorials of his benefactress Plotina. In the very height of its prosperity the
                    city was ravaged by the Vandals; the Visigoths followed, and turned the
                    amphitheatre into a stronghold, which at a later date was set on fire along with
                    the gates of the city when Charles Martel drove out the Saracens. Nîmes became a
                    republic under the protection of Pippin the Short; and in 1185 it passed to the
                    counts of Toulouse, who restored its prosperity and enclosed it with ramparts
                    whose enceinte, less extensive than that of Augustus, may still be traced in the
                    boulevards of the present day. The city took part in the crusade against the
                    Albigenses in 1207. Under Louis VIII. it received a royal garrison into its
                    amphitheatre; under Louis XI. it was captured by the duke of Burgundy, and in
                    1420 was recovered by the dauphin (Charles VII. ). On a visit to Nîmes Francis
                    I. enriched it with a university and a school of arts. By 1558 about
                    three-fourths of the inhabitants had become Protestant, and the city suffered
                    greatly during the religious wars. From the accession of Henry IV. till the
                    revocation of the edict of Nantes (1685) the Protestant community devoted itself
                    to active industry; but after that disastrous event great numbers went into
                    exile or joined the Camisards. Louis XIV. built a fortress (1687) to keep in
                    check the disturbances caused by the rival religious parties. Nîmes passed
                    unhurt through the storms of the Revolution; but in 1815 Trestaillon and his
                    bandit followers pillaged and burned and plundered and massacred the
                    Bonapartiste and Protestants. Since then the city has remained divided into two
                    strongly-marked factions—Catholics and Protestants; happily, however, there has
                    been no repetition of such scenes. Domitius Afer (Quintilian’s master), Jacques
                    Saurin the Protestant divine, Nicot the introducer of tobacco into France,
                    Séguier the archaelogist, Guizot, and Reboul (the Provencal poet whose statue
                    adorns the Promenade de la Fontaine) are among the celebrated natives of
                    Nîmes.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
