<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0917-0365-0352-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NERVA (9th edition, volume 17, page 352)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb7v">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx0652b">Consulates</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw1v">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2t79r">Digestion</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:876196">Consuls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880656">Cost</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1029821">Murderers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1029781">Murder</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137147">Suet</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937144">Galba</term>
                    <term ref="fast:893579">Digestion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:846504">Capitols</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n365/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NERVA</label> (32-98 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.),</hi> Roman
                    emperor from 96 to 98, was called to the throne on the murder of Domitian
                    (September 18, 96; Suet., <hi rend="italic">Dom.,</hi> 17; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Corp. Inscr. Lat.,</hi> vi. 472). His full name was Marcus Cocceius Nerva
                    (Henzen, 5435), and his family, though of no great antiquity, had attained to
                    considerable distinction under the emperors. The Μ. Cocceius Nerva who was
                    consul in 36 B.c. was probably his great-grandfather. His grandfather of the
                    same name (consul <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 22 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.)</hi>
                    was a lawyer of high reputation and an intimate friend of the emperor Tiberius
                    (Tac., <hi rend="italic">Ann.,</hi> iv. 58, vi. 26; Front., <hi rend="italic">De
                        Aqueed.,</hi> 102). His father is usually identified with the “Nerva filius”
                    who is mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Digest</hi> as a prominent jurist, and
                    who was possibly consul in 40 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> Of his mother a
                    single inscription tells us that she was Sergia Plautilla, daughter of Laenas
                    (Orelli, 777).</p>
                <p>Nerva must have been born in 32 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> for he was
                    sixty-four years old at the time of his accession in 96 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >a.d.</hi> In early manhood he had been on friendly terms with Nero, whose
                    taste for versification he shared (Martial, viii. 70; Pliny, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ep.,</hi> v. 3), and by whom, in 65, he was decorated with the “insignia
                    triumphalia” (Tac., <hi rend="italic">Ann.,</hi> xv. 72). He had been praetor
                    (166) and twice consul, in 71 with the emperor Vespasian for colleague (Orelli,
                    1634), and again in 90 with Domitian. Towards the close of the latter’s reign he
                    is said to have excited suspicion and to have been banished to Tarentum on a
                    charge of conspiracy (Dio Cass., <hi rend="italic">Epit.,</hi> lxvii. 15;
                    Philostr., <hi rend="italic">Apoll.</hi><hi rend="italic">Tyan.,</hi> vii. 8).
                    He is described as a quiet, kindly, dignified man, honest of purpose, but
                    unfitted by age and temperament, as well as by feeble health, to bear the weight
                    of empire. Nevertheless his selection by Domitian’s murderers as that prince’s
                    successor seems to have been generally approved, and his short rule, in spite of
                    occasional exhibitions of weakness, justified the choice. His accession brought
                    a welcome relief from the terrible strain of the last few years. The reign of
                    terror was at an end and liberty restored. The new emperor recalled those who
                    had been exiled by Domitian; what remained of their confiscated property was
                    restored to them, and a stop was put to the vexatious prosecutions which
                    Domitian had encouraged. But the popular feeling demanded more than this. The
                    countless informers of all classes who had thriven under the previous régime now
                    found themselves swept away, to borrow Pliny’s metaphor (Pliny, <hi
                        rend="italic">Paneg.,</hi> 35), by a hurricane of revengeful fury, which
                    threatened to become as dangerous in its indiscriminate ravages as the system it
                    attacked. It was finally checked by Nerva, who was stung into action by the
                    sarcastic remark of the consul Fronto that, “bad as it was to have an emperor
                    who allowed no one to do anything, it was worse to have one who allowed every
                    one to do everything” (Dio Cass., <hi rend="italic">Epit.,</hi> Ixviii. 1).</p>
                <p>Nerva seems to have followed the custom established by his predecessors of
                    announcing at the outset the general lines of his future policy. Domitian had
                    been arbitrary and high-handed, and had heaped favours on the soldiery while
                    humiliating the senate;- Nerva naturally enough assumed the opposite attitude,
                    and showed himself anxious in every way to respect the traditional privileges of
                    the senate, and such maxims of constitutional government as still survived. He
                    pledged himself to put no senator to death. His chosen councillors in all
                    affairs of state were senators, and the hearing of claims against the fiscus was
                    taken from the imperial procuratores and entrusted to the more impartial
                    jurisdiction of a praetor and a court of “judices” (Dio Cass., <hi rend="italic"
                        >Eρit.,</hi> Ixviii. 2; <hi rend="italic">Digest,</hi> i. 2, 2; Pliny, <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n366/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0917-0366-0353"/><hi rend="italic">Paneg.,</hi> 36). It was
                    thus, as Pliny magniloquently says, that Nerva united the “principate” with
                    “freedom.”</p>
                <p>No one probably expected from Nerva a vigorous administration either at home or
                    abroad. But he seems to have set himself honestly enough to carry through such
                    reforms as were either suggested by his own benevolent inclinations, or
                    imperatively demanded by the necessities of the moment. The economical condition
                    of Italy evidently excited his alarm and sympathy. The last mention of a “lex
                    agraria” in Roman history is connected with his name, though how far the measure
                    was strictly speaking a “law” is uncertain. Under the provisions of this “lex,”
                    large tracts of land were bought up and allotted to poor citizens. The cost was
                    defrayed partly from the imperial treasury, but partly also from Nerva’s private
                    resources, and the execution of the scheme was entrusted to commissioners <hi
                        rend="italic">(Dig.,</hi> xlvii. 21, 3; Dio Cass., <hi rend="italic"
                        >Epit.,</hi> lxviii. 2; Pliny, <hi rend="italic">Ep.,</hi> vii. 31; <hi
                        rend="italic">Corp. Inscr. Lat.,vi,</hi> 1548). This agrarian law was
                    probably as shortlived in its effects as preceding ones had been, but a reform
                    more lasting in its results was the provision of a regular maintenance at the
                    public cost for the children of poor parents in the towns of Italy (Aur. Vict.,
                        <hi rend="italic">Ep.,</hi> 24), the provision being presumably secured by
                    imposing a yearly charge for this purpose on state and municipal lands. On coins
                    of the year 97 Nerva is represented seated upon his curule chair and stretching
                    out a helping right hand to a boy and a girl. The legend on the coins is “tutela
                    Italiae” (Eckhel, vi. 408; Marquardt, <hi rend="italic">Staatsverwaltung,</hi>
                    ii. 138, note 6). Private individuals were also encouraged to follow the
                    imperial example; and among those who responded was the younger Pliny, whose
                    charitable institution in his own town of Comum seems to have followed directly
                    on that of the emperor himself <hi rend="italic">(Hermes,</hi> iii. 101; Pliny,
                        <hi rend="italic">Ep. ad T.,</hi> 8). In the hands of Trajan, Hadrian, and
                    the Antonines, Nerva’s example bore fruit in the institution of the
                    “alimentationes,” the most genuinely charitable institution of the pagan world.
                    These measures Nerva supplemented by others which aimed at lightening the
                    financial burdens which already weighed heavily on the declining industry of
                    Italy. The cost of maintaining the imperial postal system was transferred to the
                    “fiscus,” from the same source apparently money was found for repairing the
                    public roads and aqueducts, and lastly the lucrative but unpopular succession
                    duty “vicesima hereditatum,” was so readjusted as to remove the grosser abuses
                    connected with it (Pliny, <hi rend="italic">Paneg., 37). At</hi> the same time
                    Nerva did his best to reduce the overgrown expenditure of the state (Pliny, <hi
                        rend="italic">Ep.,</hi> ii. 1). A commission was appointed to consider the
                    best modes of retrenchment, and the outlay on shows and games was cut down to
                    the lowest possible point. It was these efforts which earned for him the epithet
                    “frugalissimus” (Pliny, <hi rend="italic">Paneg.,</hi> 51). Nerva seems
                    nevertheless to have soon wearied of the uncongenial task of governing, and his
                    anxiety to be rid of it was quickened by the discovery that not even his
                    blameless life and mild rule protected him against intrigue and disaffection.
                    Early, apparently, in 97 he detected a conspiracy against his life headed by L.
                    Calpurnius Crassus, but he contented himself with a hint to the conspirators
                    that their designs were known, and with banishing Crassus to Tarentum. This
                    ill-judged lenity provoked a few months later an intolerable insult to his
                    dignity. The praetorian guards had keenly resented the murder of their patron
                    Domitian, and now, at the instigation of one of their two prefects, Casperius
                    Aelianus, whom Nerva had retained in office, they imperiously demanded the
                    execution of Domitian’s murderers, the chamberlain Parthenius, and Petronius
                    Secundus, Aelianus’s colleague. Nerva vainly strove to save, even at the risk of
                    his own life, the men who had raised him to power, but the soldiers,
                    disregarding his protests, brutally murdered the unfortunate men, and finally
                    forced Nerva to propose a vote of thanks for the deed (Dio Cass., <hi
                        rend="italic">Epit.,</hi> lxviii. 4; Aur. Vict., <hi rend="italic">Ep.,</hi>
                    24). This crowning humiliation convinced Nerva of the necessity of placing the
                    reins of government in stronger hands than his own. Following the precedent set
                    by Augustus, Galba, and Vespasian, he resolved to adopt as his colleague and
                    destined successor a younger and more vigorous man, and his choice fell upon Μ.
                    Ulpius Trajanus, already well known as a distinguished soldier, and at the time
                    in command of the legions on the Rhine. In October 97, in the temple of Jupiter
                    on the Capitol, Trajan was formally adopted as his son, and declared his
                    colleague in the government of the empire (Pliny, <hi rend="italic">Paneg.,</hi>
                    8). For three months Nerva ruled jointly with Trajan (Aur. Vict., <hi
                        rend="italic">Ep.,</hi> 24); but on January 27, 98, he died somewhat
                    suddenly. He was buried in the sepulchre of Augustus, and divine honours were
                    paid him by his successor. The verdict of history upon his reign is best
                    expressed in his own words,—“I have done nothing which should prevent me from
                    laying down my power, and living in safety as a private man.” In the Rome of
                    to-day the memory of Nerva is still preserved by the ruined temple in the Via
                    Alessandrina (il Colonacce) which marks the site of the Forum begun by Domitian,
                    but which Nerva completed and dedicated (Suet., <hi rend="italic">Dom.,</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">5</hi>; Aur. Vict., 12).</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> Dio Cass., <hi rend="italic">Epit.,</hi>
                    Ixviii. 1-4; Aurelius Victor, 12, and ⅛nΛ, 24; Zonaras, xi. 20; compare also
                    Pliny, <hi rend="italic">Epistolse</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Panegyricus</hi>;
                    Tillemont, <hi rend="italic">Histoire des Empereurs Romains</hi>; Merivale, <hi
                        rend="italic">History of the</hi><hi rend="italic">Romans</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">under the Empire</hi>; H. Schiller, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">d.</hi><hi rend="italic">Kaiserzeit.</hi>
                    * (H. F. P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
