<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0521-0480-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NICE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 480</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cq1v">Ligurians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz3256r">Storms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1176048">Winter</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:803903">Aix</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:998754">Ligurians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1105547">Sardinians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n521/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NICE</label>, a city of France, the chief town of the
                    department of Alpes Maritimes, and previous to 1860 the capital of the countship
                    of Nice (Nizza) in the kingdom of Sardinia, is situated in 43° 42' N. lat. and
                    7° 16' E, long., 739 miles by rail from Paris, and occupies a fine position at
                    the mouth of the Paillon (Paglione), a stream (often dried up in summer) which,
                    after a course of 20 miles, enters the northern end of the Baie des Anges. A
                    steep isolated limestone hill, 315 feet in height, running back for some
                    distance from the shore, forms the historical nucleus of the town. Formerly
                    crowned by a castle, which previous to its destruction by the duke of Berwick in
                    1706 was one of the strongest fortresses on the coast, it is now laid out as a
                    public pleasure-ground, and planted with aloe, cactus, agave, and palm. Towards
                    its south-west corner stands a tower (Tour Bellanda or Clérissy) dating, it is
                    believed, from the 5th century. The old town stretches along the western base of
                    the hill; the “town of the 18th century” occupies the ground farther west, which
                    slopes gently towards the Paillon; and away to the north-east and north and west
                    beyond the stream lie the ever-growing quarters of the modern city. To the east
                    of the hill, and thus out of sight of the more fashionable districts, the
                    commercial quarter surrounds the port. The whole frontage of Nice is composed of
                    fine embankments: the Quai des Ponchettes, constructed in 1770 round the base of
                    the castle hill, is continued westward by the Quai du Midi as far as the Pont
                    des Anges, which crosses the mouth of the Paillon; and from the public gardens
                    and the municipal casino on the other side of the stream the Promenade des
                    Anglais, a boulevard 85 feet wide, extends for more than a mile to the mouth of
                    the Magnan, and is likely to be prolonged to the Var. A pier projecting into the
                    sea from the promenade contains a “crystal palace” and a sea-bathing
                    establishment. The course of the Paillon also is embanked on both sides, and at
                    one part the Place Masséna, one of the largest public squares in the city, and
                    the principal resort of foreign visitors, has been laid out across the stream.
                    Besides a Roman Catholic cathedral—Ste Réparate, dating from <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n522/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0522-0481"/> 1650—Nice possesses a Russian church, two
                    synagogues, and several Protestant chapels. Architecturally the most remarkable
                    church is Notre Dame, a modern Gothic building with two towers 213 feet high,
                    erected by the town in 1835 to commemorate its preservation from cholera. The
                    secular buildings include the town-house, the prefecture, the theatres, the
                    hospitals, the lycée (founded by the Jesuits in the 17th century), the natural
                    history museum, the library (especially rich in theology), and, at some distance
                    from the town, the astronomical and meteorological observatory on Mount Gros.
                    The industrial establishments comprise perfume factories, distilleries,
                    oil-works, furniture and wood work factories, confectionery works, soap-works,
                    tanneries, and a national tobacco factory employing several hundred persons.
                    Besides the vine, the trees principally cultivated in the neighbourhood are the
                    olive, the orange, the mulberry, and the carob; and the staple exports are oil,
                    agricultural produce, fruits, and flowers. The harbour, which as yet only covers
                    10 acres, is being enlarged. In 1881 the population of the city was 54,953, and
                    of the commune 66,279,—an increase respectively of about 9000 and 13,900 since
                    1872. During winter there is a large proportion of strangers from all parts of
                    the world.</p>
                <p>Protected towards the north by hills which rise stage behind stage to the main
                    ridge of the Alps, Nice is celebrated for the mildness of its climate. The mean
                    temperature is 60° Fahr., that of winter being 49°,of spring 56°, of summer 72°,
                    and of autumn 63°. For a few nights in winter the mercury sinks below freezing
                    point, but snow is practically unknown, falling, on an average, only half a day
                    in the year. The highest reading of the thermometer is rarely above 90°. There
                    are sixty-seven days with rain in the course of the year; but it usually falls
                    in heavy showers which soon leave the sky clear again, though the whole annual
                    amount exceeds 32 inches. Fine days and rainy days are almost equally
                    distributed throughout the different seasons. The winds are very variable,
                    sometimes changing several times a day. Apart from the ordinary land and sea
                    breezes, the most frequent is the east wind, which is especially formidable
                    during autumn. The south-west wind is moist and warm; the north-east, which is
                    happily rare, brings storms of hail and even snow in winter. The mistral (from
                    the north-west) and the tramontane (from the north) are generally stopped by the
                    mountains; but when they do reach the city they raise intolerable dust-storms.
                    For two thousand years the climate of Nice has been considered favourable in
                    chest complaints. Those who are requiring rest, and those suffering from gout,
                    asthma, catarrhs, rachitic affections, scrofula, stone, also experience benefit;
                    but the reverse is the case when heart disease, nervous disorders, or ophthalmia
                    are concerned. Autumn is the best season; in spring the sudden changes of
                    temperature demand great care. Means of passing the time pleasantly are fairly
                    abundant. The city is at its liveliest during the carnival festivities, in
                    which, ' as at Rome, battles are waged with sweetmeats and flowers.</p>
                <p>Nice <hi rend="italic">(Nicaea)</hi> was founded about two thousand years ago by
                    the Phocaeans of Marseilles, and received its name in honour of a victory <hi
                    rend="italic">{.νίκη)</hi> over the neighbouring Ligurians. It soon became one
                    of the busiest trading stations on the Ligurian coast; but as a city it had an
                    important rival in the town of Cemenclium, which continued to exist till the
                    time of the Lombard invasions, and has left its ruins at Cimiez (Italian,
                    Cemella), 2⅛ miles to the north. In the 7th century Nice joined the Genoese
                    league formed by the towns, of Liguria. In 731 it repulsed the Saracens; but in
                    859 and 880 they pillaged and burned it, and for the most of the 10th century
                    remained masters of the surrounding country. During the Middle Ages Nice had its
                    share in the wars and disasters of Italy. As an ally of Pisa it was the enemy of
                    Genoa, and both the king of France and the emperor of Germany endeavoured to
                    subjugate it; but in spite of all it. maintained its municipal liberties. In the
                    course of the 13th and 14th centuries it fell more than once into theΙιands of
                    the counts of Provence; and at length in 1388 it placed itself under the
                    protection of the counts of Savoy. The maritime strength of Nice now rapidly
                    increased till it was able to cope with the Barbary pirates; the fortifications
                    were largely extended and the roads to the city improved. During the struggle
                    between Francis I. and Charles V. great damage was caused by the passage of the
                    armies invading Provence; pestilence and famine raged in the city for several
                    years. It was in Nice that the two monarchs in 1538 concluded, through the
                    mediation of Paul III., a truce of ten years; and a marble cross set up to
                    commemorate the arrival of the pope still gives its name, Croix de Marbre, to
                    part of the town. In 1543 Nice was attacked by the united forces of Francis I.
                    and Barbarossa; and, though the inhabitants, with admirable courage, repulsed
                    the assault which succeeded the terrible bombardment, they were ultimately
                    compelled to surrender, and Barbarossa was allowed to pillage the city and to
                    carry off 2500 captives. Pestilence appeared again in 1550 and 1580. In 1600
                    Nice was taken by the duke of Guise. By opening the ports of the countship to
                    all nations, and proclaiming full freedom of trade, Charles Emmanuel in 1626
                    gave a great stimulus to the commerce of the city, whose noble families took
                    part in its mercantile enterprises. Captured by Catinat in 1691, Nice was
                    restored to Savoy in 1696; but it was again besieged by the French in 1705, and
                    in the following year its citadel and ramparts were demolished. The treaty of
                    Utrecht in 1713 once more gave the city back to Savoy; and in the peaceful years
                    which followed the “new town” was built. From 1744 till the peace oi
                    Aix-la-Chapelle (1748) the French and Spaniards were again in possession. In
                    1775 the king of Sardinia destroyed all that remained of the ancient liberties
                    of the commune. Conquered in 1792 by the armies of the French Republic, the
                    countship of Nice continued to be part of France till 1814; but after that date
                    it reverted to Sardinia. By a treaty concluded in 1860 between the Sardinian
                    king and Napoleon III. it was again transferred to France, and the cession was
                    ratified by nearly 26,000 electors out of a total of 30,700. Nice is the seat of
                    a bishopric, at present dependent on the archbishopric of Aix, and the
                    headquarters of a military division forming part of the corps d’armée of
                    Marseilles. Masséna and Garibaldi were natives of the city.</p>
                <p>See Roubaudi, <hi rend="italic">Nice</hi><hi rend="italic">et ses</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">environs,</hi> Turin, 1843; Tisserand, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hist,</hi><hi rend="italic">de la cité</hi><hi rend="italic">de Nice,</hi>
                    Nice, 1862; Lacoste. <hi rend="italic">Nice</hi><hi rend="italic">pittoresque
                    et</hi><hi rend="italic">pratique,</hi> Nice, 1876.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
