<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0684-0627-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NUMIDIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 627</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj57">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34n208">Vandals</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:843856">Caesarism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1205459">Algeria</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1242088">Sahara</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n684/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NUMIDIA</label> was the name given to a large tract of
                    country in the north of Africa, extending along the Mediterranean Sea from the
                    confines of Mauretania to those of the Roman province of Africa. The term was,
                    however, employed in very different senses, and within very different limits, at
                    different periods of time. When Carthage was at the height of its power, and the
                    Romans first came into contact with the nations of northern Africa, the name of
                    Numidia was applied to the whole country from the river Mulucha (now called the
                    Mulιiya), about 100 miles west of Oran, to the frontier of the Carthaginian
                    territory, which nearly coincided with the modern regency of Tunis. It is in
                    this sense that the term is employed by Polybius, and all succeeding historians
                    down to the close of the Roman republic. The Numidians, as thus defined, were
                    divided into two great tribes, the Massyli on the east, and the Massaesyli on
                    the west,—the limit between the two territories being the river Ampsaga, which
                    enters the sea to the west of the remarkable promontory called Tretum, now known
                    as the Seven Capes. At the time of the Second Punic War the eastern tribe was
                    under the government of Masinissa, who took part with the Romans in the contest,
                    while his rival Syphax, king of the Massaesylians, supported the cause of the
                    Carthaginians. In consequence of this, after the close of the war, Syphax’s
                    dominions were forfeited, and united with those of Masinissa, who now ruled the
                    whole Numidian people from the frontier of Mauretania to the boundary of the
                    Carthaginian territory. That monarch, who attained to a great age, retained the
                    "whole of these extensive dominions till his death in 148 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.,</hi> as was the case also with his son and successor Micipsa; but after
                    the death of the latter in 118, the ambition of his nephew <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Jugurtha</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.)</hi> involved him in a war with Rome,
                    which ended in his defeat and death in 106.</p>
                <p>Numidia was not, hoλvever, incorporated with the Roman empire until a later
                    period. After the death of Jugurtha the western portion of his dominions was
                    added to those of Bocchus, king of Mauretania, while the remainder continued to
                    be governed by native princes until the civil war between Caesar and Pompey, in
                    which Juba, then king of Numidia, having espoused the cause of the latter, and
                    supported Scipio and Cato in Africa, was defeated by Caesar, and put an end to
                    his own life (46 -e.c.). Numidia, in the more restricted sense which it had now
                    acquired, became for a short time a Roman province, but in the settlement of
                    affairs after the battle of Actium (30) it was restored to Juba II., son of the
                    preceding monarch, who had acquired the favour of Augustus. A few years later,
                    however, Juba was transferred to the throne of Mauretania, including the whole
                    western portion of the ancient Numidian monarchy as far as the river Ampsaga,
                    while the Roman province of Numidia, which was now definitely constituted,
                    comprised only the tract between that river and the Tusca, which formed the
                    western limit of the Roman province of Africa. But though thus restricted in
                    extent—so as nearly to correspond with the modern French province of
                    Constantine, while the kingdom of Numidia in the wider sense had included the
                    whole of Algeria—the Roman province of Numidia attained a high degree of
                    prosperity and civilization, and was studded with numerous towns, the importance
                    of which is attested by inscriptions still extant, as well as by the massive
                    remains of their ancient monuments and works of public utility. This period of
                    prosperity continued to be favoured by unbroken <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n685/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0685-0628"/> peace for more than four centuries, until the
                    invasion of the Vandals in 428 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> reduced it to a
                    condition of gradual decay; and the invasion of the Arabs in the 8th century
                    again brought desolation upon the land, which was aggravated by continual
                    misgovernment until the conquest of Algeria by the French within the present
                    century.</p>
                <p>The physical character of the country has been already described in the article
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Algeria.</hi> It may be briefly observed that the whole
                    tract of northern Africa from the river Mulucha to the frontiers of the regency
                    of Tunis may be divided into three parallel zones or regions: the Tell, or
                    fertile district near the sea, the broad inland plateaus beyond it, and the
                    Sahara, or barren region to the south of these uplands, sloping thence down to
                    the great desert which is generally known by that name. The central upland tract
                    assumes a more rugged and mountainous character in the eastern district, which
                    formed the Roman province of Numidia, and now constitutes the French province of
                    Constantine. But this elevated region breaks down abruptly towards the east,
                    where it sends out only a few offshoots into the plains of Tunis, as well as to
                    the south where it faces the wide expanse of the Sahara. It is here that is
                    situated the mountain group called the Aures (the Mons Aurasius of Procopius),
                    of which the highest summit, called by the Arabs Jebel Chellia, attains to an
                    elevation of 7580 feet.</p>
                <p>The name of the Numidians appears to have been nothing more than a Latinized form
                    of the Greek term Nomades, vaguely applied by them to the wandering tribes of
                    northern Africa. It could never have had any ethnographical signification; and
                    there can be no doubt that the people thus designated were merely a portion of
                    the great Berber race, which extended in ancient times from the shores of the
                    Atlantic to the confines of Egypt, and which still, under the name of Kabyles,
                    forms a portion of the population of both Algeria and Tunis. The Gaetulians, who
                    at the same period occupied the southern slopes of the mountains towards the
                    Sahara, appear to have stood in much the same relation to the Numidians that the
                    tribes called Tuaricks or Tuareg do at the present day to the comparatively
                    civilized Kabyles of Algeria. But the Roman authority over these wanderers of
                    the desert was of a very precarious character, and a line of outposts near the
                    foot of the mountain range formed the limit of their practical dominion towards
                    the south.</p>
                <p>The chief towns of Numidia under the Romans were :— Cirta, the capital, in the
                    interior, subsequently called Constantina, which name it still retains;
                    Rusicada, on the coast, serving as its port, on the site now occupied by
                    Philippeville; and east of it the more important city of Hippo Regius (well
                    known as the see of the celebrated Augustine), near the modern Bona. South of
                    Cirta, in the interior, λvere Theveste (now Tebessa) and Lambaesa (now
                    Lambessa), with extensive Roman remains. But there were not less than ten towns
                    with the title of “coloniae,” and in the 5th century the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Notitia</hi> enumerates no less than 123 episcopal sees.</p>
                <p>For details concerning the condition of Numidia as a Roman province, see <hi
                    rend="italic">Corp. Inscτ. Lat.,</hi> vol. viii. (1881). A more popular account
                    will be found in the <hi rend="italic">Algérie</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Romaine</hi> of G. Boissiere (2 vols 8vo, Paris, 1883). (E. H. B. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
