<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0249-0238-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NASSAU</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 238</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rv0d79g">Riches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j20">Fruit</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd7z">Graining</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1175881">Wine</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1048908">Othoes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1132936">Steins</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:933759">Franks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n249/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NASSAU</label>, now forming the bulk of the government
                    district of Wiesbaden, in the Prussian province of Hesse-Nassau, was till 1866
                    an independent and sovereign duchy of Germany, consisting of a compact mass of
                    territory, 1830 square miles in area, bounded on the S. and W. by the Main and
                    Rhine, on the N. by Westphalia, and on the E. by Hesse. This territory is
                    divided into two nearly equal parts by the river Lahn, which flows from east to
                    west into the Rhine. The southern half is almost entirely occupied by the Taunus
                    Mountains, which attain a height of 2900 feet in the Great Feldberg, while to
                    the north of the Lahn is the barren Westerwald, culminating in the
                    Salzburgerkopf (2000 feet). The valleys and low-lying districts, especially the
                    Rheingau, are very fertile, producing abundance of grain, flax, hemp, and fruit;
                    but by far the most valuable product of the soil is its wine, which includes
                    several of the choicest Rhenish varieties (Johannisberger, Marcobrunner,
                    Assmannshauser, &amp;c.). Nassau is one of the most thickly wooded regions in
                    Germany, about 42 per cent, of its surface being occupied by forests, which
                    yield good timber and harbour large quantities of game. The rivers abound in
                    fish,—the salmon fisheries on the Rhine being especially important. There are
                    upwards of a hundred mineral springs in the district, most of which formerly
                    belonged to the duke, and afforded him a considerable part of his revenue. The
                    best-known are those of Wiesbaden, Ems, Soden, Schwalbach, Schlangenbad,
                    Geilnau, and Fachingen. The other mineral wealth of Nassau includes iron, lead,
                    copper, building <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n250/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0250-0239"/> stone, coals, slate, a little silver, and a bed
                    of malachite. Its manufactures, including cotton and woollen goods, are
                    unimportant, but a brisk trade is carried on by rail and river in wine, timber,
                    grain, and fruit. There are few places of importance besides the above-named
                    spas; Höchst is the only manufacturing town. Wiesbaden, with 50,238 inhabitants,
                    is the capital of the government district as it was of the duchy. In 1864 the
                    duchy contained 468,311 inhabitants, of whom 242,000 were Protestants (including
                    the reigning house), 215,000 Roman Catholics, and 7000 Jews. The ecclesiastical
                    jurisdiction was in the hands of the Protestant bishop of Wiesbaden and the
                    Roman Catholic bishop of Limburg. Education was amply provided for in numerous
                    higher and lower schools. The annual revenue of the dukedom was about 4,000,000
                    guldens (£400,000). It furnished a contingent of 6000 men to the army of the
                    German Confederation.</p>
                <p>During the Boman period the district enclosed by the Lahn, the Main, and the
                    Rhine was at first occupied by the Mattiaci and then by the Alemanni. The latter
                    were subdued by the Franks under Clovis in 496, and at the partition of Verdun
                    in 843 the country became part of the Eastern or German empire. Christianity
                    seems to have been introduced in the 4th century. The founder of the house of
                    Nassau is usually recognized in Count Otho of Laurenburg, brother of King Conrad
                    I., who flourished on the banks of the Lahn in the 10th century. His successors
                    afterwards took the title of counts of Nassau, from a castle which they erected
                    on a steep hill overlooking the Lahn, and in 1192 transferred their allegiance
                    from the archbishop of Treves to the emperor of Germany. In 1255 Walram and
                    Otho, the two sons of Count Henry the Rich, divided between them their paternal
                    inheritance, which had in the meantime been steadily increasing, and founded the
                    two Nassovian dynasties which have flourished down to our own times.</p>
                <p>The fortunes of the Othonian or younger branch have been the more brilliant, but
                    belong properly to the history of Holland. In 1564 Count William of Nassau, the
                    hero of the Dutch war of independence, succeeded to the principality of Orange,
                    which furnished the historical title of himself and his descendants. The house
                    is now represented by the king of the Netherlands.</p>
                <p>Adolf of Nassau, the son of the founder of the elder or Walram line, and
                    progenitor of the dukes of Nassau, became emperor of Germany in 1292, but was
                    defeated and slain in 1298 by his rival Albert of Austria. In 1366 the head of
                    the house was created a prince of the empire, and the Reformation was introduced
                    in the second half of the 16th century. The territories of the house of Walram
                    were frequently partitioned among various branch lines, few of which perpetuated
                    themselves beyond a few generations. At the beginning of the 19th century'we
                    find two lines still flourishing—Nassau-Ufingen and Nassau-Weilburg. Both these
                    joined the Rhenish Confederation in 1806, and the prince of Nassau-Ufingen, as
                    head of his family, received the ducal title from the hands of Napoleon. After
                    the battle of Leipsic both princes threw in their lot with the allies. In 1816
                    the duke of Nassau-Ufingen died, and the prince of Weilburg succeeded to the
                    whole of the Nassovian territory, with the title of duke of Nassau.</p>
                <p>This prince had already, in 1814, granted his subjects a limited constitution,
                    providing for two representative chambers on a landed-property basis, and this
                    came into force in 1818. The estates, however, came almost at once into
                    collision with the duke on the question of the ducal domains, and the
                    dissensions arising from this source were not compromised till 1834. In 1835 the
                    duchy took an important step in the development of its material prosperity by
                    joining the Zollverein. In 1848 Duke Adolf was compelled to yield to the temper
                    of the times and grant a more liberal constitution, with a single chamber
                    elected by universal suffrage; but the following years witnessed a series of
                    reactionary measures which reduced matters to their former unsatisfactory
                    condition. The duke adhered steadfastly to his Conservative principles, while
                    his people showed their sympathies by returning one Liberal chamber after
                    another. In 1866, though the chambers refused a vote of credit for military
                    purposes, the duke espoused the cause of Austria, and in doing so sealed the
                    fate of his duchy. A little later he was a fugitive before the Prussian troops,
                    and on October 3d, 1866, Nassau was formally incorporated with the kingdom of
                    Prussia.</p>
                <p>The little town of Nassau, on the right bank of the Lahn, 15 miles above Coblenz,
                    is interesting as the birthplace of the celebrated Prussian statesman, Baron
                    Stein. Adjacent are Burg Stein, his ancestral seat, and Burg Nassau, the cradle
                    of the Nassovian dukes. Nassau is said to have existed as early as the 8th
                    century under the name of Nasonga. Population (1880) 1786.</p>
                <p>See Schliepħake, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic">von
                    Nassau,</hi> 1866-76; Amoldi, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >von Nassau-Oranien; the Annals</hi> of the “Verein für Nassauische
                    Alterthumskunde nud Geschichtsforschung”; Daniel, <hi rend="italic">Handbuch der
                    Geographie,</hi> 5thed., 1881.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
