<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0513-0472-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NIAGARA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 472</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="14" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1156484">Tribes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:848897">Cataract</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:845200">Canadians</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:845196">Canadianisms</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="14" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g6z">Rocks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47659j0m">Descent</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj6q">Canadians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204832">Ontario</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204310">Canada</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n513/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NIAGARA</label>, a river in North America forming a portion
                    of the great lake and river system known as the <hi rend="smallcaps">St
                    Lawrence</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.v.'),</hi> flows northward from Lake Erie (573
                    feet above sea-level) to Lake Ontario, separating the State of New York from the
                    province of Ontario in Canada, and within the 33 miles of its course makes a
                    total descent of 328 feet. On issuing from Lake Erie the river is only about
                    three-fourths of a mile broad, and for the first two miles is somewhat swift; it
                    then divides and passes round Grand Island, broadens and assumes the
                    tranquillity of a lake until the commencement of the rapids, where it suddenly
                    narrows and makes a descent of about 52 feet in the mile before its hurried and
                    troubled waters are precipitated over a lofty chasm forming falls of unexampled
                    grandeur. The breadth of the river immediately before making the leap is 4750
                    feet, but the centre is occupied by Goat Island, rising about 40 feet above the
                    water, and occupying a breadth of about 1000 feet, a distance of about 1400 feet
                    separating it from the American side and about double that distance from the
                    Canadian side, while the length of the verge line between the island and the
                    Canadian side is moreover increased by an inward horseshoe curve. The height of
                    the fall on the American side is about 164 feet, and on the Canadian side about
                    150 feet; the discharge is about 18,000,000 cubic feet per minute. Tha waters
                    plunge into an abyss about 1000 feet wide, and during the next seven miles make
                    a descent of about 104 feet through a deep ravine with perpendicular banks
                    rising-to a height of from 200 to 350 feet, the breadth of the river varying
                    from 250 to 400 yards. Three miles below the great falls the whirlpool rapids
                    are formed by a sudden turn in the channel causing the waters to impinge against
                    the Canadian shore, where they have made a deep indentation, and to rush back to
                    the American side in a great whirl or eddy, rendered more furious by the uneven
                    bed of the river, and the narrow space into which it contracts. After issuing
                    from the gorge at Lewiston the river enters on a tranquil course, which
                    continues to Lake Ontario. The point where the gorge ceases marks the
                    termination of a table-land in an escarpment facing northwards; and it has been
                    generally held that the falls were situated here at the time when the river
                    first began to flow, that is, subsequently to the great Ice Age. Recent study
                    has suggested a much more complicated theory, making a great part of the gorge
                    older than the Ice Age, and thus reducing the period for which the modern river
                    has flowed from several hundred thousands of years to one-tenth of that time.
                    The rate of recession is very uncertain; while it would appear from the best
                    maps that some parts have receded at least 100 feet since 1841, others have
                    remained more or less· stationary. At the present site of the falls the edge of
                    the cataract is formed by strata of hard limestone reaching to a depth of about
                    80 feet; and by the action of the spray the softer shaly strata below have been
                    hollowed out so as to form the “Cave of Winds,” which may be entered from the
                    Canadian side. The river is crossed by a suspension bridge for foot passengers,
                    about 250 yards below tho falls, and a mile and a half farther down by two
                    railway bridges about a hundred yards apart,—one of which has a carriage way 18
                    feet below; the other, a cantilever bridge, completed in December 1883, carries
                    a double line of rails.</p>
                <p>The name Niagara (“thunder of waters”) is the invention of an Indian tribe who
                    adopted it as their own designation, from the fact that it was descriptive of
                    the remarkable natural phenomenon situated within their territory. This tribe,
                    on account of their peaceful proclivities, were also called the Neuter Nation;
                    but, to avoid <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n514/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0514-0473"/> the fury of the Iroquois, they finally joined
                    them in 1723 against the Hurons, and from this time they ceased to exist as a
                    separate tribe. The first printed allusion to the cataract is in the record of a
                    voyage by Jacques Cartier in 1535. Its position was first mentioned by Samuel
                    Champlain in a map attached to his voyages published in 1613. The earliest
                    description is that by Father Hennepin, who visited it in 1678, and published an
                    account of it accompanied with a sketch giving a view of a third fall on the
                    north side caused by the presence of a large rock on Table Rock. The rock and
                    cascade are mentioned by Kalm the Swedish naturalist, who visited Niagara in
                    1750, but they had disappeared a few years previously. Some writers indeed
                    mention as many as six falls, and there can at least be no doubt that within the
                    last two hundred years the aspect of the falls has been greatly altered. Goat
                    Island extended, up to a comparatively recent period, for about another half
                    mile northerly in a triangular prolongation; and the number of small islands was
                    perhaps larger than at present. Large masses fell in 1818, 1828, 1843, and 1847,
                    and in June 1850 Table Rock disappeared.</p>
                <p>See Sir Charles Lyell, <hi rend="italic">Travels in North America,</hi> 1845;
                    George W. Holley, <hi rend="italic">Niagara,</hi> 1880; paper by Professor
                    Tyndall on “Niagara” in <hi rend="italic">Macmillan’s Magazine,</hi> vol.
                    xxviii. (May 1873); paper by G. W. Holley in <hi rend="italic">Scribner's
                    Magazine</hi> (August 1876); Dr Julius Pohlmann, <hi rend="italic">Life History
                    of the Niagara River,</hi> 1883.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
