<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0371-0358-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NET</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 358</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40k055">Twine</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2cf8t">Nets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n87332f">Netting</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4pv6b75c">Rowing</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cr5nf24">Modeling</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1036191">Nets</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1036214">Netting</term>
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1159845">Twine</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1100781">Rowing</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1024369">Modeling</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n371/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NET</label>. A net consists of a fabric of thread, twine, or
                    cord, the intersections of which are firmly knotted so as to form meshes or
                    interspaces of fixed dimensions,—the meshes being usually lozenges of uniform
                    size. The art of netting is intimately related to weaving, knitting, plaiting,
                    and pillow-lace and machine-lace making, from all of which, however, it is
                    distinguished by the knotting of the intersections of the cord. It is one of the
                    most ancient and universal of arts, having been in all times commonly practised
                    among the rudest and most primitive tribes, to whom the net is of great
                    importance in hunting and fishing.</p>
                <p>Net-making, as a modern industry, is principally concerned with the manufacture
                    of the numerous forms of net used in fisheries, but netting is also largely
                    employed for many and varied purposes, as for catching game and birds, for the
                    temporary division of fields, for protecting fruit in gardens, for collecting
                    insects, for hammocks, and ship use, for screens and other furniture purposes,
                    for ladies’ hair, house bags, &amp;c. While to a large extent net-making
                    continues to be a handicraft, since the early part of the 19 th century numerous
                    forms of machine have been invented for netting, and several of these have been
                    successfully introduced on a large scale in factories for the manufacture Of
                    fishing nets. Such fishing nets were formerly made principally from hemp
                    fibre—technically called “twine”; but since the adaptation of machinery to
                    net-making cotton has been increasingly used. Cotton nets, being more flexible
                    and lighter than those made of twine, are much more easily handled and stowed,
                    and in practice they are rapidly superseding all others.</p>
                <p>The forms of fishing nets vary according to the manner in which they are intended
                    to act. This is either by entangling the fish in their complicated folds, as in
                    the trammel; receiving them into pockets, as in the trawl; suspending them by
                    the body in the meshes, as in the mackerel-net; imprisoning them within their
                    labyrinthlike chambers, as in the stake-net; or drawing them to shore, as in the
                    seine (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Fisheries,</hi> vol. ix. p. 247). The parts of a
                    net are the head or upper margin, along which the corks are strung upon a rope
                    called the head <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n372/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0372-0359"/> rope; the foot is the opposite or lower margin,
                    which carries the foot-rope, on which in many cases leaden plummets are made
                    fast. The meshes are the squares composing the net. The width of a net is
                    expressed by the term “over”; <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> a day-net is three
                    fathoms long and one over or wide. The lever is the first row of a net. There
                    are also accrues, false meshes, or quarterings, which are loops inserted in any
                    given row, by which the number of meshes is increased. To bread or breathe a net
                    is to make a net. Dead netting is a piece without either accrues or stole
                    (stolen) meshes, which last means that a mesh is taken away by netting into two
                    meshes of the preceding row at once.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Hand-Netting.—</hi> Net-making as a handicraft is a simple and
                    easily acquired art; the labour is not hard; and the implements and materials
                    are easily obtained and inexpensive, while a little practice in meshing is
                    sufficient to develop wonderful dexterity of movement. The tools used in netting
                    are the needle, an instrument for holding and netting the material; it is made
                    with an eye E, a tongue T, and a fork F (fig. 1). The twine is wound on it by
                    being passed alternately between the fork and round the tongue, so that the
                    turns of the string lie parallel to the length of the needle, and are kept on by
                    the tongue and fork. A spool or mesh-pin is a piece of wood on which the loops
                    are formed (round, as in fig. 2, or flat, as in fig. 3), the circumference or
                    the spool determining the size of the loops. Each loop contains two sides of the
                    square mesh; therefore, supposing that it be required to <hi rend="subscript"> 1
                    o</hi> — „</p>
                <p>make a mesh 1 inch square,-that is, <hi rend="superscript"> f</hi> ⅛∙ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> * <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> ⅛ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> r</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ∙ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> Flg</hi> ' <hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∙</p>
                <p>measuring 1 inch from knot to knot,—a spool 2 inches in circumference must be
                    used. Large meshes may be formed by giving the twine two or more turns round the
                    spool, as occasionmayrequire; or the spool may be made flat, and of a sufficient
                    width, having a portion cut away to admit the finger and thumb to grasp it
                    conveniently (fig. 3). The method of making the hand-knot in pets known as the
                    fisherman’s knot is more easily acquired by example than described in writing.
                    Fig. 4 shows the course of the twine in forming a single knot. From the
                    last-formed knot the twine passes over the front of the mesh-pin <hi
                    rend="italic">h,</hi> and is caught behind by the little finger of the left
                    hand, forming the loop <hi rend="italic">s,</hi> thence it passes to the front
                    and is caught at <hi rend="italic">d</hi> by the left thumb, then through the
                    loops s and <hi rend="italic">m</hi> as indicated, after which the twine is
                    released by the thumb and the knot is drawn ’ ‘ taut” or tight. Fig. 5 shows the
                    form of the fisherman s knot, and fig. 6 is a bend knot used for uniting two
                    ends of twine.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Machine-Netting.—</hi> So long ago as 1778 a netting-machine
                    was patented by William Horton, William Ross, Thomas Davies, and John Golby.
                    From that time till the end of the 18th century several other patents for
                    similar· machines were secured in Great Britain, but there is no evidence that
                    any of them was practically successful. In 1802 the French Government, through
                    the Société d’Encouragement pour ΓIndustrie Nationale, offered a reward of
                    10,000 francs to the person who should invent an automatic machine for
                    net-making. The reward attracted the attention of Jacquard, who submitted a
                    model of a machine which was brought under the notice of Napoleon I. and Carnot.
                    Jacquard was summoned to Paris by the emperor, who, with forcible if profane
                    point, asked of the inventor—“Are you the man who pretends to do what God
                    Almighty cannot—tie a knot in a stretched string ?” Jacquard’s model, which is
                    incomplete, was deposited in the Conservatoire des Arts et Métiers; it was
                    awarded a prize, and he himself received an appointment in the Conservatoire,
                    where he was not long in peι ’ fecting his famous Jacquard attachment to the
                    common loom. In 1806 Μ. Buron of Bourgthéroulde (Eure) submitted to the Société
                    d’Encouragement a model of a netting-machine for which he was awarded a gold
                    medal. His model is also deposited in the Conservatoire. Meantime attention
                    continued to be given to the problem in the United Kingdom, and the first to
                    succeed practically in inventing an efficient machine and in establishing the
                    industry of machine net-making was Mr James Paterson of Musselburgh. Paterson,
                    originally a cooper, served in the army through the Peninsular war, and was
                    discharged after the battle of Waterloo. From his early days he had devoted his
                    mind to the invention of a net-making machine, and on his retirement from the
                    army he set himself to carry out his purpose. After much labour he succeeded,
                    and established a machine net factory in Musselburgh about 1820. The early form
                    of machine was, however, imperfect, the knots it formed slipped readily, and,
                    there being much prejudice against machine nets, the demand for his manufactures
                    was small. Mr Walter Ritchie, a native of Musselburgh, devised a method for
                    forming the ordinary hand-knot on the machine nets, and the machine, so
                    improved, and patented in July 1835, became the foundation of an extensive and
                    flourishing industry. Paterson’s factory about 1849 passed into the hands of
                    Messrs J. &amp; W. Stuart, by whom the machine and processes have been still
                    further developed and perfected.</p>
                <p>The mechanism of the Paterson net-loom or machine is complex, and not to be
                    understood without elaborate diagrams or actual inspection. It consists of an
                    arrangement of hooks, needles, and sinkers, one of each being required for every
                    mesh in the breadth being made. The needles hold the meshes, while the hooks
                    seize the lower part of each and twist it into a loop. Through the series of
                    loops so formed a steel wire is shot, carrying with it twine for the next range
                    of loops. This twine the sinkers successively catch and depress sufficiently to
                    form the two sides and loop of the next mesh to be formed. The knot formed by
                    threading the loops is now tightened up, the last formed mesh is freed from the
                    sinkers and transferred to the hooks, and the process of looping, threading, and
                    knotting thus continues.</p>
                <p>Another form of efficient net-loom, working on a principle distinct from that of
                    Paterson, was invented and patented in France by Μ. Onésiphore Pecqueur in 1840,
                    and again in France and in the United Kingdom in 1849. The machine of Pecqueur
                    was improved on by many subsequent inventors; and especially the additions made
                    by MM. Baudouin and Jouannin, patented in the United Kingdom in 1861, greatly
                    perfected its principle. In this machine separate threads or cords running
                    longitudinally for each division of the mesh are employed, as will be seen from
                    fig. 7, which represents a section of the net with the knots loose to show their
                    structure. It will also be observed that the alternate threads <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi> and <hi rend="italic">b</hi> are differently disposed—the <hi
                    rend="italic">a</hi> series being drawn into simple loops over and through which
                    the threads of the <hi rend="italic">b</hi> series have to pass. On the machine
                    the <hi rend="italic">a</hi> series of threads are arranged vertically, while
                    the <hi rend="italic">b</hi> series are placed horizontally in thin lenticular
                    spools. Over the horizontal <hi rend="italic">b</hi> series is a range of hooks
                    equal in number with the threads, and set so that they seize the <hi
                    rend="italic">b</hi> threads, raise them, and give them a double twist, thus
                    forming a row of open loops. The loops are then depressed, and, seizing the
                    vertical <hi rend="italic">a</hi> threads, draw them crotchet-like through the
                    <hi rend="italic">b</hi> loops into loops sufficiently long and open to pass
                    right over the spools containing the <hi rend="italic">b</hi> threads (fig. 8),
                    after which it only remains to tighten the threads and the mesh is complete. The
                    machines work well λvith steam-power; and each requires only one female
                    attendant.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Bobbin Net,</hi> which is the foundation of machine-made lace,
                    is made by the intertwisting—not knotting—of contiguous threads (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Lace,</hi> vol. xiv. p. 185).</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n373/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0373-0360"/>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Wire-netting,</hi> which is in extensive demand for garden use,
                    poultry coops, and numerous like purposes, is also a twisted structure made
                    principally by machine power. The chief centre of wire-net making is Warrington
                    in Lancashire. (J. PA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
