<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0917-0661-0604-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">NOVA ZEMBLA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 17, page 604</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="25" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1039481">Norwegians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="25" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4dr2p79d">Land</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n661/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NOVA ZEMBLA</label>, or, more correctly, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Novaya Zemlya</hi><hi rend="italic">(i.e.,</hi> “New Land”), is a large island,
                    surrounded by many small ones, situated in the <hi rend="smallcaps">Arctic
                    Ocean</hi> (see vol. ii., plate xxvi.), and belonging to the Russian empire. It
                    lies between 70° 30' and 77° N. lat. and between 52“ and 69° E. long., in the
                    shape of an elongated crescent 600 miles in length, with an average width of 60
                    miles, and an estimated area of 40,000 square miles, separating the Kara Sea on
                    the east from that part of the Arctic Ocean which is often called Barents’s Sea.
                    The north-eastern extremity of Novaya Zemlya lies a little to the west of the
                    meridian of the peninsula of Yalmal, from the extremity of which it is only 160
                    miles distant. Its southern part, bending towards the south-east, appears as a
                    continuation of the Vaigatch (Vaygach) Island, from which it is separated by the
                    Kara Strait, 30 miles in width,—the island itself being separated from the
                    continent by the narrow Ugrian Strait, only 7 miles broad. Novaya Zemlya is cut
                    through about the middle by a narrow winding channel, the Matotchkin (Matochkin)
                    Shar, which also connects the Arctic Ocean with the Kara Sea.</p>
                <p>While the eastern coast runs as a regular curve, with deeper indentations only in
                    its middle, the western is deeply indented by numerous and in some cases
                    fjord-like bays, studded, like the rest of the coast, with many islands. Amongst
                    the principal on the western coast are several parallel fjords at the southern
                    extremity and the wide bay of Sakhanikha. Then farther north is the Kostin Shar,
                    bounded on the north by Cape Podrezoff, which forms the southern extremity of
                    Gusinaya Zemlya or Goose Land, in 72“ N. lat.; Möller Bay, 40 miles wide,
                    between Goose Land and Britvin Promontory, has several fjord-like bays, with
                    good anchorages. A broad indentation between Britvin and Sukhoi Nos
                    Promontories, which has received the general name of Marquis de Traversé Bay,
                    includes several bays with good anchorages for larger vessels. Several other
                    large and deep bays follow until Admiralty Peninsula (75° N. lat.) is reached;
                    of these the chief are Krestovaya and Mashigin. Farther on, Nordenskjöld’s Bay
                    is worthy of notice.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Orography and Geology.—</hi> The interior of Novaya Zemlya is
                    almost unknown; still, the broad features of its structure can be inferred from
                    data obtained at various points on the coast. Two orographical regions must be
                    distinguished. The first of these, south of lat. 72°, appearing as a
                    continuation of the Pay-Kho mountains, is a plateau of moderate height, with
                    several low parallel ridges (2000 feet) running north-west, and separated by
                    level valleys dotted with numerous lakes. It consists of gneisses and
                    clay-slates, with layers of augitic porphyry (north of Kostin Shar), and thick
                    beds of Silurian and perhaps Devonian limestones, continued on Vaigatch Island,
                    where they are partially covered with Carboniferous deposits. On the north-west
                    it terminates in the low plateau (300 to 400 feet) of Goose Land. The middle and
                    northern parts of Novaya Zemlya, on the other hand, form an alpine region with
                    isolated peaks and a complicated system of spurs and deep valleys, extending
                    even under the sea. Instead of being, as it has been frequently described, a
                    single chain running in the main direction of the island closer to its western
                    coast, it appears to be rather a system of shorter chains running due
                    north-east, and disposed in échelons displaced eastwards as they advance towards
                    the north. They terminate seawards in several promontories having the same
                    direction; but the difference of the geological structure on the two sides of
                    the Matotchkin Shar would suggest that it is rather a combination of two
                    longitudinal valleys connected by a transverse cleft than one transverse valley.
                    The highest parts of the alpine region (the Mitusheff Kamen, 3200 feet; Wilczek,
                    3900 feet; and other peaks to the west rising perhaps to 4000 and 4650 feet) are
                    in the neighbourhood of this channel; south of the eastern entrance<pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n662/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0662-0605"/> is a peak about 5000 feet in height. Farther
                    north the region sinks much lower, while that part of northern Novaya Zenιlya
                    which bends eastward seems to consist of a more massive swelling of land,
                    covered with an immense ice-sheet descending north and south to the sea-coast.
                    The whole of the alpine region is covered with fields of snow descending in
                    broad strips along the slopes of the isolated peaks, and feeding glaciers in the
                    deeper valleys.</p>
                <p>The geological structure of the central region is of the most varied description.
                    The primary rocks which appear at Mitusheff Kamen are overlaid with thick beds
                    of quartzites and clay-slates containing sulphite of iron, -with subordinate
                    layers of talc or mica slate, and thinner beds of fossiliferous limestone,
                    Silurian or Devonian. More recent clay-slates and marls belonging to the middle
                    Jurassic occur in the western coast-region about Matotchkin Shar. About 74° N.
                    lat. the crags of the eastern coast are composed of grey sandstone, while in 76°
                    Barents’s Islands, and possibly a much greater part of the northern coast, show
                    Carboniferous strata. Traces of Eocene deposits, produced under a warmer
                    climate, which are so widely developed in other parts of the polar basin, have
                    not yet been discovered on Novaya Zemlya. During the Glacial period its glaciers
                    were much larger than at present, whilst during a later portion of the
                    Quaternary period (to judge by the marine fossils found as high as 300 feet
                    above the sea) Novaya Zemlya, like the whole of the arctic coast of Russia, was
                    submerged for several hundred feet. At present it appears to partake of the
                    movement of upheaval common to the whole of northern Russia.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Climate.—</hi> Though milder than that of north-eastern
                    Siberia, the climate of Novaya Zemlya is colder even than that of Spitzbergen.
                    The average temperature about the Matotchkin Shar has been found from three
                    years’ observations to be 17° Fahr., and it decreases towards the south, being
                    only 14 <hi rend="superscript"> o-</hi> 9 at Kamenka (70° 35' N.). At Shallow
                    Bay, in 73° 55', it has been found to be 19 <hi rend="superscript"> o,</hi> 6.
                    In the middle parts of the western coast the average temperature of the winter
                    is - 4°; that of the summer at Matotchkin Shar is 36 <hi rend="superscript">
                    o-</hi> 5,— that is, lower than at Boothia Felix, or Melville Island. On the
                    western coast also warm west winds bring considerable moisture, which is
                    condensed by the mountains, and thus a cloudy sky intercepts the already scanty
                    sunlight. On the eastern coast the summer temperature is less still, the average
                    for the year being probably 2° Fahr, lower than that of corresponding latitudes
                    of the western coast. The coasts of Novaya Zemlya are less icebound than might
                    be supposed owing to the influence of a warm current which flows along the coast
                    on the north-west, and which may be considered as a continuation of the Gulf
                    Stream. There are years in which the island can be circumnavigated without
                    difficulty. The southern shores, besides experiencing the cold influence of the
                    Kara Sea, are washed by a cold current which issues from Kara Strait and flows
                    northwards along the south-western coast.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Flora.—</hi> Grass does not grow to any extent except in Goose
                    Land, where the soil is covered with finer débris. Elsewhere even the leaved
                    lichens are precarious, though the leather lichens flourish, especially the <hi
                    rend="italic">Vermicaria</hi><hi rend="italic">geographia.</hi> Of Phanerogams,
                    only the <hi rend="italic">Dryas</hi><hi rend="italic">octopetala</hi> covers
                    small areas of the débris, ami is interspersed with isolated <hi rend="italic"
                    >Cochlearia,</hi><hi rend="italic">Stereocaulon</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >paschale,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Papaver</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >nudicaule.</hi><hi rend="italic">Silene</hi><hi rend="italic">acaulis,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Saxifraga</hi><hi rend="italic">oppositifolia,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Arenaria</hi><hi rend="italic">rubella,</hi> five or six species
                    of <hi rend="italic">Draba,</hi> as well as the <hi rend="italic">Dryas</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">octopctala</hi> ami <hi rend="italic">Myosotis,</hi> are found
                    where the débris permits. Where a layer of thinner clay has been deposited in
                    sheltered places, the surface is covered with <hi rend="italic"
                    >Platypetalum</hi><hi rend="italic">purpurascens,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Saxifragae,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Draba alpina</hi>; and a carpet of
                    mosses allows the <hi rend="italic">Salix</hi><hi rend="italic">polaris</hi> to
                    develop its two dwarf leaflets and its catkins. Where a thin sheet of humus,
                    fertilized by lemmings, has accumulated in the course of ages, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Rhodiola rosea,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Erigon uniflorum,</hi>
                    a <hi rend="italic">Ranunculus nivalis,</hi> or an <hi rend="italic"
                    >Oxyria</hi><hi rend="italic">reniformis</hi> make their appearance, with here
                    and there a <hi rend="italic">Vaccinium</hi> (which, however, never flowers).
                    Even where a carpet of plants has developed under specially favourable
                    circumstances, they do not dare raise their stems more than a few inches, and
                    their brilliant flowers spring direct from the soil, concealing the developed
                    leaflets, whilst their horizontally-spread roots grow out of proportion; only
                    the <hi rend="italic">Salix</hi><hi rend="italic">lanata</hi> rises to 7 or 8
                    inches, sending out roots 1 inch thick and 10.to 12 feet long. One hardly
                    understands how these plants propagate; vegetation seems to be maintained, at
                    least partially, by seeds brought by birds or by currents. All this, of course,
                    applies only to the better-known neighbourhoods of Matotchkin and Kostin
                    Straits; north of 74° N. but veιy few species have been found at all <hi
                    rend="italic">{Saxifraga oppositifolia,</hi><hi rend="italic">1 apaver
                    nudicaule, Draba alpina,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Oxyria digyna).</hi> In all,
                    the phanerogamic flora of Novaya Zemlya and Vaigatch now numbers 185 species, of
                    which 30 have not yet been found on the main island, but may yet be discovered
                    in its southern part. Of the total, 131 are Dicotyledons. As to the
                    much-discussed genetic connexions of the Novaya Zemlya flora, it appears,
                    according to Μ. Kjellmann <hi rend="superscript"> ,</hi> s researches, that it
                    belongs to the Asiatic arctic region rather than to the European. Eleven species
                    are what Hooker and Grisebach regard as old glacial, 56 are purely alpine, and 6
                    have been found in other alpine regions of Europe; 36 non-alpine species belong
                    to the flora of middle Europe, 41 to’ the Scandinavian flora, and only 16 to
                    that of arctic Russia, whilst 29 have not been found in Europe at all.
                    Altogether, 156 species are European (132 from arctic Europe), and 177 Asiatic
                    (164 from arctic Asia), whilst 11 are wanting in both arctic Europe and
                    Asia.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Fauna.—</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Υ∖∖q</hi> desolate
                    interior of Novaya Zemlya shows hardly a trace of animal life, save perchance a
                    solitary vagrant bird, a few lemmings, an ice-fox, a brown or λvhite bear, and
                    at times immigrant reindeer. Even insects are few; the very mosquitoes of the
                    tundras are wanting, and only a solitary bee flies among the scanty flowers. The
                    sea-coast, however, is occupied by countless numbers of birds, which come from
                    the south for the breeding season, and at certain parts of the sea-coast the
                    rocks are covered with millions of <hi rend="italic">Uria troile,</hi> and the
                    air is resonant with their cries, while numberless flocks of ducks, geese, and
                    swans swarm every summer on the valleys and lakes of the southern part of the
                    island. Whales, walruses, seals, and dolphins are still abundant. Only two
                    species of fish are of any importance,—the <hi rend="italic">goltzy</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(Salmo</hi><hi rend="italic">alpinus)</hi> in the western rivers,
                    and the <hi rend="italic">omul</hi><hi rend="italic">(Salmo</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">omul)</hi> in the eastern.</p>
                <p>The following is a list of the land mammals (some of them not satisfactorily
                    determined) :— <hi rend="italic">Ursus arctos</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >maritimus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Rangifer tarandus</hi> (Pallas), <hi
                    rend="italic">Vulpes</hi><hi rend="italic">vulgaris</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >lagopus,</hi><hi rend="italic">Canis</hi><hi rend="italic">lupus,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Cuniculus torquatus</hi> (Pallas), perhaps <hi rend="italic">Mus
                    groenlandica,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Myodeg obensis.</hi> The birds are <hi
                    rend="italic">∙.-Stryx nictca, Falco</hi><hi rend="italic">buteo,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Tringa</hi><hi rend="italic">maritima,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Plectroρhanes nivalis, Otocorys alpestris,</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Strepsilas</hi><hi rend="italic">collaris,</hi> all endemic; many species of
                    ducks, <hi rend="italic">Harelda</hi><hi rend="italic">glacialis</hi> being the
                    most common, <hi rend="italic">Somateria</hi><hi rend="italic">spectabilis</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">mollissima</hi> in company with the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ccρhus Mandtii</hi>; several species of geese and swans <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Cygnus</hi><hi rend="italic">musicus</hi> included); as also <hi rend="italic"
                    >Larus glaucus, Uria</hi><hi rend="italic">troile, U. bruen-nichii,</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Alca ptetorhina.</hi> The marine mammals are :—the walrus, <hi
                    rend="italic">Odobaenus</hi><hi rend="italic">rosmarus</hi>; seals, <hi
                    rend="italic">Phoca vitulina,</hi><hi rend="italic">P.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >leporina,</hi><hi rend="italic">P. groenlandica</hi> (O. Müller) in the Kara
                    Sea, <hi rend="italic">P. barbata</hi> (?); and dolphins, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Delphinus Orca</hi> and <hi rend="italic">D.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >delphis</hi><hi rend="italic">(I).</hi></p>
                <p>The numbers of sea mammals in the sea around Novaya Zemlya and the vast
                    quantities of birds attracted Russian hunters as soon as they became acquainted
                    with the northern Ural, and even in the 16th century they had extended their
                    huts <hi rend="italic">(stanovishtcha)</hi> to the extreme north of the island.
                    Many of them wintered for several consecutive years on Novaya Zemlya without
                    suffering great losses from scurvy; but no inhabitants have ever tried to
                    establish themselves permanently on the island. The hunters were very often
                    extremely successful; but the industry has always been subject to great
                    vicissitudes. During the last twenty-five years the Archangel and Kola hunters
                    have but rarely visited Novaya Zemlya; on the other hand, both it and the Kara
                    Sea are now more and more visited by Norwegians. A few Samoyede families,
                    recently settled by the Russian Government at Karmakuly, have remained there for
                    several consecutive years, living chiefly by hunting the reindeer which abound
                    on the eastern coast, and of which two varieties are distinguished, one like
                    that of Spitzbergen.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> Novaya Zemlya seems to have been known to
                    Novgorod hunters in the 11th century; but its geographical discovery was four
                    centuries later, at the time of the great movement for the discovery of the
                    north-eastern passage. In 1553 Sir Hugh Willoughby sighted what was probably
                    Goose Land; Chancellor penetrated into the White Sea. In 1556 Burrough reached
                    the southern extremity of the island (the first western European to do so).
                    William Barents touched the island (1594) at Sukhoi Nos (73° 46'), and followed
                    the coast northward to the Orange Islands and southward to the Kostin Shar.
                    Rumours of silver ore having been found induced the Russian Government to send
                    out expeditions to the island during the second half of the 18th century. Y
                    ushkoff visited it in 1757; and in 1760 Savva Loshkin cruised along all the
                    eastern coast, spent two winters there, and in the next year, after having
                    reached Cape Begehrte (Begheerte), returned along the western coast, thus
                    accomplishing the first circumnavigation; but the valuable records of his voyage
                    in Russian archives have been lost. In 1768 Rozmysloff reached Goose Land and
                    penetrated into the Kara Sea by the Matotchkin Shar, where he spent the winter;
                    in the following year he pursued the exploration of the Kara Sea, but was
                    compelled to return and abandon his ship. Pospeloff investigated the alleged
                    discovery of silver at Silver Bay in 1806. The first real scientific information
                    about the island is due to the expeditions of Count Lütke in 1821, 1822, 1823,
                    and 1824. Nearly the whole of the western coast as far as Cape Nassau, as well
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit17newyrich/page/n663/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0917-0663-0606"/> as the Matotchkin channel, was visited and mapped
                    during these expeditions, and abundance of most valuable scientific information
                    obtained. In 1832 Pakhtusoff mapped the eastern coast as far as Matotchkin Shar;
                    and in 1835 Pakhtusoff and Tsivolka mapped the coast as far as 74° 24'. The next
                    expedition was that of Karl Baer in 1838, whose matchless descriptions still are
                    the most valuable of all our sources of information about this region.</p>
                <p>À new era of scientific exploration of Novaya Zemlya and of the neighbouring seas
                    begins in 1868. The measurements of temperature made in that year by Bessels and
                    by Dufferin between Bear Island and Novaya Zemlya, and partly those made by
                    Yarjinsky in his dredgings off the Murman coast, established the existence of a
                    warm current crossing Barents’s Sea, and led to the publication of Petermann’s
                    remarkable treatise on the Gulf Stream. The existence of the warm current was
                    further confirmed by the measurements of Yarjinsky in 1869, by Maydell and
                    Middendorff in 1871, and by the more recent and closer investigations of
                    And-reeff in 1880-82. On the other side, since 1868 the Norwegian sea-hunters,
                    availing themselves of the suggestions of Mohn, Nordenskjöld, and Petermann,
                    have brought in most valuable geographical information. In 1870 Johannesen
                    penetrated as far east as 79° E. long., in 76° 13' N. lat., and afterwards
                    accomplished the second circumnavigation of Novaya Zemlya. The measurements of
                    Johannesen, Ulve, Mack, Torkildsen, Qvale, and Nedrevaag enabled the first map
                    of the Kara Sea worthy of the name, as also of northern Novaya Zemlya, to be
                    drawn up. These and subsequent explorations led the way for Nordenskjold’s
                    famous voyages (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Polar Regions). Two</hi> recent
                    undertakings must be mentioned, however,—the establishment of a permanent
                    station on Novaya Zemlya, the wintering at Karmakuly of Lieutenant Tyaghin, and
                    the crossing of the island in 1878 by Μ. Grinevetskiy from Karmakuly to the
                    eastern coast; and the last Dutch expedition of the “Dijmphna,” which, along
                    with the steamer “Varna,” wintered in the Kara Sea. (P. A. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
