<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0524-0501-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MANTEGNA, Andrea (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    501)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93k3f">Madonna</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g68c">Virginal</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44m91m0x">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wd3q15g">Angels</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1747280">Virgins</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1167649">Virginity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:808746">Angels</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n524/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MANTEGNA, <hi rend="smallcaps">Andrea</hi></label>
                    (1431-1506), one of the chief heroes in the advance of painting in Italy, was
                    born in or near Padua, of very humble parentage. It is said that in his earliest
                    boyhood Andrea was, like Giotto, put to shepherding or cattle-herding; but this
                    can have lasted only a very short while, as his natural genius for art developed
                    with singular precocity, and excited the attention of Francesco Squarcione, who
                    entered him in the guild of painters before he had completed his eleventh
                    year.</p>
                <p>Squarcione, whose original vocation was tailoring, appears to have had a
                    remarkable enthusiasm for ancient art, and a proportionate faculty for acting,
                    with profit to himself and others, as a sort of artistic middleman; his own
                    performances as a painter were merely mediocre. He travelled in Italy, and
                    perhaps in Greece also, collecting antique statues, reliefs, vases, &lt;fcc.,
                    forming the largest collection then extant of such works, making drawings from
                    them himself, and throwing open his stores for others to study from, and then
                    undertaking works on commission for which his pupils no less than himself were
                    made available. As many as one hundred and thirty-seven painters and pictorial
                    students passed through his school, established towards 1440, which became
                    famous all over Italy. Mantegna was, as he deserved to be, Squarcione’s
                    favourite pupil. Squarcione adopted him as his son, and purposed making him the
                    heir of his fortune. Andrea was only seventeen when he painted, in the church of
                    St Sophia in Padua, a Madonna picture of exceptional and recognized excellence.
                    He was no doubt fully aware of having achieved no common feat, as he marked the
                    w*ork with his name and the date, and the years of his age. This painting was
                    destroyed in the 17th century.</p>
                <p>The affectionate relation between Squarcione and Mantegna was not destined to
                    continue long. As the youth progressed in his studies, he came under the
                    influence of Jacopo Bellini, a painter considerably superior to Squarcione,
                    father of the celebrated painters Giovanni and Gentile, and of a daughter
                    Niccolosia; and at some date, which may have been towards 1450, Jacopo gave
                    Niccolosia to Andrea in marriage. This connexion of Andrea with the pictorial
                    rival of Squarcione is generally assigned as the reason why the latter became
                    alienated from the son of his adoption, and always afterwards hostile to him.
                    Another suggestion, which rests, however, merely on its own internal
                    probability, is that Squarcione had at the outset used his pupil Andrea as the
                    unavowed executant of certain commissions, but that after a while Andrea began
                    painting on his own account, thus injuring the professional interests of his
                    chief, and incurring his animosity. The remarkably definite and original style
                    formed by Mantegna may be traced out as founded on the study of the antique in
                    Squarcione’s atelier, followed by a diligent application &lt;&gt;f principles of
                    work exemplified by Paolo Uccello and Donatello, with the practical guidance and
                    example of Jacopo Bellini in the sequel.</p>
                <p>Among the other early works of Mantegna are the fresco of two saints over the
                    entrance-porch of the church of S.</p>
                <p>Antonio in Padua, 1452, and an altarpiece of St Luke and other saints for the
                    church of St Justina, now in the Brera Gallery in Milan, 1453. It is probable,
                    however, that before this time some of the pupils of Squarcione, including
                    Mantegna, had already begun that series of frescos in the chapel of St
                    Christopher, in the church of S. Agostino degli Eremitani, by which the great
                    painter’s reputation was fully confirmed, and which remain to this day
                    conspicuous among his finest achievements.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>His fellow-workers were Bono of Ferrara, Ansuino of Forli,
                    and Niccolo Pizzolo, to whom considerable sections of the fresco-paintings are
                    to be assigned. The acts of St James and St Christopher are the leading subjects
                    of the series. St James Exorcising may have been commenced by Pizzolo, and
                    completed by Mantegna. The Calling of St James to the Apostleship appears to be
                    Mantegna’s design, partially carried out by Pizzolo; the subjects of St James
                    baptizing, his appearing before the judge, and going to execution, and most of
                    the legend of St Christopher, are entirely by Mantegna.</p></note> The now
                    censorious Squarcione found much to carp at in the earlier works of this series,
                    illustrating the life of St James; he said the figures were like men of stone,
                    and had better have been coloured stone-colour at once. Andrea, conscious as he
                    was of his great faculty and mastery, and of the transcendent display he had
                    here made of these, seems nevertheless to have felt that there was something in
                    his old preceptor’s strictures; and the later subjects, from the legend of St
                    Christopher, combine with his other excellences more of natural character and
                    vivacity. Trained as he had been in the study of marbles and the severity of the
                    antique, and openly avowing that he considered the antique superior to nature as
                    being more eclectic in form, he now and always affected precision of outline,
                    dignity of idea and of figure, and he thus tended towards rigidity, and to an
                    austere wholeness rather than gracious sensitiveness of expression. His
                    draperies are tight and closely folded, being studied (as it is said) from
                    models draped in paper and woven fabrics gummed. Figures slim, muscular, and
                    bony, action impetuous but of arrested energy, tawny landscape, gritty with
                    littering pebbles, mark the athletic hauteur of his style. He never changed,
                    though he developed and perfected, the manner which he had adopted in Padua; his
                    colouring, at first rather neutral and undecided, strengthened and matured.
                    There is throughout his works more balancing of colour than fineness of tone.
                    One of his great aims was optical illusion, which he carried out by a mastery of
                    perspective that, though not always impeccably correct, nor absolutely superior
                    in principle to the highest contemporary point of attainment, was worked out by
                    himself with strenuous labour, and an effect of actuality astonishing in those
                    times.</p>
                <p>Successful and admired though he was in Padua, Mantegna left his native city at
                    an early age, and never afterwards resettled there; the hostility of Squarcione
                    has been assigned as the cause. The rest of his life was passed in Verona,
                    Mantua, and Rome—chiefly Mantua; Venice and Florence have also been named, but
                    without confirmation.</p>
                <p>It may have been in 1459 that he went to Verona; and he painted, though not on
                    the spot, a grand altarpiece for the church of S. Zenon, a Madonna and angels,
                    with four saints on each side. The Marquis Lodovico Gonzaga of Mantua had for
                    some time been pressing Mantegna to enter his service; and the following year,
                    1460, was perhaps the one in which he actually established himself at the
                    Mantuan court, residing at first from time to time at Goit∩, but, from December
                    1466 onwards, with his family in Mantua itself. His engagement was for a salary
                    of 75 lire (about £30) a month, a sum so large for that period as to mark
                    conspicuously the high regard in which his art was held. He was in fact the
                    first painter of any eminence <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n525/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0525-0502"/> ever domiciled in Mantua. He built a stately
                    house in the city, and adorned it with a multitude of paintings. The house
                    remains, but the pictures have perished. Some of his early Mantuan works are in
                    that apartment of the Castello which is termed the Camera degli Sposi,—full
                    compositions in fresco, including various portraits of the G mzaga family, and
                    some figures of genii, &lt;tc. In 1488 he went to Rome at the request of Pope
                    Innocent VIII., to paint the frescos in the chapel of the Belvedere in the
                    Vatican; the duke of Mantua created him a cavalière before his departure. This
                    series of frescos, including a noted Baptism of Christ, was ruthlessly destroyed
                    by Pius VI. in laying out the Museo Pio-Clementino. The pope treated Mantegna
                    with less liberality than he had been used to at the Mantuan court; but on the
                    whole their connexion, which ceased in 1490, was not unsatisfactory to either
                    party. Mantegna then returned to Mantua, and went on with a series of works—the
                    nine tempera-pictures, each of them 9 feet square, of the Triumph of
                    Caesar—which he had probably begun before his leaving for Rome, and which are
                    now in Hampton Court. These superbly invented and designed compositions,
                    gorgeous with all splendour of subject-matter and accessory, and with the
                    classical learning and enthusiasm of one of the masterspirits of the age, have
                    always been accounted of the first ruιk among Mantegna’s works. They were sold
                    in 1G28 along with the bulk of the Mantuan art treasures, and were not, as is
                    commonly said, plundered in the sack of Mantua in 1G3O. They are now greatly
                    damaged by patchy repaintings. Another work of Mantegna’s later years was the
                    so-called Madonna della Vittoria, now in the Louvre. It was painted in tempera
                    about 1495, in commemoration of the battle of Fornovo, which Gonzaga found it
                    convenient to represent to his lieges as an Italian victory, though in fact it
                    had been a French victory; the church which originally housed the picture was
                    built from Mantegna’s own design. The Madonna is here depicted with various
                    saints, the archangel Michael and St Maurice holding her mantle, which is
                    extended over the kneeling Γrancesco Gonzaga, amid a profusion of rich
                    festooning and other accessory. Though not in all respects of his highest order
                    of execution, this counts among the most obviously beautiful and attractive of
                    Mantegna’s works,— from which it must be said that the qualities of beauty and
                    attraction are often excluded, in the stringent pursuit of those other
                    excellences more germane to his severe genius, tense energy passing into haggard
                    passion.</p>
                <p>Vasari eulogizes Mantegna for his courteous, distinguished, and praiseworthy
                    deportment, although there are indications of his having been not a little
                    litigious in disposition. With his fellow-pupils at Padua he had been
                    affectionate; and fortwoof them, Dario da Trevigi and Μ ιrco Zoppo, he retained
                    a steady friendship. That he had a high opinion of himself was natural, for no
                    artist of his epoch could produce more manifest vouchers of high and progressive
                    attainment. He became very expensive in his habits, fell at times into
                    difficulties, and bad to urge his valid claims upon the duke’s attention. After
                    his return to Mantua from Rome his prosperity was at its height, until the death
                    of his wife. He then formed some other connexion, and became at an advanced age
                    the father of a natural son, Giovanni Andrea; and at the last, although he
                    continued launching out into various expenses and schemes, he had serious
                    tribulations, such as the banishment from Mantua of his son Francesco, who had
                    incurred the duke’s displeasure. Perhaps the aged master and connoisseur
                    regarded as barely less trying the hard necessity of parting with a beloved
                    antique bust of Faustina. Very soon after this transaction he died in Mantua, on
                    13th September 150G In 1517 a handsome monument was set up to him by his sons in
                    the church of S. Andrea, where he had painted the altarpiece of the mortuary
                    chapel.</p>
                <p>We have spoken as yet of Mantegna as a painter and architect; he was no less
                    eminent as an engraver, and is reported to have been a sculptor and poet as
                    well, though we arc not aware that any verses of his are extant, or that his
                    sculptural practice extended beyond making a drawing for a statue of Virgil. As
                    an engraver his history is somewhat obscure, partly because he never signed or
                    dated any of his plates, unless in one single disputed instance, 1472. The
                    account which has come down to us is that Mantegna began engraving in Borne,
                    prompted by the engravings produced by Ba&lt;∙cio Baldini of Florence after
                    Sandro Botticelli; nor is there anything positive to invalidate this account,
                    except the consideration that it would consign all the numerous and elaborate
                    engravings made by Mantegna to the last sixteen or seventeen years of his life,
                    which seems a scanty space for them. To get over this difficulty, it has been
                    suggested, but without any evidence, that he began engraving while still in
                    Padua, under the tuition of a distinguished goldsmith, Niccolδ. He engraved
                    about fifty plates, according to the usual reckoning; some thirty of them are
                    indisputable—often large, full of figures, and highly studied. Among the
                    principal examples are Roman Triumphs (not the same compositions as the Hampton
                    Court pictures), A Bacchanal Festival, Hercules and Antaeus, Marine Gods, Judith
                    with the Head of Holophernes, the Deposition from the Cross, the Entombment, the
                    Resurrection, the Man of Sorrows, the Virgin in a Grotto. Mantegna has sometimes
                    been credited with the important invention of engraving with the burin on
                    copper. This claim cannot be sustained on a comparison of dates, but at any rate
                    he introduced the art into upper Italy. Several of his engravings are supposed
                    to be executed on some metal less hard than copper. The technique of himself and
                    his followers is characterized by the strongly marked forms of the design, and
                    by the oblique formal hatchings of the shadows. The prints are frequently to be
                    found in two states, or editions. In the first state, the prints have been taken
                    off with the roller, or even by hand-pressing, and they are weak in tint; in the
                    second state, the printing press has been used, and the ink is stronger.</p>
                <p>The influence of Mantegna on the style and tendency of his age was very marked,
                    and extended not only to his own flourishing Mantuan school, but over Italian
                    art generally. His vigorous perspectives and trenchant foreshortenings pioneered
                    the way to other artists; in solid antique taste, and the power of reviving the
                    aspect of a remote age with some approach to system and consistency, he
                    distanced all contemporary competition. He did not, however, leave behind him
                    many scholars of superior faculty. His two legitimate sons were painters of only
                    ordinary ability. His favourite pupil was known as Carlo del Mantegna; Caroto of
                    Verona was another pupil, Bonsignori an imitator. Giovanni Bellini, in his
                    earlier works, obviously followed the lead of his brother-in-law Andrea.</p>
                <p>The works painted by Mantegna, apart from his frescos, are not numerous;
                    thirty-three or thereabouts are regarded as fully authenticated. We may name,
                    besides those already specified—in the Naples museum, St Euphemia, a fine early
                    work; in Casa Melzi, Milan, the Madonna and Child with Chanting Angels, 1461; in
                    the Tribune of the Uffizi, Florence, three pictures remarkable for scrupulous
                    finish; in the Berlin Museum, the Dead Christ with two Angels; in the Louvre,
                    the two celebrated pictures of mythic allegory—Parnassus, and Minerva Triumphing
                    over the Vices; in the London National Gallery, the Virgin and Child enthroned,
                    with the Baptist and the Magdalen, a late example; the monochrome of Vestals,
                    lately bought from Hamilton Palace; the Triumph of Scipio (or Phrygian Mother of
                    the Gods received by the Roman Commonwealth), a tempera in chiaroscuro, painted
                    only a few months before the master’s death; in the Brera, Milan, the Dead
                    Christ, with the two Maries weeping, a remarkable <hi rend="italic">tour de
                    force</hi> in the way of foreshortening, which, though it has a stunted
                    appearance, is in correct technical perspective as seen from all points of view.
                    With all its exceptional merit, this is an eminently ugly picture. It remained
                    in Mantegna’s studio unsold at his death, and was disposed of to liquidate
                    debts. (W. Μ. R.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
