<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0523-0500-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MANSUR, Mansoor, or more properly (9th edition, volume
                    15, page 500)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xr51">Mohammedans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v698h77">Mohammedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn01b24">Omayyads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882n4f">Berbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bc6v">Caliphs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4833n637">Rose</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:844315">Caliphate</term>
                    <term ref="fast:844318">Caliphs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100524">Roses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830652">Berbers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n523/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MANSUR, <hi rend="smallcaps">Mansoor</hi>, or more
                    properly</label>, with the article, <hi rend="smallcaps">Al-Mansur,</hi> “the
                    victorious,” a surname <hi rend="italic">(lakab')</hi> assumed by not a few
                    Mohammedan princes. Among the personages commonly referred to by this title the
                    following may be noticed.</p>
                <p>1. Abu Ja'far ibn Mohammed, second caliph of the house of 'Abbas, who reigned
                    754-775 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> See <hi rend="smallcaps">Mohammedan
                    Empire.</hi></p>
                <p>2. Abù Tâhir Isma'il ibn Al-Kâim, third Fatimite caliph of Africa (946-953).
                    Under Al-Kâim, his father, the Fatimites, already weakened by their conflict
                    with the Omayyads of Spain, were threatened with utter ruin by a Berber rising
                    under Abù Yezid, a poor nonconformist (Tbâdi) schoolmaster, who appeared as a
                    religious reformer, and gathered round him the Sunnites, who detested the
                    Fatimites. In 944 Abιi Yezid conquered the capital Kairawân, and recognized the
                    spiritual headship of the Spanish caliph. While the Spanish caliph and his
                    vassals stripped the Fatimite of his remoter possessions, Abd Yezid pressed him
                    at home, and during the siege of Susa Al-Kâim died, and was succeeded by
                    Al-Mansdr. Then the fortunes of war rapidly turned. Abd Yezid alienated many of
                    his followers by lapsing into habits of arrogant luxury and by treachery towards
                    the Sunnites. At length he lost all he had won, fell into the hands of
                    Al-Mansdr, and was put to death (947). The caliph built the city of Man-sdriyah
                    on the field of the decisive battle and made it hi.s residence; the empire was
                    rapidly restored, and the Spanish vassals driven from Africa. Al-Mansdr died at
                    Mansdri-yah, and was succeeded by Al-Mo'izz, the conqueror of Egypt (see vol.
                    vii. p. 750 sg ’.).</p>
                <p>3. Ibn Abi 'Amir Mohammed, commonly called Almanzor by European writers, of an
                    ancient but not illustrious Arab family, which had its seat at Torroχ near
                    Algeciras, was born 939 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.,</hi> and began life as a
                    lawyer at Cordova. In 967 he obtained a place at the court of Hakam II., the
                    Andalusian caliph, and by an unusual combination of the talents of a courtier
                    with administrative ability and address in dealing with men, rapidly rose to
                    distinction, enjoying in particular the powerful support of Subh, the favourite
                    of the caliph and mother of his heir Hisliâm. On the death of Hakam (976) the
                    accession of a minor gave fresh scope to the genius of Ibn Abi 'Amir, who
                    threaded his way with consummate but unscrupulous talent through the intrigues
                    of the court, and in 978 became prime minister. He now aimed at absolute
                    dominion. The weak young caliph, absorbed in exercises of piety, was easily
                    reduced to a cipher, but at first Ibn Abi 'Amir had to share the power with his
                    father-in-law Ghâlib, the best general of Andalusia, and his chief aid, along
                    with the mother of Hishâm, in the steps that had raised him to power. At last a
                    rupture took place between the two ministers, and ended in a war in which Ghâlib
                    professed himself the champion of the caliph and called in the aid of the
                    Christians of Leon. But his rival had anticipated the struggle; he had long
                    before found means to add military to administrative reputation, and since he
                    rose to the direction of affairs had remodelled the army so as to make it more
                    formidable and more devoted to his cause. Ghâlib fell in battle (981); a
                    victorious campaign chastised the Leonese; and on his return to Cordova the
                    victor assumed the regal surname of Λl-Mansûr billah, and became practically
                    sovereign of Andalusia. The caliph was a mere prisoner of state, holding a
                    nominal dignity, and Al-Mansxrr ultimately assumed the title as well as the
                    prerogatives of king (996). Unscrupulous in the means by which he rose to power,
                    he wielded the sovereignty nobly. His strict justice and the enlightened
                    excellence of his internal administration were not less notable than his
                    military prowess. But it is by the latter that he is best known. His arms were
                    the terror of the Christians, and raised the Moslem power in Spain to a pitch it
                    had never before attained. He fought more than <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n524/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0524-0501"/> fifty campaigns, all glorious, and destroyed many
                    cities, including the three capitals of Leon, Pampeluna, and Barcelona, and the
                    sacred shrine of Santiago de Compostella. In Africa his armies were for a time
                    hard pressed by the revolt of Ziri, viceroy of Mauretania, but before his death
                    this enemy had also fallen. Al-Mansür died at Medinaceli 10th August 1002, and
                    was succeeded by his son Modaffar.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>His life is brilliantly described in vol. iii. of Dozy,
                    Histoire des Μusιιlmans d'Espagne.</p></note></p>
                <p>4. Abd Ydsuf Ya'kdb ibn Yusuf (Jacob Almanzor), of the Moorish dynasty of the
                    Almohades, the conqueror of Alphonse» III. in the great battle of Alarcos
                    (1195), reigned 1184-99.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
