<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0206-0189-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MADRID (9th edition, volume 15, page 189)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1012869">Mayors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1141812">Tacca</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="fast:937895">Gardens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n206/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MADRID</label>, capital of the above province and of Spain,
                    is situated in 40° 24' 35'' N. lat. and 3° 41' 5Γ' W. long., on the left bank of
                    the Manzanares, a subtributary of the Tagus, at a maximum elevation of 2372 feet
                    above the sea-level. The population (397,816 in 1877) was over 400,000 in 1881.
                    The town is nearly in the centre of the kingdom, almost equidistant from the
                    Mediterranean, the Atlantic, and the Bay of Biscay. The site consists of some
                    sandy hills of little elevation, in the midst of an extensive plain, bounded to
                    the view on the north only by the Sierra Guadarrama. The basin in which it
                    stands is of Tertiary formation, consisting of gypsum, marl, and limestone.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n207/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0207-0190"/>
                <p>Owing to its elevated and exposed situation, the climate of Madrid has some
                    marked peculiarities. In winter the mean temperature is 43° Fahr., and as many
                    as sixteen degrees of frost have been observed; the mean in summer is 76° Fahr.,
                    but a temperature of 107° has been registered; and the daily oscillation
                    sometimes amounts to as much as 57°. The readings in sun and shade at the same
                    moment are also widely different. The tendency to inflammatory disorders in the
                    population is, as might be expected from these circumstances, very pronounced;
                    but against it must be set the advantages of a dry atmosphere and a cloudless
                    sky, and in point of fact the city is not exceptionally unhealthy; its salubrity
                    has been much enhanced by the recent introduction of a plentiful supply of pure
                    water from the Lozoya (32 miles distant).</p>
                <p>The form of Madrid proper is almost that of a square with the corners rounded
                    off; from east to west it measures rather less than from north to south. It was
                    formerly surrounded by a poor wall, partly of brick, partly of earth, some 20
                    feet in height, and pierced by five principal gates <hi rend="italic"
                    >(puertas)</hi> and eleven “portillos.” Of these gateways only three, the Puerta
                    de Alcalâ on the east, the Puerta de Toledo on the south, and the Portillo de
                    San Vicente on the west, now actually exist; the first and the third were
                    erected in the time of Charles III., and the second in honour of the restoration
                    of Ferdinand VII.; all have some architectural pretensions. The Manzanares (or
                    rather its bed, for the stream is at most seasons of the year quite
                    insignificant) is spanned by six bridges, the Puente de Toledo and that of
                    Segovia being the chief. The Puerta del Sol (formerly the east gate and tower of
                    the city, having on its front a representation of the sun—</p>
                <p>whence the name) is now the central plaza, and the favourite lounge and place of
                    most traffic in the city; the animated scene it presents has been described with
                    more or less fulness in almost every book of Spanish travel. On its south side
                    stands the Palacio de la Gobernacion, or Home Office, a heavy square building,
                    by a French architect, J. Marquet, and dating from 1768. From the Puerta del Sol
                    diverge, immediately or mediately, almost all the principal streets of
                    Madrid—eastward by north, the Calle de Alcala, terminating in the Prado;
                    eastward, the Carrera de San Geronimo, terminating by the Plaza de las Cortes
                    also in the Prado; southward, the Calle de Carretas; westward, the Calle Mayor,
                    which leads to the council chamber and to the palace, and the Calle del Arenal,
                    terminating in the Plaza de Isabel II. and the opera-house; north-westward, the
                    Calles de Preciados and Del Carmen; and northward, the Calle de la Montera,
                    which afterwards divides into the Calle de Fuencarral to the left and the Calle
                    de Hortaleza to the right. Of these the Calle de Alcalâ is the finest; it is
                    bordered on both sides with acacias, and contains some elegant buildings,
                    including the museum of natural history, formerly the general customhouse,
                    dating from 1769, and the offices of the Board of Trade (Ministerio de Hacienda)
                    on the north side, and on the south the palace of the duke of Sesto (the site of
                    which is about to be occupied by the new buildings of the Banco de Espana or
                    Bank of Spain); its irregularity in point of width and level, however, detracts
                    much from its appearance. The Plaza de las Cortes is so called from the Congreso
                    de los Diputados, or House of Commons, on its north side, a building in the
                    Corinthian style, but of little merit; the square contains a bronze <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n208/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0208-0191"/> statue of Cervantes, by Sola, erected in 1835.
                    The Calle de Carretas ranks with the Carrera de San Geronimo and Calle de la
                    Montera for the excellence of its shops. From the Calle Mayor is entered the
                    Plaza Mayor, a rectangle of about 430 feet by 330, formerly the scene of
                    tournaments, bull fights, autos-de-fe, and similar exhibitions, which used to be
                    viewed by the royal family from the balcony of one of the houses called the
                    Panaderia (belonging to the guild of bakers). The square, which was built under
                    Philip III. in 1619, is surrounded by an arcade; the houses are uniform in
                    height and decoration. In the centre stands a bronze equestrian statue of Philip
                    III., designed by Pantoja, cast by Juan de Bologna, and finished by Pedro Tacca.
                    From the south-east angle of the Plaza Mayor the Calle de Atocha, one of the
                    principal thoroughfares of Madrid, leads to the outskirts of the city; at the
                    southwest angle of the same square the Calle de Toledo begins, the chief mart
                    for the various woollen and silken fabrics from which the picturesque costumes
                    peculiar to the peninsula are made. In the Plaza de Isabel II., at the western
                    extremity of the Calle del Arenal, stands the royal opera-house, the principal
                    front of which faces the Plaza del Oriente and the royal palace. In the centre
                    of the plaza is a fine bronze equestrian statue of Philip IV.; it was designed
                    by Velazquez and cast by Tacca, while Galileo is said to have suggested the
                    means by which the balance is preserved. The gift of the grand-duke of Tuscany
                    in 1640, it stood in the Buen Retiro gardens until 1844.</p>
                <p>As compared with other capitals, Madrid has very few buildings of much interest
                    architecturally or otherwise. There is no cathedral. The Basilica de Nuestra
                    Senora de Atocha, on the Paseo de Atocha, a continuation of the Calle de Atocha,
                    originally founded in 1523, after being destroyed by the French was rebuilt by
                    Ferdinand VII.; it contains one of those miraculous images attributed to St Luke
                    with which Spain abounds, and is specially associated in history with the name
                    of Queen Isabella II. The collegiate church of San Isidro el Real, in the Calle
                    de Toledo, dates from 1651; it has no architectural merit, but contains one or
                    two valuable pictures and other works of art. The modern Gothic church of San
                    Geronimo el Real occupies a conspicuous site eastward of the town; it is not at
                    present used as a place of worship. Of secular buildings unquestionably the most
                    important is the royal palace (Palacio Real) on the west side of the town, on a
                    rising ground overhanging the Manzanares. It occupies the site of the ancient
                    Moorish alcazar, where a hunting seat was built by Henry IV.; this was enlarged
                    and improved by Charles V. when he first made Madrid his residence in 1532, was
                    further developed by Philip II., but ultimately was destroyed by fire in 1734.
                    The present edifice was begun under Philip V. in 1737 by Sacchetti of Turin, and
                    was finished in 1764. It is in the Tuscan style, and is 470 feet square and 100
                    feet in height, the material being white Colmenar granite, resembling marble. To
                    the north of the palace are the royal stables and coachhouses, remarkable for
                    their extent; to the south is the armoury (Museo de la Real Armeria), containing
                    what is probably the best collection of the kind anywhere to be met with. After
                    the Palacio Real may be mentioned the royal picture gallery (Real Museo de
                    Pinturas), adjoining the Salon del Prado; it was built about 1785 for Charles
                    III. by Juan de Villanueva, as a museum of natural history and academy of
                    sciences. It contains the collections of Charles V., Philip II., and Philip IV.,
                    and the pictures number upwards of two thousand. The specimens of Titian,
                    Raphael, Veronese, Tintoretto, Velazquez, Vandyck, Rubens, and Teniers are
                    numerous and remarkable, giving it a claim to be regarded as the finest picture
                    gallery in the world. The palaces of the grandees are generally noteworthy only
                    for their size. There are some seventeen theatres of all classes. The bull-ring
                    (Plaza de Toros), to the east of the town, accommodates 12,000 spectators; the
                    present building dates from 1874. Of the promenades and open places of public
                    resort the most fashionable and most frequented is the Prado (Paseo del Prado,
                    Salon del Prado) on the east side of the town, with its northward continuation
                    the Paseo de Recoletos. To the south of the town is the Paseo de las Delicias,
                    and on the west, below the royal palace, and skirting the Manzanares, is the
                    Paseo de la Virgen del Puerto, used chiefly by the poorer classes. Eastward from
                    the Prado are the Buen Retire gardens, with the usual ponds and pavilions, and a
                    poor menagerie. The gardens were formerly the grounds surrounding a royal
                    hunting seat, on the site of which a palace was built for Philip IV. in 1633; it
                    was destroyed during the French occupation.</p>
                <p>Modern educational movements have not left Madrid unaffected, and considerable
                    improvements in this respect have taken place within recent years. There are
                    upwards of 100 official primary schools (attended by 4810 boys and 3958 girls),
                    and a large number of private ones; among the other educational
                    instrumentalities the numerous schools connected with various Protestant
                    missions claim special mention. There are two normal schools. The university of
                    Alcala, founded by Cardinal Ximenes in 1508, was transferred in 1836 to Madrid,
                    and has since that time undergone much reforιn and extension. In 1882 the
                    teaching staff numbered 88, and the students 7000. Of these 2400 belonged to the
                    faculty of law, 2500 to that of medicine, 400 to that of science, 1400 to that
                    of pharmacy, and 250 to that of philosophy and literature. The faculty of
                    theology was suppressed in 1868, and has not been re-established. Madrid also
                    has schools of agriculture, architecture, civil and mining engineering, the fine
                    arts, veterinary science, and music. The school of military engineering is at
                    Guadalajara. Among the educational institutions may be reckoned the botanical
                    garden, originated in 1781, the national library, with those of the palace, the
                    university, and San Isidro, and the museum of natural science, exceedingly rich
                    in the mineralogical department. The principal learned society is the Royal
                    Spanish Academy, founded in 1713 for the cultivation and improvement of the
                    Spanish tongue. The Academy of History possesses a good library, rich in MSS.
                    and incunabula, as well as a fine collection of coins and medals. There are
                    likewise academies of the fine arts, the exact sciences, moral and political
                    science, medicine arid surgery, and jurisprudence and legislation, all
                    possessing libraries. There are also anthropological, economical, and
                    geographical societies, and a scientific and literary athenaeum. The charitable
                    institutions include upwards of eighteen hospitals, the largest of which
                    contains 1200 beds; there are three foundling hospitals and six for orphans. The
                    military hospital is large and well conducted. There are very good schools for
                    the blind and for deaf mutes, and a number of asylums of various kinds.</p>
                <p>The manufactures of Madrid are inconsiderable; every article of food and
                    clothing, almost without exception, is imported. The most important industries
                    are the manufactures of tobacco and cigars, gold and silver wares, tapestry and
                    carpets, porcelain, hats, mirrors, and beer. Little wine is grown near the
                    capital, and not much fruit; but the markets are well supplied, and regularly,
                    from all quarters of the kingdom. Madrid is still the principal, one might
                    almost say the only, focus of the now largely developed railway system of the
                    peninsula. The suburbs of the town are rapidly extending, especially towards the
                    north and south. The immediate environs are uninteresting. About 6 miles to the
                    north-west lies the fine hunting seat El Pardo, restored by Charles III.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n209/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0209-0192"/>
                <p>Spanish archaeologists have frequently claimed for Madrid a very high antiquity,
                    but the earliest authentic historical mention of the town (Majrit, Majoritum)
                    occurs in an Arab chronicle, and does not take us farther back than to the first
                    half of the 10th century. The place was finally taken from the Moors by Alphonso
                    VI. (1083), and was made a hunting-seat by Henry IV., but first rose into
                    importance when Charles V,, benefiting by its keen air, made it his occasional
                    residence. Philip II. created it his capital and “only court” <hi rend="italic"
                    >{ûnica</hi><hi rend="italic">corte)</hi> in 1560. To this day it only ranks,
                    however, as “villa,” not as “ciudad.” Fruitless attempts were made by Philip
                    III. and Charles III. respectively to transfer the seat of government to
                    Valladolid and to Seville.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
