<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0570-0543-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARIGNOLLI, Giovanni de’ (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    543)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025421">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163443">Uzbeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hh25">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1241948">Saba</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n570/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARIGNOLLI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Giovanni de’</hi></label>, a
                    notable traveller to the far East of the 14th century, born probably prior to
                    1290, and sprung from a noble family in Florence. The family is long extinct,
                    but a street near the cathedral (Via de’ Cerretani) formerly bore the name of
                    the Marignolli.</p>
                <p>In vol. V. pp. 628-29 some account has been given of the extraordinary episode of
                    intercourse between Europe and China in the first half of the 14th century. In
                    1338 there arrived at Avignon, where Benedict XII. held his court, an embassy
                    from the great khan of Cathay, bearing letters to the pontiff from the khan
                    himself, and from certain Christian nobles of the Alan race in his service.
                    These latter represented that they had been eight years without a spiritual
                    guide, and earnestly desired one. The pope replied to the letters, and appointed
                    four ecclesiastics as his legates to the khan’s court. The name of Marignolli, a
                    Franciscan of some repute for learning, appears, as John of Florence, third on
                    the letters of commission. We know not what became of his colleagues; he was the
                    chief if not the sole envoy who actually went.</p>
                <p>The mission left Avignon in December 1338, picked up the Tartar envoys at Naples,
                    and sailed across the Black Sea to Caffa, whence they travelled to the court of
                    Mohammed Uzbek, khan of the Golden Horde, at Sarai on the Volga. The khan
                    entertained them hospitably during the winter of 1339-40, and then sent them
                    across the steppes to Armalec or Almaligh, the northern seat of the house of
                    Chaghatai, in what is now the province of Hi. “There,” says Marignolli, “we
                    built a church, bought a piece of ground .... sung masses, and baptized several
                    persons, notwithstanding that only the year before the bishop and six other
                    minor friars had there undergone glorious martyrdom for Christ’s salvation.”
                    Quitting Almaligh in 1341, they seem to have reached Peking (by way of Kamil or
                    Hand) in May or June 1342. They were well received by the reigning khan, the
                    last of the Mongol dynasty in China.</p>
                <p>“The grand kaam, when he beheld the great horses <hi rend="italic"
                    >(dextrarios)</hi> and the pope’s presents, with his letter, and that of King
                    Robert (of Naples) too, with their golden seals, and when he saw us also,
                    rejoiced greatly, being delighted, yea exceedingly delighted with everything. .
                    . . And when I entered the kaam’s presence, it was in full festival vestments,
                    with a very fine cross carried before me, and candles and incense, whilst <hi
                    rend="italic">Credo in mum Deuιn</hi> was chaunted, in that glorious palace
                    where he dwells. And when the clιaunt was ended I bestowed a full benediction,
                    which he received with all humility.”</p>
                <p>An entry in the Chinese annals fixes the year of Marignolli’s presentation by its
                    mention of the arrival of the great horses from the kingdom of Fulang <hi
                    rend="italic">(Farang</hi> or Europe), one of which was 11 feet 6 inches in
                    length, and 6 feet 8 inches high, and black all over!</p>
                <p>Marignolli stayed at Peking or Cambalec three or four years, after which he
                    travelled through eastern China to Zayton or <hi rend="smallcaps">Chinchew</hi>
                    (7.v.), quitting China apparently in December 1347, and reaching Columbum
                    (Kaulam or Quilon in Malabar) in Easter week of 1348. At this place he found a
                    church of the Latin communion, probably founded by Jordanus of Séverac, who had
                    been consecrated bishop of Columbum by Pope John XXII. in 1328. Here Marignolli
                    remained sixteen months, after which he proceeded on what seems a most devious
                    voyage. First he visited the shrine of St Thomas near the modern Madras, and
                    then proceeded to what he calls the kingdom of Saba, and identifies with the
                    Sheba of Scripture, but which seems from various particulars to have been Java.
                    Taking ship again for Malabar on his way to Europe, he encountered great storms,
                    of which he gives an imaginative account :—</p>
                <p>. . . . “The sea as if in flames, and fire-spitting dragons flying by, which, as
                    they passed, slew persons on board the other junks, whilst ours remained
                    untouched, by God’s grace, and by virtue of the Body of Christ which I carried
                    with me, and through the merits of the glorious Virgin and of St Clare.”</p>
                <p>They found shelter in the little port of <hi rend="italic">Pervilis</hi>
                    (Beru-wala or Berberyn) in the south-west of Ceylon; but here the legate fell
                    into the hands of “a certain tyrant Coya Jan (Khoja Jahân), an eunuch and an
                    accursed Saracen,” who professed to treat him with all deference, but detained
                    him four months, and plundered all the gifts and Eastern rarities that he was
                    carrying home. This detention in “Seyllan” enables Marignolli to give a variety
                    of curious particulars regarding Adam’s Peak and other marvels. After this we
                    have only fragmentary notices, showing that his route to Europe lay by Ormuz,
                    the ruins of Babel, Baghdad, Mosul, Aleppo (“where there were many Christians
                    who dressed after the Latin fashion, and spoke a language very near the French;
                    at any rate like the French of Cyprus ”), and thence to Damascus and Jerusalem.
                    In 1353 he arrived at Avignon, and delivered a letter from the great khan to
                    Pope Innocent VI. In the following year the emperor Charles IV., on a visit to
                    Italy, made Marignolli one of his chaplains. Soon after, the pope made him
                    bishop of Bisignano; but he seems to have been in no hurry to reside there. He
                    appears to have accompanied the emperor to Prague; in 1356 he is found acting as
                    envoy to the pope from Florence; and in 1357 he is at Bologna. We know not when
                    he died. The last trace of Marignolli is a letter addressed to him, which was
                    found last century among the records in the Chapter Library at Prague. The
                    writer is an unnamed bishop of Armagh, easily identified with Richard Fitz
                    Ralph, a strenuous foe of the Franciscans, who had broken lances in controversy
                    with Ockham and Burley. The letter implies that some intention had been
                    intimated from Avignon of sending <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n571/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0571-0544"/> Marignolli to Ireland in connexion with matters
                    then in debate. The wrath of Fitz Ralph is sorely stirred at this, and he
                    brandishes the shillelah in a style of energetic metaphor very like what we have
                    been used to from like quarters in later days.</p>
                <p>Fitz Ralph’s contemptuous language had probably a good deal of foundation. The
                    fragmentary notes of Marignolli’s Eastern travels often contain most vivid
                    remembrance and graphic description, but combined with an incontinent vanity,
                    and an incoherent lapse from one thing to another, matched by nothing in
                    literature but the conversation of Mrs Nickleby. They have no claim to be called
                    a narrative, and it is with no small pains that anything like <hi rend="italic"
                    >a</hi> narrative can be pieced out of them. Indeed the mode in which they were
                    elicited curiously illustrates how little mediaeval travellers thought of
                    publication. The emperor Charles, instead of urging his chaplain to write a
                    history of his vast journeys, set him to the repugnant task of recasting the
                    annals of Bohemia; and he consoled himself by salting the insipid stuff by
                    interpolations, <hi rend="italic">à propos de bottes,</hi> of his recollections
                    of Asiatic travel.</p>
                <p>Nobody seems to have noticed the work till 1768, when the chronicle was published
                    in vol. ii. of the <hi rend="italic">Monumenta</hi><hi rend="italic">Hist.
                    Bohemias</hi><hi rend="italic">nusquam antehac edita</hi> by Father Gelasius
                    Dobner. But, though Marignolli was thus at last in type, no one seems to have
                    read him till 1820, when an interesting paper on his travels was published by J.
                    G. Meinert. The late Professor Kunstmann of Μunich also devoted to the subject
                    one of a series of very intelligent papers on the ecclesiastical travellers of
                    the Middle Ages. And the whole of the passages bearing on the journey were
                    excerpted, translated, and commented on by Col. H. Yule in a collection printed
                    in 1866.</p>
                <p>Monumenta Historica, &lt;fcc., collegit, &lt;fcc., P. Gelasius Dobner a S.
                    Catherin», tom. ii., Prague, 1768; Meinert, in Abhandl. der K. Böhm. Gesellsch.
                    der <hi rend="smallcaps">Wîss«m-</hi> schaften, vii.; Kunstmann, in Historische
                    Politische Blättern von Phillips und Görres, Bd. xxxviii. pp. 7θi,793, Munich,
                    1859; Wadding, Annales Minorum, vii.; Sbaralea, Supplent. et Castigatio ad
                    Scriptores Trium Ordd. S. Francisci a Waddingo, Rome, 1806; Cathay and the Way
                    Thither, Hak. Soc., 1866. (H. Y.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
