<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0150-0135-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MACDONALD, Étienne-Jacques- (9th edition, volume 15,
                    page 135)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1010769">Marshals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002769">Love</term>
                    <term ref="fast:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1009087">Marching</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cn6z196">Love</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649t8s">Camping</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9q77g">Desertion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90f3q">Deserts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n150/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MACDONALD, <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Étienne-Jacques-</hi></label><hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph-Alexandre</hi>
                    (1765-1840), duke of Taranto, and marshal of France, was born at Sancerre on
                    November 17, 1765. His father came of an old Jacobite family, which had followed
                    James II. to France, and was a near relative of the celebrated Flora Macdonald
                    (1722-1790), the heroine whose courage and fidelity were at one critical period
                    the sole means by which Prince Charles Edward was enabled to elude his enemies
                    after the defeat of Culloden in 1746. In 1784 Macdonald joined the legion raised
                    by the second Marshal Maillebois to support the revolutionary party in Holland
                    against the Prussians, and after it was disbanded he received a commission in
                    the regiment of Dillon. On the breaking out of the Revolution, the regiment of
                    Dillon remained eminently loyal, nearly all its officers emigrating with the
                    princes, with the exception of Macdonald, who was in love with a Mademoiselle
                    Jacob, whose father was enthusiastic for the doctrines of the Revolution. His
                    love was successful, and directly after his marriage he was appointed
                    aide-de-camp to General Dumouriez. He also distinguished himself at Jemmapes,
                    and was promoted colonel in 1794. He refused to desert to the Austrians with
                    Dumouriez, and as a reward was made general of brigade, and appointed to command
                    the leading brigade in Pichegru’s invasion of Holland. His knowledge of the
                    country proved most useful, and he was instrumental in the capture of the Dutch
                    fleet by the French hussars. In 1797 he was made general of division, and
                    transferred first to the army of the Rhine and then to that of Italy. When he
                    reached Italy, the peace of Campo Formio had been signed, and General Bonaparte
                    had returned to France; but, under the direction of Berthier, Macdonald first
                    occupied Rome, of which he was made governor, and then in conjunction with
                    Championnet he defeated General Mack, and revolutionized the kingdom of Naples
                    under the title of the Parthenopaean Republic. When Suwaroff invaded northern
                    Italy, and was winning back the conquests of Bonaparte, General Macdonald
                    collected all the troops in the peninsula and moved northwards. With but 30,000
                    men he attacked, at the Trebbia, Suwaroff with 50,000, and after three days’
                    fighting, during which he held the Russians at bay, and gave time for Moreau to
                    come up, he retired in good order to Genoa. After this gallant behaviour he was
                    made governor of Versailles, and acquiesced in, if he did not co-operate in, the
                    events of the 18th Brumaire. In 1800 he received the command of the army in
                    Switzerland which was to maintain the communications between the armies of
                    Germany and of Ital^. He carried out his orders to the letter, and at last, in
                    the winter of 1800-1, he was ordered to march over the Splügen Pass. This
                    achievement is fully described by Mathieu Dumas, who was chief of his staff, and
                    is at least as noteworthy as Bonaparte’s famous passage of the Saint Bernard
                    before Marengo, though followed by no such successful battle. On his return to
                    Paris he married the widow of General Joubert, and was appointed French
                    plenipotentiary in Denmark. Returning in 1805 he associated himself with Moreau,
                    and incurred the dislike of Napoleon, who did not include him in his first
                    creation of marshals. Till 1809 he remained without employment, but in that year
                    Napoleon, hard pressed at Aspern, gave Macdonald the command of a division in
                    the army of the viceroy of Italy which was to march from Italy to his help. He
                    led the army from Italy till its junction with Napoleon, and at Wagram commanded
                    the attack on the Austrian centre which won the victory. Napoleon made him
                    marshal of France on the field of battle, and presently created him duke of
                    Taranto. In 1810 he served in Spain, and in 1812 he commanded the left wing of
                    the grand army for the invasion of Russia. After sharing in the battles of
                    Lützen and Bautzen, he was ordered to invade Silesia, where Blücher defeated him
                    with great loss at the Katzbach. After the terrible battle of Leipsic he was
                    ordered with Prince Poniatowski to cover the evacuation of Leipsic, and after
                    the blowing up of the bridge, he managed to swim the Elster, while Poniatowski
                    was drowned. During the defensive campaign of 1814 Macdonald again distinguished
                    himself, and was one of the marshals sent by Napoleon to take his abdication in
                    favour of his son to Paris. When all were deserting their old master, Macdonald
                    remained faithful to him. Macdonald was directed by Napoleon to give in his
                    adherence to the new régime, and was presented by him with the sabre of Murad
                    Bey for his fidelity. He was made a peer of France at the Restoration, and,
                    having once passed his word to the new order of things, remained faithful during
                    the Hundred Days. In 1816 he became chancellor of the Legion of Honour, a post
                    he held till 1831, and took a great part in the discussions in the House of
                    Peers. In 1823 he married Mademoiselle de Bourgony, and at last had a son,
                    Alexander, who succeeded on his death in 1840 as duke of Taranto. From 1830 his
                    life was spent in retirement at his country place Courcelles.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n151/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0151-0136"/>
                <p>Macdonald had none of that military genius which distinguished Davoust, Masséna,
                    and especially Ney, nor of that military science conspicuous in Marmont and St
                    Cyr, but nevertheless his campaign in Switzerland gives him a rank far superior
                    to such mere generals of division as Oudinot and Dupont. This capacity for
                    independent command made Napoleon, in spite of his defeats at the Trebbia and
                    the Katzbach, trust him with large corps d’armée till the end of his career. As
                    a man, his character cannot be spoken of too highly; no stain of cruelty or
                    faithlessness rests on him. He retained always the frank honour of a soldier of
                    fortune; but he never forgot that he was a gentleman, or disgraced the new
                    nobility of Napoleon by ridiculous pretensions.</p>
                <p>Maδdonald was especially fortunate in the accounts of his military exploits,
                    Mathieu Dumas and Ségur having been on his staff in Switzerland. See Dumas, <hi
                    rend="italic">Événements Militaires</hi>; and Ségur’s rare tract, <hi
                    rend="italic">Lettre sur la campagne du Général Macdonald dans les Grisons
                    en</hi> 1800 <hi rend="italic">et</hi> 1801 (1802). Also consult Pelet’s
                    excellent <hi rend="italic">Campagne de</hi> 1809, and Ségur’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Éloge</hi> (1842).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
