<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0664-0633-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MATTHEW of Paris (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    633)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1095688">Respect</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006241">Majorities</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:794216">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:874681">Confessors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z981">Abbots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47p8tc5z">Abbeys</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xn1j">Monks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n664/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MATTHEW <hi rend="smallcaps">of Paris</hi></label>, one of
                    our most important writers in connexion with English mediaeval history, was born
                    about the year 1200, or possibly somewhat earlier. His surname was probably
                    derived either from his having been born in Paris or having studied in the
                    university there; but his English origin is proved by the tone in which he
                    uniformly speaks of foreigners, especially the French, while his knowledge of
                    the French language is attested by the fact of his having written in that
                    language, and also by the introduction of many French words in his Latin
                    writings.</p>
                <p>We have it on his own authority, as recorded in an autograph marginal note (MS.
                    Cott., Nero, D. 1, fol. 1656), that he assumed the monastic habit at the abbey
                    of St Alban’s on the 21st of January 1217. In 1236 he accompanied the
                    newly-elected prior of his abbey, John of Hertford, to London, to attend the
                    ceremony of the nuptials of Henry III. and Eleanor of Provence; and in October
                    1247 he was at Westminster, in order to be present at the celebration of the
                    feast of St Edward the Confessor, when he was desired by the king himself to
                    write an account of the proceedings, The most important event in his tranquil
                    and uneventful life (which was passed chiefly within the walls of his monastery)
                    occurred in the year 1248, when he was sent on a mission to the Benedictine
                    monastery of Holm (Throndhjem), which had become involved in difficulties owing
                    to the maladministration of one of its abbots. He returned to England after more
                    than a year’s absence, and we can trace him as attending the royal court at
                    Winchester in July 1251, and as present at York on the occasion of the marriage
                    of Henry’s daughter with Alexander II. of Scotland, some six months later. In
                    March 1257 Henry himself visited St Alban’s, and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n665/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0665-0634"/> remained at the monastery for a whole week.
                    During this time he not only admitted Matthew to his table and to conversations
                    in his private chamber, but also communicated to him facts and details of an
                    historical character derived from his own personal knowledge and experience.
                    Among other information, Matthew tells us that Henry repeated to him from memory
                    the titles of the English baronies to the number of two hundred and fifty. The
                    last incident recorded by the historian himself with respect to his own career
                    is the faét that he exerted his influence with Henry on behalf of the university
                    of Oxford, when that body found its privileges endangered by the encroachments
                    of the bishop of Lincoln. In his latter years, Matthew’s growing infirmities
                    compelled him to have recourse to the aid of a fellow-monk in order to complete
                    his works; this assistance is to be traced in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Anglorum</hi> from 1252 to the end of the work
                    (1253); in the <hi rend="italic">Abbreviatio</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Chronicorum</hi> for the years 1253, 1254, and 1255; andin the <hi
                    rend="italic">Chronica</hi><hi rend="italic">Majora</hi> for the years 1258 and
                    1259. Matthew died after the month of May 1259, and his portrait, as he lay on
                    his couch when dead, was drawn by his fellow-monk.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Works.—</hi> Matthew Paris’s chief work, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Major,—</hi> often styled the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chronica</hi><hi rend="italic">Majora,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> is a
                    narrative professing to record the outlines of human history from the creation,
                    and terminating with the year 1259. It was long supposed that Roger of Wendover
                    was the author of a much larger proportion of the work than was really the case;
                    but the question may be regarded as finally set at rest by the decisive
                    investigations and conclusions of Dr Luard, as stated at length in his prefaces
                    to the volumes of his edition of the work in the Rolls Series. He concludes that
                    the <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Major</hi> down to the year
                    1189 was the work of John de Celia, abbot of St Alban’s from the year 1195 to
                    1214; that it was then continued by Roger of Wendover on the same plan and from
                    the same sources to the year 1235, the whole work down to this date passing for
                    a long time as the production of the latter writer exclusively, and being known
                    as the <hi rend="italic">Flores</hi><hi rend="italic">Historiarum</hi>; that it
                    was then transcribed by Matthew Paris, who, however, made numerous corrections
                    and additions, but, in the opinion of Professor Stubbs, “interpreted” rather
                    than “interpolated”; that it was then continued by the same writer, and is, from
                    1235 to the year 1259, exclusively his work. In style, in vividness of
                    narration, and in descriptive power Matthew far excels his two predecessors. He
                    is also entitled to the praise of having been a warm advocate of English rights
                    and liberties, and a sturdy opponent alike of regal and papal tyranny; in fact,
                    the national sentiment may be said first to receive adequate expression in his
                    pages. The work, moreover, is not only the best source of information with
                    respect to events in England during the reign of Henry III. down to the
                    commencement of the Barons’ Wars, but is also an authority with respect to
                    Continental affairs, especially those of France and the empire.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Anglorum</hi> of Matthew is
                    mainly an abridgment of his larger work,—the chief feature of difference being
                    the omission of almost everything relating to foreign events. Sometimes,
                    however, details and more particularly personal anecdotes are introduced, with
                    many minute facts and circumstances which would be sought for in vain elsewhere,
                    and largely illustrate contemporary usages and the general condition of society.
                    Besides the above,'Matthew wrote an <hi rend="italic">Abbreviatio</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Chronicorum,</hi> extending from the year 1100 to 1255. Of this
                    only one manuscript exists,—that in the author’s own handwriting, preserved in
                    the Cottonian collection in the British Museum, and printed in the third volume
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Anglorum,</hi> edited by
                    Sir Francis Madden. Matthew also compiled a <hi rend="italic">Liber</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Additamentorum</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Supplementorum,</hi>
                    containing documents illustrative of the Greater Chronicle. This is contained in
                    the folio edition of Matthew’s writings edited by Wats, and published in</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Vitae</hi><hi rend="italic">viginti</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >trium Abbatum</hi><hi rend="italic">S. Albani,</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Lives
                    of the Abbots of St Alban</hi><hi rend="italic">'s,</hi> does not bear Matthew’s
                    name, but is unquestionably the production of his pen. The biographies which
                    belong to the period preceding the Norman Conquest contain valuable and
                    interesting notices, but also include much of what is evidently fabulous. The
                    <hi rend="italic">Fitae</hi><hi rend="italic">duorum Offarum,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Lives of the two</hi><hi rend="italic">Offas,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">—</hi> the one a mythical character, the other the historic
                    monarch of Mercia,—is a composition of little value, and some doubt attaches to
                    the authorship. Both the foregoing, however, are included in the edition by
                    Wats.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Editions. —</hi> The best edition of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Major</hi> is that by Dr Luard, published in
                    five volumes in the Rolls Series, 1872-80. Of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Minor</hi> an edition in three volumes in the
                    same series was edited by Sir Frederic Madden, 1866-69. (J. B. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
