<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0516-0493-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MANNA (9th edition, volume 15, page 493)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1007783">Manna</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821510">Australians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821509">Australianisms</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45717v01">Saracens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r724">Presents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zn7v">Sugar</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n516/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MANNA</label>, a concrete saccharine exudation obtained by
                    making incisions in the trunk of the flowering or manna ash tree, <hi
                    rend="italic">Fraxinus Ornus,</hi> I.. At the present day the manna of commerce
                    is collected exclusively in Sicily from cultivated trees, chiefly in the
                    districts around Capaci, Carini, Cinisi, and Favarota, small towns 20 to 25
                    miles west of Palermo, and in the townships of Geraci, Castelbuono, and other
                    places in the district of Cefalù, 50 to 70 miles east of Palermo. In the <hi
                    rend="italic">frassinetti</hi> or plantations the trees are placed about 7 feet
                    apart, and after they are eight years old, and the trunk at least 3 inches in
                    diameter, the collection of manna is begun. This operation is performed in July
                    or August during the dry weather, by making transverse incisions 1∣ to 2 inches
                    long, and about 1 inch apart, through the bark, one cut being made each day, the
                    first at the bottom of the tree, another directly above the first, and so on. In
                    succeeding years the process is repeated on the untouched sides of the trunk,
                    until the tree has been cut all round and exhausted. It is then cut down, and a
                    young plant arising from the same root takes its place. The finest or flaky
                    manna appears to have been allowed to harden on the stem. A very superior kind,
                    obtained by allowing the juice to encrust pieces of wood or straws inserted in
                    the cuts, and called <hi rend="italic">manna a cannolo,</hi> is not found in
                    commerce in England. The fragments adhering to the stem after the finest flakes
                    have been removed are scraped off, and form the small or Tolfa manna of
                    commerce. That which flows from the lower incisions is often collected on tiles
                    or on a concave piece of the prickly pear <hi rend="italic">{Opuntia},</hi> but
                    is less crystalline and more glutinous, and is less esteemed.</p>
                <p>Manna of good quality dissolves at ordinary temperatures in about G parts of
                    water, forming a clear liquid. Its chief constituent is mannite or manna sugar,
                    a hexatomic alcohol, C <hi rend="subscript"> 6</hi> H <hi rend="subscript">
                    8</hi> (OH) <hi rend="superscript"> 0</hi>, which likewise occurs, in much
                    smaller quantity, in certain species of <hi rend="italic">Fucus</hi> and in
                    plants of several widely separated natural orders. Of this substance the best
                    manna contains 70 to 80 per cent. It crystallizes in shining rhombic prisms from
                    its solution in boiling alcohol. Manna possesses mildly laxative properties, and
                    on account of its sweet taste is employed as a mild aperient for children. It is
                    less used in England now than formerly, but is still largely consumed in South
                    America. In Italy mannite is prepared for sale in the shape of small cones
                    resembling loaf sugar in shape, and is frequently prescribed in medicine instead
                    of manna.</p>
                <p>The manna of the present day appears to have been unknown before the 15th
                    century, although a mountain in Sicily with the Arabic name Gibelman, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> “manna mountain,” appears to point to its collection
                    there during the period that the island was held by the Saracens, 827-1070. In
                    the 16th century it was collected in Calabria in Italy, and until recently was
                    produced in the Tuscan Maremma, but neither from that locality nor from the
                    States of the Church is any now brought into commerce, although the name of
                    Tolfa, a town near Civita Vecchia, is still applied to an inferior variety of
                    the drug.</p>
                <p>Various other kinds of manna are known, but none of these have been found to
                    contain mannite. Alhagi manna (Persian and Arabic <hi rend="italic"
                    >tar-angubin)</hi> is the produce of <hi rend="italic">Alhagi</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">camelorum,</hi> Fisch., a small, spiny, leguminous plant, growing
                    in Persia, Afghanistan, and Baluchistan. This manna occurs in the form of small,
                    roundish, hard, dry tears, varying from the size of a mustard seed to that of a
                    coriander, of a light-brown colour, sweet taste, and senna-like odour. The
                    spines and pods of the plant are often mixed with it. It is collected near,
                    Kandahar and Herat, and imported into India from Cabul and Kandahar to the
                    extent of about 2000 lb. annually, and is valued, at about thirty shillings per
                    lb. Tamarisk manna (Persian <hi rend="italic">gaz-angubin,</hi> tamarisk honey)
                    exudes in June and July from the sleuder branches of <hi rend="italic">Tamarix
                    gallica,</hi> var. <hi rend="italic">nιannifera,</hi> Ehrenb., in the form of
                    honey-like drops, which, in the cool temperature of the early morning, are found
                    in the solid state. This secretion is caused by the puncture of an insect, <hi
                    rend="italic">Coccus manniparus,</hi> Ehrenb. In the valleys of the peninsula of
                    Sinai, especially in the Wady el-Sheikh, this manna (Arabic <hi rend="italic"
                    >man)</hi> is collected by the Arabs and sold to the monks of St Catherine, who
                    supply it to the pilgrims visiting the convent. It is found also in Persia and
                    the Punjab, but does not appear to be collected in any quantity. This kind of
                    manna seems to be alluded to by Herodotus (vii. 31). Under the same name of <hi
                    rend="italic">gaz-angubin</hi> there are sold commonly in the Persian bazaars
                    round cakes, of which a chief ingredient is a manna obtained to the south-west
                    of Ispahan, in the month of August, by shaking the branches or scraping the
                    stems of <hi rend="italic">Astragalus</hi><hi rend="italic">florulentus</hi> and
                    <hi rend="italic">A. adscendens,</hi> Boiss. and Hausskn.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See <hi rend="italic">Bombay Lit. Tr.,</hi>
                    vol. i. art. 16, for details as to the gaz-angubin. A common Persian sweetmeat
                    consists of wheat-flour kneaded with manna into a thick paste.</p></note><hi
                    rend="italic">Shirkhist,</hi> a kind of manna known to writers on materia medica
                    in the 16th century, is still found in the bazaars of north-west India, being
                    imported from Afghanistan and Turkestan to a limited extent. Haussknecht states
                    that it is the produce of <hi rend="italic">Cotoneaster</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >nummularia,</hi> Fisch, and Mey. <hi rend="italic">(Rosaceae),</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Atraphaxis</hi><hi rend="italic">spinosa,</hi> I.. <hi
                    rend="italic">(Polygonaceae),</hi> and that it is brought chiefly from
                    Herat.</p>
                <p>Oak manna, according to Haussknecht, is collected from the twigs of <hi
                    rend="italic">Quercus</hi><hi rend="italic">Vallonea,</hi> Kotschy, and <hi
                    rend="italic">Q. persica,</hi> Jaub. and Spach, on which it is produced by the
                    puncture of an insect during the month of August. This manna occurs in the state
                    of agglutinated tears, and forms an object of some industry among the wandering
                    tribes of Kurdistan at the present day. It is collected before sunrise, by
                    shaking the grains of manna on to linen cloths spread out beneath the trees, or
                    by dipping the small branches in hot water and evaporating the solution thus
                    obtained. A substance collected by the inhabitants of Laristan from <hi
                    rend="italic">Pyrus glabra,</hi> Boiss., strongly resembles oak manna in
                    appearance.</p>
                <p>Australian manna is found on the leaves of <hi rend="italic">Eucalyptus</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">viminalis,</hi> Lab.; the Lerp manna of Australia is of animal
                    origin.</p>
                <p>Briançon manna is met with on the leaves of the common <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Larch</hi><hi rend="italic">{q.v.</hi>), and a kind of manna was at one time
                    obtained from the cedar, but none of these are now collected for commercial
                    purposes.</p>
                <p>The manna of Scripture, notwithstanding the miraculous circumstances which
                    distinguish it in the Biblical narrative from anything now known, answers in its
                    description very closely to the tamarisk manna.</p>
                <p>See <hi rend="italic">Pharmacographia,</hi> p. 409; Hanbury, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Science Papers,</hi> p. 355- 368; Stewart, <hi rend="italic">Punjab
                    Plants,</hi> Lahore, 1869, pp. 57-92; Geoffroy, <hi rend="italic">Mat.
                    Med.,</hi> ii. (1741) p. 584; Dobson, <hi rend="italic">Proc. Roy. Soc. Van
                    Diemen's Land,</hi> i. (1851) p. 234.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
