<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0682-0651-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAZARIN, Jules (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    651)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1085637">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996178">Lenses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881894">Cousins</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n577">Queens</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dk97">Lenses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n682/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAZARIN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jules</hi></label> (1602-1661),
                    cardinal, the successor of Richelieu, and forerunner of Louis XIV., was the
                    elder son of Pietro Mazarini, the intendant of the household of Philip Colonna,
                    and of his wife Ortensia Buffalini, a connexion of the Colonnas, and was born at
                    Piscina in the Abruzzi on July 14, 1602. He was educated by the Jesuits at Rome
                    till his seventeenth year, when he accompanied<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n683/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0683-0652"/> Jerome Colonna as chamberlain to the university
                    of Alcala in Spain. There he distinguished himself more by his love of gambling
                    and his gallant adventures than by study, but made himself a thorough master,
                    not only of the Spanish language and character, but also of that romantic
                    fashion of Spanish love-making which was to help him greatly in after life, when
                    he became the servant of a Spanish queen. On his return to Rome he took his
                    degree as Doctor Utriusque Juris, and then became captain of infantry in the
                    regiment of Colonna, which took part in the war in the Valtelline. During this
                    war he gave proofs of much diplomatic ability, and Pope Urban VIII. entrusted
                    him, in 1629, with the difficult task of putting an end to the war of the
                    Mantuan succession. His success marked him out for further distinction. He was
                    presented to two canonries in the churches of St John Lateran and Sta Maria
                    Maggiore, although he had only taken the minor orders, and had never been
                    consecrated priest; he negotiated the treaty of Turin between France and Savoy
                    in 1632, became vice-legate at Avignon in 163∙I., and nuncio at the court of
                    France from 1634-36. But he began to wish for a wider sphere than papal
                    negotiations, and, seeing that he had no chance of becoming a cardinal except by
                    the aid of some great power, he accepted Richelieu’s offer of entering the
                    service of the king of France, and in 1639 became a naturalized Frenchman. In
                    1640 Richelieu sent him to Savoy, where the regency of Christine, the duchess of
                    Savoy, and sister of Louis XIII., was disputed by her brothers-in-law, the
                    princes Maurice and Thomas of Savoy, and he succeeded not only in firmly
                    establishing Christine but in winning over the princes to France. This great
                    service was rewarded by his promotion to the rank of cardinal on the
                    presentation of the king of France in December 1641. On the 4th December 1642
                    Cardinal Richelieu died, and on the very next day the king sent a circular
                    letter to all officials ordering them to send in their reports to Cardinal
                    Mazarin, as they had formerly done to Cardinal Richelieu. Mazarin was thus
                    acknowledged supreme minister, but he still had a difficult part to play. The
                    king evidently could not live long, and to preserve power he must make himself
                    necessary to the queen, who would then be regent, and do this without arousing
                    the suspicions of the king or the distrust of the queen. His measures were ably
                    taken, and when the king died on May 14, 1643, to every one’s surprise her
                    husband’s minister remained the queen’s. The king had by a royal edict cumbered
                    the queen-regent with a council and other restrictions, and it was necessary to
                    get the parlement of Paris to overrule the edict, and make the queen absolute
                    regent, which was done with the greatest complaisance. Now that the queen was
                    all-powerful, it was expected she would at once dismiss Mazarin and summon her
                    own friends to power. One of them, Potier, bishop of Beauvais, already gave
                    himself airs as prime minister, but Mazarin had had the address to touch both
                    the queen’s heart by his Spanish gallantry and her desire for her son’s glory by
                    his skilful policy abroad, and he found himself able easily to overthrow the
                    clique of Importants, as they were called. That skilful policy was shown in
                    every arena on which the great Thirty Years’ War was being fought out. Mazarin
                    had inherited the policy of France during the Thirty Y ears’ War from Richelieu.
                    He had inherited his desire for the humiliation of the house of Austria in both
                    its branches, his desire to push the French frontier to the Rhine and maintain a
                    counterpoise of German states against Austria, his alliances with the
                    Netherlands and with Sweden, and his four theatres of war—on the Rhine, in
                    Flanders, in Italy, and in Catalonia. This is not the place to examine the
                    campaigns of the last five years of the great war (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Condé,</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Turenne),</hi> but it was Mazarin alone who
                    directed the French diplomacy of the period. He it was who made the peace of
                    Brömsebro between the Danes and the Swedes, and turned the latter once again
                    against the empire; he it was who sent Lionne to make the peace of Castro, and
                    combine the princes of North Italy against the Spaniards, and who made the peace
                    of Ulm between France and Bavaria, thus detaching the emperor’s best ally. He
                    made one fatal mistake,—he dreamt of the French frontier being the Rhine and the
                    Scheldt, and that a Spanish princess might bring the Spanish Netherlands as
                    dowry to Louis XIV. This roused the jealousy of the United Provinces, and they
                    made a separate peace with Spain in January 1648; but the valour of the French
                    generals made the skill of the' Spanish diplomatists of no avail, for Turenne’s
                    victory at Zusmarshausen, and Condé’s at Lens, caused the peace of Westphalia to
                    be definitely signed in October 1648. This celebrated treaty belongs rather to
                    the history of Germany than to a life of Mazarin; but two questions have been
                    often asked, whether Mazarin did not delay the peace as long as possible in
                    order to more completely ruin Germany, and whether Richelieu would have made a
                    similar peace. To the first question Mazarin’s letters, published by Μ. Cheruel,
                    prove a complete negative, for in them appears the zeal of Mazarin for the
                    peace. On the second point, Richelieu’s letters in many places indicate that his
                    treatment of the great question of frontier would have been more thorough, but
                    then he would not have been hampered in France itself.</p>
                <p>We must now notice that strange period of the Fronde which has always been
                    variously treated, for modern historians have written its history from many
                    different standpoints, all of which can be categorically supported from the
                    varying mémoires of the principal actors. Now, however, thanks to the labours of
                    Μ. Cousin on the <hi rend="italic">carnets</hi> of Mazarin, which contain the
                    substance of his inmost thoughts, and of Μ. Cheruel on the letters written to
                    and by Mazarin, it is possible to construct a more accurate and trustworthy
                    history of the Fronde than has ever yet been attempted. It is not, however,
                    intended here to trace the whole history of the Fronde, interesting as that
                    would be, but merely to trace the policy of Mazarin throughout the epoch. The
                    origin of both the Frondes was partly Mazarin’s fault. In 1645 the parlement of
                    Paris had protested against certain taxes, and had been checked by a <hi
                    rend="italic">lit de justice</hi>; and when, in 1648, it united its members in
                    the Chambre de Saint Louis for the general reform of the kingdom, Mazarin and
                    the queen, instead of holding another <hi rend="italic">lit de justice,</hi>
                    calling the states-general, or transferring the parlement out of Paris, any of
                    which measures would have broken its power, foolishly believed in the influence
                    of the victory of Lens, and threw the people of Paris on the side of the
                    parlement by the arrest of Broussel. The Fronde of the princes and the nobles,
                    on the other hand, was largely due to Mazarin’s absorption of political power.
                    These Frondeurs were not, like their ancestors, moved by great religious and
                    political sympathies, but by merely selfish aims for restoring the old licence
                    of duel and intrigue, and were only united in one sentiment, hatred to Mazarin.
                    That this was so was greatly Mazarin’s own fault; he had tried consistently to
                    play off Gaston of Orleans against Condé, and their respective followers against
                    each other, and had also, as his <hi rend="italic">carnets</hi> prove, jealously
                    kept any courtier from getting into the good graces of the queen-regent except
                    by his means, so that it was not unnatural that the nobility should hate him,
                    while the queen found herself surrounded by his creatures alone. Events followed
                    each other quickly; the day of the barricades was followed by the peace of Ruel,
                    the peace of Ruel by the arrest of the princes, by the battle of Rethel, and
                    Mazarin’s exile to Brühl before the union of the two <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n684/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0684-0653"/> Frondes. It was while in exile at Brühl that
                    Mazarin saw the mistake he had made in isolating himself and the queen, and that
                    his policy of balancing every party in the state against each other had made
                    every party distrust him. So by his counsel the queen, while nominally in league
                    with De Retz and the parliamentary Fronde, laboured to form a purely royal
                    party, wearied by civil dissensions, who should act for her and her son’s
                    interest alone, under the leadership of Mathieu Molé, the famous premier
                    president of the parlement of Paris. The new party grew in strength, and in
                    January 1652, after exactly a year’s absence, Mazarin returned to the court.
                    Turenne had now become the royal general, and out-manoeuvred Condé, while the
                    royal party at last grew to such strength in Paris that Condé had to leave the
                    capital and France. In order to promote a reconciliation with the parlement of
                    Paris, Mazarin had again retired from court, this time to Sedan, in August 1652,
                    but he returned finally in February 1653. Long had been the trial, and greatly
                    had Mazarin been to blame in allowing the Frondes to come into existence, but he
                    had retrieved his position by founding that great royal party which steadily
                    grew until Louis XIV. could fairly have said “I.’JÉtat, c’est moi.” As the war
                    had progressed, Mazarin had steadily followed Richelieu’s policy of weakening
                    the nobles on their country estates. Whenever he had an opportunity he destroyed
                    a feudal castle, and by destroying the towers which commanded nearly every town
                    in France, he freed such towns as Bourges, fur instance, from their long
                    practical subjection to the neighbouring great lord.</p>
                <p>The Fronde over, Mazarin had to build up afresh the power of France at home and
                    abroad. It is to his shame that he did so little at home. Beyond destroying the
                    brick and mortar remains of feudalism, he did nothing for the people. But abroad
                    his policy was everywhere successful, and opened the way for the policy of Louis
                    XIV. He at first, by means of an alliance with Cromwell, recovered the
                    north-western cities of France, though at the price of yielding Dunkirk to the
                    Protector. On the Baltic, France guaranteed the treaty of Oliva between her old
                    allies Sweden, Poland, and Brandenburg, which preserved her influence in that
                    quarter. In Germany he, through Lionne, formed the leagueA&gt;f the Rhine, by
                    which the states along the Rhine bound themselves under the headship of France
                    to be on their guard against the house of Austria. By such measures Spain was
                    induced to sue for peace, which was finally signed in the Isle of Pheasants on
                    the Bidassoa, and which is known as the treaty of the Pyrenees. By it Spain
                    recovered Franche Comté, but ceded to France Roussillon, and much of French
                    Flanders; and, what was of greater ultimate importance to Europe, Louis XIV. was
                    to marry a Spanish princess, who was to renounce her claims to the Spanish
                    succession if her dowry was paid, which Mazarin knew could not happen at present
                    from the emptiness of the Spanish exchequer. He returned to Paris in declining
                    health, and did not long survive the unhealthy sojourn on the Bidassoa; after
                    some political instruction to his young master, he passed away at Vincennes on
                    March 9, 1661, leaving a fortune estimated at from 18, to 40 million livres
                    behind him, and his nieces married into the greatest families of France and
                    Italy.</p>
                <p>The man who could have had such success, who could have made the treaties of
                    Westphalia and the Pyrenees, who could have weathered the storm of the Fronde,
                    and left France at peace with itself and with Europe to Louis XIV., must have
                    been a great man; and historians, relying too much on the brilliant memoirs of
                    his adversaries, like De Retz, are apt to rank him too low. That he had many a
                    petty fault there can be no doubt; that he was avaricious and double-dealing was
                    also undoubted; and his <hi rend="italic">carnets</hi> show to what unworthy
                    means he had recourse to maintain his influence over the queen. What that
                    influence was will be always debated, but both his <hi rend="italic"
                    >carnets</hi> and the Brühl letters show that a real personal affection,
                    amounting to passion on the queen’s part, existed. Whether they were ever
                    married may be doubted; but that hypothesis is made more possible by Μ. CherueΓs
                    having been able to prove from Mazarin’s letters that the cardinal himself had
                    never taken more than the minor orders, which could always be thrown ott. With
                    regard to France he played a more patriotic part than Condé or Turenne, for he
                    never treated with the Spaniards, and his letters show that in the midst of his
                    difficulties he followed with intense eagerness every movement on the frontiers.
                    It is that immense mass of letters, now in course of publication, that prove the
                    real greatness of the statesman, and disprove De Betz's portrait, which is
                    carefully arranged to show off his enemy against the might of Richelieu. To
                    concede that the master was the greater man and the greateι <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ,</hi> statesman does not imply that Mazarin was but a foil
                    to his predecessor. It is true that we find none of those deep plans for the
                    internal prosperity of France which shine through Richelieu’s policy. Mazarin
                    was not a Frenchman, but a citizen of the world, and always paid most attention
                    to foreign affairs; in his letters all that could teach a diplomatist, is to be
                    found, broad general views of policy, minute details carefully elaborated, keen
                    insight into men’s characters, cunning directions when to dissimulate or when to
                    be frank. From first to last the diplomatist peeps forth, and gives the key to
                    his character, and to the causes of his success. Italian though he was by birth,
                    education, and nature, France owed him a great debt for his skilful management
                    during the early years of Louis XIV., and the king owed him yet more, for he had
                    not only transmitted to him a nation at peace, but had educated for him his
                    great servants Le Tellier, Lionne, and Colbert. Literary men owed him also much;
                    not only did he throw his famous library open to them, but he pensioned all
                    their leaders, including Descartes, Voiture, Balzac, and Pierre Corneille. The
                    last-named, the greatest of them all, did not care for Mazarin as a paymaster
                    only, but as a statesman; he was a profound royalist, believing that absolutism
                    alone could save France from the horrors of religious wars, or the selfish
                    turbulence of a Fronde, and to Mazarin he applied, with an adroit allusion to
                    his birthplace, in the dedication of his <hi rend="italic">Pompée,</hi> the line
                    of Virgil—</p>
                <p>“Tu regere imperio populos, Romane, memento.”</p>
                <p>All the earlier works ’ on Mazarin, and early accounts of his administration, of
                    which the best were Bazin’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                    France sous Louis XIII.</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >soils</hi><hi rend="italic">le</hi><hi rend="italic">Cardinal Mazarin,</hi> 4
                    vols., 1846, and Saint-Aulaire’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de la Fronde,</hi> have been superseded by Μ. Cheruel’s admirable
                    <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de France pendant</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">la minorité</hi><hi rend="italic">de Louis XIV.,</hi> 4 vols.,
                    1879-80, which covers from 1643-51, and its sequel <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">de France sous</hi><hi rend="italic">le
                    Ministère</hi><hi rend="italic">de. Cardinal Mazarin,</hi> 2 vols., 1881-82,
                    which is the first account of the period written by one able to sift the
                    statements of De Retz and the memoir writers, and rest upon such documents as
                    Mazarin’s letters and <hi rend="italic">carnets.</hi> To Μ. Cheruel the
                    Government of France has entrusted the task of editing Mazarin’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Letters,</hi> of which two volumes have at present appeared, which
                    must be carefully studied by any student of the history of France. For his “<hi
                    rend="italic">carnets</hi>” reference must be made to Μ. Cousin’s articles in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Journal des Savants</hi>; for his early life to Cousin’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Jeunesse</hi><hi rend="italic">de Mazarin,</hi> 1865, and for
                    the careers of his nieces to Renée’s <hi rend="italic">Les Nieces de
                    Mazarin,</hi> 1856. For the Mazarinades or squibs written against him in Paris
                    during the Fronde, see Moreau’s <hi rend="italic">Bibliographic des
                    Mazarinades,</hi> 1850, containing an account of 4082 Mazarinades. On the
                    Fronde, also, consult Gaillardin’s <hi rend="italic">Histoire</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de Louis XIV.,</hi> 6 vols., 1876-78, and Feillet’s interesting
                    <hi rend="italic">Misère au temps de la Fronde.</hi> For his foreign policy,
                    besides his <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> see Valfrey’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hugues de Lionne,</hi> and Mignet s <hi rend="italic">Histoire des
                    Négociations</hi><hi rend="italic">relatives</hi><hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">la Succession d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Espagne.</hi> (Η. Μ.
                    S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
