<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0328-0309-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MAIZE, or Indian Corn (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    309)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:878993">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="fast:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838229">Breading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198482">Bread</term>
                    <term ref="fast:900541">Ear</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812576">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838515">Brewers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205190">Peru</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204739">Maryland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49w0934b">Germs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49w0930d">Fodder</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hm8r">Bread</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94f4j">Ear</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n328/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MAIZE, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Indian Corn</hi></label>, <hi
                    rend="italic">Zea Mays,</hi> I.., from <hi rend="italic">ζea</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">ζu&lt;i,</hi> which appears to have been “spelt” <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Triticum</hi><hi rend="italic">spelta,</hi> I..), according to the description
                    of Theophrastus, is of the tribe <hi rend="italic">Phalarideae.</hi>.of the
                    order <hi rend="italic">Gramineae</hi> or grasses. It is unknown in the native
                    state, but is most probably indigenous to tropical America (Endlicher, <hi
                    rend="italic">Gen. Pl.,</hi> No. 742). Small grains of an unknown variety have
                    been found in the ancient tombs of Peru. Bonafous, however <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Histoire naturelle</hi><hi rend="italic">du Ma'is∖,</hi> quotes authorities
                    (Bock, 1532, Ruel and Fuchs) as believing that it came from Asia, and maize was
                    said by Santa Rosa de Viterbo to have been brought by the Arabs into Spain in
                    the 13th century. A drawing of maize is also given by Bonafous from a Chinese
                    work on natural history, <hi rend="italic">Li-chi-tclιin,</hi> dated 1562, a
                    little over sixty years after the discovery of the New World. It is not figured
                    on Egyptian monuments, nor was any mention made of it by Eastern travellers in
                    Africa or Asia prior to the 16th century. On the authority, however, of Mr J.
                    Crawford, who resided for nine years in Java, Bonafous says it had been
                    cultivated from a very ancient period in the Asiatic islands under the equator,
                    and that it was received thence into China, and so passed westwards into India
                    and Turkey, hence its name of “Turkey corn,” under which title Gerard in 1597
                    figured and described seven kinds, as well as one called “Corne of Asia.” Both
                    Gerard and Bonafous think that it first came from the East, but that on the
                    discovery of America it was reintroduced into Europe from that country. The
                    former observes :—“These kinds of graine were first brought into Spaine, and
                    then into other provinces of Europe out of Asia, which is in the Turkes
                    Dominions; as also out of America and the Hands adioyn-ing from the East and
                    West Indies and Virginia, &amp;c.” Humboldt and others, however, do not hesitate
                    to say that it originated solely in America. It had been long and extensively
                    cultivated there at the period of the discovery of the New World. The plant is
                    monoecious, producing the staminate (male) flowers in a large feathery panicle
                    at the summit, and the (female) dense spikes of flowers, or “cobs,” in the axils
                    of the leaves below, the long pink styles hanging out like a silken tassel. They
                    are invested by the sheaths of leaves, much used in packing oranges in South
                    Europe, and the more delicate ones for cigarettes in South America. The
                    accompanying figures are after Nees von Esenbeck, <hi rend="italic">Gen. Pl. Fl.
                    Germ.</hi> Fig. 1 shows a branch of the terminal male inflorescence. Fig. 2 is a
                    single spikelet of the same, containing two florets, with the three stamens of
                    one only protruded. Fig. 3 is a spike of the female inflorescence, protected by
                    the sheaths of leaves,—the blades being also present. Usually the sheaths
                    terminate in a point, the blades being arrested. Fig. 4 is a spikelet of the
                    female inflorescence, consisting of two outer glumes, the lower one ciliated,
                    which enclose two florets,—one barren (sometimes fertile), consisting of a
                    flowering glume and pale only, and the other fertile, containing the pistil with
                    elongated style. The mass of styles from the whole spike is pendulous from the
                    summit of the sheaths, as in fig. 3.</p>
                <p>Fig. 5 shows the fruit or grain.</p>
                <p>More than three hundred varieties are known, which differ more among themselves
                    than those of any other cereal. Some come to maturity in two months, others
                    require seven months; some are as many feet high as others are inches; some have
                    kernels eleven times larger than others. They vary similarly in shape and size
                    of ears, colour of the grain, which may be white, yellow, purple, striped,
                    &amp;c., and also in physical characters and chemical composition,—in short, in
                    all those characters in which the different species of a genus differ among
                    themselves. The varieties grown most abundantly in the United States may be
                    roughly grouped into four great classes. The “Flint” varieties are most common
                    east of Lake Erie and north of Maryland, and the “Dent” varieties are the common
                    ones west and south of these points. The “Horsetooth” varieties are grown
                    extensively only in the south, and there they are grown along with the dent.
                    These three classes pass into each other by every gradation, and the grain from
                    all is similar in chemical composition. The “Sweet” varieties are not grown for
                    the ripe grain, but for boiling corn, and that the stalks may serve as “corn
                    fodder.” “Green corn” was an important food with the native Indians. Many of the
                    tribes celebrated its season with religious ceremonies and festivals. In the
                    large cities of America “green corn” is a table luxury, but in the smaller towns
                    and country districts it is an important article of food. Chemical analysis, as
                    well as common experience, shows that this is a very nutritious article of food,
                    being richer in albuminoids <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n329/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0329-0310"/> than any other cereals when ripe (calculated in
                    the dry weight). It is capable of being grown in the tropics from the level of
                    the sea to a height equal that of the Pyrenees, and in the south and middle of
                    Europe, but it cannot be grown in England with any chance of profit, except
                    perhaps as fodder. Frost kills the plant in all its stages and all its
                    varieties; and the crop does not flourish well if the nights are cool, no matter
                    how favourable the other conditions. Consequently it is the first crop to
                    disappear as one ascends into the mountain regions, and comparatively little is
                    grown west of the great plains of North America. In Brittany, where it scarcely
                    ripens the grain, it furnishes a strong crop in the autumn upon sandy soil where
                    clover and lucern will yield but a poor produce. It prefers a deep, rich, warm,
                    dry, and mellow soil, and hence the rich bottoms and fertile prairies of the
                    Mississippi basin constitute the region of its greatest production. Illinois
                    leads in total amount, producing in 1879 nearly 326 millions of bushels, or 105
                    bushels per head of population. The region of chief production in the United
                    States may be described as a rude ellipse 900 miles long from east to west by
                    600 miles wide, with Springfield (the capital of Illinois) as its centre. This
                    region produces annually from 1000 to 1400 millions of bushels, or nearly
                    three-fourths of the total crop of the country.</p>
                <p>As an article of food, maize is one of the most extensively used grains in the
                    world. Although rich in nitrogenous matter and fat, it does not make good bread.
                    A mixture of rye and corn meal, however, makes an excellent coarse bread,
                    formerly much used in the Atlantic States, and a similar bread is now the chief
                    coarse bread of Portugal, and some parts of Spain. When the harder “flint”
                    varieties are roasted, the grains “pop,” the skin bursts, and the white interior
                    swells up, emitting a pleasant odour. It is either baked into cakes called <hi
                    rend="italic">tortilla</hi> by the Indians of Yucatan, or made into a kind of
                    porridge, as in Ireland. When deprived of the. gluten it constitutes oswego,
                    maizena, or corn flour (see Letheby’s <hi rend="italic">Lectures on Food,</hi>
                    p. 19; and <hi rend="italic">Foods,</hi> by E. Smith, 156). Maize contains more
                    oil than any other cereal, ranging from 3 ’ 5 to 9 ’ 5 per cent, ia the
                    commercial grain. This is one of the factors in its va <hi rend="superscript">
                    1</hi> ue for fattening purposes. In distilling and some other processes this
                    oil is separated and forms an article of commerce. When maize is sown broadcast
                    or closely planted in drills, the ears may not develop at all, but the stalk is
                    richer in sugar and sweeter, and this is the basis of growing “corn-fodder.” The
                    amount of forage that may be produced in this way is enormous; 50,000 to 80,000
                    B) of green fodder are grown per acre, which makes 8000 to 12,000 lb as
                    field-cured. Sugar and molasses have from time to time been manufactured from
                    the corn stalks, but at present this manufacture is not commercially
                    successful.</p>
                <p>In the treeless western prairies maize is often grown for fuel, as in many places
                    fuel can be procured so cheaply in no other way. A hundred bushels of ears is
                    equal in heating power to a cord of the best hard wood, and may be grown for a
                    price less than a cord of hard wood brings in the large cities. The use of corn
                    in the industries, as the raw material for the manufacture of alcohol, whisky,
                    starch, glucose, oil, and various food products, increases year by year, with
                    the increase of facilities for production and the increasing applications of
                    chemistry to the arts.</p>
                <p>For fuller details see a paper by Professor W. H. Brewer, Yale Col., Conn., from
                    which some of the above details are taken, as well as the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Special Report on Cereal Products,</hi> Washington, 1882, and the 38th <hi
                    rend="italic">Annual Report</hi> of the New York State Agricultural Society,
                    1878. (G. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
