<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0688-0657-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MEASLES (9th edition, volume 15, page 657)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208479">Fiji</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v30g">Symptoms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zh9p">Stage</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45t3g156">Catarrh</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1140998">Symptoms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952743">Health</term>
                    <term ref="fast:848912">Catarrh</term>
                    <term ref="fast:923528">Fever</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n688/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MEASLES</label><hi rend="italic">{Morbilli,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Rubeola</hi>; German, <hi rend="italic">Masern</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi> French, <hi rend="italic">Rougeole),</hi> an acute
                    infectious disease occurring mostly in children. It appears to have been known
                    from an early period in the history of medicine, mention being made of it in the
                    writings of Rhazes and others of the Arabian physicians in the 10th century. For
                    long, however, its specific nature was not recognized, and it was held to be a
                    variety of small-pox. After the non-identity of these two diseases had been
                    established, measles and scarlet fever continued to be confounded with each
                    other; and in the account given by Sydenham of epidemics of measles in London in
                    1670 and 1674 it is evident that even that accurate observer had not as yet
                    clearly perceived their pathological distinction, although it would seem to have
                    been made a century earlier by Ingrassias, a physician of Palermo. It is only w
                    ithin a comparatively recent period that measles has come to be universally
                    regarded as a distinct and independent malady.</p>
                <p>Like the other eruptive fevers (exanthemata), to which class of diseases measles
                    belongs, its progress is marked by several stages more or less sharply
                    defined.</p>
                <p>After the reception of the contagion into the system a period of incubation or
                    latency precedes the development of the disease, during which scarcely any
                    disturbance of the health is perceptible. This period appears to vary in
                    duration, but it may be stated as generally lasting for from ten to fourteen
                    days, when it is followed by the invasion of the symptoms specially
                    characteristic of measles. These consist in the somewhat sudden onset of acute
                    catarrh of the mucous membranes. Sneezing, accompanied with a watery discharge,
                    sometimes bleeding, from the nose, redness and watering of the eyes, cough of a
                    short, frequent, and noisy character, with little or no expectoration,
                    hoarseness of the voice, and occasionally sickness and diarrhoea, are the chief
                    local phenomena of this stage. But along with these there is well-marked febrile
                    disturbance, the temperature being elevated (102°-104° F.), and the pulse rapid,
                    while headache, thirst, and restlessness are usually present to a greater or
                    less degree. In some instances, however, these initial symptoms are so slight
                    that they almost escape notice, and the child is allowed to associate with
                    others at a time when, as will be afterwards seen, the contagion of the disease
                    is most active. In rare cases, especially in young children, convulsions usher
                    in, or occur in the course of, this stage of invasion, which lasts as a rule for
                    four or five days, the febrile symptoms, however, showing some tendency to
                    undergo abatement after the second day. On the fourth or fifth day after the
                    invasion, sometimes later, rarely earlier, the characteristic eruption appears
                    on the skin, being first noticed on the brow, cheeks, chin, also behind the
                    ears, and on the neck. It consists of small spots of a dusky red or crimson
                    colour, slightly elevated above the surface, at first isolated, but tending to
                    become grouped together into patches of irregular, occasionally crescentic,
                    outline, with portions of skin free from the eruption intervening. The face
                    acquires a swollen and bloated appearance, which, taken along with the catarrh
                    of the nostrils and eyes, is almost characteristic, and renders the diagnosis at
                    this stage a matter of no difficulty. The eruption spreads downwards over the
                    body and limbs, which are soon thickly studded with the red spots or patches.
                    Sometimes these become confluent over a considerable surface, giving rise to a
                    larger area of uniform redness. The rash continues to come out for two or three
                    days, and then begins to fade in the order in which it first showed itself,
                    namely, from above downwards. By the end of about a week after its first
                    appearance scarcely any trace of the eruption remains beyond a faint staining of
                    the skin. Occasionally during convalescence slight peeling of the epidermis
                    takes place, but much less frequently and distinctly than is the case in scarlet
                    fever, At the commencement of the eruptive stage the fever, catarrh, and other
                    constitutional disturbance, which were present from the beginning, become
                    aggravated, the temperature often rising to 105° or more, and there is headache,
                    thirst, furred tongue, and soreness of the throat, upon which red patches
                    similar to those on the surface of the body may be observed. These symptoms
                    usually decline as soon as the rash has attained its maximum, and often there
                    occurs a sudden and extensive fall of temperature, indicating that the crisis of
                    the disease has been reached. In favourable cases convalescence proceeds
                    rapidly, the patient feeling perfectly well even before the rash has faded from
                    the skin.</p>
                <p>Measles may, however, occur in a very severe or malignant form, in which the
                    symptoms throughout are of urgent character, the rash but feebly developed, and
                    of dark purple hue, while there is great prostration of strength, accompanied
                    with intense catarrh of the respiratory or gastro-intestinal mucous membrane.
                    Such cases, always of serious import, are happily rare, occurring mostly in
                    circumstances of bad hygiene, both as regards the individual and
                    his*surroundings. On the other hand, cases of measles are often met with of so
                    mild a form throughout that the patient can scarcely be persuaded to submit to
                    treatment.</p>
                <p>Measles as a disease derives its chief importance in the view of medical men from
                    the risk, by no means slight, ofcertain complications which are apt to arise
                    during its course, more especially inflammatory affections of the respiratory
                    organs. These are most liable to occur in the colder seasons of the year and in
                    very young and delicato children. It has been already stated that irritation of
                    the respiratory passages is one of the symptoms characteristic of measles, but
                    that this subsides with the decline of the eruption. Not unfrequently, however,
                    these symptoms, instead of abating, become aggravated, and bronchitis of the
                    capillary form (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Bronchitis),</hi> or pneumonia,
                    generally of the diffuse or lobular variety (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Pneumonia),</hi> impart a gravity to the case which it did not originally
                    possess. By far the greater proportion of the mortality in measles is due to its
                    complications, of which those just mentioned are the most common, but which also
                    include inflammatory affections of the larynx, with attacks resembling croup,
                    and also diarrhoea assuming a dysenteric character. Or there may remain as
                    direct results of the disease chronic ophthalmia, or discharge from the ears,
                    with deafness, and occasionally a form of gangrene affecting the tissues of the
                    mouth or cheeks and other parts of the body, leading to disfigurement and even
                    endangering life.</p>
                <p>Apart, however, from those immediate risks, it deserves to be borne in mind that
                    in measles there appears to be a tendency in many cases for the disease to leave
                    behind a weakened and vulnerable condition of the general health, which may
                    render children, previously robust, delicate and liable to chest complaints, and
                    is in not a few instances the precursor of some of those tubercular affections
                    to which the period of childhood and youth is liable.</p>
                <p>These various effects or sequelae of measles plainly indicate that although in
                    itself a comparatively mild <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n689/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0689-0658"/> ailment, it cannot safely be regarded with
                    indifference. Indeed it is doubtful whether any other disease of early life
                    demands more careful watching as to its influence on the health. Happily many of
                    those attending evils now alluded to may by proper management be averted.</p>
                <p>Measles is a disease of the earlier years of childhood. Like other infectious
                    maladies, it is admittedly rare, though not unknown, in nurslings or infants
                    under six months old. It is comparatively seldom met with in adults, but this is
                    simply due to the fact that most persons have undergone an attack in early life,
                    since, where this has not been the case, the old suffer equally with the young.
                    All races of men appear liable to this disease, provided that which constitutes
                    the essential factor in its origin and spread exists, namely, contagion. Some
                    countries enjoy long immunity from outbreaks of measles, but it has frequently
                    been found in such cases that when the contagion has once been introduced the
                    disease extends with great rapidity and virulence. This was shown in two
                    well-known instances in recent times,—namely, the epidemic in the Faroe Islands
                    in 1846, where, within six months after the arrival of a single case of measles,
                    more than three-fourths of the entire population were attacked and many
                    perished; and the similarly produced and still more destructive outbreak in Fiji
                    in 1875, in which it was estimated that about one-fourth of the inhabitants were
                    cut off by the disease within a period of about three months (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Fiji).</hi> In both these cases the great mortality has been
                    ascribed to the complications of the malady, specially induced by over-crowding,
                    by insanitary surroundings, the absence of proper nourishment and nursing for
                    the sick, and the utter prostration and terror of the people, rather than to any
                    marked malignancy in the type of the disease.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Transactions of the
                    Epidemiological Society.</hi> London, 1877.</p></note> Not a few authorities,
                    however, while fully recognizing the baneful effect of these unfavourable
                    conditions, are yet disposed to hold that epidemics of this kind, when occurring
                    in what might be termed a virgin soil, are apt to possess an innate severity. In
                    many lands, such as the United Kingdom, measles is rarely absent, especially
                    from large centres of population, where sporadic cases are found in greater or
                    less number at all seasons. Every now and then epidemics arise from the
                    extension of the disease among those members of a community who have not been in
                    some measure'protected by a previous attack. There are few diseases so
                    contagious as measles, and its rapid spread in epidemic outbreaks is no doubt
                    due to the well-ascertained fact that contagion is most potent in the earlier
                    stages, even before its real nature has been evinced by the characteristic
                    appearances on the skin. Hence the difficulty of timely isolation, and the
                    readiness with which the disease is spread in schools and families. There is
                    little doubt too that the contagion may be carried from one place to another by
                    persons themselves unaffected, as well as by clothing, &amp;c., although its
                    tenacity and activity in this respect is apparently much less marked than that
                    of small-pox or scarlet fever. Of the nature of the infecting agent nothing
                    certain is known. Recent investigations into the mode of origin of others of the
                    acute infectious diseases, and the discovery in the blood and tissues in the
                    case of some of them of lower forms of organic life (bacilli), which can be
                    isolated and can by inoculation be made to communicate the particular malady to
                    which they are related, give countenance to the opinion, now widely entertained,
                    that the infecting principle of the exanthemata is of this nature. The subject,
                    however, is still under investigation, and more information is wanting before
                    definite statements can be made. Second attacks of measles are occasionally
                    observed, but they are rare.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Treatment.—</hi> The treatment of measles embraces the
                    preventive measures to be adopted in the case of an outbreak by the isolation of
                    the sick at as early a period as possible. Epidemics have often, especially in
                    limited localities, been curtailed by such a precaution. In families with little
                    house accommodation this measure is frequently, for the reason already referred
                    to regarding the communicable period of the disease, ineffectual; nevertheless
                    where practicable it ought to be tried, for it is a grave error needlessly to
                    expose the healthy children in a family to the risk of infection under the idea
                    that they must necessarily take the disease at some time or other. The
                    unaffected children should likewise be kept from school for a time (probably
                    about three weeks from the outbreak in the family would suffice if no other case
                    occur in the interval), and all clothing in contact with the patient should be
                    subjected to disinfection or thorough washing. In extensive epidemics it is
                    often desirable to close the schools of a locality for a time. As regards
                    special treatment, in an ordinary case of measles little is required beyond what
                    is necessary in febrile conditions generally, Confinement to bed in a somewhat
                    darkened room, into which, however, air is freely admitted in such a manner as
                    to avoid the risk of draughts, light nourishing liquid diet (soups, milk,
                    &amp;c.), and mild diaphoretic remedies such as the acetate of ammonia or
                    ipecacuanha, are all that is necessary in the febrile stage. When the catarrhal
                    symptoms are very severe, the hot bath or warm packing to the body generally or
                    to the chest and throat afford relief, and the same measures may with advantage
                    be adopted should the eruption be but feebly developed or tend to recede, and
                    especially should convulsions set in. The serious chest complications of measles
                    are to be dealt with by those measures applicable for the relief of the
                    particular symptoms (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Bronchitis, Pneumonia).</hi> The
                    inhalation of vapour and the use of the preparations of ammonia are of special
                    efficacy. Diarrhoea is treated by the usual remedies, including carefully
                    administered doses of Dover’s powder, chalk, &amp;c. During convalescence the
                    patient must be guarded from exposure to cold, and for a time after recovery the
                    state of the health ought to be watched with the view of averting the evils,
                    both local and constitutional, which but too often follow this disease. -</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">German Measles</hi><hi rend="italic">(Rötheln,</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Epidemic Roseola)</hi> is a term applied to a contagious eruptive
                    disorder having certain points of resemblance to measles, and, according to some
                    observers, also to scarlet fever, but exhibiting its distinct individuality in
                    the fact that it protects from neither of these diseases. It occurs most
                    commonly in children, and is occasionally seen in extensive epidemics. Beyond
                    confinement to the house in the eruptive stage, which, from the slight symptoms
                    experienced, is often difficult of accomplishment, no special treatment is
                    called for. There is little doubt that the disease is often mistaken for true
                    measles, and many of the alleged second attacks of the latter malady are
                    probably cases of rötheln. The chief points of difference are the following
                    :—</p>
                <p>1. The absence of distinct premonitory symptoms, the stage of invasion, which in
                    measles is usually of four days’ duration, and accompanied with well-marked
                    fever and catarrh, being in rötheln either wholly absent or exceedingly slight,
                    enduring only for one day.</p>
                <p>2. The eruption of rötheln, which, although as regards its locality and manner of
                    progress similar to measles, differs somewhat in its appearance, the spots being
                    of smaller size, paler colour, and with less tendency to grouping in crescentic
                    patches. The rash attains its maximum in about one day, and quickly disappears.
                    There is no accompanying increase of temperature in this stage as in
                    measles.</p>
                <p>3. The milder character of the symptoms of rötheln throughout its whole course,
                    and the absence of complications and of liability to subsequent impairment of
                    health such as have been seen to appertain to measles. (J. 0. A.) <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n690/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0690-0659"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
