<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0660-0629-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MATHEMATICS (9th edition, volume 15, page 629)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1161531">Units</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804885">Algebra</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1046386">Operationalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1132026">Statics</term>
                    <term ref="fast:851789">Chains</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m6295w">Statics</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93f63">Chains</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40r9m60q">Units</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40r9m368">Algebra</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dv1cn3t">Functions</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n660/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MATHEMATICS</label>. Any conception which is definitely and
                    completely determined by means of a finite number of specifications, say by
                    assigning a finite number of elements, is a mathematical conception. Mathematics
                    has for its function to develop the consequences involved in the definition of a
                    group of mathematical conceptions. Interdependence and mutual logical
                    consistency among the members of the group are postulated, otherwise the group
                    would either have to be treated as several distinct groups, or would lie beyond
                    the sphere of mathematics.</p>
                <p>As an example of a mathematical conception we may take “a triangle”; regarded
                    without reference to its position in space, this is determined when three
                    elements are specified, say its three sides; or we may take a “colour
                    sensation,” which, on Young’s theory, is determined when the amounts of the
                    three fundamental colour sensations that enter into it are stated. As an example
                    of a non-mathematical conception we may take “a man,” “a mineral,” “iron,” no
                    one of which admits of being so determined by a finite number of specifications
                    that all its properties can be truly said to be deducible from the
                    definition.</p>
                <p>A mathematical conception is, from its very nature, abstract; indeed its
                    abstractness is usually of a higher order than the abstractness of the logician.
                    Thus, for instance, we may neglect the other attributes of a body and consider
                    merely its form; we thus reach the abstract idea of “form.” But the form of an
                    irregular fragment of stone does not admit of being finitely specified, and is
                    therefore not susceptible of mathematical treatment. If, however, we have a
                    carefully squared cubical block of granite to deal with, for most practical
                    purposes its form is specified by stating that it is a cube, and assigning one
                    element, viz., an edge of the abstract mathematical cube by which we replace it.
                    This example illustrates at once the limits of mathematical reasoning and the
                    nature of the bearing of mathematics on practice.</p>
                <p>A variety of words have been used to denote the dependence of a mathematical
                    conception upon its elements. It is frequently said, for instance, that the
                    conception is a “function” of its elements. One word has recently come into use
                    which is very convenient, inasmuch as it draws attention at once to the
                    fundamental idea involved in mathematical conception and to the prime object of
                    mathematical contemplation, viz., “manifoldness.”</p>
                <p>Number is involved in the notion of a manifoldness both directly, as any one can
                    see, and also indirectly in a manner which the mind untrained to mathematical
                    thinking does not so readily understand. Take on the one hand the case of a
                    triangle considered without reference to its position but merely as composed of
                    three limited straight lines, it may be completely determined in various ways by
                    assigning three elements. A triangle may therefore be called a triple discrete
                    manifoldness. A plane quadrilateral considered in the same way (being fully
                    determined when four sides and a diagonal are known) is a quintuple discrete
                    manifoldness; and a plane polygon of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> sides a (2n -
                    3)-ple discrete manifoldness. Consider on the other hand the assemblage of
                    points on a given straight line, they are infinite in number yet so related that
                    any one of them is singled out by assigning its distance from an arbitrarily
                    chosen fixed point on the line. Such an assemblage is called a onefold
                    continuous manifoldness, or simply a onefold manifoldness; another example of
                    the same kind is the totality of instants in a period of time. The assemblage of
                    points on a surface is a twofold manifoldness; the assemblage of points in
                    tridimensional space is a threefold manifoldness; the values of a continous
                    function of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> arguments an ??-fold manifoldness.</p>
                <p>It should be observed that the distinction between discrete and continuous
                    manifoldness is not of necessity inherent in the conception. For one purpose we
                    may treat a conception as a discrete manifoldness, for another as a continuous
                    manifoldness. Thus we have seen that an unlimited straight' line may be treated
                    as a onefold continuous manifoldness; but, if we regard it as a whole, and with
                    reference to the fact that its position in space is determined by four data, it
                    becomes a quadruple discrete manifoldness.</p>
                <p>The primary, although not the only, operation in the treatment of a discrete
                    manifoldness is numbering or counting; hence arises the pure mathematical
                    science of number, comprehending (abstract) <hi rend="italic">Arithmetic</hi>
                    and its higher branch commonly called the <hi rend="italic">Theory of
                    Numbers.</hi> Without entering into a discussion of the definitions and axioms
                    of the science of number, it will be sufficient here to remark that all
                    numerical operations are reducible to three fundamental laws commonly called the
                    commutative, associative, and distributive laws. The four fundamental processes,
                    or four species, as they are sometimes called, two of which, addition and
                    multiplication, are direct, and two, subtraction and division, inverse, are
                    solely defined by and derive their meaning from the three laws of operation just
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p>A careful consideration of the methods in vogue for dealing with continuous
                    manifoldness shows that they reduce themselves to two, which may be called the
                    synoptic method and the analytic method. In the synoptic method we deduce the
                    properties of a manifoldness by contemplating it as a whole, aiding our
                    understanding, when it is necessary to do so, by a diagram, a model, or any
                    other concrete device more or less refined according to circumstances. In the
                    analytic method we fix our attention upon the individual elements of the
                    manifoldness, usually defining each element by a definite number of
                    specifications the variation of which leads us from element to element of the
                    given manifoldness. We examine the properties of an element in the most general
                    manner, and from them we predicate the properties of the manifoldness as a
                    whole.</p>
                <p>The best and most familiar examples of the synoptic treatment of manifoldness are
                    the different varieties of pure geometry. Among these we may mention the
                    apagogic geometry of the Greeks, which starts with a collection of definitions
                    and axioms, enunciates and proves proposition after proposition with great
                    attention to strict logical form and with continual reference to the grounds of
                    inference, but pays little attention to the ordering of theorems with a view to
                    mutual illustration, and carefully suppresses all traces of the method by which
                    the propositions were or might have been discovered. It is true that the Greeks
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n661/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0661-0630"/> were in possession of a method, called by them
                    analysis, which had for its object the discovery of geometrical truth. But this
                    consisted merely in taking any proposition suspected to be true and tracing its
                    consequences until one was reached which either contradicted a known proposition
                    or else was true and capable of leading by a direct process of reasoning
                    (synthesis) to the proposition in question. In this we have no trace of the
                    systematic development of geometric truth, and the method was apparently
                    regarded by the ancients themselvês as imperfect, for it makes no figure in such
                    of their systematic treatises as have reached us. In somewhat sharp contrast
                    with the Grecian geometry, but still essentially synoptic in method, stand the
                    different varieties of modern geometry,—which aims at greater generality in its
                    definitions, pays less explicit attention to logical form, but arranges
                    geometrical propositions as much as possible in the natural order of development
                    or discovery, and above all makes extensive use of the principle of continuity.
                    As examples of the modern geometry may be cited the descriptive geometry <hi
                    rend="italic">{Géométrie</hi><hi rend="italic">Descriptive,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Darstellende Geometrie')</hi> of Monge; the projective geometry
                    <hi rend="italic">{Géométrie</hi><hi rend="italic">Projective,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Geometrie der</hi><hi rend="italic">Lage)</hi> of Poncelet,
                    Steiner, and Von Staudt; and the geometry of transformation in general, of which
                    projective geometry is but a particular case. There is one other highly
                    interesting form of modern geometry, which, although analytic in some of its
                    developments, and often exhibited in close alliance with other analytical
                    methods, is nevertheless synoptic as to its fundamental principle, viz.,
                    arithmic geometry <hi rend="italic">{Abzählende Geometrie)</hi> or theory of
                    characteristics, which originated in the characteristic equations of Plücker,
                    and was developed into a powerful special method by Chasles and others. See <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Geometry</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">Curve.</hi></p>
                <p>Geometry, however, is not the only field for the synoptic treatment of
                    manifoldness. This is obvious if we reflect that any magnitude whatever may be
                    represented by a line; so that any function of not more than two elements may be
                    represented by a geometrical construction and treated by any method applicable
                    in geometry. Since the famous dissertation of Riemann, <hi rend="italic">On the
                    Hypotheses that form the Basis of Geometry,</hi> mathematicians have been
                    familiar with the fact that the methods of geometry suitably generalized can be
                    applied to the treatment of an »-fold manifoldness; and in point of fact the
                    synoptic treatment of manifoldness under the name of »-dimensional geometry has
                    been usefully employed by Cayley and others as an adjunct to the analytic
                    method.</p>
                <p>The fundamental characteristic of the analytical treatment of an »-fold
                    manifoldness is the specification of an element by means of » continuously
                    varying quantities or variables (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Measurement).</hi> For
                    dealing with continuous as distinguished from discrete quantity we have the
                    special analytical method of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Infinitesimal
                    Calculus</hi><hi rend="italic">{q.vf</hi> built upon the notion of a limit, with
                    its various branches, viz., the differential calculus, the integral calculus
                    including differential equations, the calculus of functions, and the theory of
                    functions in general (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Function).</hi> But, whether we
                    make use of the algorithm of the infinitesimal calculus or not, we find upon
                    examination that all analytical operations with continuous quantity fall under
                    the three laws of commutation, association, and distribution, so that they are
                    fundamentally identical with the operations with discrete quantity; the
                    difference so far as there is any consists simply in the greater generality of
                    the operand. The same fact may be looked at instructively in another light.
                    Whether we consider analytical processes in concrete applications or look at
                    them abstractly, we are equally led to the notion of a unit, by the
                    multiplication or subdivision of which all the other quantities that enter into
                    our calculus are derived. The exigencies of continuity are met by allowing that
                    the multiplication or subdivision of the unit can be carried on to an unlimited
                    extent; but in any case where analytical formulae have to be reduced to
                    arithmetical calculation (in which of course only a finite number of figures or
                    arithmetical symbols can be used) the subdivision (or multiplication) of the
                    unit actually stops short at a certain point; in other words, all our methods
                    are, in practice at least, discrete. Here therefore we have the meeting point of
                    discrete and continuous quantity, and on this ground alone we might infer the
                    fundamental identity of their laws of operation.</p>
                <p>The abstract science of quantity which we have just seen to be the essential part
                    of the analytic treatment of manifoldness receives the name of <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Algebra</hi><hi rend="italic">{&lt;pv.).</hi> It was found very
                    early in the history of that science that the full development of which it is
                    capable could not be attained without great extension of the idea of quantity.
                    This necessity first arose in connexion with the inverse operations, such as
                    subtraction, the extraction of roots, and the numerical solution of algebraical
                    equations (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Equation),</hi> of which root extraction is
                    merely a particular case. In this way arose essentially negative quantities, and
                    the so-called impossible or imaginary quantities. The former may be said to
                    depend on a new abstract unit - 1, and the latter upon new units ÷ √≡^ι. The
                    numbers having ± 1 for abstract unit are usually classed as real numbers, and in
                    that case we may regard the ordinary imaginaries of algebra as depending on the
                    new unit + √'≡T, or ι, defined by the equation ι <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>
                    + 1 = 0. But the extension was soon carried farther by the classical researches
                    of Hamilton and Grassmann.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>- In this connexion should be mentioned the great services of De Morgan,
                    whose bold speculations on the fundamental principles of mathematical science
                    have perhaps met with less than their due share of appreciation. '</p></note>
                    The theory of sets and the <hi rend="smallcaps">Quaternions</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">{q. V.)</hi> of the formerand the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ausdehnung</hi><hi rend="italic">si</hi><hi rend="italic">ehre</hi> of the
                    latter opened up a boundless field for algebra, and led to a total revolution in
                    our ideas of quantity.</p>
                <p>In view of the great extension thus effected in the meaning of quantity, it
                    becomes an interesting if somewhat difficult undertaking to define the word. The
                    following may be taken as a provisional definition :— <hi rend="italic">Quantity
                    is that which is operated with according to fixed mutually consistent
                    laics.</hi> Both operator and operand must derive their meaning from the laws of
                    operation. In the case of ordinary algebra these are the three laws already
                    indicated, in the algebra of quaternions the same save the law of commutation
                    for multiplication and division, and so on. It may be questioned whether this
                    definition is sufficient, and it may be objected that it is vague; but the
                    reader will do well to reflect that any definition must include the linear
                    algebras of Peirce, the algebras of logic, and others that may be easily
                    imagined, although they have not yet been developed. This general definition of
                    quantity enables us to see how operators may be treated as quantities, and thus
                    to understand the rationale of the so-called symbolical methods. In combining
                    operations, it is often observed that the combinations of operators fall under a
                    few simple laws, in some cases in fact under the three laws of ordinary algebra;
                    these operators are therefore quantities according to the general definition,
                    and can be treated as such.</p>
                <p>From the historical development of the analytic method there is little danger of
                    the error arising that its application is peculiar to any special kind of
                    manifoldness. As examples of its use in deducing the properties of
                    tridimensional space we may cite the Cartesian geometry, the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Géométrie</hi><hi rend="italic">de Position</hi> of Carnot, and the line
                    geometry of Plücker (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Geometry).</hi> Its use in the
                    various branches of applied mathematics, of which geometry is merely one of the
                    simplest, is far more common than that of the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n662/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0662-0631"/> synoptic method, although most branches of
                    applied mathematics are mixtures using the one or the other, as happens to be
                    convenient. In addition to those already mentioned, we may enumerate the
                    following as among the more important departments of applied mathematics
                    Kinematics; Abstract Dynamics, including Statics and Kinetics whether of a
                    Particle, of a Rigid Solid, of an Elastic Solid, of a Fluid, or of a Chain;
                    Statistical Mathematics, as exemplified in the Theory of Annuities, and the
                    Kinetic Theory of Gases; the Mathematical Theory of Diffusion whether of Heat or
                    of Matter; the Theory of Potential; and so on. See <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Mechanics, Hydromechanics, Annuities, Heat, Electricity, Magnetism,
                    &amp;c.</hi></p>
                <p>The two great methods employed in the investigation of manifoldness must of
                    course be, at bottom, identical; and every conclusion arrived at by the one must
                    be reachable by the other. The exact nature of the connexion between them will
                    be well seen by studying two instances. One of these is the treatment of areas
                    by Euclid and the treatment by the analytical method, which are carefully
                    compared in the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Geometry,</hi> vol. x. p. 379. The
                    other is the connexion between the descriptive and the metrical properties of
                    loci. The former include all properties such as intersection, tangency, etc.,
                    depending on position merely, and are obviously the natural product of the
                    synoptic method. The latter include all relations involving the lengths of lines
                    and the magnitudes of angles, they depend therefore on expression in terms of a
                    unit, and are the natural product of the analytic method. Nevertheless the
                    analytic method furnishes descriptive properties of loci, and by the
                    introduction of “the absolute” descriptive theorems are made to furnish metrical
                    relations, as has been fully shown by Cayley, Clifford, and Klein (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Measurement). (g. ch.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
