<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0610-0583-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARTINEAU, Harriet (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    583)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1161461">Unitarians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1161454">Unitarianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:962708">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45t3g226">Unitarianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1ms2d">Reviews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d21rp3w">Health</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n610/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARTINEAU, <hi rend="smallcaps">Harriet</hi></label>
                    (1802-1876), English woman of letters, was born at Norwich, where her father was
                    a manufacturer. The family was of Huguenot extraction, but had adopted Unitarian
                    views. Her education, which included Latin and French, as well as domestic
                    accomplishments, was received partly at home, and partly under a Mr Perry, to
                    whose lessons in logical English composition she ascribed something of her later
                    clearness of thought and statement. The atmosphere of her home was industrious,
                    intellectual, and' austere; she herself was clever, weakly, and unhappy, and
                    was, moreover, already growing deaf. At the age of fifteen the state of her
                    health and temper led to a prolonged visit to her father’s sister, Mrs Kentish,
                    who kept a school at Bristol. Here, in the companionship of amiable and talented
                    people, her life became happier. Here, also, she fell under the influence of the
                    Unitarian minister, Dr Carpenter, from whose instructions, she says, she derived
                    “an abominable spiritual rigidity and a truly respectable force of conscience
                    strangely mingled together.” From 1819 to 1830 she again resided chiefly at
                    Norwich. The first part of this period was mainly spent in quiet and almost
                    secret study and in needlework. About her twentieth year her deafness became
                    confirmed, and she habitually from that time used an ear trumpet. In 1821 she
                    began to write anonymously for the <hi rend="italic">Monthly Repository,</hi> a
                    Unitarian periodical, and was assured by her brother that authorship was her
                    proper career. A little later she published <hi rend="italic">Devotional
                    Exercises and Addresses, Prayers, and Hymns.</hi></p>
                <p>In 1826 her father died, leaving a bare maintenance to his wife and daughters.
                    His death had been preceded by that of his eldest son, and was shortly followed
                    by that of the young man to whom Harriet was engaged. Mrs Martineau and her
                    daughters soon after lost all their means by the failure of the house where
                    their money was placed. Harriet had to earn her living, and, being precluded by
                    her deafness from teaching, took up authorship in earnest and toiled with
                    incredible industry. She reviewed for the <hi rend="italic">Repository</hi> at
                    the rate of £15 a year, wrote stories (afterwards collected as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Traditions of Palestine),</hi> gained in one year (1830) three essay-prizes of
                    the Unitarian Association, and eked out her income by needlework. In 1831 she
                    was seeking a publisher for a series of tales designed as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Illustrations of Political Economy.</hi> After many failures she accepted very
                    disadvantageous terms, and the first number appeared amidst gloomy
                    prognostications from the publisher. The sale, however, was immediate and
                    enormous, the demand increased with each new number, and from that time her
                    literary success was secured. In 1832 she moved to London; she at once became
                    the fashien, and her acquaintance was eagerly sought. Till 1834 she continued to
                    be occupied with her political economy series and with a supplemental series of
                    <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of Taxation.</hi> Four stories dealing with the
                    poor-law came out about the same time. These tales, direct, lucid, written
                    without any appearance of effort, and yet practically effective, display the
                    characteristic qualities of their author’s style. In 1834, when the whole series
                    was complete. Miss Martineau paid a long visit to America. Here her open
                    adhesion to the Abolitionist party, then small and very unpopular, gave great
                    offence, which was deepened by the publication, soon after her return, of <hi
                    rend="italic">Society in America</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">Retrospect of
                    Western Travel.</hi> An article in the <hi rend="italic">Westminister
                    Review,</hi> “<hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> Γhe Martyr Age of the United
                    States,” introduced English readers almost for the first time to the struggles
                    of the Abolitionists. In these American writings Miss Martineau shows less than
                    her usual calmness and judicial common sense, but it will scarcely be denied
                    that there was some ground for her vehemence. The American books were followed
                    by a novel, <hi rend="italic">Deerbrook,—</hi> a story of middle class country
                    life, lacking the delicate humour of Miss Austen or the touch of farce that
                    enlivens Miss Edgeworth’s tales, but delightfully clear in style, wholesome in
                    spirit, and well sustained in point of interest. To the same period belong two
                    or three little handbooks, forming parts of a <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                    Service.</hi> The veracity of her <hi rend="italic">Maid of all Work</hi> led to
                    a widespread belief, which she regarded with some complacency, that she had once
                    been a maid of all work herself.</p>
                <p>In 1839, during a visit to the Continent, Miss Martineau’s health, which had long
                    been bad, broke down entirely. She retired to solitary lodgings in Tynemouth,
                    and remained a prisoner to her couch till 1844. She was still busy, and, besides
                    a novel <hi rend="italic">{The Hour and the Man),</hi> published some tales for
                    children, and <hi rend="italic">Life in the Sick-room.</hi> These volumes
                    contain some of her best work, and possess a charm of tender feeling to balance
                    the somewhat cold rationality that predominates in most of Miss Martineau’s
                    writing. During this illness she for a second time declined a pension on the
                    civil list, fearing to compromise her political independence. Her letter on the
                    subject was published, and some of her friends raised a small annuity for her
                    soon after.</p>
                <p>In 1844 Miss Martineau underwent a course of mesmerism, and in a few months was
                    restored to health. Her recovery excited much discussion and controversy.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n611/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0611-0584"/>
                <p>She herself felt no doubt either of its reality or of its being due to mesmerism,
                    and not unnaturally resented the incredulity of others. She eventually published
                    an account of her case in sixteen <hi rend="italic">Letters on Mesmerism,</hi> a
                    proceeding which caused great offence to some members of her family. On finding
                    herself set free from the bondage of ill-health, she removed to Ambleside, where
                    she built herself the house in which the greater part of her after life was
                    spent. In 1845 she published three volumes of <hi rend="italic">Forest and Game
                    Lazo Tales,</hi> in which the ιhethod of her political economy series was again
                    applied. In 1846 she made an Eastern tour with some friends. She was abroad for
                    eight months, visiting Egypt, Palestine, and Syria, and on her return published
                    <hi rend="italic">Eastern Life.</hi> The tendency of this work is to display
                    humanity passing through one after another of the world’s historic religions,
                    the conception of the Deity and of Divine government becoming at each step more
                    and more abstract and indefinite. The ultimate goal Miss Martineau believed to
                    be a philosophic atheism, but this belief she did not expressly declare in <hi
                    rend="italic">Eastern Life,</hi> considering it to be outside the province of
                    that book. She published about this time <hi rend="italic">Household
                    Education,</hi> expounding the modern theory, in which freedom and rationality,
                    rather than command and obedience, are regarded as the most effectual
                    instruments of education. Her practical interest in all schemes of instruction
                    led her to start a series of lectures, addressed at first to the school children
                    of Ambleside, but afterwards extended, at their own desire, to their elders. The
                    subjects of these lectures were sanitary principles and practice, the histories
                    of England and North America, and the scenes of her Eastern travels. At the
                    request of Mr Charles Knight she wrote for him, in 1849, <hi rend="italic">The
                    History of the Thirty Years' Peace,—</hi> a characteristic instance of Miss
                    Martineau’s remarkable powers of labour. “From the first opening of the books to
                    study for the history to the depositing of the MS. of the first volume at press
                    was,” she says, “exactly six months. The second volume took six months to
                    do.”</p>
                <p>In 1851 Miss Martineau edited a volume of <hi rend="italic">Letters on the Laws
                    of Man's Nature and Development.</hi> Its form is that of a correspondence
                    between herself and Mr H. G. Atkinson (in which the latter has much the larger
                    share), and it expounds that doctrine of philosophical atheism to which Miss
                    Martineau had, in <hi rend="italic">Eastern Life,</hi> depicted the course of
                    human belief as tending. The existence of a first cause is not denied, but is
                    declared unknowable, and the authors, while regarded by others as denying it,
                    certainly considered themselves to be affirming the doctrine of man’s moral
                    obligation. Mr Atkinson was a zealous exponent of mesmerism, and the prominence
                    given to the topics of mesmerism and clairvoyance no doubt tended to heighten
                    the disapprobation with which the book was received. The reviewers were almost
                    unanimous in condemnation, and the publication caused a lasting division between
                    Miss Martineau and some of her friends.</p>
                <p>The new philosophical bent of her studies directed Miss Martineau’s attention to
                    the works of Comte, and she undertook a condensed English version of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Philosophie</hi><hi rend="italic">Positive.</hi> It appeared in
                    1853, and to most readers is more useful and intelligible than the original. She
                    had begun in the previous year to write articles, chiefly biographical, for the
                    <hi rend="italic">Daily News.</hi> Among these were the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters from Ireland,</hi> written during a visit to that country in the summer
                    of 1852. She also wrote a considerable number of essays upon different
                    manufactures for <hi rend="italic">Household Words,</hi> and another series for
                    the same periodical upon the treatment of blindness, deafness, idiotcy, &amp;c.,
                    besides a <hi rend="italic">Guide to Windermere,</hi> followed afterwards by a
                    <hi rend="italic">Complete Guide to the</hi><hi rend="italic">Lahes.</hi> She
                    had been for many years a contributor to the <hi rend="italic">Westminister
                    Review,</hi> and was one of the little band of supporters whose pecuniary
                    assistance, in 1854, prevented its extinction or forced sale. In the early part
                    of 1855 Miss Martineau found herself suffering from heart disease. Having always
                    felt it one of her duties to write her autobiography, and believing the time
                    before her to be but brief, she now at once set about this task, and on its
                    completion caused the book to be printed that it might be ready for speedy
                    publication at her death. But her life, which she supposed to be so near its
                    close, was prolonged for other twenty years, her death not taking place until
                    1876.</p>
                <p>These years were by no means idle. She continued to contribute to the <hi
                    rend="italic">Daily News,</hi> for which she wrote in all more than 1600
                    articles, and to the <hi rend="italic">Westminster Review,</hi> as well as to
                    other papers, and her biographical sketches were collected and reprinted from
                    the <hi rend="italic">Daily News</hi> in a volume which has justly become one of
                    the best-known of her works. In point of style it is probably the most excellent
                    of them all. The form and method leave nothing to be desired, and the perception
                    of character is shrewd, sincere, and, roughly speaking, reliable. But in reading
                    the book we feel that the biographies, divided by the editor into groups of
                    royal, political, &amp;c., fall far more naturally into two larger classes,—the
                    biographies of persons whom Miss Martineau liked, and the biographies of persons
                    whom she disliked. All are doubtless in a sense true, as all photographs are
                    true, but the difference between a flattering and an unflattering photograph is
                    considerable.</p>
                <p>She also produced two books on the government of India, and was continually
                    occupied in promoting schemes of reform and benevolence. Her poorer neighbours
                    owed much to her kindly and enlightened efforts, and her servants found in her a
                    friend as well as a mistress. Her long and busy life bears the consistent
                    impress of two leading characteristics,—industry and sincerity. Her work was
                    invariably sound, and its motive invariably respectable. The verdict which she
                    records on herself in the autobiographical sketch left to be published by the
                    <hi rend="italic">Daily News</hi> is probably very near to that which will be
                    recorded by future judgment. She says,—“Her original power was nothing more than
                    was due to earnestness and intellectual clearness within a certain range. With
                    small imaginative and suggestive powers, and therefore nothing approaching to
                    genius, she could see clearly what she did see, and give a clear expression to
                    what she had to say. In short, she could popularize while she could neither
                    discover nor invent.” Her judgment on large questions was clear and sound, and
                    was always the judgment of a mind naturally progressive and Protestant. Mentally
                    she was a true daughter of her Huguenot ancestors. But it is impossible to read
                    her autobiography without suspecting that she was subject to considerable
                    prejudices, especially in her judgment of persons, and that her temper,
                    particularly in earlier life, was unamiable, hard, and unforgiving. She seems,
                    indeed, to have possessed the sort of disposition which shows to much greater
                    advantage in its relation to juniors, inferiors, and dependants than in its
                    relations to elders and superiors, and which therefore appears more amiable in
                    the closing than in the opening years of life. Her autobiography reveals also a
                    weakness which was perhaps unavoidable. The publication of her political economy
                    tales brought her into great and sudden notice; many persons of high position,
                    official and otherwise, desired to enlist her advocacy on the part of their
                    particular projects. She found her help much courted, and much help eagerly
                    proffered to her. Her deafness, which suffered her to hear only what was
                    directly addressed to herself, assisted to make her a central figure, and to
                    induce the belief that hers was one of the most potent if not actually the most
                    potent voice in English politics. Her deafness was in another direction probably
                    advantageous. It led her to find solitude easier than most companionship, and
                    saved her from many distractions of attention. It may indeed fairly be surmised
                    that but for her deafness she could never have found time to achieve the amazing
                    quantity of work that she did, while the courageous, cheerful, and unobtrusive
                    spirit in which she bore her infirmity remains an example and an encouragement
                    to all her fellow-sufferers. (C. BL. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
