<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0658-0627-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MATÉ, or Paraguay (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    627)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205550">Paraguay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1202667">Uruguay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4251ft9s">Tea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zn7v">Sugar</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43x83n13">Sugars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1144120">Tea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1075502">Preparedness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137272">Sugar</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n658/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MATÉ, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Paraguay</hi></label><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Tea,</hi> consists of the dried leaves of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ilex ρaraguayensis,</hi> St Hil.,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Mr J. Miers has proved that <hi rend="italic">1.
                    curitibensis, I. gig</hi><hi rend="italic">antea,</hi><hi rend="italic">1.
                    ovali-folia, I. Humboldtiana,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">I. nigropunctata,</hi>
                    besides several varieties of these species, are in general use for preparing
                    maté.</p></note> an evergreen shrub or small tree belonging to the same natural
                    order as the common holly, a plant to which it bears some resemblance in size
                    and habit. The leaves are from 6 to 8 inches long, shortlystalked, oblong
                    wedge-shaped, rounded at the upper end, and finely toothed at the margin. The
                    small white flowers grow in forked clusters in the axils of the leaves; the
                    sepals, petals, and stamens are four in number; and the berry is 4-seeded. The
                    plant grows abundantly in Paraguay, Corrientes, Chaco, and the south of Brazil,
                    forming woods called <hi rend="italic">yerbales.</hi> One of the principal
                    centres of the maté industry is the Villa Real, a small town above Asuncion on
                    the Paraguay river; another is the Villa de San Xavier, in the district between
                    the rivers Uruguay and Parana.</p>
                <p>Although maté appears to have been used from time immemorial by the Indians, the
                    Jesuits were the first to attempt its cultivation. This was commenced at their
                    branch missions in Paraguay and the province of Rio Grande de San Pedro, where
                    some plantations still exist, and furnish the best tea that is made. From this
                    circumstance the names Jesuits’ tea, tea of the Missions, St Bartholomew’s tea,
                    &amp;c., are sometimes applied to maté. Under cultivation the quality of the tea
                    improves, but the plant remains a small shrub with numerous stems, instead of
                    forming, as in the wild state, a tree with a rounded head. From cultivated
                    plants the leaves are gathered every two or three years, that interval being
                    necessary for restoration to vigorous growth. The collection of maté is,
                    however, chiefly effected by Indians employed for that purpose by merchants, who
                    pay a money consideration to Government for the privilege.</p>
                <p>When a yerbal or mate wood is found, the Indians, who usually travel in companies
                    of about twenty-five in number, build wigwams and settle down to the work for
                    about six months. Their first operation is to prepare an open space, called a
                    <hi rend="italic">tatacua,</hi> about 6 feet square, in which the surface of the
                    soil is beaten hard and smooth with mallets. The leafy branches of the maté are
                    then cut down and placed on the tatacua, where they undergo a preliminary
                    roasting from a fire kindled around it. An arch of poles, or of hurdles, is then
                    erected above it, on which the maté is placed, a fire being lighted underneath.
                    This part of the process demands some care, since by it the leaves have to be
                    rendered brittle enough to be easily pulverized, and the aroma has to be
                    developed, the necessary amount of heat being only learned by experience. After
                    drying, the leaves are reduced to coarse powder in mortars formed of pits in the
                    earth well rammed. Maté so prepared is called <hi rend="italic">caa gazu</hi> or
                    <hi rend="italic">yerva do polos,</hi> and is chiefly used in Brazil. In
                    Paraguay and. the province of Parana in the Argentine Republic, the leaves are
                    deprived of the midrib before roasting; this is called <hi rend="italic"
                    >caa-miri.</hi> A very superior quality, or <hi rend="italic">caa-cuys,</hi> is
                    also prepared in Paraguay from the scarcely expanded buds. More recently a
                    different method of drying maté has been adopted, the leaves being heated in
                    large cast iron pans set in brick work, in the same way that tea is dried in
                    China: it is afterwards powdered by machinery.</p>
                <p>The different methods of preparation influence to a certain extent the value of
                    the product, the maté prepared in Paraguay being considered the best, that of
                    Oran and Paranagua very inferior. The leaves when dried are packed tightly in
                    serons or oblong packages made of raw hides, which are then carefully sewed up.
                    These shrink by exposure to the sun, and in a couple of days form compact
                    parcels each containing about 200 lb of tea; in this form it keeps well. The tea
                    is generally prepared for use in a small silver-mounted calabash, made of the
                    fruit of <hi rend="italic">Crescentia</hi><hi rend="italic">Cujete</hi> (Cuca)
                    or of <hi rend="italic">Cucurbita</hi><hi rend="italic">lagcnaria</hi> (Cabaço),
                    usually about the size of a large orange, the tapering end of the latter serving
                    for a handle. In the top of the calabash, or <hi rend="italic">maté</hi><note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The word <hi rend="italic"
                    >caa</hi> signified the plant in the native Indian language. The Spaniards gave
                    it a similar name, <hi rend="italic">yerba.</hi><hi rend="italic">Maté</hi>
                    comes from the language of the Incas, and originally means a calabash. The
                    Paraguay tea was called at first <hi rend="italic">yerva do</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">maté,</hi> and then, the <hi rend="italic">yerva</hi> being
                    dropped, the name <hi rend="italic">mate</hi> came to signify the same
                    thing.</p></note><hi rend="italic">?</hi> a circular hole about the size of a
                    florin is made, and through this opening the tea is sucked by means of a
                    bom-billa. This instrument consists of a small tube 6 or 7 inches long, formed
                    either of metal or a reed, which has at one end a bulb made either of extremely
                    fine basket-work or of metal perforated with minute holes, so as to prevent the
                    particles of the tea leaves from being drawn up into the mouth. Some sugar and a
                    little hot water are first placed in the gourd, the yerva is then added, and
                    finally the vessel is filled to the brim with boiling water, or milk previously
                    heated by a spirit lamp. A little burnt sugar or lemon juice is sometimes added
                    instead of milk. The beverage is then handed round to the company, each person
                    being furnished with a bombilia. The leaves will bear steeping about three
                    times. The infusion, if not drunk soon after it is made, rapidly turns black.
                    Persons who are fond of maté drink it before every meal, and consume about 1 oz.
                    of the leaves per day. In the neighbourhood of Parana it is prepared and drunk
                    like Chinese tea. Maté is generally considered disagreeable by those
                    unaccustomed to it, having a somewhat bitter taste; moreover, it is the custom
                    to drink it so hot as to be unpleasant. But in the south-eastern republics it is
                    a much-prized article of luxury, and is the first thing offered to visitors. The
                    <hi rend="italic">gaucho</hi> of the plains will travel on horseback for weeks
                    asking no better fare than dried beef washed down with copious draughts of maté,
                    and for it he will forego any other luxury, such as sugar, rice, or biscuit.
                    Maté acts as a restorative after great fatigue in the same manner as tea. Since
                    it does not lose its flavour so quickly as tea by exposure to the air and damp,
                    it is more valuable to travellers.</p>
                <p>Some writers attribute deleterious effects to its use, while others praise it to
                    an almost incredible degree. Its physiological action does not appear to have
                    been carefully worked out, but its extensive use in countries where tea and
                    coffee are known seems to indicate that it may possess virtues peculiar to
                    itself.</p>
                <p>Its properties appear to be chiefly due to theine or caffeine. Analvsed bv Dr H.
                    Byasson, 100 grains were found to yield</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Caffni∏P. .</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Grains 1'850</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Glutinous substance or peculiar fatty matter and colouring
                            matter</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>3'870</p><p>2'380</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>0'630</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell><p>3'920</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Malic acid not estimated.</p></cell>
                        <cell/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n659/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0659-0628"/>
                <p>According to analyses made by Alonzo Robbins it also contains about 1 <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 5 of a peculiar tannin which does not precipitate
                    potassio-tartrate of antimony, nor tan leather. The glutinous substance
                    resembles in consistence common birdlime, and is considered by Byasson to be a
                    compound ether, the alcohol of which would be near cholesterin. Since the
                    beginning of the 17th century maté has been drunk by all classes in Paraguay,
                    and it is now used throughout Brazil and the neighbouring countries. In 1855 the
                    amount of mate annually consumed in South America was estimated by Von Bibra at
                    15,000,000 lb, and the consumption is now probably three or four times as great;
                    in Brazil it brings in a revenue of about £410,000. In the Argentine 'Republic
                    alone the consumption is not less than 27,000,000 ⅛ per annum, or about 13 lb
                    per head, while the proportion of tea and coffee consumed is only about 2 lb of
                    the former and ∣ lb of the latter per head. The export of mate from Brazil to
                    foreign countries has also increased from 2,720,475 kilos in 1840 to 5,206,485
                    kilos in 1850, 6,808,056 kilos in 1860, 9,507,086 kilos in 1870, and 14,063,731
                    kilos in 1879-80.</p>
                <p>See Scully, Brazil, London, 1866; Mansfield, Brazil, &lt;kc., London, 1856;
                    Pharmaceutical Journal (3), vol. vii. p. 4; (3), vol. viii. p. 615, 1627;
                    Christy, New Commercial Plants, No. 3, London, 1880; Mulhall, Progress of the
                    World, 1880, p. 488; Zeitschrift Oesterreichischer Apothekerverein, 1882, pp.
                    273, 285, 310.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
