<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0608-0581-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARTIN (9th edition, volume 15, page 581)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8dp2t">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fn10z9f">Nests</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45x25p07">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xk84v4n">Swallows</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239509">Africa</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1240495">Asia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204480">Alaska</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204543">Australia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1036179">Nests</term>
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1176048">Winter</term>
                    <term ref="fast:957310">Hirundo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1104803">Sand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n608/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARTIN</label><note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The older English form, Martlet (French, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Martelet'),</hi> is, except in heralds’ language, almost obsolete, and when
                    used is now applied in some places to the <hi rend="smallcaps">Swift</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">{q.v. ).</hi></p></note> (French, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Martinet),</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Hirundo urbica</hi> of Linnaeus and <hi
                    rend="italic">Chelidon urbica</hi> of modern ornithologists, a bird very well
                    known throughout Europe, including even Lapland, where it is abundant, retiring
                    in winter to the south of Africa.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Since the publication of the account of this species in
                    YarrelΓs <hi rend="italic">British Birds</hi> (ed. 4, ii. p. 354), Mr Gurney has
                    informed the writer of a specimen obtained out of a migratory flock flying very
                    high on the Qua'qua’ river, lat. 19° 10' S., by the expedition of Messrs Jameson
                    and Ayres, 23d October 1880.</p></note> It also inhabits the western part of
                    Asia, and appears from time to time in large flocks in India; but the boundaries
                    of its range and those of at least one of its Eastern congeners cannot as yet be
                    laid down. The Martin (or House-Martin, as it is often called, to distinguish it
                    from the Sand-Martin presently to be mentioned) commonly reaches its
                    summer-quarters a few days later than the <hi rend="smallcaps">Swallow</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">(q.v.),</hi> whose habits its own so much resemble that heedless
                    persons often disregard the very perceptible differences between them, the
                    Martin’s white rump and lower parts being conspicuous as it flies or clings to
                    its “loved mansionry” attached to our houses, for, as Shakespeare wrote—</p>
                <p>“No jutty, frieze, Buttress, nor coign of vantage, but this bird Hath made his
                    pendent bed and procreant cradle.”</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">—Macbeth,</hi> act i. sc. 6.</p>
                <p>This nest, made of the same material as the Swallow’s, is, however, a far more
                    difficult structure to rear, and a week or more is often occupied in laying its
                    foundations— the builders clinging to the wall while depositing the mud of which
                    it is composed. But, the base once securely fixed, the superstructure is often
                    quickly added till the whole takes the shape of the half or quarter of a
                    hemisphere, and a lining of soft feathers, mixed with a few bents or straws,
                    fits it for its purpose. The Martin sets about building very soon after its
                    return, and a nest that has outlasted the winter’s storms is almost at once
                    reoccupied; though if a new nest be needed its construction often involves great
                    delay, for any excess of wet or drought retards the operation, and the work is
                    generally placed in such an exposed situation that heavy driving rains will
                    frequently wash away the half-dried walls. However, the bird mostly perseveres
                    against these and other untowardnesses, contriving in the course of the summer
                    to raise a second or, rarely, a third brood of offspring—though it is certain
                    that the latest broods often die in the nest—apparently through failure of food.
                    Yet what seem to be adults of this species are observed in England every year so
                    late as November, and there are several instances of its appearance within a few
                    days of the winter solstice; but it is to be remarked that these late birds are
                    almost certainly strangers, and not natives of the locality in which they are
                    seen.</p>
                <p>The Sand-Martin, <hi rend="italic">Hirundo</hi><hi rend="italic">riparia</hi> of
                    Linnaeus and <hi rend="italic">Cotile riparia</hi> of modern writers, differs
                    much in appearance and habits from the former. Its smaller size, mousecoloured
                    upper surface, and jerking flight ought to render it easily recognizable from
                    the other British <hi rend="italic">Hirundinidx;</hi> but through carelessness
                    it is seldom discriminated, and, being the first of the Family to return to its
                    northern home, the “early Swallow” of newspaper-writers would seem to be nearly
                    always of this species. Instead of the clay-built nest of the House-Martin, this
                    bird bores, with a degree of regularity and an amount of labour rarely excelled
                    in its Class, horizontal galleries in a natural or artificial escarpment. When
                    beginning its excavation, it clings to the face of the bank, and with its bill
                    loosens the earth, working from the centre outwards, assuming all sorts of
                    positions—as often as not hanging head downwards. The form of the boring and its
                    length depend much on the nature of the soil; but the tunnel may extend to 4, G,
                    or even 9 feet. The gallery seems intended to be straight, but inequalities of
                    the ground, and especially the meeting with stones, often cause it to take a
                    sinuous course. At the end is formed a convenient chamber lined with a few grass
                    stalks and feathers, the latter always beautifully arranged, and upon them the
                    eggs are laid. The Sand-Martin has several broods in the year, and is much more
                    regular than other <hi rend="italic">Hirundinidae</hi> in its departure for the
                    south. The kind of soil needed for its nestinghabits makes it a somewhat local
                    bird; but no species of the Order <hi rend="italic">Passeres</hi> has a
                    geographical range that can compare with this. In Europe it is found nearly to
                    the North Cape, and thence to the Sea of Okhotsk. In winter it visits many parts
                    of India, and South Africa to the Transvaal territory. In America its range is
                    even more extraordinary, extending (due regard being of course had to the season
                    of the year) from Melville Island to Caiçara in Brazil, and from Newfoundland to
                    Alaska.</p>
                <p>The Purple Martin of America,<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>In 1840 an example is said to have been killed at Kingstown
                    in Ireland, the skin of which is in the Dublin Museum of Science and
                    Art.</p></note><hi rend="italic">Hirundo</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Progne</hi><hi rend="italic">purpurea,</hi> requires some remarks as being such
                    a favourite bird in Canada and in the United States. Naturally breeding in
                    hollow trees, it readily adapts itself to the nest-boxes which are very commonly
                    set up for its accommodation; but its numbers are in some years and places
                    subject to diminution in a manner which has not yet been satisfactorily
                    explained. The limits of its range in winter are not determined, chiefly owing
                    to the differences of opinion as to the validity of certain supposed kindred
                    species found in South America; but according to some authorities it reaches the
                    border of Patagonia, while in summer it is known to inhabit lands within the
                    Arctic Circle. The male is almost wholly of a glossy steel-blue, while the
                    female is much duller in colour above, and beneath of a brownish-grey.</p>
                <p>Birds that may be called Martins<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>The <hi rend="italic">Martin</hi> of French colonists (in
                    the Old World) is an <hi rend="italic">Acridotheres,</hi> one of the <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Starlings</hi> fø.u).</p></note> occur almost all over the
                    world except in New Zealand, which is not regularly inhabited by any member of
                    the Family. The ordinary Martin of Australia is the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Hirundo</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Hylochelidon nigricans</hi> of most
                    ornithologists, and another and more beautiful form is the Ariel or Fairy-Martin
                    of the same country, <hi rend="italic">Hirundo</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lagenoplastes ariel.</hi> This last builds of mud a bottle-shaped nest, as does
                    also the Bock-Martin of Europe, <hi rend="italic">Hirundo</hi> or <hi
                    rend="italic">Biblis rupestris∙,</hi> but space fails wherein to tell more of
                    these interesting birds. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
