<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0527-0504-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MANUCODE (9th edition, volume 15, page 504)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m9h">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20h6f">Inventors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206005">Guinea</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:832970">Birds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1033950">Nats</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1006685">Males</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821510">Australians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821509">Australianisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:966490">Ibises</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n527/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MANUCODE</label>, from the French, an abbreviation of <hi
                    rend="italic">Manucodiata,</hi> and the Latinized form of the Malay <hi
                    rend="italic">Manuk-dewata,</hi> meaning, says Crawfurd <hi rend="italic">(Malay
                    and Engl. Dictionary,</hi> p. 97), the “bird of the gods,” and a name applied
                    for more than two hundred years apparently to Birds-of-paradise in general. In
                    the original sense of its inventor, Montbeillard <hi rend="italic">(Hist.
                    Nat.</hi><hi rend="italic">Oiseaux,</hi> iii. p. 163), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Manucode</hi> was restricted to the King Bird-of-paradise and three allied
                    species; but in English it has curiously been transferred<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Manucodiata</hi> was used
                    by Brisson <hi rend="italic">{Ornithologie,</hi> ii. p. 130) as a generic term
                    equivalent to the Linnaean <hi rend="italic">Paradisea.</hi> In 1783 Boddaert,
                    when assigning scientific names to the birds figured by Daubenton, called the
                    subject of one of them <hi rend="italic">(Pl. enlum.</hi> 634) <hi rend="italic"
                    >Manucodia chalybea,</hi> the first word being apparently an accidental
                    curtailment of the name of Brisson’s genus to which he referred it. Nevertheless
                    some writers have taken it as evidence of an intention to found a new genus by
                    that name, and hence the importation of <hi rend="italic">Manucodia</hi> into
                    scientific nomenclature, and the English form to correspond.</p></note> to a
                    small group of species whose relationship to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Paradiseidx</hi> has been frequently doubted, and must be considered uncertain.
                    These Manucodes have a glossy steel-blue plumage of much beauty, but are easily
                    distinguished from other birds of similar coloration by the outer and middle
                    toes being united for some distance, and they are very remarkable for the
                    extraordinary convolution of the trachea, in the males at least, with which
                    singular structure is correlated the loud and clear voice of the birds. The
                    convoluted portion of the trachea lies on the breast, between the skin and the
                    muscles, much as is found in the females of the genus <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ilhynchaea,</hi> in the males of the Curassows <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Cracidae),</hi> and in a few other birds, but wholly unknown elsewhere among
                    the <hi rend="italic">Passeres.</hi> The Manucodes are peculiar to the Papuan
                    Sub-region (including therein <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n528/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0528-0505"/> the peninsula of Cape York), and comprehend,
                    according to Mr Sharpe <hi rend="italic">(Cat. B. Brit. Museum,</hi> iii. p.
                    164), two genera, for the first of which, distinguished by the elongated tufts
                    on the head, he adopts Lesson’s name <hi rend="italic">Plιonygama,</hi> and for
                    the second, having no tufts, but the feathers of the head crisped, that of <hi
                    rend="italic">Manucodia'</hi><hi rend="italic subscript"> f</hi> and Mr W. A.
                    Forbes <hi rend="italic">(Proc. Zool. Society,</hi> 1882, p. 349) observes that
                    the validity of the separation (which has not yet been generally acknowledged)
                    is confirmed by what is now known of their tracheal formation. Of <hi
                    rend="italic">Phonygama</hi> Mr Sharpe recognizes three species, <hi
                    rend="italic">P. keraudreni</hi> (the type) and <hi rend="italic">P.
                    jamesi,</hi> both from New Guinea, and <hi rend="italic">P. gouldi,</hi> the
                    Australian representative species; but the first two are considered by Mr Elliot
                    <hi rend="italic">(Ibis,</hi> 1878, p. 56) and Count Salvador! <hi rend="italic"
                    >(Ornitöl.</hi><hi rend="italic">della, Papuasia,</hi> ii. p. 510) to be
                    inseparable. There is a greater unanimity in regard to the species of the
                    so-called genus <hi rend="italic">Manucodia</hi> proper, of which four are
                    admitted — <hi rend="italic">Μ. chalybeata,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >clιcdybea</hi> from north-western New Guinea, <hi rend="italic">Μ. comriei</hi>
                    from the south-eastern part of the same country, <hi rend="italic">Μ. atra</hi>
                    of wide distribution within the Papuan area, and <hi rend="italic">Μ.
                    jobiensis</hi> peculiar to the island which gives it a name. Little is known of
                    the habits of these birds, except that they are as already mentioned remarkable
                    for their vocal powers, which, in <hi rend="italic">P. keraudreni,</hi> Lesson
                    describes <hi rend="italic">(Voy. de la Coquille,</hi> Zoologie, i. p. 638) as
                    enabling them to pass through every note of the gamut. Mr Wallace <hi
                    rend="italic">(Ann. Nat. History,</hi> ser. 2, XX. p. 476) remarked that <hi
                    rend="italic">Μ. atra</hi> was very powerful and active, clinging suspended to
                    the smaller branches of trees, on the fruits of which alone it appears to feed.
                    <hi rend="italic">Μ. gouldl,</hi> according to an informant quoted by Mr Forbes
                    <hi rend="italic">(ut supra),</hi> frequents in pairs the dense palm-forests,
                    perching high up, uttering a very deep and loud guttural note; it is graceful in
                    its movements, evincing more curiosity than timidity on being approached. As
                    with members of the <hi rend="italic">Paradiseidae</hi> generally, the
                    nidification of the Manucodes is still shrouded in mystery. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(a. n.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
