<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0915-0565-0538-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">MARGUERITE de Valois (9th edition, volume 15, page
                    538)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                        Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933759">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1076505">Princesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888134">Daughters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964412">Husbands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v18f">Princesses</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xg2s">Boring</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pz51m4r">Borings</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n565/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">MARGUERITE <hi rend="smallcaps">de Valois</hi></label>. The
                    name Marguerite was common in the Valois dynasty, and during the 16th century
                    there were three princesses, all of whom figure in the political as well as in
                    the literary history of the time, and who have been not unfrequently confounded.
                    The first and last are the most important, but all deserve some account.</p>
                <p>I. <hi rend="smallcaps">Marguerite</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">d’Angoulême</hi>
                    (1492-1549). This, the most celebrated of the Marguerites, bore no less than
                    four surnames. By family she was entitled to the name of Marguerite de Valois;
                    as the daughter of the Count d’Angoulême she is more properly and by careful
                    writers almost invariably called Marguerite d’Angoulême. From her first husband
                    she took during no small part of her life the appellation Marguerite d’Alençon,
                    and from her second, Henri d’Albret, king of Navarre, that of Marguerite de
                    Navarre. She was born at Angoulême on the 12th April 1492, and was two years
                    older than her brother Francis I. She was betrothed early to Charles, Duke
                    d’Alençon, and married him in 1509. She was not very fortunate in this first
                    marriage, but her brother’s accession to the throne made her, with their mother
                    Louise of Savoy, the most powerful woman of the kingdom. She became a widow in
                    1525, and was sought in marriage by many persons of distinction, including, it
                    is said, Charles V. and Henry VIII. In 1527 she married Henri d’Albret, titular
                    king of Navarre, who was considerably younger than herself, and whose character
                    was not faultless, but who seems on the whole, despite slander, to have both
                    loved and valued his wife. Navarre was not reconquered for the couple as Francis
                    had promised, but ample apanages were assigned to Marguerite, and at Nérac and
                    Pau miniature courts were kept up, which yielded to none in Europe in the
                    intellectual brilliancy of their frequenters. Marguerite was at once one of the
                    chief patronesses of letters that France possessed, and the chief refuge and
                    defender of advocates of the Reformed doctrines. Round her gathered Marot,
                    Bonaventure Desperiers, Denisot, Peletier, Brodeau, and many other men of
                    letters, while she protected Rabelais, Dolet, àc. For a time her influence with
                    her brother was effectual, but latterly political rather than religious
                    considerations made him discourage Lutheranism, and a fierce persecution was
                    begun against both Protestants and freethinkers, a persecution which drove
                    Desperiers to suicide and brought Dolet to the stake. Marguerite herself,
                    however, was protected by her brother, and her personal inclinations seem to
                    have been rather towards a mystical pietism than towards dogmatic Protestant
                    sentiments. Nevertheless bigotry and the desire to tarnish the reputation of
                    women of letters have led to the bringing of odious accusations against her
                    character, for which there is not the smallest foundation. Marguerite died in
                    1549. By her first husband she had no children, by her second a son who died in
                    infancy, and a daughter, Jeanne d’Albret, who became the mother of Henry IV.
                    Although the poets of the time are unwearied <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit15newyrich/page/n566/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0915-0566-0539"/> in celebrating her charms, she does not, from the
                    portraits which exist, appear to have been regularly beautiful, but as to her
                    sweetness of disposition and strength of mind there is universal consent.</p>
                <p>Her literary work has not yet been given entirely to the world, but the printed
                    portion of it makes her a considerable figure in French literature. It consists
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Heptameron,</hi> of poems entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Les Marguerites de la Marguerite des Princesses,</hi> and of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Letters.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Heptameron,</hi> constructed as its name
                    indicates on the lines of the <hi rend="italic">Decameron</hi> of Boccaccio,
                    consists of seventy-two short stories told to each other by a company of ladies
                    and gentlemen who are stopped in the journey homewards from Cauterets by the
                    swelling of a river. It was not printed till 1558, ten years after the author’s
                    death. Internal evidence is strongly in favour of its having been a joint work,
                    in which more than one of the men of letters who composed Marguerite’s household
                    took part. It is a delightful book, and strongly characteristic of the French
                    Benaissance. The sensuality which characterized the period appears in it, but in
                    a less coarse form than in the great work of Rabelais; and there is a poetical
                    spirit which, except in rare instances, is absent from <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pantagruel.</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> are interesting and good.
                    The <hi rend="italic">Marguerites</hi> consist of a very miscellaneous
                    collection of poems, mysteries, farces, devotional poems of considerable length,
                    spiritual and miscellaneous songs, &amp;c. Other poems, said to be of equal
                    merit, are still unprinted, or have appeared only in part.</p>
                <p>IT. The second <hi rend="smallcaps">Marguerite</hi> (1523-1574), daughter of
                    Francis I., married the duke of Savoy in 1559. She is noteworthy as having given
                    the chief impulse at the court of her brother Henry II. to the first efforts of
                    the l'iéiade.</p>
                <p>III. The third <hi rend="smallcaps">Marguerite</hi> (1553—1 G15), called more
                    particularly Marguerite de Valois, was great-niece of the first and niece of the
                    second, being daughter of Henry II. by Catherine de’Medici. She was born in
                    1553. When very young she became famous for her beauty, her learning, and the
                    looseness of her conduct. She was married to Henry of Navarre, afterwards Henry
                    IV., on the eve of St Bartholomew’s Day. Both husband and wife were extreme
                    examples of the licentious manners of the time, but they not unfrequently lived
                    together for considerable periods, and nearly always on good terms. Later,
                    however, Marguerite was established in the castle of Usson in Auvergne, and
                    after the accession of Henry the marriage was dissolved by the pope. But Henry
                    and Marguerite still continued friends; she still bore the title of queen; she
                    visited Marie de’ Medici on equal terms; and the king frequently consulted her
                    on important affairs, though his somewhat parsimonious spirit was grieved by her
                    extravagance. Marguerite exhibited during the rest of her life, which was not a
                    short one, the strange Valois mixture of licentiousness, pious exercises, and
                    the cultivation of art and letters, and died in 1615. She left letters and
                    memoirs, the latter of which are admirably written, and rank among the best of
                    the 16th century. She is the “Reine Margot” of anecdotic history and
                    romance.</p>
                <p>The best editions of the works of Marguerite d’Angoulême are—of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Heptameron,</hi> that of Leroux de Lincy, 3 vols., Paris, 1855; of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> that of Genin, Paris, <hi rend="italic"
                    >2</hi> vols., 1842-43; and of the <hi rend="italic">Marguerites,</hi> that of
                    Frank, Paris, 4 vols., 1873; the <hi rend="italic">Heptameron</hi> is also
                    obtainable in several cheap editions. The <hi rend="italic">Mémoires</hi> of
                    Marguerite de Valois are contained in the collection of Michaud and Poujoulat,
                    and have been published separately by Guessard, Lalanne, Caboche, &amp;c. (G.
                    SA.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
