<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0711-0239-0088-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">GUY, Thomas</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659g16">Bear</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5cs84">Mercerization</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zv9m">Streets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term ref="fast:952579">Head</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829302">Bears</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133704">Stocks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864222">Cliffs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1016921">Mercerization</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193640239?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">GUY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label>, an
                    eminent bookseller, founder of the hospital for sick and lame in Southwark which
                    bears his name, was the son of Thomas Guy, lighterman and coal-dealer in
                    Horsley-down, Southwark. He was put as apprentice, in 1660, to a bookseller in
                    the porch of Mercer’s Chapel; and set up trade with a stock of about L.200, in
                    the house which formed the angle between Cornhill and Lombard Street. The
                    English bibles being at that time very badly printed, Mr Guy engaged with others
                    in a scheme for printing them in Holland, and importing them; but this being put
                    a stop to, he contracted with the university of Oxford for their privilege of
                    printing them, and carried on a trade in bibles for many years to a considerable
                    advantage. The bulk of his fortune, however, was acquired by purchasing seamen’s
                    tickets during Queen Anne’s wars, and by South-Sea stock in the memorable year
                    1720. To show what great events spring from trivial causes, it is asserted that
                    the public owe the dedication of the greater part of his immense fortune to
                    charitable purposes, to the indiscreet officiousness of his maidservant in
                    interfering with the mending of the pavement before his door. Guy, it seems, had
                    agreed to marry her, and, preparatory to his nuptials, had ordered the pavement
                    before his door, which was in a neglected state, to be mended, as far as a
                    particular stone which he pointed out. The maid, whilst her master was out,
                    innocently looking on the paviers at work, observed a broken place they had not
                    repaired, and mentioned it to them; but they told her <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193640252?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0711-0252-0089"/>that Mr Guy
                    had directed them not to go so far. “Well,” said she, “do you mend it; tell him
                    I bade you, and I know , he will not be angry.” It happened, however, that the
                    poor girl presumed too much on her influence over her careful lover, with whom a
                    few extraordinary shillings of expense turned the scale totally against her. The
                    men obeyed; Guy was enraged to find his orders exceeded; his matrimonial scheme
                    was renounced; and, instead of marrying, he built hospitals in his old age. In
                    the year 1707 he built and furnished three wards on the north side of the outer
                    court of St Thomas’s Hospital in Southwark, and gave L.100 to it annually for
                    eleven years preceding the erection of his own hospital; and, some time before
                    his death, he erected the stately iron gate, with the large houses on each side,
                    at the expense of about L.3000. He was seventy-six years of age when he formed
                    the design of building the hospital which bears his'name, contiguous to that of
                    St Thomas’s; and he lived to see it roofed in, having died in the year 1724. The
                    charge of erecting this vast pile amounted toL.18,793, and he left L.219,499 to
                    endow it; a much larger sum than had ever before been dedicated to charitable
                    uses by any one man in this kingdom. He erected at Tamworth in Staffordshire,
                    the place of his mother’s nativity, and of which he had been representative in
                    parliament, an alms-house, with a library, for fourteen poor men and women; and
                    for their pensions, as well as for putting out poor children as apprentices, he
                    bequeathed L.l25a year. Lastly, he bequeathed L.1000 to every one who could
                    prove himself related to him in any degree, however remote.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Guy,</hi> a rope used to keep steady any weighty
                    body whilst it is hoisting or lowering, particularly when the ship is shaken by
                    a tempestuous sea.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Guy</hi> is likewise a large slack rope, extending
                    from the head of the main-mast to the head of the fore-mast, and having two or
                    three large blocks fastened to the middle of it. This is chiefly employed to
                    sustain the tackle used to hoist in and out the cargo of a merchant ship, and is
                    accordingly removed from the mast-head as soon as the vessel is laden or
                    delivered.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Guy’s</hi><hi rend="italic">Cliff,</hi> in
                    Warwickshire, a great cliff on the west side of the Avon and the north side of
                    Warwick, where in the time of the Britons there was an oratory, and in that of
                    the Saxons an hermitage, and where Guy, earl of Warwick, is said to have retired
                    after being fatigued with the toils and pleasures of the world, to have built a
                    chapel, and cohabited with the hermit. This hermitage was kept up till the reign
                    of Henry VI. when Richard Beauchamp, earl of Warwick, established there a
                    chantry, which derived its name from the king-maker, and, in memory of the
                    famous Guy, erected a large statue in the chapel, eight feet in height, at the
                    same time raising a roof over the adjacent springs.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
