<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-4181-0238-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PERRAULT, Claude (7th edition, volume 17, page
                    238)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zz3k">Design</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16x10">Plans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891345">Designers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891253">Design</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065224">Planning</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1142246">Tales</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103658">Saints</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193494181?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PERRAULT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Claude</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated architect, was born at Paris in the year 1613. His father, an
                    advocate of the parliament, caused him to study medicine, anatomy, and the
                    mathematics; and he even took the degree of doctor of physic in the faculty of
                    Paris. But Colbert, the celebrated French minister, having advised him to
                    undertake a translation of Vitruvius, the studies in which he found it necessary
                    to engage in order to understand that writer inspired him with a decided taste
                    for architecture, and gave a new direction to his pursuits. When the Academy of
                    Sciences was established, in 1666, Perrault was admitted a member of this body,
                    and was employed to furnish designs and building-plans for the Observatory. But
                    this edifice, which, with all its merits, is in a heavy style, was far from
                    giving any indication of the talents which Perrault afterwards displayed. His
                    grand work is the palace of the Louvre, the façade of which was designed by him,
                    and is certainly one of the noblest monuments of architecture in the world. The
                    building had been commenced, and even part of the façade raised according to the
                    designs of Lavau. But Colbert, dissatisfied with these, which he justly
                    considered as deficient in grandeur, and unsuitable to the nature of the
                    subject, appealed to the genius of other architects; and Perrault produced a
                    design so superior to those of his competitors, that it immediately obtained a
                    decided preference. Nevertheless, before commencing the work, the king wished to
                    have the ideas of the best artists of Italy; and with this view, Bernini, who
                    then enjoyed a great reputation, both as a sculptor and an architect, was sent
                    for from Rome, and received in France with the greatest distinction. But the
                    pre-eminent merit of Perrault was, notwithstanding, fully recognised; his plans
                    were adopted by the court, although objections had been strenuously urged as to
                    the practicability of their execution; and a model constructed by the artist
                    himself at length removed every doubt on the subject, by proving that the
                    difficulties raised were altogether imaginary, and that the solidity of the
                    fabric might be rendered commensurate with the beauty of the design. Such were
                    the preliminaries of the erection of this monument, which may justly be regarded
                    as the masterpiece of French architecture, and the finest edifice that exists in
                    Paris. Perrault furnished designs for other works, particularly the triumphal
                    arch erected at the extremity of the Rue Saint-Antoine, the foundation-stone of
                    which was laid on the 6th of August 1670; and, in all his works, he displayed
                    that superiority of genius, which was first exhibited in his translation of
                    Vitruvius, particularly in the plates with which it was enriched, and which have
                    ever been considered as masterpieces of their kind. The first edition of this
                    work appeared in 1673, and the second in 1684, in one volume folio; after which
                    the translator published an abridgement in one volume 12mo. To the same author
                    we are likewise indebted for another work, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ordonnances</hi><hi rend="italic">des Cinq</hi><hi rend="italic">Espèces de
                    Colonnes selon</hi><hi rend="italic">la Methode</hi><hi rend="italic">des
                    Anciens,</hi> in one volume folio, forming a kind of supplement to the
                    translation of Vitruvius, and containing explanations of several points which
                    had not been touched upon in the notes to that work. Of his other productions
                    the principal are, 1. Essais de Physique, 1680—1688, in two vols. 4to, and four
                    vols. 12mo; 2. Mémoires pour servir à ΓHistoire <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193494194?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0717-4194-0239"/> Naturelle des
                    Animaux, Paris, 1671-1676, in folio; 3. Recueil d’un grand Nombre des Machines
                    de son Invention, for raising and transporting the heaviest weights, Paris,
                    1700, in one vol. 4to. Claude Perrault assisted his brother Charles in preparing
                    the memoirs relating to the establishment of the Academy of Sciences, and that
                    of Painting and Sculpture, and took a warm interest in the success of that
                    institution. He died at Paris, on the 9th of October 1688, in consequence, it is
                    believed, of having wounded himself whilst dissecting, in the Jardin du Roi, a
                    camel which had died of some contagious disease; and the faculty of medicine
                    caused his portrait to be placed <hi rend="subscript"> -</hi> amongst those of
                    their most distinguished members. <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Perrault,</hi><hi rend="italic">Charles,</hi> the brother of
                    Claude, was born at Paris on the 12th of January 1628, and at the age of eight
                    was placed in the college of Beauvais, where he'distinguished himself in
                    scholastic disputation, and in making verses with extreme facility, “indice
                    trompeur d’un talent qui ne mûrit presque jamais.” On leaving school, he found
                    that burlesque was in vogue; and a friend having suggested to him the idea of
                    translating the sixth book of the AEneid in the manner of Scarron, he executed
                    the travesty in a manner which attracted the commendation both of Voltaire and
                    of Marmontel. But when his ideas were matured by reflection, he ceased to attach
                    any value to such effusions; and, having completed his studies, he was admitted
                    as advocate, in which capacity he pleaded two causes with success. Colbert,
                    however, soon deprived the law of his services, and, in the year 1664, appointed
                    him first commissary for the superintendence of royal buildings, an office the
                    duties of which he discharged with equal zeal and ability, nobly justifying the
                    confidence of the minister, and regarding himself as the representative of men
                    of letters and of artists at the court. The Academy of Painting, Sculpture, and
                    Architecture, and that of Sciences∕were founded on memoirs drawn up by Charles
                    Perrault, who had now become comptroller-general of buildings; and he was
                    admitted into the French Academy in 1671, in the room of the bishop of Léon. But
                    the impracticable character of Colbert having at length wearied out his
                    patience, he retired from his public situation, and, devoting himself to
                    literature, produced his poem entitled <hi rend="italic">Siècle</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">de Louis XIV.,</hi> which appeared in 1687, and involved him in a
                    war with the learned, by reason of his exalting the modern in comparison with
                    the ancient authors. He defended himself, however, in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Parallèle des Anciens et Modernes,</hi> which appeared at Paris in 1688,
                    afterwards attracted the notice of Bayle, and excited very considerable
                    attention. One of his principal antagonists was Boileau, who attacked him with
                    great asperity, and, as usual, had all the scoffers on his side; but at length
                    they were, in some measure, reconciled, although, on the part of Boileau, the
                    <hi rend="italic">amende</hi> was made in a tone which savoured more of contempt
                    than of conciliation. His poem on Painting was, however, generally admired; but
                    his Tales in verse, entitled <hi rend="italic">Grisélidès,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Peau</hi><hi rend="italic">d'Ane,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Souhaits</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Ridicules,</hi> are prolix and heavy. Perrault died at Paris on
                    the 16th of May 1703. Besides the works already indicated, he wrote, 1. Recueil
                    des divers Ouvrages en prose et en vers, Paris, 1675, in 4to; 2. Courses de
                    Têtes et de Bagues, faites par le Roi et par les Princes et les Seigneurs de sa
                    Cour, en 1662, Paris,· 1669, in folio; 3. Cabinet des Beaux-Arts, <hi
                    rend="italic">ibid.</hi> 1690, in folio; 4. A Translation of the Fables of
                    Faërne; 5. Memoirs of his Life, for the use of his children; 6. <hi
                    rend="italic">E</hi><hi rend="italic">Oublieux</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Les
                    Fontanges,</hi> manuscript comedies, which, in 1822, passed into the rich and
                    valuable collection of Μ. de Soleinne. D’Alembert included the éloge ofCharles
                    Perrault amongst those of the members of the French Academy (tom. ii. p. 165.)
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
