<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-1919-0064-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PARAIBA, or Parahyba (7th edition, volume 17, page
                    64)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838162">Brazilians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098511">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:990901">Lakes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1043442">Ocean</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pp32">Roads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09wd60">Villas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206830">Brazil</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193491919?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PARAIBA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Parahyba</hi></label>, a
                    province of Brazil, in South America, bounded on the south by Pernambuco, on the
                    north by Rio Grande da Norte, on the west by Sera, and on the east by the
                    Atlantic Ocean. It comprehends about two thirds of the old captaincy of
                    Itamarca, and has between eighteen and nineteen leagues of seacoast, whilst
                    towards the interior it extends westward about sixty leagues. It derives its
                    name from the river Paraiba or Parahyba, which, originating in the Serra da
                    Jabitica, in Cayriris Velhos, not far from the source of the Capibaribe, runs to
                    the north-east, and discharges itself into the Atlantic by two mouths on either
                    side of the island of St Beneto∙ Its principal tributary is the Paraibuna, which
                    flows down from the back of the Serra da Montequeira, under the name of the Rio
                    Preto, which is a mere translation of the Indian name for the river. It is about
                    fifty yards in breadth at the junction, flowing with a rapid and turbid current,
                    over a sandy channel eminently auriferous. Caldcleugh informs us that the
                    current of the Paraiba is also very rapid, being about seven miles in the hour,
                    and the water cool, being twelve degrees under the temperature of the air. “The
                    road was excessively bad, being extremely narrow, with a gulley down the centre;
                    and the soil being a red clay, was very insecure, from the humidity. From the
                    summit the views on all sides were magnificent; but more particularly the one
                    which extended along the valley of the Paraiba. Here and there the eye caught a
                    glimpse of the river glistening amidst the deepest and most luxuriant
                    vegetation.” This description does not agree with the account sometimes given of
                    Paraiba, that two thirds of the whole surface are incapable of any kind of
                    culture. Mr Southey justly characterizes this statement as very erroneous; and
                    recent travellers confirm the fact, that a great part of it possesses a prolific
                    soil, and an agreeable although hot climate. The suriàce of the country,
                    however, is very uneven, elevated ridges traversing it in various directions. Mr
                    Koster travelled to Paraiba from Recife, by way of Goiana. The road between
                    Goiana and Paraiba, a distance of thirteen leagues, presents nothing
                    particularly interesting. The hills are steep, but not high; the principal
                    objects are woods, plantations, and cottages. Returning by the seacoast, he
                    found a considerable portion of it uninhabited; but wherever the land was low,
                    and the surf not violent, cottages were seen, and the banks of the rivers were
                    partially settled. When the action of the tide ceases, the streams all become
                    insignificant, and most of them quite dry. Nearly the whole of Brazil is
                    celebrated for its vegetable productions, particularly timber; and Paraiba is
                    not deficient in this respect. It is noted for the excellence of its Brazil
                    wood, and its sugar, the culture of which, however, has much declined, on
                    account of the droughts which are frequently experienced here; and cotton has
                    taken its place, that plant being said to endure a want of water better than the
                    cane. In the year 1820 a few Britons established themselves here, in connection
                    with some merchants at Pernambuco, for the purpose of reviving and extending the
                    trade. The exports of sugar at one time exceeded nine hundred chests annually,
                    but in 1819 it had sunk to less than half that quantity; whilst in the same
                    period the cultivation of cotton had increased in proportion as the cane had
                    decreased.</p>
                <p>Paraiba, the capital of the province, is situated on the south bank of the river
                    Paraiba, about ten miles from the sea, the river being navigable for a
                    considerable way above the town. The port is capacious and secure, and defended
                    by two or three forts. Vessels of one hundred and fifty tons can pass the bar;
                    sumacas can ascend to the capital, and canoes as far as the town of Pilar, which
                    is situated about forty miles higher up. When this captaincy was taken
                    possession <hi rend="italic">of by</hi> the Dutch in 1634, it contained only
                    seven hundred families and twenty engenhos. They changed the name of the capital
                    to Ferdinand, in honour of the Prince of Orange; and gave a sugar loaf for its
                    arms, in allusion to the great quantity of sugar obtained from the district, and
                    in conformity to a plan then adopted for granting armorial bearings significant
                    of the principal leading articles in the different captaincies under their
                    dominion. The principal street is broad and well paved; the houses are mostly of
                    one story, but some of the buildings are described as handsome. There are
                    several large and respectable convents here, but of late years they have fallen
                    into decay. Indeed the same thing may also be said of the city, for much of the
                    commerce which it once enjoyed is now centred in Recife, a seaport in
                    Pernambuco. The lower town, which consists of small houses, is situated, Mr
                    Koster states, upon the borders of a spacious basin or lake, formed by the
                    junction of three rivers, which discharge their waters into the sea by one
                    considerable stream. These rivers are probably the Paraiba and its two
                    confluents the Guarahu and the small river Unhaby. “The banks of the basin,” he
                    adds, “are covered with mangroves, as in all the salt-water rivers of this
                    country; and they are so close and thick that there seems no outlet. I did not
                    follow the river down to the sea, but I understand that there are in it some
                    fine islands, with good land, quite uncultivated.” One of these has since been
                    cleared, and some salt-works erected upon it, Paraiba lies out of the road from
                    the sertam to Recife; that is, out of the direct way from the towns upon the
                    coast farther north; the inhabitants of the interior will therefore, in
                    preference to Paraiba, make for Recife, as the more extensive market for their
                    produce. Notwithstanding the richness and fertility of the lands of this
                    province, a decided preference is given to plantations nearer to Recife, so that
                    those of Paraiba are to be purchased at a much lower price. The population of
                    this small city may amount to three thousand.</p>
                <p>Besides the capital, this province contains seven towns in the eastern part, or
                    that next the ocean, with a few arraials; and two in the western part. The names
                    of those in the east are, Pilar, Alhandra, Villa Real, Villa do Cort-de<pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193491932?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0717-1932-0065"/>,
                    Villa da Rainha, St Miguel, and Montemor; and those in the west are Pombal and
                    Villa Nova da Souza. None of them are of any extent or material importance.
                    Villa da Rainha, commonly called Campinha Grande, stands in an extensive plain,
                    one hundred and twenty miles northwest from the capital, near a lake which
                    supplies the inhabitants with water. In seasons of drought, which are by no
                    means rare, the lake is dry, and the inhabitants are compelled to fetch their
                    water a distance of six miles. The river Mamanguape, whose embouchure is ten
                    miles north of Point Lucena, but dry in summer a few miles up from the sea,
                    gives its name to a settlement near its banks, which is larger than most of the
                    towns of the province. It is a thriving place, and forms a convenient stage
                    between Rio Grande and Goiana. The population of Paraiba was estimated in 1812
                    at 122,000. From the census of 1830 it is stated at 240,000, which appears to be
                    too large an allowance of inhabitants for such a small tract of a country so
                    thinly peopled as Brazil is, considering its vast extent. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >(r. r. r.)</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Paraiba,</hi> the name of a large river in
                    the Brazilian province of Rio de Janeiro, which see.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
