<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0717-2530-0111-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">PASSOVER (7th edition, volume 17, page 111)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term ref="fast:834550">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137151">Suffering</term>
                    <term ref="fast:838229">Breading</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198482">Bread</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204236">Israel</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t2w">Feasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gt5fn8v">Suffering</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hm8r">Bread</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193492530?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">PASSOVER</label>, a solemn festival of the Jews, instituted
                    in commemoration of their exod from Egypt, because, the night before their
                    departure, the destroying angel, who put to death all the first-born of the
                    Egyptians, passed over the houses of the Hebrews without entering therein, as
                    they were marked with the blood of the lamb which had been killed the evening
                    before, and which, for this reason, was called the <hi rend="italic">paschal
                    lamb.</hi> This feast was called <hi rend="italic">pascha</hi> by the Greeks and
                    Romans, not, we presume, from <hi rend="italic">πασχω, I suffer,</hi> as
                    Chrysostom, Irenaeus, and Tertullian suppose, but from the Hebrew word <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">pesah,</hi> signifying <hi rend="italic">passage.</hi> What God
                    ordained concerning the passover of the Jews is contained in Exodus (c.xii.).
                    The month of the departure from Egypt was looked upon, from this time, as the
                    first month of the sacred or ecclesiastical year; and on the fourteenth day of
                    this month, between the two vespers, that is, between the sun’s decline and his
                    setting, or rather, according to our manner of reckoning, between two o’clock in
                    the afternoon and six o’clock in the evening, at the equinox, they were required
                    to kill the paschal lamb, and to abstain from leavened bread. The day following,
                    being the fifteenth, reckoning from six o’clock of the foregoing evening, which
                    concluded the fourteenth day, was the grand feast of the passover, which
                    continued seven days. But it was only the first and the seventh day that were
                    solemn. The lamb killed was to be without any defect, a male, and yeaned that
                    year. If no lamb could be found, they might take a kid. They killed a lamb or a
                    kid in every family; and if the number of those who lived in the house was not
                    sufficient to eat a lamb, two houses might join together. With the blood of the
                    paschal lamb they sprinkled the doorposts and lintels of every house, that the
                    destroying angel, at the sight of the blood, might pass over them, and thus
                    spare the Hebrew children. They were required to eat the lamb the same night
                    that followed the sacrifice. They ate it roasted, with unleavened bread, and a
                    salad of wild lettuce; the Hebrew says literally, with bitter things, as
                    mustard, or any thing of this nature, to give it a relish. It was forbidden to
                    eat any part of it raw, or boiled in water, nor were they to break a bone of the
                    victim;<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Exodus, vii. 46;
                    Numbers, ix. 12; John, xix. 36.</p></note> and if any thing remained until the
                    day following, it was thrown into the fire. They who ate of it were to be in the
                    posture of travellers, having their loins girt, their shoes on their feet, their
                    staves in their hands, and eating in a hurry. But this last part of the ceremony
                    was little observed, at least it was of no obligation, excepting only on that
                    night when they went forth out of Egypt. During the whole eight days of the
                    passover no leavened bread was to be used; and whoever should eat any, was
                    threatened with being cut off from his people.</p>
                <p>The Jews observed the firstand last day of the feast, yet so as that it was
                    allowed to dress victuals, which was forbidden on the Sabbath-day. The
                    obligation of keeping the passover was so strict, that whoever neglected to do
                    it was condemned to death.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>Numbers, ix. 13.</p></note> But those who had any lawful impediment, as a
                    journey, sickness, or any uncleanness, voluntary or involuntary, as, for
                    example, those who had been present at a funeral, or by any other accident had
                    been defiled, were to defer the celebration of the passover till the second
                    month of the ecclesiasticaLyear, or till the fourteenth day of the month Jair,
                    which answers to April and May. It was thus that the Lord ordered Moses, upon
                    the occasion of an inquiry by some Israelites, who had been obliged to pay the
                    last offices to some of their relations, and who being thus polluted, were not
                    capable of partaking of the paschal sacrifice.<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Chronicles, χχχ, 1, 2, Ac.</p></note> The
                    modern Jews observe in general the same ceremonies which were practised by their
                    ancestors in the celebration of the passover. Upon the fourteenth of Nisan, the
                    first-born fast in memory of God’s smiting the first-born of the Egyptians; but
                    the morning prayers are the same with those which are said on other festivals.
                    They take the roll of the Pentateuch out of the chest, and read as far as the
                    end of the twelfth chapter of Exodus, and also what is contained in the
                    eighteenth chapter of Numbers, relating to the passover. The matron of the
                    family then spreads a table, and sets on it two unleavened cakes, and two pieces
                    of the lamb, a shoulder boiled and another roasted, to put them in mind that God
                    had de-’ livered them with a stretched-out arm. To this they add some small
                    fishes, because of the leviathan; a hard egg, because of the ziz; some meal,
                    because of the behemoth, these three animals being appointed for the feast of
                    the elect in the other life; and pease and nuts for the children, to provoke
                    their curiosity to inquire into the reason of the ceremony. They likewise use a
                    kind of mustard, which has the appearance of mortar, to represent their making
                    bricks in Egypt. The father of the family sits down <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193492543?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0717-2543-0112"/> along with his
                    children and slaves, because upon this day all are free. Being seated, he takes
                    bitter herbs, and dips them in the mustard, then eats, and distributes to the
                    rest. All then partake of the lamb, the history and institution of which is at
                    the same time recited by the master of the family. The whole repast is attended
                    with hymns and prayers. They pray for the prince under whose dominion they live,
                    according to the advice of Jeremiah (xxix. 7), “Seek the peace of the city
                    whither I have caused you to be carried away captives, and pray unto the Lord
                    for it; for in the peace thereof shall ye have peace.” The same things are put
                    in practice during the two following days; and the festival is concluded by the
                    ceremony called <hi rend="italic">habdala,</hi> or distinction. This ceremony is
                    performed at the close of the Sabbath-day, at which time the master of the house
                    usually pronounces certain benedictions, accompanied with certain formalities,
                    requesting that everything may succeed well the week following. After going out
                    of the synagogue, they eat leavened bread for the last time.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See Leo of Modena, iii. c. 3,
                    and the Rabbin.</p></note> Whilst the temple remained, they brought thither
                    their lambs, and there sacrificed them, offering the blood to the priest, who
                    poured it out at the foot of the altar. The passover was typically predictive of
                    Christ, who is the Christian passover.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Corinthians, v. 7.</p></note> As the destroying angel passed
                    over the houses marked with the blood of the paschal lamb, so the wrath of God
                    passes over those whose souls have been sprinkled with the blood of Christ. The
                    paschal lamb was killed before Israel was delivered; so it was necessary that
                    Christ should suffer before we could be redeemed. It was killed before Moses’s
                    law or Aaron’s sacrifices were enjoined, to show that deliverance comes to
                    mankind by none of them, but only by the true passover, that Lamb of God slain
                    from the foundation of the world.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Romans, iii. 25; Hebrews, ix. 14.</p></note> It was killed
                    the first month of the year, which prefigured that Christ should suffer death in
                    this month.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>John, xviii.
                    28.</p></note> It was killed in the evening;<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Exodus, xii. 6.</p></note> and so Christ suffered in the
                    last days, and at this period of the day.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Matthew, xxvii. 46; Hebrews, i. 2.</p></note> At evening
                    also the sun sets, which shows that it was the Son of righteousness who was to
                    suffer and die, and that at his passion universal darkness should overshadow the
                    earth.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Luke, xxiii.
                    44.</p></note> The passover was roasted with fire, to denote the sharp and
                    dreadful pains which Christ should suffer, not only from men, but also from God.
                    It was to be eaten with bitter herbs, not only to putthem in remembrance of
                    their bitter bondage in Egypt, but also to typify our mortification to sin, and
                    readiness to undergo afflictions for Christ.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Colossians, i. 24.</p></note> Many persons erroneously
                    imagine that the passover was instituted in memory of the Israelites having
                    passed the Red Sea; although it is certain the feast was held, and received its
                    name, before the Israelites left Egypt, and consequently several days before
                    they passed the Red Sea. Besides the passover celebrated on the fourteenth of
                    the first month, there was a second passover, held on the fourteenth of the
                    second month after the equinox, instituted by God in favour of travellers and
                    sick persons, who could not attend at the first, nor be present at Jerusalem on
                    the day. The Greeks, and even some of the Catholic doctors, take occasion, from
                    the thirteenth, eighteenth, and nineteenth chapters of St John, to conclude,
                    that Jesus anticipated the day marked for the passover in the law; but the
                    authority of three evangelists seems to establish the contrary.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
