<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-0094-0372-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ETCHING (7th edition, volume 9, page 372)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1066737">Plate</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1066824">Plating</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1152598">Tools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:925697">Fires</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mk65g52">Plating</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mn8h">Plate</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b46t0h12b">Tools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193750094?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ETCHING</label>, a method of engraving on copper, in which
                    the lines or strokes, instead of being cut with a tool or graver, are eaten in
                    with aquafortis. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Engraving.</hi></p>
                <p>Etching, though not very modern, is of later invention than engraving with the
                    tool, of which it was at first only an imitation, practised by painters and
                    other artists, as they could much sooner form their hands to, and attain a
                    facility of, working in this way than with the grayer. But being nevertheless
                    considered as a counterfeit kind of engraving, and therefore inferior to the
                    other, it <hi rend="superscript"> wa</hi> ≡ cultivated in a very confined
                    manner; the closeness of the resemblance of the work to that performed by the
                    tool being made the test of its merit, and consequently the principal object of
                    aim in those who pursued it. This servile restriction of the art of etching to
                    the imitation of the original kind of engraving was a great cause of retarding
                    its advancement towards perfection, as many of the most able masters cramped
                    their talents by the obse∏∙</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193750107?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-0107-0373"/>
                <p>ance of so narrow a rule. This may be seen in the instances of Sadelcrs,
                    Swaneberg, Villamena, and particularly Le Bosse, who, in his treatise on
                    engraving, has laid it down as a principle, that the perfection of this kind
                    consists in the close similitude of the work to that executed with the tool. But
                    this absurd prepossession has been since worn out; and the method of working
                    with aquafortis has been so far improved, that instead of being now deemed a
                    spurious kind of engraving, it evidently appears, in many modem works, the*
                    foundation of an excellence that could never have been produced without it;
                    since, though the neatness and uniformity of the hatches which attend the use of
                    the tool is more advantageous with respect to portraits, yet the liberty and
                    facility of the other manner gives a much greater opportunity to exercise the
                    force of genius and fancy in historical engraving, where the effect of die
                    whole, and not the minute exactness in finishing all the parts, constitutes the
                    principal value.</p>
                <p>There are two methods practised of engraving in this way; the one with a hard
                    varnish or ground, and the other with a soft. The former was at one time much
                    used, being better accommodated to the intention of imitating the engraving with
                    the tool; as the firmness of the body of the varnish gave more opportunity of
                    retouching the lines, or enlarging them with the oval-pointed needles, called by
                    the French <hi rend="italic">échoppes,</hi> as was practised by Le Bosse and
                    otlιers for that purpose. The latter has now almost wholly superseded the use of
                    the other, by the free manner of working it admits of; which affords a power of
                    expression incompatible with the greater inflexibility of the hard varnish, that
                    confines the lines and hatches to such a regularity and sameness, as give
                    stiffness of manner and coldness of effect to the work.</p>
                <p>The combination of the use of the tool and aquafortis, which are now both
                    employed in many cases, has, how- ( wer, given that perfection to engraving
                    which it at present assesses. The truth and spirit of the outline wdιich the
                    nethod of working with aquafortis affords, and the variety bf shades which the
                    different kinds of black produce in his way, as well as other means of
                    expressing the peeu-iar appearance and character of particular subjects, fur-
                    <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> ιish what was defective in the sole usc of the
                    tool; whilst, in the other hand, the exactness and regularity of the ines, which
                    are required for finishing many kinds of deigns, are supplied by the graver; and
                    by a judicious ap- )lication of both, that complete finishing is obtained which
                    íither of them alone must necessarily want.</p>
                <p>The manner by which this is performed, is by covering he surface of the plate
                    with a proper varnish, or <hi rend="italic">ground,</hi> is it is called, whieh
                    is capable of resisting aquafortis, and hen scoring or seratehing away, by
                    instruments resembling ιeedles, the parts of this varnish or ground, in the
                    plaees '’here the strokes or hatches of the engraving are intend'd to be; then,
                    the plate being covered with aquafortis, he parts which are exposed by removing
                    the ground or - <hi rend="superscript"> τ</hi> arnish are corroded or eatcn away
                    by it, whilst the rest, ιeing secured and defended from the aetion of the acid,
                    ’ enιain untouched.</p>
                <p>There are two methods of etching, as has been already observed, the difference of
                    which consists as well in the rind of the varnish or ground as in that of the
                    aquafortis adapted to each kind; but the general methods of performing them are
                    alike in both cases. These varnishes or grounds are distinguished by the names
                    of <hi rend="italic">hard</hi> or <hi rend="italic">soft</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi> tor in their consistence, or the resistance which they give to the
                    needles, lies their essential variation from eaeh other. 1he hard varnish, it is
                    with good reason conjectured, was 'ot the first in use, but soon took the plaee
                    of the other, <hi rend="superscript"> lnc</hi> was for some time the most
                    received in practice, on account of its admitting the work to be made more like
                    that of the graver; the soft has since, however, in its turn prevailed, to the
                    exclusion in some degree of the hard, except in the case of particular subjects,
                    but not so entirely as to take away the expediency of showing how it is
                    performed. The manner of etching with the soft varnish is now, however, one of
                    the most important objects of the art of engraving; and it is at present in
                    universal use, sometimes alone, but more frequently intermixed with the work of
                    the tool, and in some eases with great advantage, even where the whole is
                    intended to pass for being performed by the graver.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Preparation of the soft varnish, according to Mr Lawrence, am
                    eminent English engraver at Paris.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> il</hi> Take of virgin wax and asphaltum eaeh two ounces, of black
                    pitch and Burgundy pitch each half an ounce. Melt the wax and ţiitch in a new
                    earthenware glazed pot, and add to them, by degrees, the asphaltum, finely
                    powdered. Let the whole boil till sueh time as that, taking a drop upon a plate,
                    it will break when it is cold, on bending it double two or three times betwixt
                    the fingers. The varnish, being then enough boiled, must be taken off the fire,
                    and, letting it cool a little, must be poured into warm water, that it may work
                    the more easily with the hands, so as to be formed into balls, which must be
                    rolled up, and put into a piece of taffety for use.”</p>
                <p>It must be observed, first, that the fire be not too violent, for fear of burning
                    the ingredients, a slight simmering being sufficient; secondly, that whilst the
                    asphaltum is putting in, and even after it is mixed with them, the ingredients
                    should be stirred continually with the spatula; and, thirdly, that the water
                    into which this composition is thrown should be nearly of the same degree of
                    warmth with it, in order to prevent a kind of cracking that happens when the
                    water is too cold.</p>
                <p>The varnish ought always to be harder in summer than in winter; and it will
                    beeome so if it be suffered to boil longer, or if a greater proportion of the
                    asphaltum or brown resin be used. The experiment above mentioned, of the drop
                    suffered to cool, will determine the degree of hardness or softness that may be
                    suitable to the season when it is used.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Preparation of the hard varnish used by Callot, commonly called
                    the</hi> Florence Varnish.—Take four ounces of fat oil, very clear, and made of
                    good linseed oil, like that used by painters; heat it in a clean pot of glazed
                    earthenware, and afterwards put to it four ounces of mastieh well powdered, and
                    stir the mixture briskly till the whole be well melted; then pass the whole mass
                    through a piece of fine linen iqto a glass bottle with a long neck, that can be
                    stopped very securely; and keep it for the use that will be below explained.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Method of applying the soft varnish to the plate, and of
                    blackening it.</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> The plate being well polished and
                    burnished, as also cleansed from all greasiness by ehalk or Spanish white, fix a
                    hand-vicc on the edge of the plate where no work is intended to be, to serve as
                    a handle for managing it when warm; then put it upon a chafing-dish, in which
                    there is a moderate fire, and cover the whole plate equally with a thin coat of
                    the varnish; and whilst the plate is warm, and the varnish upon it in a fluid
                    state, beat every part of the varnish gently with a small ball or dauber made of
                    eotton tied up in taffety; whieh operation smoothes and distributes the varnish
                    equally over the plate.</p>
                <p>When the plate is thus uniformly and thinly covered with the varnish, it must be
                    blackened by a piece of flambeau, or of a large eandle which affords a copious
                    smoke; sometimes two or even four such eandles are used together, for the sake
                    of dispatch, that the varnish may not grow eold; which if it does during the
                    operation, the plate must then be heated again, that it may be in a melted <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193750120?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0709-0120-0374"/>
                    state when that operation is performed; but great care must be taken not to burn
                    it, which, when it happens, may be easily perceived by the varnish appearing
                    burnt and losing its gloss. The following expedient is made use of for the more
                    commodiously blackening the varnish, and is particularly necessary where the
                    plates are large: Fix a strong hook in the roof of the room, through which pass
                    four pieces of cord of equal length, at the end of which are fixed four iron
                    rings of about four inches in diameter, for supporting the corners of the plate.
                    The plate, being thus suspended in the air, with the varnished side downwards,
                    may be blackened with great convenience; but this is not, however, absolutely
                    requisite, excepting in the case of large plates, which could not, without
                    difficulty, be suspended, unless this or some other such contrivance were made
                    use of.</p>
                <p>It is proper to be very cautious in keeping the flambeau or candle at a due
                    distance from the plate, lest the wick should touch the varnish, which would
                    both sully and mark it. If it appear that the smoke has not penetrated the
                    varnish, the plate must again be placed for some little time over the
                    chafing-dish; and it will be found that, in proportion as the plate grows hot,
                    the varnish will melt and incorporate with the black which lay above it, in such
                    a manner that the whole will be equally pervaded by it.</p>
                <p>Above all things, in this operation, the greatest caution should be used to keep
                    the fire all the time moderate; and to move frequently the plate, and change the
                    place of all the parts of it, that the varnish maybe alike melted everywhere,
                    and kept from burning. Care must also be taken, that during this time, and even
                    till the varnish be entirely cold, no filth, sparks, or dust, fly on it; for
                    they would then stick fast and spoil the work.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Method of applying the hard varnish.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >—</hi> This is precisely the same as that for the soft; it is spread equally
                    over the warm plate with the taffety-ball, and smoked in the same manner; only,
                    after it is smoked, it must be baked, or dried over a gentle fire of charcoal,
                    till the smoke from the varnish begins to decrease; taking care not to overheat
                    the plate, which would both soften it and burn the varnish.</p>
                <p>The plate being thus prepared, and an exact drawing of the outlines of the design
                    made upon thin paper, the other side of the paper must be well rubbed with chalk
                    or Spanish whitening, or, which is better, with red chalk scraped to a powder:
                    the loose chalk is then cleared off with a linen rag, and the stained side of
                    the paper is laid upon the varnish, fixing the corners to the plate with wax or
                    wafers, to prevent its shuffling; and with a blunted needle or pointer the
                    drawing is slightly traced, and communicates to the varnish an exact outline of
                    the design to be etched.</p>
                <p>A variety of pointers is necessary for the work. Those used for the broad large
                    strokes ought to be very blunt, exceedingly round, and well polished at the
                    point; the sole of a shoe answers very well for polishing the points. The finest
                    ought to be as sharp as a needle. If any scratches or false strokes happen in
                    the working, they are to be stopped up with a hair pencil dipped in Venetian
                    varnish mixed with lamp blaek, by which means these places will be defended from
                    the action of .the aquafortis.</p>
                <p>The next operation is that of eating or corroding the plate with aquafortis, in
                    order to which a border of soft wax, being a composition of bees-wax melted and
                    tempered with a little Venice turpentine and tallow, must be fastened round the
                    plate about an inch high, in the form of a little wall or rampart, to contain
                    the aquafortis. At one of the corners of this border a gutter is usually made,
                    which serves for commodiously pouring the aquafortis off the plate. The plate
                    being thus bordered, take a due quantity of the refiner’s aquafortis, mix it
                    with half its quantity of com mon water, and pour it gently on, till it rise
                    above a finger’s breadth above the surface of the plate; then, if <hi
                    rend="subscript"> a</hi>]I things have been rightly conducted, it will soon be
                    seen that the aquafortis exerts its action in the hatches which have been
                    strongly touched; but those more weakly engraved will appear at first clear, and
                    of the colour of the copper. The menstruum must therefore be suffered to
                    continue on the plate till its effects become visible on the more tender parts;
                    then the aquafortis should be poured off, the plate washed with clean water, and
                    dried before the fire; after which take a small pencil dipped into the Venetian
                    varnish, and cover with it the lighter parts of the plate. This being done, the
                    aquafortis must again be poured on, and suffered to continue a longer or a
                    shorter time, according to the strength of the menstruum or the nature of the
                    engraving; after which it must be poured off as before, and the plate
                    immediately washed with water.</p>
                <p>It may not be improper to observe, that, when the aquafortis is on the plate, a
                    feather should be used to cleanse away the foulness of the verdigris that
                    gathers in the hatches when the aquafortis ∙operates on them, and to give it
                    more room to exert its action; for by moving the aquafortis to and fro on the
                    plate by the feather, and brushing away the black saline matter where it appears
                    to be formed, the hatches will be cleansed, and the aquafortis exert its whole
                    force equally on every part.</p>
                <p>The plate being thus sufficiently corroded by the aquafortis, and well washed
                    with water, it must be warmed at the fire, and the border of wax removed; after
                    which it must be made hotter till the varnish melt; then it must be well wiped
                    with a linen cloth, and afterwards rubbed well with oil of olives, when it will
                    be ready to be retouched and finished by the graver.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
