<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0709-0419-0397-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">EUGUBIAN, or Eugubine Tables (7th edition, volume 9,
                    page 397)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z892m1t">Celtic</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j09w45x">Celts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3825s">Inscriptions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j39364">Monuments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w37kv50">Alphabet</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20d44">Alphabeting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w218">Alphabets</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:916316">Etruscans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1141775">Tableting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025892">Monuments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:805945">Alphabet</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193750419?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">EUGUBIAN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Eugubine
                    Tables</hi></label>, <hi rend="italic">Tabulce Eugu-binoe,</hi> inscribed
                    tablets in bronze, found in 1444 at La Schieggia, near Gubbio <hi rend="italic"
                    >{Eugubiurn),</hi> in the duchy of Urbino. These tablets are seven in number,
                    five of them containing inscriptions in Umbric, mixed with Etruscan, and the
                    remaining two inscriptions in Latin characters. They were at first believed to
                    be of very high antiquity; but it is now pretty generally agreed that they are
                    not more ancient than the fourth century before the Christian era. The learned
                    reader will find copies of these remarkable monuments in Dempster’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Etruria</hi><hi rend="italic">Regalis</hi> (vol. i. p. 91, et
                    seqq.), and also some curious details respecting them in the supplement to that
                    work by the senator Buonarotti (vol. ii. p. 101). According to Lanzi, they refer
                    entirely to the mode of sacrifice, the particular forms of prayer, and other
                    religious rites of certain Umbrian communities, who were united in a sort of
                    federal bond; but the explanations of the learned Italian are much too arbitrary
                    and hypothetical to be of any authority; and, in point of fact, we are still as
                    ignorant of the <hi rend="italic">language</hi> of these inscriptions as when
                    the tablets were first discovered, nearly four centuries ago. (See article <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Etruscans.)</hi> But as the character has proved less
                    untractable than the text, an Etruscan alphabet has been constructed, by means
                    of which we are enabled to read the words which as yet we cannot interpret.
                    Previously to the time (1732) when Bourguet undertook this difficult task,
                    several persons had attempted it, and failed. But, by carefully comparing the
                    tablets in the Roman character with those in the Etruscan, the ingenious
                    Frenchman discovered that the former were a compendium of the latter, and that
                    many words were common to both sets; and, having obtained this key, he
                    succeeded, by pursuing the comparison he had instituted, in constructing an
                    alphabet which, though far from being complete, was yet much more perfect than
                    any <hi rend="superscript"> 7</hi> which had preceded it. Since the time of
                    Bourguet, however, no further progress has been made in this confined but
                    interesting field of inquiry; and as the language has hitherto baffled every
                    artifice of interpretation, the contents of these curious monuments of antiquity
                    still remain undeciphered. The discovery of a bilingual inscription, which is
                    not an impossible event, would, however, furnish the needful key, and lead
                    directly to the solution of an enigma alike vexatious and interesting to the
                    scholar. Should this ever happen, or should some rare effort of sagacity or
                    miracle of fortune unexpectedly put any inquirer on the right road without such
                    aid, we venture to prognosticate that the language of these inscriptions will be
                    found to be radically Celtic, perhaps a dead dialect of that language,
                    intermixed with terms of Pelasgic origin. That the Umbri were Celts, or at least
                    of Celtic origin, there can be little doubt; and it seems equally certain that
                    the Etruscans, who ultimately predominated over all the other tribes which from
                    time to time had settled in <pb break="no" facs="nls:193750432?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0709-0432-0398"/> Etruria, were also, in part at least, of northern
                    descent. It would therefore be strange indeed if in these inscrip* tions, five
                    of which are in the Umbric mixed with the Etruscan character, no traces were
                    found of that primitive language which successive immigrations from the north
                    must have diffused over a considerable portion of the great plain of Italy. The
                    Eugubine Tables were first published by Smetius, 1588; then by Gruter, <hi
                    rend="italic">Inscript,</hi> vol. i. p. 142. (Bourguet, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Dissert. Mem. Cort.</hi> tom. i. p. 1; Dempster, <hi rend="italic">De
                    Etruria</hi><hi rend="italic">Regali,</hi> ubi supra; and Lanzi, <hi
                    rend="italic">Saggio di Lingua</hi><hi rend="italic">Etrusca.</hi> See also <hi
                    rend="italic">Beitrage zur Deutung der</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Euguhinischeη</hi><hi rend="italic">Tafeln von Lassen.</hi> Bonn, 1833.) <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
