<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0328-0305-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WAGER (9th edition, volume 24, page 305)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1169489">Wagers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025265">Money</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1002619">Losers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42b8vd88">Contractions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f47h15q">Oaths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c73">Betting</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n328/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WAGER</label>. The law of wagers may be divided for purposes
                    of convenience into two great classes, dealing respectively with procedure and
                    with substantive law. In both classes the legal importance of the wager has
                    tended to diminish.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Procedure.—</hi> Determination of cases, civil and criminal, by
                    means of wager or analogous forms of procedure is a characteristic feature of
                    archaic law. The <hi rend="italic">legis actio sacramenti</hi> at Rome—at first
                    a real, then a fictitious wager—the wager of battle and of law in England, of
                    the highest antiquity in their origin, survived up to a comparatively late
                    period in the history of both legal systems. The form of the wager survived long
                    after its reason had been forgotten. The general prevalence of the wager form of
                    proceeding is perhaps to be attributed to the early conception of a judge as a
                    mere referee who decided the dispute submitted to him, not as an executive
                    officer of the state, but as an arbitrator casually called in (see Maine, <hi
                        rend="italic">Ancient Law,</hi> c. x.). Wager of battle in England was a
                    mode of trial which was allowed in certain cases, viz., on a writ of right (see
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Writ),</hi> and on appeals of treason and felony (see
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Appeal).</hi> A full account of the judicial combat
                    will be found under <hi rend="smallcaps">Duel</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Ordeal.</hi> Wager of law <hi rend="italic">(vadiatio legis)</hi> was a
                    right of a defendant in actions of simple contract debt and of detinue. It
                    superseded the ordeal (itself called <hi rend="italic">lex</hi> in the Assize of
                    Clarendon and other ancient constitutional records). The mode of proceeding in a
                    wager of law was an interesting relic of that system of compurgation—traced by
                    Blackstone to the Mosaic law, Ex. xxii. 10—which was employed in many legal
                    systems, especially the Scandinavian, and had probably an appreciable effect on
                    the development of the English <hi rend="smallcaps">Jury (</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >q.v.)</hi> It also has some points of resemblance, perhaps some historical
                    connexion, with the <hi rend="italic">sponsio</hi> and the decisory oath of
                    Roman law, and the reference to oath of Scots law (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Oath).</hi> The use of the oath instead of the real or feigned combat—real
                    in English law, feigned in Roman law—no doubt represents an advance in legal
                    development. The technical term <hi rend="italic">sacramentum</hi> is the bond
                    of union between the two stages of law. In the wager of law the defendant, with
                    eleven compurgators, appeared in court, and he swore that he did not owe the
                    debt or (in detinue) that he did not detain the plaintiff’s chattel; while the
                    compurgators swore that they believed that he spoke the truth. It was an
                    eminently unsatisfactory way of arriving at the merits of a claim, and it is
                    therefore not surprising to find that the policy of the law was in favour of its
                    restriction rather than of its extension. Thus it was not permitted where the
                    defendant was not a person of good character, where the king sued, where the
                    defendant was the executor or administrator of the person alleged to have owed
                    the debt, or in any actions other than those named, even though the cause of
                    action were the same. No wager of law was allowed in <hi rend="italic"
                        >assumpsit,</hi> even though the cause of action were a simple debt. This
                    led to the general adoption of <hi rend="italic">assumpsit—</hi> proceeding
                    originally upon a fictitious averment of a promise by the defendant—as a means
                    of recovering debts. Where a penalty was created by statute, it became a common
                    form to insert a proviso that no wager of law was to be allowed in an action for
                    the penalty. Wager of law was finally abolished by 3 aud 4 Will. IV. c. 42.
                    Another form of the judicial wager in use up to 1845 was the feigned issue by
                    which questions arising in the course of Chancery proceedings were sent for
                    trial by jury in a common law court. The plaintiff averred the laying of a wager
                    of <hi rend="italic">£5</hi> with the defendant that a certain event was as he
                    alleged; the defendant admitted the wager, but disputed the allegation; on this
                    issue was joined. 8 and 9 Vict. c. 109 enabled such questions to be referred by
                    the Chancery to the common law courts in a direct manner.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Substantive Law.—</hi> A wager may be defined as “a promise to
                    pay money or transfer property upon the determination or ascertainment of an
                    uncertain event” (Anson, <hi rend="italic">Law of Contract,</hi> p. 171). At
                    common law wagers were legally enforceable, subject to certain rules dictated by
                    considerations of public policy, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> that they did not
                    lead to immorality or breach of the peace, or expose a third person to ridicule.
                    Actions or wagers were not favoured by the judges; and, though a judge could not
                    refuse to try such an action, he could, and often did, postpone it until after
                    the decision of more important cases. Parliament gradually intervened to confine
                    the common law within narrower limits, both in commercial and non-commercial
                    wagers, and both by general and temporary enactments. An example of the latter
                    was 7 Anne c. 16, avoiding all wagers and securities relating to the then war
                    with France. The earliest general enactment was 16 Car. II. c. 7, prohibiting
                    the recovery of a sum exceeding .£100 lost in games or pastimes, or betting on
                    the sides or hands of the players, and avoiding securities for money so lost. 9
                    Anne c. 19 avoided securities for such wagers for any amount, even in the hands
                    of <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> holders for value without notice, and
                    enabled the loser of £10 or upwards to sue for the money he had lost within
                    three months. The hardship of the Act, as it affects securities in the hands of
                        <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> holders, was remedied by 5 and 6 Will. IV.
                    c. 41, which enacted that such securities should be taken to be held for illegal
                    consideration. Finally, 8 and 9 Vict. c. 109, § 18, enacted “that all contracts
                    or agreements, whether by parole or in writing, by way of gaming or wagering
                    shall be null and void; and that no suit shall be brought or maintained in any
                    court of law or equity for recovering any sum of money or valuable thing alleged
                    to be won upon any wager, or which shall have been deposited in the hands of any
                    person to abide the event on which any wager shall have been made; provided
                    always that this enactment shall not be deemed to apply to any subscription, or
                    contribution, or agreement to subscribe or contribute, for or towards any plate,
                    prize, or sum of <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n329/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0329-0306"/> money to be awarded to the winner or winners
                    of any lawful game, sport, pastime, or exercise.”</p>
                <p>What is a lawful game depends upon numerous statutes from 33 Hen. VIII. c. 9
                    downwards, among which may be classed the Lottery Acts (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Lotteries).</hi> A curious exception is made in some of the statutes in
                    favour of unlawful games if they are played in a royal palace. The mere making
                    of a wager is not now illegal, as it was under the earlier statutes; it is
                    simply unenforceable. The winner has no legal remedy against the loser or the
                    stakeholder. The loser can recover his stake where it still remains in the
                    stakeholder’s hands or has been paid over to the winner after notice from the
                    loser to the stakeholder not to pay it over. He cannot recover where it has been
                    paid over to the winner without notice. The agent in a wagering contract may
                    have legal rights against his principal, though the principal has none against
                    the other party. Agreements between buyers and sellers of stocks and shares to
                    pay or receive differences only (sometimes known as “time-bargains”) are within
                    8 and 9 Vict. c. 109, but a broker employed to speculate on the understanding
                    that only differences should be paid by his principal may recover indemnity
                    against the principal. Employment of an agent to bet in his own name may imply
                    an authority to pay the bet if lost, an authority that may become irrevocable
                    after payment to the winner. Though wagers themselves are now void and not
                    illegal, securities for wagers, by the combined effect of 5 and 6 Will. IV. c.
                    41 and 8 and 9 Vict. c. 109, are still either illegal (as a bet on the result of
                    a game) or void (as a bet on the result of something other than a game, such as
                    a contested election). This difference is important as affecting the question of
                    burden of proof in actions on securities originally given for wagering purposes.
                    Where the consideration is illegal, the plaintiff must show affirmatively that
                    he gave value, but the mere absence of consideration throws on him no such duty.
                    In commercial matters the most important examples are wagering policies of
                    insurance, that is, policies made by persons having no insurable interest, and
                    made void by statute (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Insurance).</hi> Sir John
                    Barnard’s Act, 7 Geo II. c. 8 (called “An Act to prevent the infamous practice
                    of stock-jobbing ”), prohibited contracts for liberty to accept or refuse any
                    public stocks or securities, and wagers relating to the stocks.</p>
                <p>In Scotland the courts refuse to try actions on wagers, as being <hi
                        rend="italic">sponsiones ludicrae,</hi> unbecoming the dignity of the
                    courts. 9 Anne c. 19 and 5 and 6 Will. IV. c. 41 extend to Scotland, but the
                    weight of judicial opinion is that 8 and 9 Vict. c. 109 does not. In the United
                    States the loser may, by the legislation of some States, recover his money if he
                    sue within a limited time, as he might have done in England under 9 Anne c.
                    19.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
