<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0361-0338-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WALSINGHAM, Sir Francis </title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 338</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b41r6n051">Maxims</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cv4br3k">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:984032">Journalism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:806713">Ambassadors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1030128">Museums</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n361/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WALSINGHAM, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Francis </hi></label>(
                    <hi rend="italic smallcaps"> c</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">.</hi> 1536-1590),
                    secretary of state under Elizabeth, was descended from an old Norfolk family,
                    and was the third and youngest son of William Walsingham of Scadbury,
                    Chislehurst, Kent, where he was born about 1536. After a good private education
                    he entered King’s College, Cambridge, but did <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n362/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0362-0339"/> not take a degree. He remained abroad during the
                    reign of Mary, and the knowledge of foreign languages he thus acquired is said
                    to have commended him to the notice of Cecil, Lord Burghley. In the parliament
                    which met in January 1558-59 he was returned for Banbury, and in that which met
                    in January 1562-63 for both Banbury and Lyme Regis; he decided to sit for the
                    latter place. Nothing further is known of his political history, till in 1568 he
                    wrote to Cecil a letter on the Darnley murder, which shows that he enjoyed the
                    confidence of Cecil and the regent Murray, and was fully convinced of Queen
                    Mary’s guilt. In the following year Ridolfi, the papal agent, was confined,
                    under suspicion of conspiracy, in Walsingham’s house. In August 1570 Walsingham
                    was selected as special ambassador to France in connexion with the negotiations
                    for the toleration of the Huguenots, and in December took up his residence as
                    permanent ambassador at Paris. On the 19th April 1572 he was successful in
                    obtaining the signature of a treaty of peace between England and France, but the
                    beneficial results of his skilful diplomacy in connexion with the negotiations
                    for the Anjou and Alençon marriages were neutralized by the uncertain and
                    changeable moods of Elizabeth, and finally frustrated by the massacre of St
                    Bartholomew. He took his leave of the king of France on 23d May 1573, and on
                    20th December of the same year he was made secretary of state. On 1st December
                    1577 he was knighted, and on 22d April of the following year made chancellor of
                    the order of the garter. In June following, along with Lord Cobham, he was sent
                    to the Netherlands to assist in arranging a pacification of the States, but the
                    extraordinary vacillation of Elizabeth rendered his mission a total failure. In
                    July 1581 he was again sent on an embassy to Paris, but his instructions were of
                    a kind both so dishonourable and so foolish that he said he wished rather the
                    queen had sent him to the Tower. In such circumstances he could only endeavour
                    to temper and qualify the policy of Elizabeth in such a manner as to prevent a
                    fatal breach in the relations between the two countries, and in this he was
                    successful. His embassy to Scotland in 1583 to endeavour to persuade James to
                    dismiss the earl of Arran was also, as he prognosticated, a failure. He
                    therefore recommended that the purpose of Elizabeth should be effected by
                    fostering a conspiracy among the Scottish nobles, but the project was not
                    carried out for some time afterwards. In 1584 Walsingham was appointed <hi
                    rend="italic">custos rotulorum</hi> of Hants and recorder of Colchester, and in
                    1585 high steward of Winchester. On 23d November 1586 he was returned member for
                    Surrey, and again on 29th October 1587.</p>
                <p>From the first Walsingham, equally with Cecil, Lord Burghley, was strongly
                    hostile to Queen Mary of Scotland. By constant watchfulness and the skilful use
                    of spies he succeeded in discovering the inmost secrets of her policy and plans.
                    He permitted the Babington conspiracy to develop until letters passed between
                    Babington and Mary which, if they are to be accepted as genuine, proved that the
                    scheme for the assassination of Elizabeth had Mary’s full approval. Mary and her
                    friends declared that Walsingham had counterfeited her ciphers; but that
                    Babington sent her letters informing her of the assassination scheme is beyond
                    denial. Mary’s friends, without any proof but her own asseveration, affirm that
                    the letters never reached her, and that Mary’s letters in reply, the
                    authenticity of which Babington to the last never doubted, were forged by the
                    agents of Walsingham. The asseveration of Mary is, however, robbed of all value
                    by the fact that, in addition to denying the authenticity of the letters, she
                    denied all knowledge of the Babington conspiracy; for Mendoza, the Spanish
                    ambassador, while the plot was in progress, wrote to Philip II. that Mary had
                    informed him she was fully acquainted with it. The accusation against
                    Walsingham, that he was an accomplice in bringing Mary to the block on false and
                    forged evidence, cannot therefore be entertained, although there cannot be any
                    doubt that he regarded her execution as a happy deliverance from a position of
                    great political embarrassment. He was one of the commissioners on her trial, and
                    on Mary hinting that the incriminating letters had been written by him, called
                    God to witness that he “had done nothing unbecoming an honest man.”</p>
                <p>By becoming surety for the debts of Sir Philip Sidney, Walsingham, on account of
                    a flaw in the power of attorney left by Sidney, found himself on Sidney’s death
                    unexpectedly involved in pecuniary ruin. But, although one of the ablest and
                    wisest of Elizabeth’s councillors, his honesty had frequently ruffled her
                    self-esteem, and she witnessed his embarrassments without deigning to lend him
                    the smallest help. He died at his house in Seething Lane, London, 6th April
                    1590, in circumstances of so great poverty that his friends buried him in St
                    Paul’s at night to save the expense of a public funeral. Walsingham was a
                    Puritan in his religious principles, but was unable to obtain for the Puritans
                    the consideration from Elizabeth he desired. He established in 1586 a divinity
                    lectureship at Oxford; he was a general patron of learning; and he encouraged
                    Sir R. Hakluyt and other navigators in their voyages of discovery. By Spenser he
                    is described as</p>
                <p>“The Great Maecenas of this age</p>
                <p>As well to all that civil acts professe</p>
                <p>As those that are inspired with martial rage.”</p>
                <p>A large number of Walsingham's letters and state documents are in the library of
                    the British Museum and State Paper Office. An account of his embassies to France
                    with letters and despatches is contained in the <hi rend="italic">Compleat
                    Ambassador,</hi> edited by Sir Dudley Digges, 1655; the ‘‘Heads of a Conference
                    between James VI. and Sir Frances Walsingham, September 1853,” is published in
                    vol. i. of the <hi rend="italic">Bannatyne Miscellany</hi>; and his “Journal
                    from December 1570 to April 15S3 " is published in vol. vi. of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Camden Miscellany</hi> (1871). The <hi rend="italic">Arcana
                    Aulica, or Walsingham’s Prudential Maxims for the Statesman and the
                    Courtier,</hi> London, 1655, said to have been translated from the Spanish, was
                    probably translated by another Walsingham than Sir Francis. In Sir Robert
                    Cotton's <hi rend="italic">Cottoni Posthuma</hi> is a short article entitled
                    “Sir Francis Walsingham's Anatomizing of Honesty, Ambition, and Fortitude."</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
