<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0589-0554-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WHITGIFT, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 554</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1153794">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1166263">Vices</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4zs2kn9v">Tracts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45m6290g">Vice</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n589/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WHITGIFT, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1530 or
                    1533-1604), archbishop of Canterbury, was descended from a middle-class family,
                    the elder brarich of which had been long settled in Yorkshire. He was the eldest
                    son of Henry Whitgift, merchant of Great Grimsby, Lincolnshire, where he was
                    born, according to one account in 1533, but according to a calculation founded
                    on a statement of his own in 1530. At an early age his education was entrusted
                    to his uncle, Robert Whitgift, abbot of the neighbouring monastery of Wellow, by
                    whose advice he was afterwards sent to St Anthony’s school, London. There he
                    lodged with his aunt, wife of the verger of St Paul’s cathedral; but, having
                    through his uncle’s teaching imbibed so much of the Reformation doctrine that he
                    declined to attend mass in the cathedral, he quarrelled with his aunt and had to
                    return home. In 1549 he matriculated at Queen’s College, Cambridge, and in May
                    1550 he migrated to Pembroke Hall, where he lιad the martyr John Bradford for a
                    tutor. On 31st May 1555 he became a fellow of Peterhouse. Having taken lιoly
                    orders in 1560, he became in the same year chaplain to Dr Cox, bishop of Ely,
                    who collated him to the rectory of Teversham, Cambridgeshire. In 1563 he was
                    appointed Lady Margaret professor of divinity at Cambridge, and his lectures
                    gave such satisfaction to the authorities that on 5th July 1566 they
                    considerably augmented his stipend. The following year he was appointed regius
                    professor of divinity, and also became master of Trinity. He had a principal
                    share in compiling the statutes of the university, which passed the great seal
                    on 25th September 1570, and in November following he was chosen vice-chancellor.
                    Macaulay’s description of Whitgift, as “a narrow, mean, tyrannical priest, who
                    gained power by servility and adulation,” is tinged with rhetorical
                    exaggeration; but undoubtedly Whitgift’s extreme High Church notions led him to
                    treat the Puritans with exceptional intolerance. In a pulpit controversy with
                    Cartwright, regarding the constitutions and customs of the Church of England, he
                    showed himself Cartwright’s inferior in oratorical effectiveness, but the
                    balance was redressed by the exercise of arbitrary authority. Whitgift, with
                    other heads of the university, deprived Cartwright in 1570 of his professorship,
                    and in September 1571 he exercised his prerogative as master of Trinity to
                    deprive him of his fellowship. In June of the same year Whitgift was nominated
                    dean of Lincoln. In the following year he published <hi rend="italic">An Answere
                    to a Certain Libel intituled an Admonition to the Parliament.</hi> To this
                    Cartwright replied by a <hi rend="italic">Second Admonition to the
                    Parliament</hi>; and in 1573 Whitgift published a third edition of his <hi
                    rend="italic">Answere,</hi> with additions bearing on Cartwright’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Admonition.</hi> Cartwright thereupon rejoined by a <hi
                    rend="italic">Replye to an Answere made of M. Doctor Whitegifte;</hi> and in
                    1574 Whitgift published <hi rend="italic">Defence of the Answere to the
                    Admonition against the Replye of</hi><hi rend="italic">T.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >C.</hi> On 24th</p>
                <p>March 1577 he was appointed bishop of Worcester, and during the absence of Sir
                    Henry Sidney in Ireland he for two and a half years acted as vice-president of
                    Wales. In August 1583 he was nominated archbishop of Canterbury, and thus was
                    largely instrumental in giving its special complexion to the church of the
                    Reformation. Although he wrote a letter to Queen Elizabeth remonstrating against
                    the alienation of church property, Whitgift always retained her special
                    confidence. In his policy against the Puritans, and in his vigorous enforcement
                    of the subscription test, he was only obeying her behests. His course of action
                    gave rise to the Mar-prelate tracts, in which the bishops and clergy were
                    bitterly attacked. Through Whitgift’s vigilance the printers of the tracts were,
                    however, discovered and punished; and in order more effectually to check the
                    publication of such opinions he got a law passed in 1593 making Puritanism an
                    offence against the statute law. In the controversy between Travers and Hooker
                    he interposed by prohibiting the preaching of the former; and he moreover
                    presented Hooker with the rectory of Boscombe in Wiltshire, in order to afford
                    him more leisure to complete his <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Polity,</hi> a
                    work which, however, cannot be said to represent either Whitgift’s theological
                    or his ecclesiastical standpoint. Towards the close of his episcopate he, in
                    conjunction with the bishop of London and other prelates, drew up the
                    Calvinistic instrument known as the Lambeth Articles. They were, however, not
                    accepted by the church. Whitgift attended Elizabeth on her deathbed, and crowned
                    James I. He was present at the Hampton Court Conference in January 1604, and
                    died at Lambeth on the 29th of the following February. He was buried in the
                    church of Croydon, and his monument there with his recumbent effigy was in great
                    part destroyed in the fire by which the church was burnt down in 1867.</p>
                <p>Whitgift is described by his biographer, Sir G. Paule, as of ‘ ‘ middle stature,
                    strong and well shaped, of a grave countenance and brown complexion, black hair
                    and eyes, his beard neither long nor thick.” He was noted for his hospitality,
                    and was somewhat ostentatious in his habits, sometimes visiting Canterbury and
                    other towns attended by a retinue of 800 horsemen. He left several unpublished
                    works, which are included among the MSS. <hi rend="italic">Angliae.</hi> Many of
                    his letters, articles, injunctions, &amp;c., are calendared in the published
                    volumes of the State Paper series of the reign of Elizabeth. His <hi
                    rend="italic">Collected Works,</hi> edited for the Parker Society by Rev. John
                    Ayre, 3 vols., Cambridge, 1851-53, include, besides the controversial tracts
                    already alluded to, two sermons published during his lifetime, a selection from
                    his letters to Cecil and others, and some portions of his unpublished MSS.</p>
                <p>A <hi rend="italic">Life</hi> of Whitgift by Sir G. Paule appeared in 1612, 2d
                    ed. 1649. It has been embodied by Strype in his <hi rend="italic">Life and Acts
                    of Whitgift,</hi> 1718. There is also a life in Wordsworth’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ecclesiastical Biography,</hi> Hook's <hi rend="italic">Archbishops of
                    Canterbury,</hi> and vol. i. of Whitgift’s <hi rend="italic">Collected
                    Works.</hi> See also Cooper’s <hi rend="italic">Athenae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Canta-</hi><hi rend="italic">brigienses.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
