<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0702-0663-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WOOLSTON, Thomas</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 663</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1093763">Religion</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n702/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WOOLSTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label>
                    (1669—1731), English deist, born at Northampton in 1669, was the son of a
                    “reputable tradesman,” entered Sidney College, Cambridge, in 1685, studied
                    theology, and was made a fellow of his college. Whiston states that he “was in
                    his younger days a clergyman of very good reputation, a scholar, and well
                    esteemed as a preacher, charitable to the poor, and beloved by all good men that
                    knew him.” After a time, by the study of Origen, he became possessed, to
                    fanaticism bordering on insanity, with the notion of the importance of an
                    allegorical interpretation of Scripture, and advocated its use in the defence of
                    Christianity both in his sermons and in his first book, <hi rend="italic">The
                    Old Apology for the Truth of the Christian Religion against the Jews and
                    Gentiles Revived</hi> (1705). For many years he published nothing, and was left
                    to pursue <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n703/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0703-0664"/> his allegorical fancies in peace. But in 1720-21
                    the publication of letters and pamphlets in advocacy of his notions, with open
                    challenges to the clergy to refute them, brought him into trouble. It was
                    reported that his mind was disordered, and Whiston states that his college
                    allowed him his fellowship, though not in residence, on account of his illness,
                    but that when he appeared at college to prove that he was well he was ordered to
                    go into residence. On his refusing to do this his fellowship was taken from him
                    (1721). Whiston interceded for him in vain, “the clamour against him running so
                    high.” In the “Life” prefixed to the collected edition of his works, his
                    non-residence is described as only “a pretence for depriving him.” From 1721 he
                    lived for the most part in London, on an allowance of £30 a year from his
                    brother and other presents. He continued to publish bitter and scurrilous
                    pamphlets against the clergy and the advocates of the literal sense of
                    Scripture. His influence on the course of the deistical controversy commenced
                    with his book, <hi rend="italic">The Moderator between an Infidel and an
                    Apostate, or the Controversy between the Author of the Discourse of the Grounds
                    and Reasons of the Christian Religion and his Reverend Ecclesiastical Opponents
                    Set in a Clear Light</hi> (1725, 3d ed. 1729). The “infidel” intended was
                    Anthony Collins, who had maintained in his book alluded to that the New
                    Testament is based on the Old, and that not the literal but only the allegorical
                    sense of the prophecies can be quoted in proof of the Messiahship of Jesus.
                    Woolston interposed as umpire in the controversy thus started, and, passing from
                    the evidence from prophecy, which alone he allowed, opened the great debate on
                    the evidential value of the miracles of Christ. He denied absolutely the proof
                    from miracles, called in question the fact of the resurrection of Christ and
                    other miracles of the New Testament, and maintained that they must be
                    interpreted allegorically, or as types of spiritual things. Two years later he
                    commenced a series of <hi rend="italic">Discourses</hi> on the same subject, in
                    which he applied the principles of his <hi rend="italic">Moderator</hi> to the
                    miracles of the Gospels in detail. The <hi rend="italic">Discourses,</hi> 30,000
                    copies of which were said to have been sold, were six in number, the first
                    appearing in 1727, the next five 1728-29, with two <hi rend="italic"
                    >Defences</hi> in 1729-30. The publication of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Moderator</hi> drew upon him a prosecution by the attorney-general in 1726 for
                    blasphemy and profaneness, which was suspended in consequence of Whiston’s
                    intercession. But the appearance of the first four of his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discourses</hi> caused the renewal of the prosecution, and on March 4,1729, the
                    trial ended in his being found guilty of the alleged crime. He was sentenced
                    (Nov. 28) to pay a fine of £25 for each of the first four <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discourses,</hi> with imprisonment till paid, and also to a year’s imprisonment
                    and to give security for his good behaviour during life, namely, to be bound
                    himself in a recognizance of £2000 and two securities of £1000 each, or four of
                    £500 each. He failed to find this security, and remained in confinement until
                    his death, though he mitigated its severity by purchasing the liberty of the
                    rules of the King’s Bench. Dr Samuel Clarke solicited at court for his release,
                    but Woolston’s death anticipated any results of his efforts. He died in prison
                    January 21, 1731.</p>
                <p>In his attack on the miracles Woolston does not raise the general philosophical
                    question of their possibility, but confines himself to the task of seeking to
                    prove that the accounts of them as given in the Gospels are, when taken
                    literally, full of contradictions, absurdities, and incredibilities, and that
                    they must therefore be interpreted as allegory, and emblems of Christ’s more
                    mysterious work. In his view, however, that work of Christ appears to be nothing
                    more than to teach the mystical sense of the Old Testament, the best part of
                    which is the “simple golden religion of nature.” He evidently had formed to
                    himself no clear theory of the origin of the accounts, of the miracles,
                    sometimes ascribing them to the fancy of the writers, sometimes to deliberate
                    invention, and he does not seek to harmonize any such view of them with their
                    emblematic character, of which he is such a fanatical advocate. Whiston remarks,
                    probably with truth, “When Woolston died he hardly knew himself whether he
                    believed the Christian religion or not.” Though it cannot be denied that he
                    anticipated, in some of his criticisms of the details of the miraculous
                    narratives, many points since urged by Reimarus, Strauss, and others, he nowhere
                    exhibits the least soundness of judgment, historical sense, or consistency of
                    thought, while his language and illustrations are coarse and offensive in the
                    extreme.</p>
                <p>Upwards of sixty more or less weighty pamphlets appeared in the next few years in
                    reply to his <hi rend="italic">Moderator</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >Discourses.</hi> As amongst the abler and most popular of them may be mentioned
                    Dr Z. Pearce’s <hi rend="italic">The Miracles of Jesus Vindicated,</hi> 1729;
                    Sherlock’s <hi rend="italic">The Tryalofthe Witnesses of the Resurrection of
                    Jesus,</hi> 1729, 13th ed. 1755; and Lardner’s <hi rend="italic">Vindication of
                    Three of Our Saviour's Miracles,</hi> 1729, Lardner being one of those who did
                    not approve of the prosecution of Woolston (see Lardner’s Life by Kippis, in
                    Lardner’s <hi rend="italic">Works,</hi> vol. i.).</p>
                <p>see Life of woolston prefixed to his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> in five
                    volumes, London, 1733; <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of Life and Writings of William
                    Whiston,</hi> London, 1749, pp. 231-35; Appendix to <hi rend="italic">Α
                    Vindication of the Miracles of our Saviour, &lt;tc.,</hi> by J. Ray, 2d ed.
                    1731; Lechler's <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Englischen Deismus,</hi> 1841;
                    Leland’s <hi rend="italic">View of the Principal Deistical Writers,</hi> 1734;
                    Leslie Stephen’s <hi rend="italic">History of English Thought in 18th
                    Century,</hi> ch. iv.; Cairns's <hi rend="italic">Unbelief in the Eighteenth
                    Century,</hi> 1880; Say one’s <hi rend="italic">Les Déistes</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Anglais,</hi> 1882.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
