<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0405-0380-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WARWICK (9th edition, volume 24, page 380)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4m90242v">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43j3985w">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hx2m">Piers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:959914">Honey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950637">Halls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887231">Dalmatians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:887617">Danes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n405/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WARWICK</label>, the county town of Warwickshire, and a
                    municipal and parliamentary borough, is finely situated on the Avon, on the
                    Warwick and Birmingham and Warwick and Napton Canals, and on a branch of the
                    Great Western Railway, 8 miles north-east of Stratford-on-Avon and 108
                    north-west of London. The glory of Warwick is still its castle, which has been
                    truly pronounced to be the “most magnificent of the ancient feudal mansions of
                    the English nobility still used as a residence.” Its position is at once
                    commanding and picturesque, standing as it does on a rock overhanging the Avon.
                    Its principal features are Caesar’s Tower, 147 feet high, built in the 14th
                    century; the Gateway Tower, in the centre; and Guy’s Tower, 128 feet, also of
                    the 14th century. There is a fine collection of pictures. The Great Hall and the
                    family apartments were destroyed by fire in 1871, but have been restored. In the
                    collegiate church of St Mary Warwick possesses one of the most interesting
                    ecclesiastical buildings in the country. We learn from Domesday that a church
                    existed before the Conquest, but of its foundation nothing is really known. It
                    was made collegiate by Roger de Newburgh, the second Norman earl. It was
                    dissolved by Henry VIII. in 1545, by whom it was granted to the burgesses of the
                    town, with an estate then worth £58, 14s. 4d. to maintain it, together with the
                    king’s school. A great part of the church was destroyed by fire in 1694, and
                    afterwards rebuilt. The glory of this church, however, is the Beauchamp Chapel,
                    founded by Earl Richard Beauchamp by will, and commenced in 1443 and completed
                    1464. It is one of the finest examples of pure Gothic in the kingdom. In the
                    centre of the chapel is the splendid tomb of the earl. The church of St
                    Nicholas, near the entrance to the castle grounds, is modern, with a tower and
                    spire, and was erected towards the end of the 18th century. St Paul’s is new.
                    The priory of St Sepulchre was founded by Henry de Newburgh on the site of an
                    ancient church for a society of canons regular. It is now a private residence.
                    One of the most interesting places in Warwick is the hospital of Robert Dudley,
                    earl of Leicester, one of the most picturesque examples of halftimber buildings
                    in England. It was originally used as the hall of the united guilds of the Holy
                    Trinity, the Blessed Virgin, and St George the Martyr. The earl of Leicester, by
                    an Act of Incorporation obtained in 1571, founded the hospital for the reception
                    of twelve poor men possessing not more than £5 a year, and a master. The first
                    master, appointed by the earl himself, was the famous Puritan, Thomas
                    Cartwright. There are numerous charities in the town, the principal being those
                    of Henry VIII., Sir Thomas White, and Thomas Oken. The first is derived from the
                    tithes of St Mary, St Nicholas in Warwick, the parish of Budbrooke, and
                    Chaddesley Corbett, Worcestershire, together with the rents of houses and lands
                    in the borough. It produces about £3000 a year, and is used for paying the
                    stipends of the vicar and an assistant minister for St Mary’s, the vicars of St
                    Nicholas and Budbrooke, the mayor, the town-clerk, yeoman, serjeant-at-mass, and
                    a beadle; while £460, 10s. is annually given in aid of the king’s school. By the
                    charity of Sir Thomas White the sum of £100 is lent, without interest, to young
                    tradesmen for a period of nine years. From the funds left for that purpose by
                    Thomas Oken, allowances are made to the poor. The area of the borough is 5512
                    acres; the population in 1861 was 10,570, in 1871 10,986, and in 1881
                    11,800.</p>
                <p>A fortress is said to have been erected here as early as the year 50, by P.
                    Octavius Scapula, and it is supposed to have been the praesidium Romanorum at
                    which a cohort of Dalmatian horse was stationed. It was destroyed by the Danes
                    in one of their incursions into Mercia, and in 915 Alfred’s daughter Ethelfleda
                    built the fortress on which the castle now stands. The town is mentioned in
                    Domesday, where we learn that “in the borough the king has in his demesne 113
                    houses, and the king’s barons have 112, from which the king receives Danegeld.
                    The bishop of Worcester has 9 dwellings, the bishop of Chester 7, the abbot of
                    Coventry 36, and four were destroyed to enlarge the castle.” In the time of
                    Edward the Confessor the sheriffwick of Warwick, with the borough and royal
                    manors, rendered £65, and “thirty-six sextars of honey, or £24, 6s. instead of
                    honey <hi rend="italic">(pro omnibus quae ad mel pertinebant).</hi> Now, with
                    the <hi rend="italic">forra</hi> of the royal manors and pleas of the county, it
                    pays per annum £145 by weight, £23 for the custom of dogs, 20s. for a sumpter
                    horse, £10 for a hawk, and 100s. for Queengold. Besides this it renders
                    twenty-four sextars of honey of the larger measure, and from the borough six
                    sextars of honey, at the sextar for 15d.” The celebrated Thurkill (or Turchill)
                    was the last Saxon earl of Warwick.</p>
                <p>William the Conqueror began his first northern campaign in 1068, and the first
                    place where his presence is distinctly recorded is Warwick. He erected here one
                    of his strong fortifications on the site of the old one. Not a vestige of it now
                    exists, but, as Mr Freeman writes, “the mound itself still remains, a monument
                    of the wisdom and energy of the mighty daughter of Aelfred, while the keep of
                    William has so utterly perished that its very site can only now be guessed
                    at.”</p>
                <p>Of the earls of Warwick who may be noticed, of course the legendary Guy, with the
                    numerous traditions relating his wonderful achievements, stands first. In proof
                    of his prowess do not his gigantic helmet, his furnace-like pot, and his mighty
                    fork remain in the castle to this day, to testify against all unbelievers?
                    Prominently in history we have Guy de Beauchamp, who came to the title in 1298,
                    and who was called by the favourite Piers Gaveston “the Black Hound of Arden.”
                    He was instrumental in taking Piers prisoner, and in leading him to Blacklow
                    Hill, close to Warwick, and there beheading him in 1311. Richard Nevil, the
                    famous “king-maker” (see below), assumed the title in right of his wife Anne,
                    and was slain at the battle of Barnet, 1471. Then the unfortunate George
                    Plantagenet, duke of Clarence, was created earl by his brother Edward IV., but
                    afterwards perished, it is said, by being drowned in a butt of Malmsey wine. The
                    title has frequently lain dormant. In 1547 it was revived in favour of the
                    Dudleys, when Viscount Lisle was created earl by Edward VI. It became extinct in
                    1589, and in 1618 was renewed in the person of Robert, Lord Rich, whose eldest
                    son was lord high admiral for the Commonwealth. Again the title became extinct
                    in 1759. The castle had long been in the possession of the Greville family,
                    having been granted to Sir Fulke Greville, Lord Brooke, by James I. when it was
                    in a ruinous condition, and he restored it, at a cost, it is said, of £20,000.
                    Dugdale says he made it “not only a place of great strength, but extraordinary
                    delight, with most pleasant gardens, walks, and thickets, such as this part of
                    England can hardly parallel; so that now it is the most princely seat that is
                    within the midland parts of this realm.” He died from the effects of a wound
                    inflicted by his own servant, September 8, 1628. His successor, Robert Greville,
                    was the son of Fulke’s first cousin, and is the Lord Brooke who is famous in the
                    civil war between Charles and the Parliament, and was appointed
                    commander-in-chief of the Parliamentary forces of Warwickshire and
                    Staffordshire. He was engaged in the first fight of the war at Edge Hill, and
                    was killed at the siege of Lichfield cathedral, on March 1, 1643. The title of
                    earl of Warwick was bestowed on Francis, eighth Lord Brooke, by George II. in
                    1746. His son George, who succeeded to the title in 1773, was a great benefactor
                    of the borough, and was lavish in his expenditure on the castle.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n406/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0406-0381"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
