<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0621-0586-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WILLIAMS, Roger (c. 1600-c</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 586</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s296">Coke</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0v131">Pastors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:866909">Coke</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1173757">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:949055">Guilds</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1084357">Puritans</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WILLIAMS, <hi rend="smallcaps">Roger (c. 1600-c</hi></label>.
                    1684), one of the founders of the colony of Rhode Island, North America, was
                    born either of Welsh or Cornish parents, but this as well as the date of his
                    birth has been the subject of dispute. In early life he went to London, where
                    his skill as a reporter commended him to the notice of Sir Edward Coke, who sent
                    him to Sutton’s Hospital (Charterhouse school). From Charterhouse he went to one
                    of the universities, but whether to Oxford or Cambridge there is no direct
                    evidence to show. The register of Jesus College, Oxford, has the following entry
                    under date 30th April 1624: “Rodericus Williams, filius Gulielmi Williams, de
                    Conwelgaio Pleb., an. Nat. 18.” If this entry refers to the founder of Rhode
                    Island he was of Welsh parentage and born about 1606. As Coke was a Cambridge
                    student, the probability is, however, that Williams was sent there; and a Roger
                    Williams matriculated at Pembroke College of that university on 1st July 1625,
                    and took his B.A. degree in January 1627. This Roger Williams was the second son
                    of William Williams, and was baptized at Gwinsea, Cornwall, on 24th July 1600, a
                    date which corresponds with a statement regarding his age made by Williams
                    himself. After leaving the university he entered on the study of law; but, soon
                    forsaking it for theology, he was admitted into holy orders and is said to have
                    had a parochial charge. On account of his Puritan beliefs he left England for
                    Massachusetts Bay, where he arrived in the beginning of 1631. He accepted an
                    invitation to become pastor of a church at Salem, on 12th April 1631, the same
                    day that the magistrates were assembled at Boston to express disapproval of the
                    scheme. To escape persecution he went to Plymouth, beyond the jurisdiction of
                    Massachusetts Bay, and became assistant pastor there; but in the autumn of 1633
                    he returned to Salem as assistant pastor, succeeding in the following year as
                    sole pastor. Chiefly on account of his pronounced opinions regarding the
                    restricted sphere of the civil magistrate in religious matters, he came into
                    conflict with the court of Massachusetts, and, being banished from the colony,
                    left with a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n622/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0622-0587"/> few sympathizers in January 1636 for Narragansett
                    Bay. At first they received a grant of land from an Indian chief, which is now
                    included in Seekonk, Massachusetts, and began to build houses, but in June
                    following he and five others embarked in a canoe for Rhode Island, and founded a
                    settlement to which Williams, in remembrance “of God’s providence to him in his
                    distress,” gave the name of Providence. In 1639 he was publicly immersed and
                    became pastor of the first Baptist church of Providence. As Massachusetts now
                    began to claim jurisdiction over Narragansett Bay, Williams proceeded in June
                    1643 to England, and through the mediation of his friend Sir Henry Vane, whose
                    acquaintance he had made at Massachusetts, obtained an independent charter, 14th
                    March 1644. In 1649 he was chosen deputy president. He again visited England in
                    1651 to obtain a more explicit charter, and remained there till 1654, enjoying
                    the friendship of Milton, Cromwell, and other prominent Puritans. On his return
                    to the colony in 1654 he was chosen president or governor, and remained in
                    office till 1658. He lived to the age of eighty-four, but the exact date of his
                    death is uncertain.</p>
                <p>Williams was the author of a <hi rend="italic">Key into the Language of the
                    Indians of America</hi> (written at sea on his first voyage to England; London,
                    1643, reprinted in vol. i. of <hi rend="italic">Collections</hi> of Rhode Island
                    Historical Society, 1827); <hi rend="italic">Mr Cotton's Letter Examined and
                    Answered,</hi> 1644; <hi rend="italic">The Bloody</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Tenent</hi><hi rend="italic">of Persecution for the Cause of Conscience,</hi>
                    1644; <hi rend="italic">Queries of Highest Consideration,</hi> 1644; <hi
                    rend="italic">The Bloody</hi><hi rend="italic">Tenent</hi><hi rend="italic">yet
                    more Bloody,</hi> 1652; <hi rend="italic">The Hireling Ministry None of
                    Christ’s,</hi> 1652; <hi rend="italic">Experiments of Spiritual Life and
                    Health,</hi> 1652; and <hi rend="italic">George Fox Digged ou,t of his
                    Burrows,</hi> 1676. A complete collection of all his letters that have been
                    recovered forms vol. vi. of the <hi rend="italic">Publications</hi> of the
                    Narragansett Club. See <hi rend="italic">Lives</hi> by Knowles (1833), Gammell
                    (1846), and Elton (1852); Spark’s <hi rend="italic">Library of American
                    Biography;</hi> Savage’s <hi rend="italic">Genealogical Dictionary of New
                    England Settlers; Biographical Cyclopedia of Representative Men of Rhode
                    Island,</hi> 1883; Guild’s <hi rend="italic">Account of the Writings of Roger
                    Williams,</hi> 1862; and Dexter’s <hi rend="italic">As to Roger Williams and his
                    Banishment from Massachusetts Bay,</hi> 1876.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
