<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0617-0582-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WILLIAM (9th edition, volume 24, page 582)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cm4s">Gueux</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w453">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:960336">Horns</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881354">Counting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n617/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WILLIAM</label> (1533-1584), surnamed the <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Silent,</hi> prince of Orange, count of Nassau, was born at
                    the castle of Dillenburg in Nassau on 16th April 1533. He was the eldest son of
                    William of Nassau (died 1559) and his second wife, Juliana of Stolberg, a woman
                    of remarkable piety and discretion, who devoted much thought and care to the
                    training of her children. In 1544 he inherited from his cousin René or Renatus
                    the principality of Orange and the great estates belonging to his family in the
                    Netherlands (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Holland,</hi> vol. xii. p. 74 <hi
                        rend="italic">sqf</hi> He was educated at the court <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n618/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0618-0583"/> of Brussels in the Roman Catholic faith.
                    Having attracted the attention of Charles V., he was invested by the emperor at
                    the age of twenty-two with the command of the army on the French frontier; and
                    it was on his shoulder that Charles V. leaned when in 1555, in the presence of a
                    great assembly at Brussels, he transferred to his son Philip the sovereignty of
                    the Netherlands. Orange was also selected to carry the insignia of the empire to
                    Ferdinand, king of the Romans, when Charles resigned the imperial crown. He took
                    part in Philip II.’s first war with France, and negotiated the preliminary
                    arrangements for the treaty of Cateau-Cambrésis (1559). He was one of the
                    hostages sent to France for the due execution of the treaty, and during his stay
                    in that country Henry II., who entirely misunderstood his character, revealed to
                    him a plan for the massacre of all Protestants in France and the Netherlands.
                    The prince was horrified by this disclosure, but said nothing; and it was on
                    account of his extraordinary discretion on this occasion that he received the
                    surname of “the Silent.” The epithet is apt to convey a mistaken impression as
                    to his general character. He was of a frank, open, and generous nature, without
                    a touch of moroseness in the ordinary intercourse of life.</p>
                <p>The persecution of the Protestants in the Netherlands, carried on with such
                    reckless ferocity by Cardinal Granvella, led Orange, Egmont, and Horn, the most
                    prominent of the great nobles, to protest against the violence of the
                    Government; and in 1563 they wrote to Philip urging him to withdraw Granvella,
                    and ceased to attend the state council. In the following year Granvella was
                    displaced, whereupon they resumed their seats at the council; yet shortly
                    afterwards it was decided by Philip that the canons of the Council of Trent, the
                    edicts, and the Inquisition should be immediately promulgated in every town and
                    village of the provinces, and that the process should be repeated every six
                    months. At the meeting of the state council at which this was formally decided
                    Orange disclaimed any responsibility for the consequences, and he whispered to
                    his neighbour that now the most extraordinary tragedy the world had ever seen
                    was about to begin. The proceedings of the Gueux or reforming party so alarmed
                    the regent, Margaret of Parma, that she was persuaded to sign an accord,
                    declaring the abolition of the Inquisition and granting liberty of worship in
                    all places where the new forms of religion had been already accepted. In
                    consequence of these concessions the great nobles undertook to restore order,
                    the prince of Orange especially distinguishing himself at Antwerp. But Philip,
                    who had been longing for an excuse to crush the independent spirits of the
                    Nether landers, now resolved to send the duke of Alva into the country, with a
                    Spanish force. Orange, since he could not count upon the hearty support of
                    Egmont or Horn, had no alternative but to resign his offices and withdraw from
                    the Netherlands (1567), taking up his residence at Dillenburg. He was warmly
                    attached to Egmont, and before his departure, at an interview at Willebroeck,
                    urged him to seek refuge in some foreign land; but Egmont was not to be
                    persuaded, and the two friends parted never to see one another again.</p>
                <p>Orange was repeatedly summoned to Brussels; but he declined to appear before the
                    Council of Disturbances, on the ground that it had no jurisdiction over an
                    independent prince and a knight of the order of the Fleece. The havoc wrought by
                    Alva filled him with grief and anger; and in 1568 he contrived to collect two
                    forces, one of which, commanded by his brothers Louis and Adolphus, gained a
                    victory in Groningen, where Adolphus fell. Alva, having ordered the execution of
                    Egmont and Horn, advanced against Louis and defeated him in East Friesland.
                    Orange then invaded Brabant, but could neither bring Alva to a decisive
                    engagement nor induce the people to rise against him. The army had therefore to
                    be disbanded, and its disappointed leader joined Wolfgang of Zweibrücken in an
                    attempt to aid the Huguenots. Acting on the advice of Coligny, Orange issued
                    letters of mark to seamen against the Spaniards; and for years the “sea beggars”
                    harassed the enemy along the coast, and often did no little harm to their own
                    countrymen. In 1572 the revolt against Spain was so far successful that Orange
                    resumed the functions of stadtholder of Holland and Zealand, a position to which
                    he had been appointed in 1559; but he professed to rule in the name of the king,
                    for as yet the people had no wish to throw off their allegiance to the Spanish
                    crown. Orange had won their confidence not only by acting as their champion but
                    by accepting the Protestant faith. He had never been an enthusiastic Catholic,
                    and as a Protestant he was distinguished among the eminent men of his time by
                    his mastery of the true principles of toleration. Meanwhile he had been using
                    the utmost diligence in bringing together an army, and his brother Louis, by a
                    brilliant stroke, had captured the city of Mons. On 15th July 1572 the estates
                    of Holland met at Dort, and, recognizing Orange as the legal stadtholder of
                    Holland, Zealand, Friesland, and Utrecht, voted the sums necessary for the
                    prosecution of the war. In August he crossed the Meuse at the head of an army,
                    trusting mainly to the promised co-operation of France. All his hopes, however,
                    were shattered by the massacre of St Bartholomew. He was obliged to disband his
                    troops, and Mons was re-taken by the Spaniards. On 14th April 1574, at the
                    village of Mook, near Nimeguen, the patriots were again routed, and Orange’s
                    brothers, Louis and Henry, slain. But many fortified places held out, and on 3d
                    October Orange, who had ordered the country to be inundated, was able to relieve
                    Leyden, which had for months been defended with splendid bravery and
                    self-sacrifice. At length the brutality and despotism of the Spaniards were so
                    fiercely and generally resented that Orange was able to enter upon a series of
                    negotiations, which resulted on 8th November 1576 in the pacification of Ghent,
                    signed on behalf of nearly all the provinces. By this treaty the provinces bound
                    themselves to drive the Spaniards from the Netherlands, to convoke the
                    states-general, and to establish freedom of worship both for Roman Catholics and
                    for Protestants.</p>
                <p>Don John of Austria, Spanish regent of the Netherlands (1576-78), granted all the
                    demands of the states; but Orange was suspicious of the intentions of the
                    Government, and in nσ way relaxed his vigilance. Troubles soon broke out, and
                    Orange was called to Brussels to the aid of the states, being elected <hi
                        rend="italic">τwwaaτd</hi> (governor) of Brabant. When the archduke Matthias
                    (afterwards emperor) was invited by the Catholic nobles to accept the position
                    of governor-general, Orange prudently refrained from resisting the scheme; and
                    he acted with equal discretion in regard to the duke of Alençon, who came
                    nominally as the protector of the liberties of the Netherlands. Orange, however,
                    retained in his own hands complete control over the movement in the seven
                    northern provinces, which by the Union of Utrecht, signed on behalf of five of
                    the provinces on 23d January 1579, laid the foundations of the commonwealth of
                    the United Netherlands. Orange’s relation to the new federal republic was
                    somewhat vaguely defined; but in his lifetime it was not felt that there was any
                    very urgent need for an exact delimitation of the relative functions of the
                    executive and the legislative authorities. Negotiations for the conclusion of
                    peace with Spain were carried on for some time in vain; and in 1580 Philip
                    issued a ban against the prince, and set a price of 25,000 gold crowns upon his
                    head. Orange pub <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n619/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0619-0584"/> lished a vigorous “apology,” and on 26th July
                    1581 the estates of the United Provinces formally renounced their allegiance to
                    the Spanish crown. An unsuccessful attempt on the life of Orange was made in
                    1582. But on 10th July 1584 he was shot dead in his house at Delft by Balthazar
                    Gerard, who seems to have been actuated in part by fanaticism, in part by the
                    hope of gain.</p>
                <p>William of Orange was tall and well-formed, of a dark complexion, with brown hair
                    and eyes. He was a man of a singularly upright and noble character. He has been
                    charged with excessive ambition; but his ruling motive was undoubtedly a love of
                    justice, for the sake of which he often risked his life and willingly sacrificed
                    his wealth and leisure. He was a born statesman, capable of forming wise and
                    far-reaching plans, and of modifying them to suit the changing circumstances in
                    which it was necessary to execute them. In moments of difficulty he displayed
                    splendid resource and courage, and he had a will of iron, which misfortunes were
                    never able either to bend or to break. To him chiefly belongs the honour of
                    having permanently crippled the tyrannical power of Spain, and of having founded
                    the independence and greatness of the United Provinces.</p>
                <p>He was married four times. His wives were (1) Anne of Egmont (died 1558), by whom
                    he had a daughter and a son, Philip William, who was seized by Alva in 1567 and
                    sent to the court at Madrid, where he was educated; (2) Anne of Saxony (divorced
                    in 1575, died in 1577), the mother of several daughters and of Maurice of Orange
                    (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Holland,</hi> vol. xii. p. 77); (3) Charlotte of
                    Bourbon (died 1582), who had six daughters; (4) Louisa, Coligny’s daughter, the
                    mother of Frederick Henry of Orange <hi rend="italic">floc.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">cit.,</hi> p. 79), who represented the family after the death
                    of his two elder brothers, and succeeded Maurice as stadtholder.</p>
                <p>See Schiller, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Abfalls der Vereinigten
                        Niederlande</hi>; Klose, <hi rend="italic">Wilhelm</hi><hi rend="italic">I.
                        von Oranien;</hi> Gachard, <hi rend="italic">Correspondance</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">de Guillaume</hi><hi rend="italic">le Taciturne</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">Correspondu</hi><hi rend="italic">nee de Philippe II.</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">sur les Affaires</hi><hi rend="italic">des</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Pays-Bas</hi>; Groen van Prinsterer, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Archives ou Correspondance Inédite de la Maison d’Orange</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">-Nassau;</hi> Juste, <hi rend="italic">Guillaume le Taciturne
                        d'après sa Correspondance et les</hi><hi rend="italic">Papiers d’État</hi>;
                    Motley, <hi rend="italic">The Rise</hi><hi rend="italic">of the Dutch
                        Republic.</hi> (J. SI.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
