<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0738-0697-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WRITING MACHINES</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 697</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:996769">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:996779">Letters</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1765196">Space</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4v40jz59">Lettering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4cj87n8t">Letters</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4gh9bf3x">Ink</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n738/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WRITING MACHINES</label>. Machines and appliances of various
                    kinds are in common use to facilitate the process of writing, and to produce
                    copies of writings already made with the pen. Such facsimile writings are
                    obtained by numerous devices, all of which, however, come under the heads (1) of
                    manifolding, (2) of processes analogous in principle to lithography, and (3) of
                    stencilling. The simplest form of manifold writing is by sheets of paper
                    prepared with lamp-black being interleaved between the sheets of white paper on
                    which the impressions are to be taken, and writing over the whole with a style
                    or other sharp-pointed instrument. By this means a considerable number of copies
                    can be made at one time, and the method is in general use among newspaper
                    writers and telegraphists in the production of what is technically known as
                    “flimsy,” where several copies of the same matter are required. Of processes
                    analogous to lithography, the best known is the “hektograph” method, in which
                    the writing is done in the first instance on paper with aniline ink, and then a
                    transfer is made to a gelatine composition which gives off a considerable number
                    of impressions. In principle the autocopyist is like the hektograph, but in this
                    apparatus the writing is done with a special ink, which is transferred to a
                    prepared and properly stretched sheet of parchment. From this parchment copies
                    are obtained precisely as from a lithographic stone on which a transfer has been
                    impressed. Of the apparatus worked in the stencil method, the cyclostyle has
                    been most extensively <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n739/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0739-0698"/> adopted. This machine consists of a frame of
                    sufficient size containing a plate of tin on which the paper from which the
                    impression is to be taken is rested. The paper is prepared in a particular way,
                    and the “pen” with which the writing is done consists of an ordinary wooden
                    holder, at the end of which is fixed on a pivot a minute wheel. The edge of the
                    wheel is studded with fine points, which, as it revolves and turns in the
                    direction of the writing, pierce the paper, thus making a perfect stencil. The
                    ink is passed over the top of this stencil by means of a roller, and the
                    impression is left on a sheet of ordinary paper placed beneath.<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The trypograph is also a
                    stencil-using device, in which a simple style is used for writing, but the paper
                    is stretched over a fine and sharply corrugated metallic plate which punctures
                    the paper as the style passes over it.</p></note></p>
                <p>The principal substitute for the pen, however, is the machine now generally known
                    as the type-writer, which in its present form dates only from 1873, but it has
                    within that time come into extensive use, especially in America, the country of
                    its origin. Numerous attempts to produce type-writing machines had been
                    previously made both in England and America. So long ago as 1714 one Henry <hi
                    rend="underline">Mill</hi> took out a patent for a machine which he described as
                    “an artificial machine or method for the impressing or transcribing of letters,
                    singly or progressively, one after another as in writing, whereby all writings
                    whatsoever may be engrossed in paper or parchment so neat and exact as not to be
                    distinguished from print”; but his instrument is said to have been clumsy and
                    useless, and led to no practical result. In 1867 the idea was taken up by Messrs
                    C. Latham Sholes and Samuel W. Soulé, printers in Milwaukee, and Mr Carlos
                    Glidden, and, after many experiments and failures, a practical working machine
                    was elaborated in 1873, which, being originally made by Messrs E. Remington and
                    Sons, of Ilion, N.Y., is known as the Remington standard type-writer. The
                    success of this machine has induced many inventors to enter the field, and now
                    three principal classes of type-writers are more or less in use. These are (1)
                    type-bar machines, (2) cylinder machines, and (3) wheel machines. The Remington
                    is the type and original of all type-bar machines, which are so called because
                    the steel types are fixed at the extremity of a bar or rod of iron. These bars
                    are in the Remington arranged in a circle around a common centre, and by
                    striking the key of any particular letter, a lever is moved which raises the
                    type-bar, and causes the type at its point to strike on an inked ribbon, and
                    impresses the letter on the paper, which lies against an india-rubber roller.
                    The type-bars are so hinged that all the types as they are struck hit precisely
                    the same spot, so that were the paper to remain stationary the impressions of
                    all the types struck would be superimposed on each other; but, by an automatic
                    mechanism, the cylinder with the paper moves a space to the left after the
                    impression of each type, and the depression of a wooden bar similarly moves the
                    cylinder a space after each word without impressing any sign. In the recent
                    forms of the Remington machine, each type bar carries two types, capital and
                    lower case, or other duplicate signs, the one a little behind the other, and
                    when a capital letter is to be printed the depression of a key shifts the
                    position of the cylinder so as to bring the second type in contact with the ink
                    ribbon. In this way from one set of keys two sets of type can be with facility
                    acted upon. With practice, an average writing speed of forty words per minute
                    can easily be attained on the Remington type-writer, and very expert writers
                    have been able to keep up a speed of from sixty to seventy words for a short
                    time. It is safe to say that type-writing can be ordinarily done at about three
                    times the speed of ordinary handwriting. In the cylindrical machines the letters
                    and signs are all upon a cylinder or “sleeve,” and the striking of a key
                    produces a combined lateral and rotary motion for bringing the proper type to
                    the common printing point. Thus, for every separate impression the entire
                    cylinder has ordinarily to make two movements of variable length, and the
                    instrument is noisy in operation, and does not possess the rapid direct action
                    of the type-bar machines. On the other hand, it is a variable spacer, giving
                    more space to such wide letters as m and w than to the narrow letters i, t, and
                    1, a distinct advantage over the type bar machines, where each letter, wide or
                    narrow, occupies precisely the same space. Of such cylinder machines the newest
                    form is the Crandall type-writer, an apparatus supplied with spare type
                    cylinders or “sleeves,” which are easily separated and attached, so that many
                    kinds of type can be brought into actual use. Of wheel machines the Columbia may
                    be taken as one of the most recent examples. It is a simple and cheap apparatus
                    in which the letters and signs are placed on the periphery of a wheel by the
                    rotation of which any desired type is brought into position for printing. The
                    machine is furnished with a dial index and pointer to indicate the type which is
                    in position. The wheel machine has the advantages of variable spacing, and
                    wheels with type of different character can readily be placed on it; on the
                    other hand, it is not capable of being run with a rapidity nearly so great as
                    can be secured with type-bar machines.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
