<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0351-0328-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WALLENSTEIN (9th edition, volume 24, page 328)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888613">Death</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:843075">Butlers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n351/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WALLENSTEIN</label> (properly <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Waldstein), Adalbert Eusebius von</hi> (1583-1634), duke of Friedland,
                    Sagan, and Mecklenburg, was born on the hereditary estate of his family,
                    Hermanic, in Bohemia, on 15th September 1583. His parents were Protestants, and
                    in early youth he attended the school of the Brothers of the Common Life at
                    Koschumberg. After the death of his parents he was sent by his uncle, Slawata,
                    to the Jesuit college at Olmiitz, where he joined the Roman Catholic Church. In
                    1599 he went to the university of Altdorf, which he had to leave in consequence
                    of some boyish follies. Afterwards he studied at Bologna and Padua, and,
                    according to the custom of the young nobles of the time, visited many places in
                    southern and western Europe. While in Padua, he gave much attention to
                    astrology, and during the rest of his life he seems never to have wavered in the
                    conviction that he might trust to the stars for indications as to his
                    destiny.</p>
                <p>For some time Wallenstein served in the army of the emperor Rudolph II. in
                    Hungary. In 1606 he returned to Bohemia, and soon afterwards he married a rich
                    widow, Lucretia Nikossie von Landeck, whose lands in Moravia he inherited after
                    her death in 1614. Supporting the archduke Ferdinand in his war with Venice, he
                    became favourably known at court, and his influence was increased by his
                    marriage with Isabella Katharina, daughter of Count Harrach, a confidential
                    adviser of the emperor Matthias.</p>
                <p>In the disturbances which broke out in Bohemia in 1618 —disturbances which proved
                    to be the beginning of the Thirty Years’ War—advances were made to Wallenstein
                    by the revolutionary party; but he preferred to associate himself with the
                    imperial cause, for which he repeatedly fought with marked success. In 1620 he
                    was made quartermaster-general of the army of the League, commanded by Tilly.
                    Wallenstein was not present at the battle of the Weissenberg (1620), but soon
                    afterwards he did brilliant service as second in command of the army which
                    opposed Bethlen Gabor in Moravia.</p>
                <p>The battle of the Weissenberg placed Bohemia absolutely at the mercy of the
                    emperor Ferdinand; and Wallenstein, who was a man of insatiable ambition, knew
                    how to turn the prevailing confusion to his own advantage. Through no very
                    honourable means he secured the inheritance of the great estates belonging to
                    his mother’s family, and the emperor sold to him on easy terms vast tracts of
                    confiscated lands. His possessions he was allowed to form into a territory
                    called Friedland, and he was raised in 1622 to the rank of an imperial count and
                    palsgrave, in 1623 to that of a prince. In 1625 he was made duke of Friedland.
                    In the government of his principality he displayed much vigour and foresight. He
                    not only placed the administration of justice on a firm basis, but by many wise
                    measures developed agriculture and mining and manufacturing industries.</p>
                <p>The early successes of the emperor Ferdinand in the Thirty Years’ War were due
                    chiefly to the army of the League, which he could only indirectly control. When
                    he was threatened with a coalition of the Protestant powers, with Christian IV.
                    of Denmark as his most active enemy, he was anxious to have an army of his own,
                    which should be more devoted than that of the League to the interests of his
                    dynasty. He had not, however, the means of securing the fulfilment of his wish.
                    In these circumstances Wallenstein saw that he might have an opportunity of
                    playing a great part in the events of the age; and accordingly, early in 1626,
                    he offered to raise an army for the imperial service. After some negotiations
                    the offer was accepted, the understanding being that the troops were to be
                    maintained at the cost of the countries they might occupy. Wallenstein had
                    always been a popular commander, and great numbers of recruits flocked to his
                    standard, so that he soon found himself at the head of an army of 30,000 men.
                    With this force he marched northwards for the purpose of co-operating with Tilly
                    against Christian IV. and Mansfeld. No engagement was fought in 1625; but on
                    April 25, 1626, Wallenstein defeated Mansfeld at the bridge of Dessau, and later
                    in the year Christian IV. was defeated by Tilly at Lutter. Wallenstein pursued
                    Mansfeld into Hungary, where the Protestant general effected a junction with
                    Bethlen Gabor. Before the end of the year Mansfeld died, and Bethlen Gabor came
                    to terms with the emperor.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n352/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0352-0329"/>
                <p>Having established peace in Hungary, Wallenstein proceeded, in 1627, to clear
                    Silesia of some remnants of Mansfeld’s army; and at this time he bought from the
                    emperor the duchy of Sagan, his outlay in the conduct of the war being taken
                    into account in the conclusion of the bargain. He then joined Tilly in the
                    struggle with Christian IV., and afterwards took possession of the duchy of
                    Mecklenburg, which was granted to him in reward for his services, the hereditary
                    dukes being displaced on the ground that they had helped the Danish king. He
                    failed to capture Stralsund, which he besieged for several months in 1628. This
                    was his first important reverse, and it caused him bitter disappointment, for he
                    had hoped that by obtaining free access to the Baltic he might be able to make
                    the emperor as supreme at sea as he seemed to be on land. It was a part of
                    Wallenstein’s scheme that he should obtain possession of the Hanseatic towns,
                    and through them destroy the naval power of the Scandinavian kingdom, the
                    Netherlands, and England. This plan completely broke down when he was compelled
                    to withdraw his troops from the brave city which he had sworn to take even if it
                    were bound with chains to heaven. Notwithstanding this check, the imperial cause
                    prospered; aud early in 1629 Christian IV. was obliged to accept terms of peace.
                    About the same time Ferdinand issued the famous edict of restitution, which
                    excited deep resentment in every Protestant state in the realm.</p>
                <p>Meanwhile Wallenstein had made for himself a host of enemies among the princes of
                    the empire. They regarded him as an upstart, and complained of the incessant
                    exactions of his army. Moreover, it was by no means clear what he intended to do
                    with the great force he had gathered around him. He was sometimes heard to speak
                    ominously of the arrogance of the princes, and it appeared probable that he
                    might try to bring them, Catholics and Protestants alike, into rigid subjection
                    to the crown. Again and again, therefore, the emperor was advised to dismiss him
                    from his command. Ferdinand was very unwilling to part with one who had served
                    him so well; but the demand was pressed so urgently by the electors in 1630 that
                    he had no alternative, and in September of that year envoys were sent to
                    Wallenstein to announce his removal. Had the emperor declined to take this
                    course, the princes would probably have combined against him; and the result
                    would have been a civil war even more serious than that which had already
                    brought so many disasters upon the country. This was perfectly understood by
                    Wallenstein, who therefore accepted the emperor’s decision calmly, and retired
                    to Gitschin, the capital of his duchy of Friedland.</p>
                <p>Some months before the dismissal of Wallenstein, Gustavus Adolphus had landed in
                    Germany, and it soon became obvious that he was by far the most formidable of
                    the enemies with whom the emperor had yet had to contend. Tilly was defeated at
                    Breitenfeld and in the battle of the Lech, where he received a mortal wound; and
                    Gustavus advanced to Munich, while Bohemia was occupied by his allies the
                    Saxons. After the battle of Breitenfeld the emperor entreated Wallenstein to
                    come once more to his aid. Wallenstein at first declined; he had, indeed, been
                    secretly negotiating with Gustavus Adolphus, in the hope that he might thus be
                    able to maintain his hold over his great possessions. In the end, however, he
                    accepted the offers made to him by Ferdinand, and in the spring of 1632 he took
                    the field with an army of more than 40,000 men. This army was placed absolutely
                    under his control, so that he assumed the position of an independent prince
                    rather than of an ordinary subject.</p>
                <p>His first aim was to drive the Saxons from Bohemia, —an object which he
                    accomplished without serious difficulty. Then he advanced against Gustavus
                    Adolphus, who attacked him near Nuremberg on the 3d of September, but was driven
                    back. On the 16th of November 1632 a decisive battle was fought at Lützen, in
                    Saxony. In this battle the imperialists were routed, but Gustavus Adolphus was
                    killed.</p>
                <p>To the dismay of Ferdinand, Wallenstein made no use of the opportunity provided
                    for him by the death of the Swedish king, but withdrew to winter quarters in
                    Bohemia. In the campaign of 1633 much astonishment was caused by his apparent
                    unwillingness to attack the enemy. The truth was that he was preparing to desert
                    the emperor. That he sincerely desired to secure for Germany the benefits of
                    peace is probable enough, but it is certain that he was also resolved to make
                    for himself a position of commanding importance. He entered into negotiations
                    with Saxony, Brandenburg, Sweden, and France; and one of his conditions was that
                    the possession of the kingdom of Bohemia should be guaranteed to him. He had
                    vast and somewhat vague schemes for the reorganization of the entire
                    constitutional system of the empire, and he himself was to have supreme
                    authority in determining the political destinies of his country.</p>
                <p>Irritated by the distrust excited by his proposals, and anxious to make his power
                    felt, he at last assumed the offensive, and in October he defeated the Swedes at
                    Steinau. Soon afterwards he entered Lusatia and took Görlitz and Bautzen, and
                    despatched a troop of cavalry as far as Berlin. He then resumed the
                    negotiations, and pressed for a full and final acceptance of his plans. In
                    December he retired with his army to Bohemia, fixing his headquarters at
                    Pilsen.</p>
                <p>It had soon been suspected in Vienna that Wallenstein was playing a double part,
                    and the emperor, encouraged by the Spaniards at his court, anxiously sought for
                    means of getting rid of him. Wallenstein was well aware of the designs formed
                    against him, but displayed little energy in his attempts to thwart them. This
                    was due in part, no doubt, to ill health, in part to the fact that he trusted to
                    the assurances of his astrologer, Seni, with whom he often conferred. He also
                    felt confident that when the time came for his army to decide between him and
                    the emperor the decision would be in his own favour.</p>
                <p>His principal officers assembled around him at a banquet on the 12th January
                    1634, when he submitted to them a declaration to the effect that they would
                    remain true to him. This declaration they signed. More than a month later a
                    second paper was signed; but on this occasion the officers’ expression of
                    loyalty to their general was associated with an equally emphatic expression of
                    loyalty to their emperor. By this time Wallenstein had learned that he had too
                    easily allowed himself to be lulled into a sense of security, and that he needed
                    to act warily. On the 24th of January the emperor had signed a secret patent
                    removing him from his command and requiring the army to obey Count Gallas; and
                    imperial agents had been labouring to undermine Wallenstein’s influence. Another
                    patent charging Wallenstein and two of his officers with high treason, and
                    naming the generals who were to assume the supreme command of the army, was
                    signed on the 18th February, and published in Prague.</p>
                <p>When Wallenstein heard of the publication of this patent, he realized the full
                    extent of his danger, and on the 23d February, accompanied by several of his
                    most intimate friends, and guarded by about 1000 men, he went from Pilsen to
                    Eger, hoping to obtain the protection of the Protestant general Bernard of
                    Weimar. After the arrival of the party at Eger, Colonel Gordon, the commandant,
                    and Colonels Butler and Leslie agreed to rid the emperor of his enemy. On the
                    evening of the 25th February Wallenstein’s supporters 111o, Kinsky, Terzky, and
                    Neumann <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n353/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0353-0330"/> were received at a banquet by the three
                    colonels, and murdered by several dragoons. Butler, accompanied by Captain
                    Devereux and a number of soldiers, then hurried to the house where Wallenstein
                    was staying, and broke into his room. He had just taken a bath, and was standing
                    in his shirt ready to go to bed. He was instantly killed by a thrust of
                    Devereux’s partisan. The body was taken to the citadel, and laid beside those of
                    his murdered comrades. Wallenstein was buried at Gitschin, but in 1732 the
                    remains were removed to the castle chapel of Münchengrätz.</p>
                <p>No direct orders for the murder of Wallenstein had been issued, but it was well
                    understood that tidings of his death would be welcome at court. The murderers
                    were handsomely rewarded for what they had done, and their deed was commended as
                    a necessary act of justice.</p>
                <p>Wallenstein was tall, thin, and pale, with reddish hair, and eyes of remarkable
                    brilliancy. He was of a proud and imperious temper, and was seldom seen to
                    laugh. He worked hard, and invariably acted on the motto that if speech is
                    silvern silence is golden. In times of supreme difficulty he listened carefully
                    to the advice of his counsellors, but the final decision was always his own, and
                    he rarely revealed his thoughts until the moment for action arrived. Few
                    generals have surpassed him in the power of quickly organizing great masses of
                    men and of inspiring them with confidence and enthusiasm; and as a statesman he
                    was distinguished for the boldness of his conceptions and the liberality of his
                    sentiments. All his good qualities were, however, marred by a furious lust for
                    power, in the gratification of which he allowed no scruples to stand in his
                    way.</p>
                <p>See Förster, <hi rend="italic">Albrecht von Wallenstein</hi> (1834); Barthold,
                        <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des grossen deutschen Kriegs</hi> (1842-43);
                    Aretin, <hi rend="italic">Wallenstein</hi> (1846); Helbig, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Wallenstein und Arnim, 1632-34</hi> (1850), and <hi rend="italic">Kaiser
                        Ferdinand und der Herzog von Friedland, 1633-34</hi> (1853); Hurter, <hi
                        rend="italic">Zur Geschichte Wallensteins</hi> (1855); Fiedler, <hi
                        rend="italic">Zur Geschichte Wallensteins</hi> (i860); L. von Ranke, <hi
                        rend="italic">Geschichte Wallensteins</hi> (3d ed., 1872); Gindely, <hi
                        rend="italic">Geschichte des dreissigjährigen Kriegs</hi> (1869). (J.
                    SI.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
