<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0731-0690-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WRESTLING and</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 690</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:937529">Games</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1025265">Money</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:943657">Gloves</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:995621">Leggings</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:825070">Back</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6j808">Gaming</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4nc5sc8g">Money</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k55x">Gloves</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vd0k">Leg</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80t1d">Popularity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n731/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WRESTLING <hi rend="smallcaps">and</hi></label> BOXING.
                    Wrestling is the art of forcing an antagonist to the ground without resorting to
                    blows or kicks. It is a trial of strength and skill between two opponents
                    standing face to face, who strive to throw one another. As a gymnastic exercise
                    it was greatly encouraged among the ancient Greeks, and the highest honours and
                    rewards were bestowed on the victors at the Olympic, Isthmian, Nemean, and other
                    games (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Games).</hi> It was also cultivated by the
                    Romans, though their tastes inclined to more savage and brutalizing exhibitions
                    than that of wrestling. It was not unknown in Egypt and at Nineveh, as may be
                    seen from the sculptures in the British Museum. At the same time it differed
                    very much in its ancient form from the wrestling of to-day, the wrestlers of old
                    being wont to compete almost if not quite nude, their bodies besmeared with oil
                    or some other kind of grease by way of making their muscles supple; but, as this
                    practice rendered it very difficult to get fair hold of one another, the
                    wrestlers were accustomed to use sand on their hands, or even to roll in the
                    dust of the arena as a corrective. In their contests they took hold of each
                    other by the arms, drew forward, pushed backward, used many contortions of the
                    body, interlocked their limbs, seized one another by the neck, throttled, lifted
                    each other off the ground, and butted like rams, though the chief point of their
                    art was to become master of their opponent’s legs, when a fall was the immediate
                    result. In England the pastime has been popular from an early period, more
                    especially in the Middle Ages, for in 1222, in Henry III.’s reign, it is on
                    record that a wrestling match took place between the men of Westminster and the
                    citizens of London in St Giles Fields, the latter winning easily. The return
                    match was held at Westminster on Lammas day following, but was interrupted by
                    the bailiff of Westminster and his associates, who maltreated the Londoners and
                    drove them into the city. At a later period Clerkenwell was the usual trysting
                    place. At one of the matches there in 1453 another riot occurred, and the lord
                    mayor.</p>
                <p>who usually attended these athletic carnivals, was again routed and driven within
                    the city boundary. In those days the prize was sometimes a ram and sometimes a
                    cock.</p>
                <p>The four English systems of wrestling include those of (1) Cornwall and Devon,
                    (2) Lancashire, (3) Catch hold, first down to lose, and (4) Cumberland and
                    Westmorland. The Cornwall and Devon men compete in strong loose linen jackets,
                    catching hold above the waist or of any portion of the jacket. Kicking, which
                    used to be a prominent feature of the west-country style, is now forbidden, and
                    the men wrestle in their stockinged feet. In order to be fairly thrown, two
                    shoulders and one hip must be on the ground, or two hips and one shoulder, and a
                    man must be thrown flat on his back before any other portion of his body touches
                    the earth ere a decision can be given against him. Formerly each county wrestled
                    under different rules, but the systems are now amalgamated and are classed as
                    one and the same. In Lancashire the wrestlers compete in their stockinged feet,
                    but are allowed to catch hold of any portion of the body. This is the most
                    barbarous of all the English systems, and includes the objectionable battling on
                    the ground which is the fatal characteristic of the French method. Tripping,
                    however, is not forbidden, and a fall is sometimes secured without a resort to
                    scrambling tactics, which is impossible under French rules. The “catch hold,
                    first down to lose” style of wrestling is of recent origin and promises to
                    become popular. The utmost simplicity distinguishes it. Ordinary wrestling
                    attire is worn, such as jersey, drawers or knickerbockers, and stockings. The
                    men on closing must not grip lower than the waist, and the competitor who
                    touches the ground first by any part of his body is the loser. This system is
                    perhaps the fairest for all parties, as the competitors set to work on equal
                    terms without that delay in getting into holds so frequent in north-country
                    wrestling. The Cumberland and Westmorland system is probably the best and most
                    scientific of all. On taking hold, the wrestlers stand up' chest to chest, each
                    placing his chin on his opponent’s right shoulder and grasping him round the
                    body, the right arm of each being under the left arm of the other, and each
                    joins his hands behind his opponent. When both have got hold the play commences.
                    Kicking is forbidden, and if one competitor lets go his hold before the other
                    the decision is given against him. If both fall on the ground—an undecided or
                    dogfall, as it is termed—they wrestle over again, but if one falls before the
                    other his defeat is registered at once. This kind of wrestling is free from
                    danger, and the German style much resembles it, but in the latter a competitor’s
                    hands are not required to remain locked behind his adversary’s back, as is the
                    practice in the north of England. No catching hold of legs, thighs, or arms is
                    allowed, but each man tries to throw his adversary by using the “buttock,” which
                    consists of facing to the right, twisting so as to place the left hip under an
                    opponent’s middle, pulling him close, stooping forwards and lifting him off the
                    ground, and throwing him; or the “crossbuttock,” facing to the right about to
                    such an extent as to turn the back to the adversary, and then proceeding as
                    before; or the “back-hank,” which consists in commencing as in the “buttock,”
                    and then passing the left leg from inside round an antagonist’s left leg, when
                    by keeping a tight hold with the arms and pulling backwards the leverage
                    supplied by the leg being inside usually secures the fall; or the “back heel,”
                    which consists in pulling an opponent towards one, putting the left heel behind
                    his right heel, forcing his leg up forwards, and throwing him bodily backwards;
                    or the “left leg hipe,” which consists in lifting and swinging him round to the
                    right, then striking the inside of his right thigh with the outside of the left
                    thigh, by which he <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n732/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0732-0691"/> gets off his balance and falls; the “right leg
                    hipe” is the same action <hi rend="italic">mutatis</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >mutandis.</hi> There is also the “left leg stroke,” which consists in striking
                    an antagonist’s right leg with one’s left leg, swinging him round to the left
                    and off his balance; the “right leg stroke” is the same thing with the right
                    leg. Of course there is an umpire to see that no competitor takes an unfair
                    advantage or plays foul, and to determine disputed points according to the rules
                    in force.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Boxing.</hi> —This, though perhaps hardly as popular as
                    wrestling, is closely identified with it in the gymnasium, if not outside it. In
                    the United Kingdom prize fighting is an illegal sport, but it is hardly likely
                    that glove boxing will ever fall into the same disrepute. Its present
                    comparative popularity is principally due to the efforts of the late Mr John G.
                    Chambers, who in 1866 founded the Amateur Athletic Club, and in conjunction with
                    the marquis of Queensberry drew up a code of rules (known as the Queensberry
                    rules), which regulate the principal glove contests throughout the kingdom, as
                    follows :—</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Challenge Cups (Open do Gentlemen Amateurs').—</hi> 1. That the
                    entries be drawn to contend by lots. 2. That the entrance fee be 10s. 3. Heavy
                    weights to be over 11 stone 4 lb; middle weights not to exceed 11 stone 4 lb;
                    light weights not to exceed 10 stone. 4. That there be three judges appointed by
                    the committee. 5. That the boxing take place in a 24 feet ring. 6. That no
                    wrestling, roughing, or hugging on the ropes be allowed. 7. That each heat
                    consist of three rounds, with one minute interval between; the duration of each
                    round to be at the discretion of the judges, but not to exceed five minutes. 8.
                    Any competitor not coming up to time shall be deemed to have lost. 9. That no
                    shoes or boots with spikes or spriggs be allowed. 10. Competitors to wear
                    jerseys. 11. Gloves to be provided by the club. 12. The cups to be boxed for
                    once in each year; the winner to receive a silver medal.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Definition of Gentleman Amateur.—</hi> Any gentleman who has
                    never competed in an open competition, or for public money, or for admission
                    money, or with professionals for a prize, public money, or admission money, and
                    who has never at any period of his life taught, pursued, or assisted in the
                    pursuit of athletic exercises as a means of livelihood. The committee reserve
                    the right of requiring a reference or of refusing an entry.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Contests for Endurance.—</hi> To be a fair stand-up boxing
                    match, in a 24 feet ring, or as near that size as practicable; no wrestling or
                    hugging allowed; the rounds to be of three minutes’ duration and one minute
                    time; if either man fall through weakness or otherwise he must get up
                    unassisted; ten seconds to be allowed him to do so; the other man meanwhile to
                    retire to his corner, and when the fallen man is on his legs the round is to be
                    resumed and continued until the three minutes have expired, and, if one man
                    fails to come to the scratch in the ten seconds allowed, it shall be in the
                    power of the referee to give his award in favour of the other man; a man hanging
                    on the ropes in a helpless state, with his toes off the ground, shall be
                    considered down; no seconds or any other person to be allowed in the ring during
                    the rounds; should the contest be stopped by any unavoidable interference, the
                    referee to name time and place for finishing the contest as soon as possible, so
                    that the match must be won or lost, unless the backers of both men agree to draw
                    the stakes. The gloves to be fair-sized boxing gloves of the best quality, and
                    new; should a glove burst or come off, it must be replaced to the referee’s
                    satisfaction. A man on one knee is considered down, and if struck is entitled to
                    the stakes. No shoes or boots with spriggs allowed. (E. D. B.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
