<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0597-0562-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WIGTOWN, or Wigton</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 562</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1053582">Parishes</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:883965">Crops</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1131380">Stairs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:891974">Devil</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:859599">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44j0b34r">Sheriffs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4416t316">Hay</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29f5v">Parishes</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843v7w">Grasses</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="7" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n597/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WIGTOWN, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Wigton</hi></label>, a
                    maritime county in the south-west corner of Scotland, forming the western
                    division of the old. district of Galloway, is bounded N. by the Irish Channel
                    and Ayrshire, E. by Kirkcudbright and Wigtown Bay, S. by the Irish Sea, and W.
                    by the Irish Channel. It is of very irregular form. Its greatest breadth, east
                    and west, is about 33 miles and its greatest length, north and south, about 26
                    miles. The area is 310,742 acres or 485∣ square miles.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Physical Features.—</hi> The coast-line has a total length of
                    about 120 miles. On the eastern boundary the estuary of the Cree expands into
                    Wigtown Bay. Between Wigtown and Luce Bays is the peninsula of the Machers, of
                    which Burrow Head is the southern extremity. Luce Bay has a length of about 15
                    miles and an average breadth of 12. By its indentation on the south and that of
                    Loch Ryan (about 9 miles long and nearly 3 broad) on the north the two-pronged
                    peninsula of the Rinns is formed, of which the Mull of Galloway, the most
                    southerly point in Scotland, is the southern extremity, and Kirkcolm Point the
                    northern. The coast is more or less precipitous, with many small inlets, few of
                    which, on account of dangerous hidden rocks, afford suitable landing-places for
                    vessels. Loch Ryan forms, however, a splendid natural harbour, of which
                    Stranraer is the port. Portpatrick on the Irish Channel is the nearest port in
                    Great Britain to Ireland, and 7 miles to the south is Port Logan. With the
                    exception of Port William on its eastern shore, Luce Bay is destitute of
                    harbours. Wigtown Bay includes on the Wigtown side the small harbours of the
                    Isle of Whithorn, Garliestown, Wigtown, and Carty, but the upper portions of the
                    bay are not navigable at low water. The county is occupied almost solely by
                    Silurian strata, its characteristic feature being a series of rocky hills, which
                    extend more or less over the whole county, attaining their highest elevation in
                    the north, on the borders of Ayrshire. A considerable number range between 400
                    and 800 feet in altitude, the highest summits being Miltonish (970 feet), on the
                    northern border, and Craigairie Fell (1000 feet) in Kirkcowan parish. A great
                    part of the county has a wild and bleak appearance, the hills being covered with
                    heath and whins, while in the lower parts there are long stretches of bog and
                    moss. The Silurian rocks are in some parts interpenetrated by small areas of
                    granite; and immense granite boulders are occasionally scattered over the lower
                    grounds, doubtless the result of the Glacial action of the Kirkcudbrightshire
                    ice bed. Along the western edge of Loch Ryan there is a narrow band of
                    Carboniferous strata, consisting of sandstones which have been classed as
                    calciferous. They rest unconformably on a narrow belt of Permian strata
                    separating them from the Silurian rocks. In the Carboniferous strata various
                    plant impressions are met with. Between Luce Bay and Loch Ryan, and on the upper
                    shores of Wigtown Bay, there are raised beaches. Galena, copper pyrites, and
                    barytes have been found in small quantities; grey shales for roofing slates and
                    flags for pavement are dug at Cairn Ryan on the eastern shores of Loch Ryan,
                    where sandstone is also quarried for building purposes; from the clays in the
                    neighbourhood of <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n598/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0598-0563"/> Stranraer bricks are manufactured. Owing to the
                    irregular hilly character of the county the streams, though numerous, are
                    generally small. The Cree, forming the boundary with Kirkcudbrightshire, flows
                    past Newton Stewart and Carty into Wigtown Bay; the Bladenoch, from Loch Maberry
                    on the Ayrshire border, falls into Wigtown Bay at the town of Wigtown, after
                    having received the Tarf, the Malzie, and the Black Burn; and the Luce, formed
                    by the junction of the Main Water and the Cross Water at New Luce, flows south
                    into Luce Bay. There are a very large number of lochs, but none of them very
                    extensive, the principal being the beautiful one in Inch parish included in the
                    grounds of Castle Kennedy, Lochs Maberry and Dornal on the Ayrshire border, Loch
                    Connel in Kirkcolm parish, Loch Ronald in Kirkcowan parish, and Castle Loch and
                    the four lochs of Mochrum in Mochrum parish. Dowalton Loch, at the junction of
                    Kirkinner, Sorbie, and Glasserton parishes, was drained in 1862.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Agriculture.</hi> —Although the rainfall exceeds the average in
                    Scotland, the climate is not specially unfavourable for the ripening of crops,
                    and frosts are not generally of long continuance. A considerable portion of
                    Wigtownshire consists of stony moors, which have insufficient soil to render
                    reclamation possible. Along the shores there is some extent of gravelly soil,
                    which, however, requires heavy manuring to render it fruitful. Where the higher
                    districts are arable a rocky soil prevails, better adapted for grass and green
                    crops than for corn crops. A large extent of the county is black top reclaimed
                    from moors; in other districts loam and clay prevail. The most common method of
                    cropping is a six years’ shift of oats, green crops, corn crop, and three years’
                    grass. According to the <hi rend="italic">Agricultural Returns</hi> for 1887,
                    the arable area was 147,063 acres or about 46 per cent, of the whole,
                    considerably above the average for even the lowland counties of Scotland. The
                    area under corn crops was 37,392 acres, of which 35,511 were under oats. The
                    latter area has not materially changed within the last thirty years, the chief
                    diminution having been in wheat, which in 1855 occupied 7343 acres and in 1887
                    only 736. Barley and bere in 1887 occupied 796 acres, rye 38, and beans 310. The
                    bulk of the green crops consists of turnips and swedes, occupying in 1887 15,678
                    acres, whilst 1902 acres were potatoes, 229 mangold, 100 carrots, 153 cabbage,
                    &amp;c., and 135 vetches. There were 69,326 acres under clover and rotation
                    grasses and 21,883 under permanent pasture. In 1881 (the latest return) there
                    were over 8009 acres under woods, and in 1887 there were 40 under nursery
                    grounds, 6 under market gardens, and 7 under orchards. The large area under
                    grass and turnips is owing to the general prevalence of dairy farming. In 1887
                    the number of cattle was 42,062, of which 21,197 were milch cows, a number
                    exceeded in only four other counties in Scotland, although in the number of its
                    cattle it is surpassed by ten counties. The Galloway cattle, a black polled
                    breed, are now chiefly confined to the eastern districts, the Ayrshire being
                    found a much more suitable breed for dairy purposes. In some cases Galloway
                    bulls are kept for breeding with Ayrshire cows. Many dairy farms send milk to
                    Glasgow and the neighbouring towns; but the manufacture of cheese has greatly
                    increased within late years, large cheese factories having been established.
                    Dunlop is now almost wholly superseded by Cheddar cheese. Horses, chiefly
                    Clydesdale, for which breed Wigtownshire has acquired some fame, numbered 5699
                    in 1887; sheep, chiefly blackfaced on the hilly farms, and in other districts
                    crosses with Leicesters and other long-woolled breeds, numbered 116,264; and
                    pigs 10,380. From 1345 returns obtained from occupiers of land in 1887, out of
                    147,104 acres 142,266 were rented and occupied and 4838 owned and occupied. The
                    following table gives a classification of agricultural holdings according to
                    size in 1880 and 1885 :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Year.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>50 acres and under.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>50 to 100 acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>100 to 200 acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>200 to 500 acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>500 to 1000 acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>Above 1000 acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p>TotaL</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p/></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Acres.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>No.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Acres.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1880</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>608</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>9241</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>208</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>16,090</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>422</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>74,576</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>88</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>32,638</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>12,271</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,210</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1347</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>146,026</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1885</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>597</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>8778</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>216</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>15,851</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="superscript">
                            421</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1 75,837</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>91</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>34,426</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>18</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>11,186</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="superscript">
                            1</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1,220</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>1344</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>147,298</p><p>1</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>According to the latest landowners’ <hi rend="italic">Return,</hi> the county was
                    divided among 1820 proprietors, possessing 309,087 acres at an annual value of
                    £230,589, or about 14s. lid. per acre. Of the proprietors 1674 possessed less
                    than one acre each. The following owned over 5000 acres each :—earl of Stair,
                    79,174; E. J. S. Blair, 37,268; earl of Galloway, 23,203; marquis of Bute,
                    20,157; Sir W. Maxwell, 16,877; James M ’ Douall, 16,290; Sir Andrew Agnew,
                    12,962; D. Hunter Blair, 8255; William Maitland, 7848; Sir J. Dalrymple Hay,
                    7400; R. Vans Agnew, 6777; W. C. S.</p>
                <p>cloister, and a small portion of the church in the Early English</p>
                <p>Hamilton, 6300; Mrs S. Ο. Μ‘Taggart, 5998; Lieut.-Col. Sir W. T. F. Agnew
                    Wallace, 5785; and R. H. J. Stewart, 5552.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>For further particulars regarding the agriculture, see a
                    paper by W. II. Ral-stone, in <hi rend="italic">Τrαηs. Royal and Highland Agric.
                    Soc.,</hi> vol. xvii., new ser. (1885).</p></note><hi rend="italic"
                    >Communication.—</hi> The Portpatrick Railway crosses the county from Newton
                    Stewart by Kirkcowan, Glenluce, and Stranraer to Portpatrick. From Newton
                    Stewart the Wigtownshire Railway passes south by Wigtown and Garliestown to
                    Whithorn. The Girvan and Portpatrick Railway branches off from the Portpatrick
                    line at East Challoch near Dunragit and passes northwards by New Luce. There is
                    a line of steamers to Ireland by Portpatrick.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures and Trade.—</hi> Although agriculture is the main
                    industry, there is a variety of small manufactures in the towns, including a
                    woollen factory at Kirkcowan, engineering and locomotive works at Stranraer,
                    hand-loom weaving in various places, distilling, tanning, and currying. The
                    fishing industry is of almost no account. There is, however, an oyster fishery
                    in Loch Ryan, and herrings are caught in Loch Ryan and the Bay of Luce. The
                    value of the salmon fisheries, including those of the rivers, is less than £1000
                    a year.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Administration and Population.—</hi> From 22,918 in 1801 the
                    population had by 1821 increased to 33,240 and by 1851 to 43,389; but it
                    declined to 42,095 in 1861, to 38,830 in 1871, and to 38,611 (males 18,143,
                    females 20,468) in 1881. In point of density Wigtown stands twenty-first among
                    the counties of Scotland, the number of persons to the square mile being 79. The
                    proportion of females to every 100 males was 112'82, the largest proportion of
                    any county with the exceptions of Orkney and Shetland and Forfar. The number of
                    persons who could speak Gaelic was only twentyeight. The town population in 1881
                    numbered 9060, the village 8574, and the rural 20,977. The county has three
                    royal burghs— Wigtown (1789), Stranraer (3455), and Whithorn (1643). The last
                    two are also police burghs (Stranraer, 6342). Part (2645) of the police burgh of
                    Newton Stewart is within the county, the remainder being in Kirkcudbrightshire.
                    Newton Stewart is also a burgh of barony, as are likewise Glenluce (901) and
                    Portpatrick (591). The county returns one member to parliament. Formerly
                    Wigtown, Stranraer, and Whithorn formed with New Galloway a group of burghs
                    returning one member, but by the Act of 1885 they were merged in the county. The
                    county includes seventeen parishes. Wigtownshire is in the same sheriffdom as
                    the counties of Kirkcudbright and Dumfries. Sheriff courts are held during
                    certain periods at Wigtown and Stranraer, and quarter sessions are held at
                    Wigtown and Glenluce.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities.—</hi> The portion of Galloway now
                    forming Wigtownshire was in early times occupied chiefly by the Novantae. When
                    the district was overrun by the Romans under Agricola in 82, they fixed their
                    headquarters at Whithorn <hi rend="italic">(Leucophibia),</hi> and one of their
                    principal stations, <hi rend="italic">Rerigonium,</hi> was on the eastern shore
                    of Loch Ryan. The Devil’s dyke, a defensive work of the Romans, extended from
                    Loch Ryan to the upper part of the Solway Firth. A sketch of the early history
                    of Galloway, including Wigtownshire, is given-under <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Kirkcudbright</hi> (vol. xiv. p. 98). The district was the scene of the labours
                    of the Christian missionary St <hi rend="smallcaps">Ninian</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >(q.v.),</hi> who arrived at Whithorn <hi rend="italic">(Candida Casa)</hi>
                    towards the close of the 4th century. Whithorn was a bishop’s see from 727 till
                    the Reformation. In addition to the caves on the sea coast, which, like those of
                    Kirkcudbrightshire, are associated with early human occupation, the ancient
                    inhabitants have left traces of themselves in cairns, standing stones, hut
                    circles, and remains of ancient villages. Numerous early relics have also been
                    dug up, including flint and other stone implements, as well as a great variety
                    of ancient bronze implements and ornaments.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>For lists with illustrations, see papers by Rev. G. wilson
                    and Sir Herbert Maxwell in <hi rend="italic">Ayr and Wigton Archaeological
                    Collections,</hi> vols, i., ii., and v.</p></note> The Dowalton crannogs were
                    the first lake dwellings discovered in Scotland, and are among the most
                    remarkable in the country.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p>See <hi rend="smallcaps">Crannogs,</hi> vol. vi. 552; and for descriptions
                    of these and other lake dwellings in Wigtownshire, consult a paper by Robert
                    Monro, in <hi rend="italic">Ayr and Wigton Arch. Coll.,</hi> vol. v., and “Notes
                    on Crannogs and Lake Dwellings of Wigtonshire,” by Rev. G. Wilson, in <hi
                    rend="italic">Proceedings Soc. Antiq. Scot.,</hi> vol. ix. pp. 368-378 and x.
                    737-739.</p><p/></note> Among the ancient fortalices may be mentioned the sea
                    towers of Carghidown and Castle Feather, south of Whithorn; the ruins of
                    Baldoon, south of Wigtown, associated with events which suggested to Scott the
                    tale of the <hi rend="italic">Bride of Lammermoor</hi>; the tower of Corsewall
                    near the west shore of Loch Ryan; the foundations of a Norse stronghold in
                    Cruggleton Bay; Dunskey at the head of Castle Bay, built in the 16th century,
                    but occupying the site of an ancient fortress; the fragments of Long Castle at
                    Dowalton Loch, the ancient seat of the</p>
                <p>M‘Doualls; the castle of Mochrum and Myrtoun Castle, the seat of the Maccullochs,
                    in Mochrum parish; and the ruined tower of Sorbie, the ancient keep of the
                    Hannays. Of the Cistercian abbey of Glenluce, founded in 1190 by Roland, lord of
                    Galloway, the principal remains are the chapter house in the Decorated style,
                    the walls of the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n599/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0599-0564"/> style. The ancient cathedral of Whithorn, though
                    in a dilapidated condition, forms a picturesque ruin, and near it are some
                    slight remains of the ancient priory founded by St Ninian. The Dominican priory
                    of Wigtown, founded in 1267, has, like the ancient castle, entirely disappeared;
                    and only some slight mounds remain of Saulseat abbey, founded for
                    Premonstratensians by Fergus, lord of Galloway, in 1148. Wigtown was probably
                    created a sheriffdom in the 13th century. In 1341 the earldom of Wigton, which
                    included the whole of the county, with the jurisdiction of a regality, was
                    bestowed upon Sir Malcolm Fleming. In 1372 the earldom was purchased by
                    Archibald Douglas, who the same year was created lord of Galloway. In the reign
                    of James I. William Douglas of Leswalt was sheriff of Wigtown and keeper of the
                    castle of Lochnaw; but in 1426 the constableship of Lochnaw, with the sheriffdom
                    of Wigtown, was acquired by Andrew Agnew. These dignities continued to be held
                    by the Agnew family tül 1682, when Sir Andrew Agnew refused to take the test and
                    was superseded by Graham of Claverhouse. At the Restoration in 1688 the office
                    of sheriff was restored to the Agnew family, and they held it till the abolition
                    of hereditary jurisdictions in 1747. The principal modern mansions are Galloway
                    House, built in 1740, the seat of the earls of Galloway; Castle Kennedy, built
                    by the first earl of Stair after the destruction of the old castle by fire in
                    1716; the baronial castle of Lochnaw, including, with large modern additions,
                    the battlemented tower of the ancient building; and Barnbarroch House, the seat
                    of R. Vans Agnew.</p>
                <p>See Symson, <hi rend="italic">Description of Galloway,</hi> 1823; Murray, <hi
                    rend="italic">Literary History of Galloway,</hi> 1882; Sir Andrew Agnew, <hi
                    rend="italic">Hereditary Sheriffs of Galloway,</hi> 1864; <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histories of Galloway,</hi> by Mackenzie, 1841, and P. II. Mackerlie, 1870-78.
                    (T. F. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
