<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0524-0499-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WELLS (9th edition, volume 24, page 499)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1173723">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:984609">Judgments</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828732">Baths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170190">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f45m">Judgments</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k224">Baths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n524/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WELLS</label>, a municipal borough in the county of Somerset,
                    England, at the foot of the Mendip Hills, 135 miles west of London. At present
                    it is a place of little importance, except for its cathedral, markets, and
                    assizes. The population of the city (726 acres) in 1881 was 4634.</p>
                <p>The city of Wells is said to have derived its name from some springs called St
                    Andrew’s Wells, which during the Middle Ages were thought to have valuable
                    curative properties. The municipality, consisting of a mayor, seven aldermen,
                    and sixteen chief burgesses, was incorporated by a charter granted by King John
                    in 1202. During Saxon times Wells was one of the most important towns of Wessex,
                    and in 905 it was made the seat of a bishopric by King Edward the Elder. About
                    the year 1091-92 Bishop John de Villula removed the see to Bath; and for some
                    years Wells ceased to be an episcopal city. After many struggles between the
                    secular clergy of Wells and the regulars of Bath, it was finally arranged in
                    1139 that the bishop should take the title of “bishop of Bath and Wells,” and
                    should for the future be elected by delegates appointed partly by the monks of
                    Bath and partly by the canons of Wells. The foundation attached to the cathedral
                    church of Wells consisted of a college of secular canons of St Augustine,
                    governed by a dean, sub-dean, chancellor, and other officials.</p>
                <p>The existing cathedral, one of the most magnificent of all the secular churches
                    of England, was begun by Bishop Joceline soon after his election to the
                    episcopate in 1220; and the greater part of the building was completed before
                    his death in 1244. According to the usual mediaeval practice, the eastern part
                    of the church was begun first, and the choir was consecrated for use long before
                    the completion of the nave, the western part of which, with the magnificent
                    series of statues on the façade, was carried out during the second half of the
                    13th century, and probably finished about the year 1300. The upper half of the
                    two western towers has never been built. The very noble and well-designed
                    central tower, 160 feet high, was built early in the 14th century; the beautiful
                    octagonal chapter-house on the north side, and the lady chapel at the extreme
                    east, were the next important additions in the same century. The whole church is
                    a building of very exceptional splendour and beauty; it is covered throughout
                    with stone groining of various dates, from the Early English of the choir to the
                    fan vaulting of the central tower. Its plan consists of a nave and aisles, with
                    two short transepts, each with a western aisle and two eastern chapels. The
                    choir and its aisles are of unusual length, and behind the high altar are two
                    smaller transepts, beyond which is the very rich Decorated lady chapel, with an
                    eastern semi-octagonal apse. The main tower is at the crossing. On the north of
                    the choir is the octagonal chapter-house, the vaulting of which springs from a
                    slender central shaft; as the church belonged to secular clergy, it was not
                    necessary to place it in its usual position by the cloister. The cloister, 160
                    by 150 feet, extends along the whole southern wall of the nave. The extreme
                    length of the church from east to west is 371 fegt. The oak stalls and bishop’s
                    throne in the choir are magnificent examples of 15th-century woodwork, still
                    well preserved.</p>
                <p>The great glory of the church, and that which makes it unique among the many
                    splendid buildings of mediaeval England, is the wonderful series of sculptured
                    figures w'hich decorate the exterior of the west front,—the work of English
                    sculptors of the latter part of the 13th century,—a series which shows that at
                    that time England was, as far as the plastic art is concerned, in no degree
                    inferior to Germany and France, or even Italy, if we except the work dona <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n525/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0525-0500"/> by Niccola, the sculptor of the wonderful
                    baptistery pulpit at Pisa. The whole of the façade, 147 feet wide, including the
                    two western towers, is completely covered with this magnificent series; there
                    are nine tiers of single figures under canopies, over 600 in number, mostly
                    large life size, with some as much as 8 feet in height, and other smaller
                    statues; these represent angels, saints, prophets, kings and queens of the
                    Saxon, Norman, and Plantagenet dynasties, and bishops and others who had been
                    benefactors to the see. There are also forty-eight reliefs with subjects from
                    Bible history, and immense representations of the Last Judgment and the
                    Resurrection, the latter alone containing about 150 figures. The whole
                    composition is devised so as to present a comprehensive scheme of theology and
                    history, evidently thought out with much care and ingenuity. As works of art,
                    these statues and reliefs are of very high merit; the faces are noble in type,
                    the folds of the drapery very gracefully treated with true sculpturesque
                    simplicity, and the pose of the figures remarkable for dignity. The main lines
                    of the sculpture throughout are carefully arranged in a severely architectonic
                    manner, so as to emphasize and harmonize with the chief features of the
                    structure. Complete self-restraint is shown in the subordination of each part to
                    the general effect of the whole—one of the great merits of English sculpture
                    down to the 16th century. Of course a great variety of hands and much diversity
                    of workmanship can be traced in this mass of sculpture, but in very few cases
                    does the work fall conspicuously below the general level of excellence, and some
                    of the best figures show the very flower and crown of English plastic art, which
                    was reaching its highest point about the time that the west front of Wells was
                        completed.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>See
                            Cockerell, <hi rend="italic">Iconography of Wells Cath.,</hi> 1851;
                            Reynolds, <hi rend="italic">Wells Cath.,</hi> 1881; and Britton, <hi
                                rend="italic">Wells Cath.,</hi> 1821. The stone used for this
                            sculpture is from the neighbouring Doulting quarry; it was once
                            decorated with gold and colour, applied on a ground of fine <hi
                                rend="italic">gesso</hi> in the usual way.</p></note></p>
                <p>The interior of the central tower presents an interesting example of the very
                    skilful way in which the mediaeval builders could turn an unexpected
                    constructional necessity into a novel and beautiful architectural feature. While
                    it was being built the four piers of the great tower arches showed signs of
                    failure, and therefore, in order to strengthen them, a second lower arch was
                    built below each main arch of the tower; and on this a third inverted arch was
                    added. Thus the piers received a steady support along their whole height from
                    top to bottom, and yet the opening of each archway was blocked up in the
                    smallest possible degree. The contrasting lines of these three adjacent arches
                    on each side of the tower have a very striking and graceful effect; nothing
                    similar exists elsewhere.</p>
                <p>On the south side of the cathedral stands the bishop’s palace, a stately moated
                    building, originally built in the form of a quadrangle by Bishop Joceline
                    (1205-1244), and surrounded by a lofty circuit wall. The hall and chapel are
                    very beautiful structures, of rather later date, mostly of the 14th century.</p>
                <p>The vicars’ college was a secular foundation for two principals and twelve
                    vicars; fine remains of this, dating from the 15th century, and other residences
                    of the clergy stand within and near the cathedral close; some of these are among
                    the most beautiful examples of mediaeval domestic architecture whieh exist
                    anywhere in England.</p>
                <p>The church of St Cuthbert in Wells is one of the finest of the many fine
                    parochial churches in Somersetshire, with a very noble tower and spire at the
                    west end. It was originally an Early English cruciform building, but the central
                    tower fell in during the 16th century, and the whole building was much altered
                    during the Perpendicular period. Though much damaged, a very interesting reredos
                    exists behind the high altar; erected in 1470, it consists of a “Jesse tree”
                    sculptured in relief. Another very beautiful reredos was discovered in 1848,
                    hidden in the plaster on the east wall of the lady chapel, which is on the north
                    side. (J. H. Μ. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
