<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0400-0377-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WARTON</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 377</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1107958">Schools</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:994503">Lays</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1432095">Scholarships</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:839665">Brothers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b46688q84">Odes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n400/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WARTON</label>. Three authors of this name, a father and two
                    sons, were leaders of reaction against the didactic poetry of Pope’s school, and
                    did much to help forward the descriptive and romantic revival.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas Warton</hi> (1688-1745), satirized in <hi
                    rend="italic">Terrae Filius</hi> (February 18, 1721) as “squinting Tom of
                    Maudlin,” was vicar of Basingstoke in Hampshire, and professor of poetry at
                    Oxford. He published nothing during his lifetime, but after his death his son
                    Joseph published some of his poetry under the title <hi rend="italic">Poems on
                    Several Occasions,</hi> 1748.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Joseph Warton</hi> (1722-1800), eldest son of the preceding,
                    was born at Dunsford, in Surrey, in 1722, and sent to Winchester school in 1736.
                    Collins was already there, and the school seems to have been at the time quite a
                    nest of singing birds, quickened into unusual ambition by a visit from Pope.
                    Collins and Warton became close friends, read Milton and Spenser together, and
                    wrote verses which they sent to the <hi rend="italic">Gentleman’s Magazine,</hi>
                    verses of such promise that Johnson formally criticized them. The two friends
                    <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n401/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0401-0378"/> went to Oxford together, and took the degree of
                    B.A. in the same year (1743). Warton was far from having the genius of Collins,
                    but he had abundance of poetical enthusiasm, and they were at one in their
                    impatience under the prevailing taste for moral and ethical poetry. Whoever
                    wishes to understand how early the discontent under Pope’s ascendency began
                    should read Warton’s <hi rend="italic">The Enthusiast,</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Love of Nature,</hi> and remember that it was written by an undergraduate
                    in 1740, while Pope was still alive. Warton sounded a bold note in 1746, in the
                    preface to his <hi rend="italic">Odes on Several Subjects.</hi> “As he is
                    convinced,” he wrote, “that the fashion of moralizing in verses has been carried
                    too far, and as he looks upon invention and imagination to be the chief
                    faculties of a poet, so he will be happy if the following odes may be looked
                    upon as an attempt to bring back poetry into its right channel.” Warton
                    thereafter married, became a country clergyman, a master in Winchester school,
                    eventually for thirty years (1766—96) a much respected headmaster, but all his
                    leisure was given to literature, and he remained constant to his conception of
                    the “right channel” in poetry, though he soon abandoned the idea of setting the
                    world right by his own example. He became an active and prominent man of
                    letters, produced an edition of Virgil, in 1753, with distinguished coadjutors,
                    and a translation of the <hi rend="italic">Eclogues</hi> and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Georgics,</hi> and a preparatory essay by himself; made the
                    acquaintance of Johnson, and wrote papers on Shakespeare and Homer in <hi
                    rend="italic">The Adventurer;</hi> published the first part of an essay on Pope
                    in 1756, an essay regarded at the time as revolutionary, by Dictator Johnson at
                    least, because it put Pope in the second rank to Shakespeare, Spenser, and
                    Milton, on the ground that moral and ethical poetry, however excellent, is an
                    inferior species; held his own against Johnson in the Literary Club; and, after
                    enduring many jests about the promised second part and the delay in its
                    appearance, published it at last, retracting nothing, in 1782. Of this essay
                    Campbell justly says that “it abounds with criticism of more research than
                    Addison’s, of more amenity than Hurd’s or Warburton's, and of more insinuating
                    tact than Johnson’s.” Warton’s edition of Pope was the work of his old age; when
                    published in 1797, it found a larger number of sympathizers with his criticism
                    of the poetic idol of the 18th century than had welcomed his first essay forty
                    years before in the same vein. The last three years of the critic’s life were
                    spent in preparing an edition of Dryden, which was completed and published by
                    his son in 1811. He died in London in February 1800, at the age of
                    seventy-eight.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas Warton</hi> (1728-1790), the younger brother of
                    Joseph, at least as active and influential as he in enlarging the poetic ideas
                    of the 18th century, was born at Basingstoke in 1728. He was still more
                    precocious as a poet than his brother—translated one of Martial’s epigrams at
                    nine, and wrote <hi rend="italic">The Pleasures of Melancholy</hi> at seventeen
                    —and he showed exactly the same bent, Milton and Spenser being his favourite
                    poets, though he “did not fail to cultivate his mind with the soft thrillings of
                    the tragic muse” of Shakespeare. He wrote as follows in 1745 :— Through Pope’s
                    soft song though all the Graces breathe, And happiest art adorn his Attic
                    page,</p>
                <p>Yet does my mind with sweeter transport glow</p>
                <p>As, at the root of mossy trunk reclined,</p>
                <p>In magic Spenser’s wildly warbled song</p>
                <p>I see deserted Una, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>In the same poem he shows the delight in Gothic churches and ruined castles which
                    inspired so much of his subsequent work in romantic revival. Most of Warton’s
                    poetry, humorous and serious,—and the humorous mock heroic was better within his
                    powers than serious verse,—was written before the age of twenty-three, when he
                    took his M.A. degree and became a fellow of his college (Trinity,</p>
                <p>Oxford). He did not altogether abandon verse; his sonnets, especially, which are
                    the best of his poems, were written later, and during the last six years of his
                    life he was poet-laureate, and one of the happiest in the execution of the
                    delicate duties that have ever held the office. But his main energies were given
                    to omnivorous poetical reading and criticism. He was the first to turn to
                    literary account the mediaeval treasures of the Bodleian Library. It was through
                    him, in fact, that the mediaeval spirit which always lingered in Oxford first
                    began to stir after its long inaction, and to claim an influence in the modern
                    world. Warton, like his brother, entered the church, and held, one after
                    another, various livings, but he did not marry. He gave little attention to his
                    clerical duties, and Oxford always remained his home. He was a very easy and
                    convivial as well as a very learned don, with a taste for pothouses and crowds
                    as well as dim aisles and romances in manuscript and black letter. The first
                    proof that he gave of his extraordinarily wide scholarship was in his <hi
                    rend="italic">Observations on the Poetry of Spenser,</hi> published in 1754,
                    when the author was twenty-six. Three years later he was appointed professor of
                    poetry and held the office for ten years, sending round, according to the story,
                    at the beginning of term to inquire whether anybody <hi rend="italic"
                    >wished</hi> him to lecture. The first volume of his monumental work, <hi
                    rend="italic">The History of English Poetry,</hi> appeared twenty years later,
                    in 1774, the second volume in 1778, and the third in 1781. A work of such
                    enormous labour and research could proceed but slowly, and it was no wonder that
                    Warton flagged in the execution of it, and stopped to refresh himself with
                    annotating the minor poems of Milton, pouring out in this delightful work the
                    accumulated suggestions of forty years. Specialists may here and there detect
                    errors and imperfections in Warton’s <hi rend="italic">History,</hi> but its
                    miscellaneous and curious lore must make it always an interesting book, while
                    its breadth and exactness of scholarship must always command wonder and respect.
                    Through this work Warton became the veritable literary father of Sir Walter
                    Scott; if he could have lived to read the <hi rend="italic">Lay</hi> and <hi
                    rend="italic">Marmion</hi> he would have found realized there what he vaguely
                    desiderated in modern poetry. Among Warton’s minor works were a selection of
                    Roman metrical inscriptions (1758); the humorous Oxford <hi rend="italic"
                    >Companion to the Guide</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Guide to the Companion</hi>
                    (1762); <hi rend="italic">The Oxford Sausage</hi> (1764); an edition of
                    Theocritus (1770); lives of Thomas Pope and Bathurst, college benefactors; a <hi
                    rend="italic">History of the Antiquities of Kiddington Parish,</hi> of which he
                    held the living (1781); and an <hi rend="italic">Inquiry into the Authenticity
                    of the Poems attributed to Thomas Rowley</hi> (1782). His busy and convivial
                    life was ended by a paralytic stroke in May 1790. (W. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
