<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0620-0585-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WILLIAM of Wykeham</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 585</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4pr7mw5j">Commons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0399k">Towers</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35b4z">Wells</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nj3s">Sealing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bv7b36b">Reformers</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47659q39">Surveyors</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:869839">Commons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1173723">Wells</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1153279">Towers</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110280">Sealing</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:874582">Conducting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n620/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WILLIAM <hi rend="smallcaps">of Wykeham</hi></label>
                    (1324-1404), bishop of Winchester and chancellor of England, was born in 1324 at
                    Wickham in Hampshire. His father was a yeoman; his mother is said to have been
                    of noble descent. He was educated at the priory school, Winchester, at the cost
                    of Sir John Scures, lord of the manor of Wickham and governor of Winchester
                    Castle, who afterwards took him into his service. When he was twenty-two years
                    old he passed into the service of Edingdon, bishop of Winchester. In 1347 the
                    bishop introduced him to the king as a young man likely to be useful from his
                    skill in architecture. Edward III., who ∙was then completing the Round Tower at
                    Windsor, made him his chaplain. But his employment for some time was mainly
                    secular: he acted as guardian of several of the king’s manors and as derk of the
                    works at Henley and elsewhere. In 1356 he was appointed surveyor of the works at
                    Windsor, and a little later surveyor and warden of several other castles. In
                    1359 he began the building of the great quadrangle to the east of the keep
                    at</p>
                <p>Windsor, a work which occupied ten years. This building established his fame as
                    an architect. Two years after its completion he was employed to build
                    Queenborough Castle (Kent). Meanwhile he was also gaining experience in affairs
                    of state. In 1360 he must have been a member of the king’s council, for he
                    appears as a witness to the ratification of the treaty of Brétigny. In 1364 he
                    became keeper of the privy seal. In 1365 he was one of the commissioners to
                    treat for peace with Scotland. And, although he was not yet in holy orders, he
                    was loaded by the king with preferments, one of which, the living of Pulham in
                    Norfolk, involved him (about 1360) in a dispute with the pope. In fact he had
                    attained to such eminence that Froissart says, “At this time there reigned in
                    England a priest called Sir William de Wican, so much in favour with the king
                    that by him everything was done.”</p>
                <p>Early in life William had received the tonsure; but it was not till 1362 that he
                    was ordained deacon and priest. In 1363 he became archdeacon of Northampton, and
                    provost and prebendary of Wells. Although at this time he possessed a number of
                    prebends, it appears, from a return which he made in 1366 on account of a papal
                    bull against pluralities, that he only held one benefice with cure of souls. On
                    the translation of Bishop Edingdon in this year from Winchester to Canterbury
                    William was nominated by the king to the vacant bishopric; but the pope withheld
                    his confirmation for some time, and it was not till October 1367 that William
                    was consecrated bishop of Winchester. A month previously he had been made
                    chancellor of England. During his first chancellorship the war with France was
                    renewed and went against the English. The blame for this fell in great measure
                    on the ministry, and in 1371 William resigned the great seal. But in 1373 he was
                    one of a committee of the Lords appointed to confer with the Commons on the
                    question of an aid. About this time he fell out with John of Gaunt, with whom he
                    had previously been on good terms. Since the overthrow of the clerical ministry
                    in 1371 John of Gaunt had been practically head of the government, but the
                    conduct of his supporters caused general discontent. In the “Good Parliament” of
                    1376 Lord Latimer was impeached, and the bishop was active in promoting his
                    trial and punishment. This was a great blow to John of Gaunt. The death of the
                    Black Prince in June 1376 enabled him to take his revenge. The bishop was
                    attacked in the council on the ground of malversation and misconduct of public
                    affairs during his chancellorship, condemned to pay an enormous fine, and
                    deprived of the temporalities of his see. The other bishops took his side and
                    regarded his punishment as an insult to their order. It was not, however, till
                    after the accession of Richard II. (1377) that William recovered his position.
                    He then received a full pardon, and was reconciled to John of Gaunt.</p>
                <p>During the next ten years he became more and more clearly identified with the
                    constitutional or Lancastrian party. In 1380 and 1381 he was named on
                    commissions for the reform of the king’s household. In 1382 he took part in a
                    conference with the Commons. Next year he successfully opposed a demand from the
                    lords of the Scottish marches for a share in the public funds in order to defray
                    the expense of guarding the border, a duty on the performance of which rested
                    their title to their lands. In 1386 he became one of the commission appointed to
                    examine into the Exchequer and to act as a sort of council of regency. It was
                    before this commission that the five “lords appellant” impeached Richard H.’s
                    favourites, who next year were condemned by the “Merciless Parliament.” A year
                    later (1389) the king suddenly resumed the reins of power. In order, apparently,
                    to conciliate the clergy, Richard at once offered the great seal to the <pb
                    break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n621/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0621-0586"/> bishop of Winchester, who after some hesitation
                    accepted the charge. His second chancellorship lasted for two years, and was
                    marked by efforts on his part to reform the government and place it on a more
                    constitutional basis. After he had held office for a year he and his colleagues
                    in the ministry resigned their appointments, and challenged a public inquiry
                    into their conduct. This being pronounced satisfactory, they resumed their
                    offices. The chancellor drew up rules for the conduct of business in the
                    council; and from this time minutes of the proceedings were regularly kept. In
                    1391 he resigned the great seal, and thenceforward retired from public life.</p>
                <p>It is, however, as the founder of two great colleges that William is principally
                    known to fame. Immediately after his promotion to the bishopric of Winchester he
                    appears to have begun to carry out his educational schemes. Between 1369 and
                    1379 he bought the land enclosed in the north-eastern corner of the city walls
                    at Oxford on which New College now stands (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Oxford,</hi>
                    vol. xviii. p. 97). Meanwhile he was taking steps to establish the sister
                    foundation at Winchester. In 1378 he obtained a licence from the pope to found a
                    college there, which was confirmed by the king four years later. The ground on
                    which Winchester College stands belonged partly to the bishop and partly to
                    other proprietors, from whom he bought it. In 1387 he began to build, and the
                    buildings were occupied by his scholars in 1393, though they do not appear to
                    have been finished till 1395. When his two colleges were established and
                    endowed, he provided them with statutes, which after several revisions took
                    their final form in 1400. Nor does he appear to have neglected his duties as a
                    bishop. He visited and reformed the hospital of St Cross near Winchester; he
                    corrected the abuses which had crept into the priory of St Swithin; and he
                    rebuilt or transformed the nave of Winchester cathedral. He kept a strict watch
                    on the clergy under his charge, endeavouring to ensure their efficiency by
                    frequently moving them from one living to another, and he promoted the material
                    prosperity of his diocese by repairs of bridges and roads. In the relations
                    between England and the papacy William of Wykeham strongly supported the
                    nationalist policy of Edward III. The Statutes of Provisors and Praemunire met
                    with his full approval. So far he was in accord with Wycliffe, but he showed no
                    sympathy with the doctrinal opinions of the reformer. Bishop Courtenay, who
                    headed the attack on Wycliffe, was a lifelong friend of the bishop of
                    Winchester, who published in 1382 the interdict condemning Wycliffe’s heresies,
                    and in 1392 sat on an episcopal commission to try his follower Henry Crumpe.
                    William of Wykeham died at Waltham on 27th September 1404, and was buried in the
                    cathedral of Winchester.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> The episcopal register of William of Wykeham
                    (preserved at Winchester); Walsingham, <hi rend="italic">Historia</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Anglicana</hi>; Lowth, <hi rend="italic">Life of William of
                    Wykeham,</hi> London, 1758; Walcott, <hi rend="italic">William of Wykeham and
                    his Colleges,</hi> 1852; Moberly, <hi rend="italic">Life of William of
                    Wykeham,</hi> Winchester, 1887. (G. W. P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
