<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0636-0599-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WINDMILL (9th edition, volume 24, page 599)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103513">Sailing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1103579">Sails</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1175820">Winds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43n20n86">Sails</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sn0149t">Sailing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pk0743s">Winds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n636/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WINDMILL</label>. The date when windmills were first erected
                    is unknown; but they were certainly used in Europe in the 12th century. Of late
                    they have generally been replaced by steam engines in Great Britain; but they
                    are still extensively employed in Holland in draining the polders and grinding
                    trass. In America they are largely used; Wolff states that in some cities in the
                    United States over 5000 windmills are manufactured annually. In spite of the
                    competition of more powerful and tractable motors, windmills may often be used
                    with success and economy, especially in new countries where fuel is scarce, and
                    for work which can be done intermittently. The Indian Government recently made
                    inquiries with a view to using windmills for irrigation, and a good deal of
                    information will be found in a report by Colonel Brownlow in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Professional Papers on Indian Engineering,</hi> vol. viii. A
                    windmill is not a very powerful motor, and in its employment its power is
                    variable and intermittent. In good situations it will generally work for about
                    eight hours out of the twenty-four on an average. Small windmills are useful on
                    farms for working machines and pumping, in brickfields for pumping, and on ships
                    for clearing out bilge water. They are employed for drainage purposes in Holland
                    and Norfolk, and for mining purposes in some new countries. In America they are
                    used to pump water at railway stations. Sir W. Thomson has proposed to utilize
                    them in charging electric accumulators. As an auxiliary to a steam engine they
                    are sometimes useful; thus at Faversham a 15-horsepower windmill raised in ten
                    months 21,000,000 gallons of water from a depth of 109 feet, saving 100 tons of
                    coal.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">European Windmills.—</hi> In all the older windmills a shaft,
                    called the wind shaft, carried four to six arms or whips on which long
                    rectangular narrow sails were spread. The wind shaft was placed at an
                    inclination of 10° or 15° with the horizontal, to enable the sails to clear the
                    lower part of the mill. The whip carrying the sail was often 30 to 40 feet in
                    length, so that the tips of the sails described a circle 60 to 80 feet in
                    diameter. The sails were rectangular, 5 to 6 feet wide, and occupying
                    five-sixths of the length of the whip. A triangular leading sail· was sometimes
                    added. Sometimes the sails consisted of a sail-cloth spread on a framework; at
                    other times narrow boards were used. The oldest mill was no doubt the <hi
                        rend="italic">post</hi> mill, the whole structure being carried on a post;
                    to bring the sails to face the wind, the structure was turned round by a long
                    lever. The post mill was succeeded by the <hi rend="italic">tower, smock,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">frock</hi> mill, in which the mill itself consisted of a
                    stationary tower, and the wind shaft and sails were carried in a revolving cap
                    rotating on the top of the tower. Meikle introduced in 1750 an auxiliary
                    windmill or fan, placed at right angles to the principal sails, for
                    automatically turning the mill face to the wind. If the wind shifts, the small
                    fan begins to revolve and, acting through gearing, rotates the cap of the mill.
                    Mills are exposed to great danger if the sails are not reefed or furled in high
                    winds, and the reefing serves also to prevent the speed of the mill becoming
                    excessive. In 1807 Sir W. Cubitt introduced automatic reefing arrangements. The
                    sails were made of thin boards held up to the wind by a weight. As the strength
                    of the wind increased, the boards were pressed back and exposed less
                    surface.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">American Windmills.</hi> —American windmills generally have the
                    sails arranged in an annulus or disk. The sails consist of narrow boards or
                    slats arranged radially, each board inclined at a constant angle of weather (see
                    below); and the impulse of the wind on these inclined surfaces drives the mill.
                    An American mill presents a larger surface for a given length of sail, and
                    consequently the construction is lighter. To turn the mill face to the wind, a
                    simple large rudder or fish-tail is used, projecting backwards in a plane at
                    right angles to the plane of rotation of the sails. There are a great variety of
                    mills in America, but those most commonly used are of two types. (1) In those
                    which have side-vane governor wheels the action equivalent to reefing the sails
                    is effected by turning the whole wheel formed by the sails oblique to the wind,
                    so as to diminish the wind’s action. A side vane projects in the plane of
                    rotation of the wheel, and the pressure of the wind on this tends to turn the
                    wheel edgeways to the wind. This turning force is counterbalanced by a weight.
                    Hence for moderate winds the wheel is held up face to the wind; for stronger
                    winds it is turned obliquely. (2) In centrifugal governor mills the slats
                    forming the wheel are connected together in sets of six or eight, each set being
                    fixed on a bar at about the middle of its length. By rotating this bar, the
                    boards or slats are brought end on to the wind, the action being analogous to
                    shutting an umbrella. The boards are held up to the wind by a weight, and are
                    also connected to a centrifugal governor. If the speed of the governor
                    increases, the balls fly out and lift the weight; at the same time the sails are
                    partially furled.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Warner’s Annular Sail WindmiU.—</hi> Messrs Warner of
                    Cripplegate (London) make a windmill somewhat similar to American mills. The
                    shutters or vanes consist of a frame covered with canvas, and these are pivoted
                    between two angle-iron rings so as to form an annular sail. The vanes are
                    connected with spiral springs, which keep them up to the best angle of weather
                    for light winds. If the strength of the wind increases, the vanes give to the
                    wind, forcing back the springs, and thus the area on which the wind acts
                    diminishes. In addition, there are a striking lever and tackle for setting the
                    vanes edgeways to the wind when the mill is stopped or a storm is expected. The
                    wheel is kept face to the wind by a rudder in small mills; in large mills a
                    subsidiary fan and gear are used. Fig. 1 shows a large mill of this kind,
                    erected in a similar manner to a tower mill. The tower is a framework of iron,
                    and carries a revolving cap, on which the wind shaft is fixed. Behind is the
                        subsidiary<pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n637/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0637-0600"/> fan with its gearing, acting on a toothed
                    wheel fixed to the cap.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Relation between the Velocity of the Wind and its Pressure on
                        Surfaces.—</hi> When a flat thin plate is exposed normally to the wind, the
                    pressure on its front surface is increased and that on its back surface somewhat
                    diminished. The resultant total pressure per square foot in the direction of the
                    wind is given approximately by the equation <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi>,= ∙005
                        <hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic superscript"> i</hi> (1)</p>
                <p>if <hi rend="italic">V</hi> is in miles per hour, or <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi>
                    &gt;=∙0023 √≈... (la)</p>
                <p>if <hi rend="italic">V</hi> is in feet per second. Thus, winds at velocities of
                    5, 10, and 20 miles per hour would give a pressure of ⅛ lb, ⅛ lb, and 2 lb
                    respectively on each square foot of a surface normal to the wind, and these may
                    be considered ordinary working velocities for windmills. In storms the velocity
                    of the wind may reach a much greater value. Pressures of 28 or 30 tt&gt; per
                    square foot have been frequently registered by anemometers, and at exceptionally
                    exposed stations pressures of 50, 80, and even 90 tt&gt; per square foot have
                    been recorded. These pressures, which are useless for working the windmill,
                    must, nevertheless, be reckoned with in deciding on its structural strength.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Pressure on Surfaces Oblique to the Wind.—</hi> The variation
                    of pressure with inclination of surface is only known experimentally.</p>
                <p>Let <hi rend="italic">R</hi> be the direction of the wind, making an angle <hi
                        rend="italic">θ</hi> with the <hi rend="subscript"> i</hi> normal to the
                    surface, supposed to be at rest. Then, if <hi rend="italic">p</hi> is the
                    pressure per square foot of surface when the wind is normal to the surface, the
                    resultant normal pressure on the oblique surface is 2cosØ . <hi rend="subscript"
                        > v f</hi>. ,,.</p>
                <p>n=Pj—cos <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> ^ <hi rend="superscript"> per ε</hi> 3
                        <hi rend="superscript"> uare loot</hi> (2).</p>
                <p>But the windmill sail moves in a direction perpendicular to the wind. Hence, if
                        <hi rend="italic">v</hi> is the velocity of the wind and <hi rend="italic"
                        >u</hi> that of the sail, the relative velocity is √u <hi rend="superscript"
                        > 2</hi> + v <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, and the direction of relative
                    motion can be found as follows. Let <hi rend="italic">aa</hi> be the plane of
                    rotation of the sail. The inclination <hi rend="italic">θ</hi> of the sail to
                    the plane of rotation is called the <hi rend="italic">angle of weather,</hi> and
                    is the same as the angle the wind makes with the normal to the sail. Set off <hi
                        rend="italic">ob = v, bc=u,</hi> then <hi rend="italic">oc</hi> is the
                    relative velocity, and this makes an angle ≠=tan^ <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>
                    with the direction of the wind and an angle <hi rend="italic">ϴ + Φ</hi> with
                    the normal to the sail. Hence for the moving sail</p>
                <p>2cos(fl + ≠) . <hi rend="subscript"> λv</hi><hi rend="subscript"> +</hi> &lt; <hi
                        rend="superscript"> s</hi> &gt;∙</p>
                <p>Before replacing <hi rend="italic">p</hi> by its value in (1) another
                    consideration requires attention. The sail generally moves faster than the wind;
                    it is not a thin-edged plane, but presents a not inconsiderable surface at right
                    angles to its direction of motion, and thus creates resistance. Of the whole
                    pressure of the wind a part only is effective, the rest being used to overcome
                    the resistance of the sail. It will be assumed that the effective pressure
                    driving the sails is only, for <hi rend="italic">V</hi> in feet per second, jo =
                    ’ 001 <hi rend="italic">v</hi><hi rend="italic                     superscript">
                        t</hi> lb per square foot, and, therefore, the effective normal pressure on
                    the sails is, for the relative velocity √v <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + w
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, n=∙001(v <hi rend="superscript"> s</hi> +u
                        <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>)j ^-θ~⅛~. The component of this in the
                    direction of motion of the sail is <hi rend="italic">n</hi> sin <hi
                        rend="italic">ϴ.</hi> Consequently the useful work of the sail expressed in
                    foot-pounds per square foot is <hi rend="superscript strikethrough">
                        sin9</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">='°°</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript                     strikethrough"> 1</hi><hi
                        rend="strikethrough">("</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript                     strikethrough"> ,</hi><hi
                        rend="strikethrough">.</hi><hi
                        rend="superscript                     strikethrough"> +,,i</hi><hi
                        rend="strikethrough">)⅛(⅜+⅜)ιt</hi><hi rend="subscript strikethrough">
                        s</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">(&gt;+⅜)</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript">
                        Bydivldta</hi> 8 <hi rend="superscript"> tl,esail</hi> into strips and
                    introducing the known values of <hi rend="italic">u, v,</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">ϴ</hi> the work done is easily found.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Best Angle of Weather.—</hi> The best angle of weather is that
                    which <hi rend="superscript"> lnake3</hi> s^T≠)l⅛07≠) <hi rend="superscript"> a
                        maximura</hi> ∙ <hi rend="superscript"> τhis</hi> K <hi rend="superscript">
                        ιves the ve</hi> σ simple rule 0 = 67⅜°- <hi rend="italic">⅛φ.</hi> Given
                    the velocity of the wind and that of the tips of the sails, the value of <hi
                        rend="italic">φ</hi> is easily found for any point of the sail, and thence
                        <hi rend="italic">θ.</hi> Thus, for</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p><hi rend="italic">U</hi><hi rend="italic">„</hi><hi
                                    rend="italic                             subscript">
                                λ</hi></p><p>-=3O</p><p><hi rend="italic">V</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>2·5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>l·5</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>10</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0∙5,</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>≠ = 72°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>68’</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>64°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>57°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>45*</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>97°</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>0 = 13∣°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16⅛°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>19⅛ <hi rend="superscript"> β</hi></p></cell>
                        <cell><p>24⅛°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>33⅛°</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>47⅜°.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Aebrse-Poww <hi rend="italic">of Windmills.—</hi> For the older kinds of
                    windmills the following rule derived from some experiments by Coulomb may be
                    used. Let <hi rend="italic">n =</hi> no. of sails, <hi rend="italic">A</hi> area
                    of each sail in square feet, <hi rend="italic">v</hi> velocity of wind in feet
                    per second; then the horse-power of the</p>
                <p>τι√4 · ·</p>
                <p>mill is <hi rend="strikethrough">i</hi><hi rend="strikethrough">θθo θθ</hi> θ;
                    this assumes the speed of the tips of the sails to be about 2⅜ to 3 times the
                    wind velocity. For American wheels Wolff gives the horse-power which may be
                    expected for an average of 8 hours per day as follows :—</p>
                <table>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>Diameter of Wheel in Feet.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Velocity of Wind in Miles per Hour.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Horse-Power of Mill.</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>Revolutions of Wheel per Minute.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>8⅜</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0·04</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>70-75</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>10</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0∙12</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>60-65</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>12</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0 21</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>55-60</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>14</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0·28</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>50-55</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0∙41</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>45-50</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>18</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0∙61</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>40-45</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>20</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>0·78</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>35-40</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><p>25</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>16</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>1∙34</p></cell>
                        <cell><p>30-35</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Further information will be found in Rankine, <hi rend="italic">The Steam Engine
                        and other Prime Movers;</hi> weisbach, <hi rend="italic">The Mechanics of
                        Engineering</hi>; and Wolff, <hi rend="italic">The Windmill as a Prime
                        Mover.</hi> (W. C. U.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
