<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0625-0590-06" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WILSON, Horace Hayman (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    590)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205406">Afghanistan</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p55dr26">Sketching</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gg1n">Clouds</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h708258">Surveying</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zd00">Surveys</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139635">Surveys</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1139579">Surveying</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048144">Orientalists</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n625/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WILSON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Horace Hayman</hi></label>
                    (1786-1860), one of the most distinguished Orientalists of England, was born in
                    London on 26th September 1786. He was educated for the medical profession, and
                    on completing his studies went out to India in 1808 as an assistant-surgeon on
                    the Bengal establishment of the East India Company. Instead of entering the
                    regular medical service, however, his knowledge of chemistry and the practical
                    analysis of metals caused him to be attached to the mint at Calcutta, where he
                    was for a time associated with John Leyden, the Scottish poet and Orientalist.
                    It was not long before he himself became deeply interested in the ancient
                    language and literature of India, and attracted the attention of Henry T.
                    Colebrooke, the famous Sanskrit scholar, on whose recommendation he was in 1811
                    appointed secretary to the Asiatic Society of Bengal. In 1813 he published the
                    Sanskrit text —with a graceful, if somewhat free, translation in English rhymed
                    verse—of Kalidasa’s charming lyrical poem, the <hi rend="italic">Meghadüta,</hi>
                    or <hi rend="italic">Cloud-Messenger</hi> (2d ed. 1843, 3d ed. 1867). He then
                    undertook the arduous task of preparing the first <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sanskrit-English Dictionary</hi> from materials compiled by native scholars
                    for the college of Fort William, supplemented by his own researches. The work
                    appeared in 1819, prefaced with an excellent general survey of Sanskrit
                    lexicology. A second, much enlarged, edition, but without the introduction, was
                    published in 1832, and has recently been reprinted at Calcutta. The appearance
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> at once placed Wilson in the first rank
                    of Sanskrit scholars; and, while patiently pursuing his study of the writings
                    and institutions of ancient India, he became one of the most valuable
                    contributors to the <hi rend="italic">Asiatic Researches</hi> and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Calcutta Quarterly.</hi> Among his more important <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n626/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0626-0591"/> contributions to these journals may be
                    mentioned essays on the “Medical and Surgical Sciences, of the Hindus” (1823);
                    the “Hindu History of Kashmir” (1824); “Hindu Fiction” (1825); and his masterly
                    “Account of the Religious Sects of the Hindus, their History, Doctrines, and
                    Practices” (1828-32). In 1827 he published <hi rend="italic">Select Specimens of
                        the Theatre of the Hindus,</hi> in 3 vols., in which, besides a very full
                    and highly appreciative survey of Indian dramaturgy, which still remains the
                    standard authority on the subject, he offered elegant translations of six
                    complete plays and short accounts of twenty-three others. This work was
                    reprinted in London in 1835, in 2 vols., and again in Wilson’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Collected Works</hi> (vols. xi. and xii.). Of considerable importance,
                    alike to Sanskrit and vernacular students, and to Eastern antiquarians
                    generally, was his next publication, the <hi rend="italic">Mackenzie
                        Collection</hi> (2 vols., 1828; 2d ed. in one vol., 1882), being a
                    descriptive catalogue of the extensive collection of Oriental, especially South
                    Indian, MSS. and antiquities made by Col. Colin Mackenzie, and purchased from
                    his widow by the Indian Government, now deposited partly in the India Office,
                    London, and partly at Madras. Neither his extensive literary researches,
                    however, nor the official duties of an assay master and mint secretary, at any
                    time prevented Wilson from taking a prominent part in all social amusements of
                    the Anglo-Indian community of Calcutta, especially in musical and theatrical
                    entertainments. His interest in political and economic affairs in India is shown
                    by his <hi rend="italic">Historical Sketch of the First Burmese War, with
                        Documents, Political and Geographical</hi> (1827, reprinted in London), and
                    his <hi rend="italic">Review of the External Commerce of Bengal from 1813 to
                        1828</hi> (1830), as well as by his <hi rend="italic">History of British
                        India from 1805 to 1835,</hi> in continuation of Mill’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >History,</hi> 3 vols. (1844-48), and largely based on his personal
                    impressions and recollections. He also acted for many years as secretary to the
                    committee of public instruction. As such, he not only organized and
                    superintended the studies of the Hindu College from the time of its
                    establishment, but took a leading part in the promotion of public education
                    among the natives, and the introduction of the English language and European
                    science, although, as one of the staunchest opponents, on grounds of expediency
                    and feasibleness, of the proposal that English should be made the sole medium of
                    instruction in native schools, he became for a time the object of bitter
                    attacks. Long, however, before this controversy came to an end he had been
                    called away to a different sphere of scholarly activity. In 1832 the university
                    of Oxford, in recognition of his services to Oriental scholarship, selected Dr
                    Wilson to be the first occupant of the newly founded Boden chair of Sanskrit.
                    Shortly after his return to England he was also appointed librarian to the East
                    India Company. He now found himself in a position singularly favourable to
                    learned research and literary pursuits; and the long record of his subsequent
                    work shows that he made the best of his opportunities. He immediately joined the
                    Royal Asiatic Society, and, succeeding Colebrooke as director (in 1837), he was
                    the very soul of the society up to the time of his death, scarcely a number of
                    its journal appearing without some interesting contribution from his pen. His
                    death took place at London on 8th May 1860.</p>
                <p>Of these contributions we need only mention here his <hi rend="superscript">
                        ,,</hi> Historical Sketch of the Kingdom of Pãndya” (1836), based on
                    documents contained in the Mackenzie collection; the continuation of his
                    “Analysis of the Puränas” (1836), begun in the <hi rend="italic">Bengal
                        Society's Journal</hi> (1832); “Civil and Religious Institutions of the
                    Sikhs” and “Religious Festivals of the Hindus” (1848); “Analysis and Revised
                    Translation of the Rock Inscriptions of Kapur di Giri” (1850); and his popular
                    lecture “On the Present State of the Cultivation of Oriental Literature” (1852).
                    Hardly less numerous, and certainly not less valuable, are his separate
                    publications during this period, by which important light was thrown on many
                    departments of Eastern inquiry. The most noteworthy of these works are the text
                    of, and commentary on, the Sãnkhyakãrikã (1837), being a very popular summary of
                    the Sãnkhya philosophy, with a translation (of the text by Colebrooke, and the
                    commentary by Wilson); translation of the <hi rend="italic">Vishnu Parana</hi>
                    (1840, 2d annotated ed. by F. E. Hall; <hi rend="italic">Works,</hi> vols. vi.
                    -x. ); <hi rend="italic">Ariana Antiqua,</hi><hi rend="italic">Antiquities and
                        Coins of Afghanistan</hi> (1841); edition of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Basakumãraeharita</hi> (1846); <hi rend="italic">Glossary of Indian
                        Revenue, Judicial, &lt;kc., Terms</hi> (1855); <hi rend="italic">Translation
                        of the First Four Ashtakas</hi> (rather more than one-half) <hi
                        rend="italic">of the Sacred Hymns of the Rigveda,</hi> 3 vols., 1850-57; <hi
                        rend="italic">Grammar of the Sanskrit Language,</hi> in several editions;
                    and two lectures on the <hi rend="italic">Religious Practices and Opinions of
                        the Hindus,</hi> delivered at Oxford in 1840. In the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Collected Works</hi> (12 vols.) the more valuable of his papers and
                    lectures form three volumes of essays on <hi rend="italic">Sanskrit
                        Literature</hi> and two volumes of essays on <hi rend="italic">The Religion
                        of the Hindus,</hi> edited by Dr R. Rost. While in point of accurate
                    scholarship Wilson was perhaps scarcely the equal of Colebrooke, any deficiency
                    in this respect is far more than counterbalanced by the many-sidedness of his
                    genius, by literary powers of a very high order, by his admirable artistic
                    taste, and by broad human sympathies, which enabled him fully to appreciate and
                    enjoy the merits and beauties of the ancient Indian literature. A considerable
                    number of Sanskrit MSS. (540 vols.) collected by Wilson in India are now in the
                    Bodleian.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
