<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0616-0581-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WILLIAM I</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 581</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93d6n">Bar</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:908898">Emperors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:945704">Governors</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1080735">Prussians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n616/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WILLIAM I</label>. (1797-1888), king of Prussia and German
                    emperor, was the second son of Frederick William III. of Prussia and Louisa, a
                    princess of Mecklenburg-Strelitz. He was born at Berlin on 22d March 1797, and
                    received the names of Wilhelm Friedrich Ludwig. He was a delicate child and had
                    to be carefully nurtured. His constitution, however, was sound, and he became
                    one of the most vigorous men in Germany. After the battle of Jena he spent three
                    years at Königsberg and Memel. Meanwhile he had given evidence of sterling
                    honesty, a strict love of order, and an almost passionate interest in everything
                    relating to war. On 1st January 1807 he received an officer’s patent, and on
                    30th October 1813 was appointed a captain. William accompanied his father in the
                    campaign of 1814, and early in the following year received the iron cross for
                    personal bravery shown at Bar-sur-Aube. He took part in the entry into Paris on
                    31st March 1814, and afterwards visited London. He joined the Prussian army in
                    the final campaign of the Napoleonic wars, and again entered Paris. The prince
                    was made a colonel and a member of the permanent military commission immediately
                    after his twentieth birthday, and at the age of twenty-one became a
                    major-general. In 1820 he received the command of a division; and during the
                    following nine years he not only made himself master of the military system of
                    his own country but studied closely those of the other European states. In 1825
                    he was promoted to the rank of lieutenant-general, and obtained the command of
                    the corps of guards. On 11th June 1829 he married Augusta of Saxe-Weimar.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n617/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0617-0582"/>
                <p>On the death of his father in 1840—the new king, Frederick William IV., being
                    childless—Prince William, as heir presumptive to the throne, received the title
                    of prince of Prussia. He was also made lieutenant-governor of Pomerania and
                    appointed a general of infantry. In politics he was decidedly Conservative; but
                    at the outbreak of the revolutionary movement of 1848 he saw that some
                    concessions to the popular demand for liberal forms of government were
                    necessary. He urged, however, that order should be restored before the
                    establishment of a constitutional system. At this time he was the best-hated man
                    in Germany, the mass of the Prussian people believing him to be a vehement
                    supporter of an absolutist and reactionary policy. He was even held responsible
                    for the blood shed in Berlin on 18th March, although he had been relieved nine
                    days before of his command of the guards. So bitter was the feeling against him
                    that the king entreated him to leave the country for some time, and accordingly
                    he went to London, where he formed intimate personal relations with Prince
                    Albert, Sir Robert Peel, Lord John Russell, Lord Palmerston, and other English
                    statesmen. On 8th June he was back at Berlin, and on the same day he took his
                    seat as member for Wirsitz in the Prussian national assembly, and delivered a
                    speech in which he expressed belief in constitutional principles. In 1849, when
                    the revolutionary party in the grand-duchy of Baden became dangerous, he
                    accepted the command of “the army of operation in Baden and the Palatinate,” and
                    his plans were so judiciously formed and so skilfully executed that in the
                    course of a few days the rebellion was crushed. At the beginning of the campaign
                    an unsuccessful attempt was made on his life. In October 1849 he was appointed
                    military governor of the Rhineland and Westphalia, and took up his residence at
                    Coblentz. In 1854 the prince was raised to the rank of a field-marshal and made
                    governor of the confederate fortress of Mainz. When the king was attacked with a
                    disease of the brain, Prince William assumed the regency (7th October 1858).</p>
                <p>On 2d January 1861 Frederick William IV. died, and his brother succeeded him as
                    William I. For the internal conflict between the king and the house of
                    representatives on the question of military reorganization, which filled up the
                    first years of his reign, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Germany</hi> (vol. x. p. 510)
                    and <hi rend="smallcaps">Prussia</hi> (vol. xx. p. 12). The events and results
                    of the war with Denmark, and of that with Austria which arose out of the
                    Schleswig-Holstein question, belong to the history of Austria and of Prussia,
                    and have been already described under those articles. The brilliant achievements
                    of the army in this last contest finally convinced the king’s subjects that his
                    aims had been wise. On his return to Berlin he was received with unbounded
                    enthusiasm, and from this time he was looked up to as a father rather than as a
                    sovereign. On the outbreak of the war with France in 1870 all Germans rallied
                    round the king of Prussia, and, when on 31st July he quitted Berlin to join his
                    army, he knew that he had the support of a united nation. He crossed the French
                    frontier on the 11th of August, and personally commanded at the battles of
                    Gravelotte and Sedan. It was during the siege of Paris, at his headquarters in
                    Versailles, that he was proclaimed German emperor on 18th January 1871. On 3d
                    March 1871 he signed the preliminaries of peace which had been accepted by the
                    French assembly; and on 21st March he opened the first imperial parliament of
                    Germany. On 16th June he triumphantly entered Berlin at the head of his
                    troops.</p>
                <p>After that period the emperor left the destinies of Germany almost entirely in
                    the hands of Bismarck, who held the office of imperial chancellor (see <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Prussia).</hi> In his personal history the most notable events
                    were two attempts upon his life in 1878,—one by a working lad called Hödel,
                    another by an educated man, Karl Nobiling. On the first occasion the emperor
                    escaped without injury, but on the second he was seriously wounded. These
                    attacks grew out of the socialist agitation; and a new reichstag, elected for
                    the purpose, passed a severe anti-socialist law, which was afterwards from time
                    to time renewed. The socialists, however, far from being crushed, again and
                    again gave proof of their power by returning a considerable number of deputies
                    to parliament. In the hope of alienating from them the mass of the working
                    class, Bismarck introduced, with the cordial approval of the emperor, a series
                    of measures for the benefit of the poorer members of the community. Until within
                    a few days of his death the emperor’s health was remarkably robust; he died at
                    Berlin on 9th March 1888.</p>
                <p>The reign of William I. marked an era of vast importance in the history of
                    Germany. In his time Prussia became the first power in Germany and Germany the
                    first power in Europe. These momentous changes were due in a less degree to him
                    than to Bismarck and Moltke; but to him belongs the credit of having recognized
                    the genius of these men, and of having trusted them absolutely. Personally
                    William was a man of a singularly noble and attractive character. His supreme
                    wish was to discharge loyally the duties which had been imposed upon him, and he
                    never shrank from any personal sacrifice that seemed to be demanded in the
                    interests of his people. The best traditions of the Hohenzollerns were
                    maintained, not only by the splendour of the achievements with which his name
                    will always be intimately associated, but by the simplicity, manliness, and
                    uprightness of his daily life.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
