<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0634-0597-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WINCKELMANN, Johann Joachim</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 597</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4t43j79n">Librarians</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bw6x">Spirits</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term n="13" ref="fasttopic:815177">Art</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:997301">Librarians</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:976135">Interest</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="5" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n634/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WINCKELMANN, <hi rend="smallcaps">Johann Joachim</hi></label>
                    (1717-1768), historian of ancient art and the founder of scientific archaeology,
                    was born at Stendal in the Altmark (Prussia) on 9th December 1717. His father
                    was a poor shoemaker, and in his early years Winckelmann had to contend with
                    great difficulties. With a passion for knowledge, however, he combined a
                    resolute will; and by acting for some time as amanuensis to an old and blind
                    rector he contrived to pass through the necessary courses of instruction at
                    school. In 1737 he attended a gymnasium at Berlin and the school at Salzwedel,
                    and in the following year he went as a student of theology to the university of
                    Halle. He took little real interest in theology, and such interest as he had
                    -was quenched partly by the influence of the philosophy of Wolff, partly by the
                    unfavourable impression made upon him by the Pietists. Through his connexion
                    with the chancellor Von Ludewig he was led to enter upon the study of German
                    history; he devoted himself also with great enthusiasm to the study of Greek
                    literature. He thought of becoming a physician, and began to attend medical
                    classes at Jena; but the accomplishment of this scheme was beyond his means, and
                    he was obliged to accept a tutorship near Magdeburg. In 1743 he was made
                    associate-rector of a school at Seehausen in the Altmark, and this appointment
                    he held for five years. He then went to Dresden, where he acted as librarian and
                    general assistant to Count Henry Von Bünau, for whose history of the Holy Roman
                    empire he collected materials. The treasures in the Dresden gallery awakened in
                    his mind an intense interest in art, which was deepened by association with
                    various artists, and especially with Oeser, who afterwards exercised so powerful
                    an influence over Goethe when Goethe was a young student at Leipsic.
                    Winckelmann’s study of ancient literature had inspired him with a strong desire
                    to visit Rome, and now he sought, through the papal nuncio Archinto, to obtain
                    the appointment of librarian to Cardinal Passionei. Nothing could be done for
                    him, however, unless he joined the Roman Catholic Church; this condition, after
                    long hesitation; he ultimately decided to comply with.</p>
                <p>In 1755 Winckelmann gave the first indication of his genius by the publication of
                    his <hi rend="italic">Gedanken über</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Nachahmung der griechischen Werke in Malerei und
                    Bildhauerkunst.</hi> This was followed by a pretended attack on the work, and a
                    defence of its principles, nominally by an impartial critic. In the <hi
                    rend="italic">Gedanken</hi> Winckelmann suggested most of the doctrines he
                    afterwards developed; and the book was warmly admired not only for the new ideas
                    it contained but for the power and charm of its style. One good result of the
                    impression it produced was that Augustus III., elector óf Saxony and king of
                    Poland, was induced to grant him a pension of 200 thalers, that he might have an
                    opportunity of prosecuting his studies in Rome. He arrived in Rome in November
                    1755, and, with the exception of some brief intervals, remained there during the
                    rest of his life. He became librarian to Cardinal Archinto, and also received
                    much kindness from Cardinal Passionei; and after their death he was received as
                    librarian and as a friend into the house of Cardinal Albani, who was forming his
                    magnificent collection in his villa at Porta Salara. In 1763, while retaining
                    this position, Winckelmann was made prefect of antiquities.</p>
                <p>From the time of his arrival in Rome he devoted himself earnestly, at first with
                    the aid of his friend Raphael Mengs, to the study of Roman antiquities, and he
                    gradually acquired what was then an unrivalled knowledge of ancient art. In 1760
                    appeared his <hi rend="italic">Description des</hi><hi rend="italic">Pierres
                    Gravées</hi><hi rend="italic">du Feu Baron de Stosch,</hi> embodying the results
                    of much work at Florence, where he had spent nine months in cataloguing the
                    engraved gems collected by his friend Baron von Stosch. He published in 1762 <hi
                    rend="italic">Anmerkungen über</hi><hi rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Baukunst der Alten,</hi> including an account of the temples at Paestum. In
                    1758 and 1762 Winckelmann visited Naples for the purpose of studying the
                    treasures excavated at Pompeii and Herculaneum; and from his <hi rend="italic"
                    >Sendschreiben</hi><hi rend="italic">von den herculanischen</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Entdeckungen</hi> (1762) and his <hi rend="italic">Nachricht von
                    den neuesten</hi><hi rend="italic">herculanischen</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Entdeckungen</hi> (1764) scholars obtained their first authentic information
                    about those groups of antiquities. Winckelmann again visited Naples in 1765 and
                    1767, and wrote for the use of the electoral prince and princess of Saxony his
                    <hi rend="italic">Briefe</hi><hi rend="italic">an Biaηconi,</hi> which were
                    published, eleven years after his death, in the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Aηtologia</hi><hi rend="italic">Romana.</hi> For several years his energies
                    were devoted chiefly to the preparation of his masterpiece, the <hi
                    rend="italic">Geschichte der</hi><hi rend="italic">Kunst des Alterthums,</hi>
                    which was issued in 1764. It at once commanded attention and was soon recognized
                    as a book that would take a permanent place in the literature not only of
                    Germany but of Europe. In this great work Winckelmann sets forth both the
                    history of Greek art and the principles on which it seemed to him to be based.
                    He also presents a glowing picture of the conditions, political, social, and
                    intellectual, which tended to foster creative activity in ancient Greece. The
                    fundamental idea of his theory is that the end of art is beauty, and that this
                    end can be attained only when individual and characteristic features are
                    strictly subordinated to the artist’s general scheme. According to Winckelmann,
                    the true artist, selecting from nature the phenomena fitted for his purpose, and
                    combining them through the imagination, creates an ideal type marked in action
                    by “noble simplicity and calm greatness,”—an ideal type in which normal
                    proportions are maintained, particular parts, such as muscles and veins, not
                    being permitted to break the harmony of the general outlines. In the historical
                    part he used not only the works of art he himself had studied but the scattered
                    notices on the subject to be found in ancient writers; and his wide knowledge
                    and active imagination enabled him to offer many fruitful suggestions as to
                    periods about which he had little direct information. The materials for the
                    study of Greek art which have been recovered since Winckelmann’s time have
                    compelled archaeologjsts to reject some of his conclusions, to modify others,
                    and to present the subject as a whole in a somewhat different light; but the
                    writer was penetrated by so fine an enthusiasm, his style is at once so strong,
                    so graceful, and so animated, and his descriptions of particular works of art
                    are so vivid and true, that his book can never wholly lose its freshness. It
                    marked an epoch by indicating the spirit in which the study of Greek art should
                    be approached, and the methods by which investigators might hope to attain to
                    solid results. To Winckelmann’s contemporaries the work came as a revelation,
                    and it exercised a profound influence on the <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n635/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0635-0598"/> best minds of the age. Goethe studied it eagerly,
                    and it was read with intense interest by Lessing, who had found in a statement
                    in the ear!iest of Winckelmann’s works the starting-point for his <hi
                    rend="italic">Laocoon.</hi></p>
                <p>Winckelmann contributed various admirable essays to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Bibliothek der Schonen Wissenschaften</hi>; and in 1766 he published his <hi
                    rend="italic">Versuch einer Allegorie,</hi> which, although containing the
                    results of much thought and reading, is not conceived in a thoroughly critical
                    spirit. Of far greater importance was the splendid work entited <hi
                    rend="italic">Monumenti</hi><hi rend="italic">Antichi</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Inediti</hi> (1767-68), prefaced by a <hi rend="italic">Trattato
                    Prelimi-ηare,</hi> presenting a general sketch of the history of art. The plates
                    in this work are representations of objects which had either been falsely
                    explained or not explained at all. Winckelmann’s explanations were of the
                    highest service to archaeology, by showing that in the case of many works of art
                    which had been supposed to be connected with Roman history the ultimate sources
                    of inspiration were to be found in Homer.</p>
                <p>In 1768 Winckelmann left Rome with the Italian sculptor Cavaceppi, intending to
                    visit Germany. But he went no farther than to Vienna, where he was received with
                    honour by Maria Theresa. At Trieste on his way back to Italy he made the
                    acquaintance of a man called Arcangeli, to whom he showed some gold coins that
                    had been given to him by the empress; Arcangeli’s cupidity was excited, and
                    during the night he entered Winckelmann’s room, and, after having tried to
                    throttle him, stabbed him five times. Winckelmann died of his wounds on 8th June
                    1768. His murderer was caught and executed.</p>
                <p>Winckelmann ranks among the foremost writers of the 18th century, and it is
                    hardly possible to overrate the services rendered by him to archaeology and the
                    study of ancient art. With wide learning and an extraordinary power of accurate
                    observation he combined imagination and feeling, and through him the modern
                    world obtained for the first time something like a true conception not only of
                    particular works of Greek art but of the general intellectual movement from
                    which they sprang. If many of his ideas have now been abandoned, that is to a
                    large extent due to the fact that scholars and thinkers were put upon the right
                    track by his researches. His character as a man corresponded to his greatness as
                    a writer. No difficulty was formidable enough to deter him from working out his
                    vast schemes; and in relation to his friends and in general social intercourse
                    he was distinguished by a noble generosity of spirit and thorough honesty of
                    purpose.</p>
                <p>An edition of his works was begun by Fernow in 1808 and completed by Meyer and
                    Schulze (1808-20). There is an admirable study of his character and work in
                    Goethe’s <hi rend="italic">Winckelmann</hi><hi rend="italic">und sein
                    Jahrhundert</hi> (1805), to which contributions were made by Meyer and Wolf. The
                    best biography of Winckelmann is the one by Justi, 2 vols., Leipsic, 1866-72.
                    (J. SI.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
