<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0575-0540-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WHIRLPOOL (9th edition, volume 24, page 540)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq8b">Tides</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43b5wj37">Whirlpools</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42r3p025">Currents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039481">Norwegians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1109941">Scylla</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150792">Tides</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174567">Whirlpools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926898">Fjords</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n575/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WHIRLPOOL</label>, a hollow in running water, caused or
                    accompanied by a whirling motion which attracts and engulfs floating objects.
                    The popular conception of a whirlpool was probably based on the ancient accounts
                    of that of Charybdis, strengthened by exaggerated rumours of the Mälström in the
                    Lofoten Islands, and, in Great Britain at least, largely consolidated by the
                    legends of Corrievreckan. The various reports of travellers and descriptions of
                    poetical “philosophers” as to the appearance of the Mälström were faithfully
                    collated and thrown into stereoscopic relief by Edgar Allan Poe in his
                    celebrated story. He describes how, with the rise of the tide, “the current
                    acquired a monstrous velocity. . . . The vast bed of the waters, seamed and
                    scarred into a thousand conflicting channels, burst suddenly into frenzied
                    convulsions—heaving, boiling, hissing—gyrating in gigantic and innumerable
                    vortices, and all whirling and plunging on to the eastward with a rapidity water
                    never elsewhere assumes, except in precipitous descents. In a few minutes more
                    there came over the scene another radical alteration. . . . The gyratory motions
                    of the subsided vortices seemed to form the germ of another more vast.
                    Suddenly—very suddenly—this assumed a distinct and definite existence, in a
                    circle of over <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n576/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0576-0541"/> a mile in diameter. The edge of the whirl was
                    represented by a broad belt of gleaming spray; but no particle of this slipped
                    into the mouth of the terrific funnel, whose interior, as far as the eye could
                    fathom it, was a smooth, shining, and jet-black wall of water, inclined to the
                    horizon at an angle of some 45°, speeding dizzily round and round with a swaying
                    and sweltering motion, and sending forth to the winds an appalling voice, half
                    shriek, half roar, such as not even the mighty cataract of Niagara ever lifts up
                    in its agony to heaven.” Nothing could escape the violence of such a vortex.
                    Whales caught in it were swallowed down, and the largest ship was engulfed as
                    easily as the smallest boat. After an hour or two the funnel slowly filled, and
                    the fragments of the vessels which it had sucked down were thrown up, dashed to
                    pieces against rocks at an unknown depth. Bearing such a reputation, whirlpools
                    were naturally avoided by the mariner; and their τeal nature long remained
                    unknown.</p>
                <p>It was supposed that every whirlpool formed round a central rock; under it opened
                    a great cavern or gulf, down which the waters rushed, and so the whirling was
                    produced as in a basin emptying through a central hole. This notion was
                    developed by Athanasius Kircher (1602-80). In his theory whirlpools marked the
                    entrances to subterranean channels connecting different seas, and the phenomena
                    of tides were produced by the alternate flow of water in opposite directions.
                    Kircher gives a curious diagram of the Mälström or “umbilicus maris,”
                    illustrating his supposition that the water, after pouring into the vast funnel,
                    flowed along a channel under the Scandinavian peninsula and rose in the Gulf of
                    Bothnia. When the level of this gulf had been raised to a sufficient height, he
                    thought that the current was reversed, and, aided by a stream pouring through a
                    subterranean tunnel from the White Sea, raised the tide on the coast of Norway.
                    Carrying his theory a degree farther to account for the Gulf Stream and the
                    Antarctic drift, Kircher, with great ingenuity, placed a grand vortex at the
                    North pole, down which all the water of the ocean tumbled, and, passing through
                    the earth’s axis, emerged at the South pole, thus keeping up “a circulation like
                    that of the blood in the human body.”</p>
                <p>The facts which gave rise to the wild theories of mediaeval geographers and the
                    extravagant descriptions of early voyagers are impressive enough in themselves
                    to rank amongst the grandest phenomena of nature. No one who has seen the
                    tide-streams racing through the Pentland Firth at 12 miles an hour, now swirling
                    along with a smooth dimpled surface, like molten glass, now meeting the
                    countercurrent and leaping high into the air in columns of water and spray, or
                    who has heard the roar of Corrievreckan as the Atlantic tide rushes between Scar
                    ba and Jura against an easterly gale, will be disposed to deny the terrible
                    danger to small open vessels or to wonder that horror strengthened imagination
                    to the confusion and exaggeration of fact.</p>
                <p>The formation of whirlpools is a natural result of water flowing rapidly in an
                    irregular channel (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Hydromechanics,</hi> vol. xii. pp.
                    468, 510); it takes place in all rivers and in every tide-race of the sea, the
                    depth, diameter, and velocity depending on accidental causes. The form of the
                    surface of an ordinary whirlpool is given by Prof. J. Thomson<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Brit.
                                Assoc. Rep.,</hi> 1852, Sections, p. 130.</p></note> as that
                    generated by the revolution of a curve whose formula is <hi rend="italic">y</hi>
                    = <hi rend="italic">c</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 3</hi> ∕ <hi rend="italic"
                        >x</hi><hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi>, where <hi rend="italic">y</hi> is the
                    depth of any point on the curve below the general level remote from the whirl,
                        <hi rend="italic">X</hi> the distance of the point from the axis of
                    revolution, and <hi rend="italic">c</hi> a constant. Every point on the surface
                    moves with the velocity a heavy body would attain in falling from the general
                    level of the water surface to that point, and any point in the interior of the
                    revolving mass has a velocity equal to that of the point on the surface
                    immediately above itself. Prof. Thomson applied his researches on the motion of
                    whirlpools to the construction of a particularly effective form of turbine.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">Brik
                                Assoc. Rcp.,</hi> 1852, Report, p. 317.</p></note></p>
                <p>All the famous whirlpools are situated in channels essentially similar in
                    configuration and in tidal phenomena: their vortices are produced at certain
                    phases of the tide or with certain directions of the wind; and they are all
                    dangerous to navigation, but the danger is due to the cause which produces the
                    whirlpools—the tidal race—not to the “roaring wells” themselves. Whirlpools in a
                    tidal stream are not stationary, but travel along with the current, filling up
                    and again forming in irregular succession. Small boats have repeatedly been
                    drawn into these vortices in the northern fjords and capsized; and trading
                    steamers in passing through a tideway are violently deflected from their course.
                    It is on record that a seventy-four gun ship has been whirled right round in the
                    vortices of the Straits of Messina. The fishermen of the Norwegian fjords and of
                    the northern island groups,—Lofoten, Faroe, Shetland, and Orkney,—still believe
                    that, if they can throw a heavy or bulky object into a whirlpool, it will close
                    up without harming their boats. Lithgow in his <hi rend="italic">Travels,</hi>
                    speaking of the Pentland Firth, says, “I denote this credibly, in a part of the
                    north-west end of this gulf there is a certain place of sea where these
                    distracted tides make their rencountering rendezvous, that whirleth ever about,
                    cutting in the middle circle a sloping hole, with which, if either ship or boat
                    shall happen to encroach, they must quickly either throw over something into it,
                    as a barrel, a piece of timber, and such like, or that fatal euripus shall then
                    suddenly become their swallowing sepulchre.” This custom, it has been supposed,
                    is sacrificial in its origin. Its continued practice, however, suggests what is
                    probably the case, that the bulky object splashing into the whirl breaks the
                    continuity of the surface and causes a collapse or filling-up. In windy weather,
                    when there is a broken sea, vortices are not formed. The tidal stream passing
                    through the irregular channels between islands gives rise to a complicated
                    series of eddies and counter-currents, which, according to the British
                    Admiralty’s <hi rend="italic">Sailing Directions,</hi> make navigation
                    dangerous, except when guided by local knowledge and aided by fair wind and a
                    favourable tide. The general effect appears to be that, as the tide rises, the
                    strength of the stream increases; and the counter-currents set up along the
                    shore, as well as the overfalls produced by inequalities of the bottom,
                    thoroughly mix the water to a depth of from 50 to 100 fathoms. This has been
                    proved by observations of temperature amongst the tidal currents off the Mull of
                    Cantyre, where at all times of the year there is no difference between the
                    surface and bottom temperature. At high water a state of rest ensues; and ebb
                    tide usually reverses the order of phenomena, the main stream, counter-currents,
                    and eddies running in the opposite direction, but with nearly equal strength,
                    until low tide brings another pause.</p>
                <p>Charybdis, a whirlpool famous in classical literature, is situated in the Straits
                    of Messina. The rise of tide at Messina does not exceed one foot, but the
                    current may attain the velocity of nearly 6 miles an hour. Where the north-going
                    flood tide meets the southrunning counter-current, and where the southerly ebb
                    meets its induced northerly stream, great eddies or <hi rend="italic"
                        >garofóla</hi> are formed, one of which is Charybdis. These depend very much
                    on the wind for the intensity of their phenomena.</p>
                <p>In ancient maps of the united Aral-Caspian Sea two whirlpools are represented.
                    Near the position laid down there are in the river Amu-Daria two whirlpools at
                    the junction of several channels. These have been recently examined<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Wood, in <hi
                                rend="italic">Joum. Roy. Geogr. Soc.</hi> (1875), xlv. p.
                        372.</p><p/></note> and found to arise from the river flowing over two
                    conical hollows in its bed, respectively 120 and 60 feet deep; these do not
                    appear to have been formed by running water, but closely resemble craters of mud
                    volcanoes.</p>
                <p>The most violent tidal current is said to be that of Salten Fjord to the south of
                    Bodö on the north-west coast of Norway, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n577/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0577-0542"/> known by the name of the Saltenström, and
                    dreaded on account of its turbulence and its numerous vortices. Opposite Salten
                    Fjord, on the western side of Vest Fjord, the wild jagged range of the Lofoten
                    Islands runs like a row of shark’s teeth from south to north. Between two of the
                    southernmost of the group, Moskenaes and Mosken, runs the Moskenström, a tidal
                    current which after low water commences to flow towards the north-east, then
                    gradually changes its direction to east, to south, and at high water to
                    southwest; after half an hour’s cessation the ebb begins to flow towards the
                    south-west, at half ebb due west, and then gradually turns through north to
                    north-east at low water. The current thus rotates round Mosken once in 12 hours.
                    It runs with a velocity of 7 miles an hour when a strong wind blows in the same
                    direction, and, as the sea-bed is very irregular and rises abruptly from 200
                    fathoms seaward of Mosken to 20 fathoms in the channel and Vest Fjord, the flow
                    is very turbulent, with occasional whirlpools and opposing currents set up along
                    the shore, giving it a character very similar to that of the Strait of Messina.
                    This is the place of the Malstrom.</p>
                <p>In the Faroe Islands several dangerous tide-races exist in which are dreaded
                    whirlpools, the two worst being’ the Quaerne off Sand Island and one round the
                    rock of Sumboe-musk off Süder Island.</p>
                <p>The Shetland and Orkney Islands are traversed by a system of formidable tideways
                    called <hi rend="italic">roosts,</hi> dangerous to fishing boats and very
                    frequently forming whirlpools. It is sufficient to refer to the swiths or wells
                    of Swona in Orkney, to the whirlpool of the Swelchie off Stroma, and the Merry
                    Men of Mey, also in the Pentland Firth. The channel of Jura Sound in the
                    Hebrides, which contains Corrievreckan whirlpool, resembles that of Mosken and
                    Messina in being narrow and of very irregular configuration. The sea to the west
                    is about 70 fathoms deep; a trough over 50 fathoms in depth and quarter of a
                    mile wide runs through towards the east, deepening about the centre to 105 and
                    120 fathoms in consecutive holes. The channel is less than a mile in width, and
                    the water is shallow (15 to 20 fathoms) from the shore out to the central
                    trough, where the deepening is abrupt. To this fact, and not to the supposed
                    existence of “a submerged rock of pyramidal form shooting up from a depth of 100
                    fathoms,” are due, in all probability, the tidal stream, running sometimes at 9
                    miles an hour, and the great vortices which are occasionally formed, as well as
                    the dangerous counter-currents and overfalls.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Folklore.—</hi> Many marvellous stories are told of the
                    dwellers in whirlpools. Fish are supposed to be more abundant there than
                    anywhere else. Whales have from earliest times been associated, if not
                    confounded, with these gulfs; and all manner of sea-beings, —krakens, trows
                    (trolls), and mermaids,—claim sanctuary beneath the turmoil. Ramus, two
                    centuries ago, tried by dint of misapplied philological ingenuity to identify
                    Charybdis with the Malstrom, alleging that the fact of Ulysses’s voyage to
                    northern seas was plainly recorded in the names of islands and headlands. For
                    the myth of Charybdis, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Scylla and Charybdis.</hi>
                    Whirlpools have been brought forward to explain the origin of the tides; but a
                    well-known Norse folk-tale in one of its forms gives to a particular vortex—the
                    Swelchie—an additional and more important office, that of maintaining the
                    salinity of the ocean. “Malstrom” (millstream) probably refers to the rapid
                    current resembling a mill-race. The Quaerne in the Faroe Islands suggests the
                    same idea from its name. A mist of poetical romance has always played over the
                    roaring surges of Corrievreckan, and this finds expression in many poems and
                    tales. Horrible sea-monsters made the gulf their home in the earliest times; but
                    they gave place to the seductive mermaid who captivated a Macphail of Cólonsay,
                    and entertained him in her coral caves and fairy palaces beneath the sea for
                    many years. Scott in his <hi rend="italic">Border Minstrelsy</hi> gives another
                    version of this story, in which Macphail outwits the mermaid and remains
                    faithful to the maid of Colonsay. The name of the whirlpool is sometimes derived
                    from <hi rend="italic">coire</hi><hi rend="italic">bhreaccn,</hi> “the speckled
                    cauldron,” referring to the foam that usually variegates its surface; but the
                    legend makes it the corry or gulf of Vrekan, a prince of Norway, who, having
                    come there to woo a Hebridean chieftain’s daughter, was swept into the
                    whirlpool, and drawn down from sight for ever. George Macdonald has embodied
                    this legend in a highly dramatic poem.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Literature.—</hi> References to whirlpools occur incidentally
                    in many places. See A. Kircher’s <hi rend="italic">Mundus Subterraneus,</hi>
                    vol. i., Amsterdam, 1664; Pontoppidan’s <hi rend="italic">Natural History of
                        Norway,</hi> 1755 (this work cites the opinions of earlier writers, Ramus,
                    Arraboe, &amp;c.). For a good description of Charybdis, see <hi rend="italic"
                        >Nicholson's Journal,</hi> vol. i. (1798) p. 12; of Corrievreckan, <hi
                        rend="italic">Athenaeum,</hi> 3d September 1864. Full and trustworthy
                    details of the actual state and dangers of special whirlpools will be found in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Sailing Directions</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Coast Pilots
                        oi</hi> the British Admiralty for the various seas. (H. R. Μ.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
