<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0611-0576-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">WILLIAM II</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 576</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4s756m31">Saints</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hn2p">Bees</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198938">Rebellion</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:875388">Conquerors</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1173757">Welsh</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n611/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WILLIAM II</label>. (1056-1100), king of England, surnamed
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">Rufüs,</hi> third son of William I. and Matilda, was born
                    in 1056. Little is known of his youth, except that in the quarrel between the
                    Conqueror and Robert he remained loyal to his father. When the Conqueror was on
                    his death <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n612/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0612-0577"/> bed he sent William to England with a letter to
                    Lanfranc, requesting the archbishop to secure his election to the throne.
                    Accordingly on 26th September 1087 William was elected and crowned at
                    Westminster. His brother Robert, to whom the Conqueror had bequeathed the duchy,
                    was not likely to give up his claim to the larger part of his father’s dominions
                    without a struggle. A general revolt in his favour broke out in the summer of
                    1088. Roger Bigod rose in Norfolk, Roger, earl of Shrewsbury, and Robert of
                    Mowbray on the western border, while Odo of Bayeux, the king’s uncle, whom he
                    had reinstated against his father’s advice in the earldom of Kent, occupied
                    Rochester. But there was little combination among the rebels. After being foiled
                    in attacks on Ilchester and Worcester, the rebellion in the west seems to have
                    died away. William won over the earl of Shrewsbury, and summoned his English
                    subjects to his aid. He promised good government, the repeal of the forest laws,
                    and the reduction of taxes. Thus conciliated, the <hi rend="italic">fyrd,</hi>
                    or national levy, flocked to his standard. It was the beginning of that alliance
                    between the monarchy and the people which, fostered by Henry I. and Henry II.
                    and confirmed by the great Edward, secured victory for the crown in its struggle
                    with the feudal aristocracy. With the aid of his English troops William took
                    castle after castle, repelled an attempted landing of the Norman fleet, and
                    forced Odo to surrender his stronghold of Rochester. The rebellion being thus
                    suppressed, he held a great council, at which, although the rebels in general
                    were leniently treated, many confiscations and sentences of banishment were
                    pronounced. A later meeting at Salisbury (November 1088) was notable for the
                    trial of William of Saint-Calais, bishop of Durham, who had been one of the
                    chief promoters of the rebellion. The bishop denied the jurisdiction of the
                    king’s court and appealed to Rome. It was the first instance of such an appeal.
                    The court, however, acting under the advice of Lanfranc, refused to allow the
                    plea, and the bishop, condemned to lose the temporalities of his see, retired to
                    Normandy.</p>
                <p>Two years later William sent an army to Normandy (Easter 1090), which under the
                    misgovernment of Robert had lapsed into a state of anarchy. The re-conquest of
                    the duchy by England was begun by the capture of St Valéry; but there was not
                    much fighting, place after place yielding to William’s lieutenants or to English
                    gold. Robert called King Philip to his aid, but William bribed him to retire. In
                    Rouen itself a popular movement took place for the surrender of the town; but
                    Henry, the duke’s youngest brother, put a stop to it by killing its leader,
                    Conan, with his own hands. In February 1091 William himself crossed the Channel,
                    and at once received homage from many of his brother’s subjects. Unable to
                    resist, Robert consented to a disgraceful peace. By the treaty of Caen William
                    engaged to pay Robert a sum of money, in return for which he received some of
                    the most important districts of eastern Normandy, as well as Cherbourg and other
                    places in the west. It was agreed, among other stipulations, that whichever
                    brother died first the other should succeed to his dominions. Later in the same
                    year William marched against Malcolm III., who had invaded Northumberland, and,
                    penetrating as far as the Firth of Forth, obliged the Scottish king to do him
                    homage. "Whether it was for the whole of Scotland or for Lothian only, history
                    does not say; but the latter is most probable. For an account of the subsequent
                    relations between Malcolm and William, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Scotland,</hi>
                    vol. xxi. p. 481. Meanwhile war had broken out again with Normandy. At Christmas
                    1093 Robert sent a challenge to his brother, reproaching him with violations of
                    the treaty. Accordingly in March 1094 William invaded Normandy a second time. On
                    this occasion fortune turned against him. Philip assisted the duke, and William,
                    who had exhausted his supplies, was unable to buy him off as before. In this
                    predicament his justiciar, Ralph Flambard, assembled an English army on the
                    pretext of an expedition to Normandy, took from each man the money which had
                    been provided for his expenses, and then dismissed the soldiers to their homes.
                    With the money so obtained William bribed the French king, and then returned to
                    England. Next year the first crusade was being preached, and Robert took the
                    cross. A peace was made between the brothers through papal mediation, William
                    supplying Robert with funds, for the repayment of which the latter pledged his
                    duchy. When, in September 1096, Robert set off for the crusade, William took
                    possession of Normandy, where he soon put an end to the anarchy which had
                    resulted from Robert’s misrule; and he held the country till his death. Shortly
                    before the acquisition of Normandy William had subdued a second rebellion in
                    England. Robert of Mowbray was again one of the chief conspirators, and he was
                    joined by William of Saint-Calais, whom the king, in accordance with the treaty
                    of Caen, had restored to his bishopric, and by others. Mowbray refused to obey a
                    summons to the king’s court, whereupon William marched against him, captured his
                    castles of Bamborough and Tynemouth, and took him prisoner (1095). As on the
                    suppression of the earlier rebellion, William called a great assembly, this time
                    consisting of all his tenants-in-chief, and by their judgment the rebels were
                    condemned. During the next two years he made a serious attempt at the conquest
                    of Wales. The southern portion of the principality had been to a great extent
                    reduced, first by Harold, afterwards by the Norman border lords. William’s
                    efforts were mainly directed against the northern districts. He made three
                    invasions, and penetrated to Snowdon, but seeming victories were immediately
                    followed by revolts, and in the end little ground was actually won.</p>
                <p>The last three years of the 11th century were much occupied by tedious wars with
                    France and efforts to recover Maine. In 1097 he quarrelled with Philip about
                    Vexin, and crossed the Channel to make good his claim to that district; but the
                    French king was able to hold his own. Next year William set about the recovery
                    of Maine. That territory had been allowed by Robert to slip out of his hands,
                    and had been governed since 1091 by Helias de la Flèche. William’s vassal,
                    Robert of Bellême, attacked Helias, and, having succeeded in taking him
                    prisoner, handed over his prize to the king. William thereupon marched into
                    Maine, and a desultory war of forays, sieges, and skirmishes followed. Fulk of
                    Anjou opposed the Norman claim; but in August 1098 a treaty was made, by which
                    William’s rights over the country were recognized, and Helias was at the same
                    time set free. William now turned again to France. Strengthened by an alliance
                    with the duke of Aquitaine, he invaded the French territory and advanced as far
                    as Pontoise. But, tiring of the fruitless war, he made a truce with Philip and
                    returned to England early in 1099. He had only been there a few months when he
                    heard that Helias de la Flèche was attacking his castles in Maine and had won
                    back Le Mans. He crossed the Channel with great speed, and’ a last campaign
                    replaced him in possession of the coveted borderland. But he took no pains to
                    secure his hold, and the Norman power in Maine fell to pieces immediately on his
                    death.</p>
                <p>William H.’s relations with Anselm form perhaps the most important episode of his
                    reign. Lanfranc died in 1089. The worst features of William’s character began at
                    once to show themselves. At the instigation or with the assistance of Ralph
                    Flambard, he applied to the possessions of the church all the principles of
                    feudal law developed <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n613/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0613-0578"/> in the interest of the monarchy. He treated
                    vacant benefices as if they had been lay fiefs and bishops as tenants-in-chief,
                    while he made simony the rule and degraded the heads of the church into servile
                    courtiers. He had kept the see of Canterbury vacant for nearly four years, when
                    a severe illness aroused him to a sense of his enormities. Sending for Anselm,
                    at that time abbot of Bee, he forced the crozier into his unwilling hands
                    (1093). Anselm insisted on three conditions,—that the temporalities of the see
                    should be fully restored, that William should act in ecclesiastical affairs by
                    his counsel, and that he should be allowed to recognize Urban II. as pope. After
                    some hesitation William yielded the first demand, and Anselm did homage for the
                    temporalities. The other two demands remained unsettled. In December 1093 Anselm
                    was consecrated archbishop of Canterbury. On the outbreak of war against
                    Normandy in 1094 Anselm offered William a contribution of £500. William declared
                    the sum insufficient and angrily rejected the gift. Anselm refused to offer
                    more, lest he should seem, even by a gift after his appointment, to be guilty of
                    simony. Other grounds of quarrel were found in the reproofs which the archbishop
                    levelled against the vices of the court, and his demand for ecclesiastical
                    reform. In 1095 a more serious dispute arose. Anselm asked leave to go to Rome
                    in order to obtain his <hi rend="italic">pallium</hi> from the pope. As this
                    involved a recognition of Urban, and William wished to secure his independence
                    by acknowledging no pope, the permission was refused. The archbishop demanded
                    that the question should be discussed at a great council. Accordingly an
                    assembly was held at Rockingham (March 1095), in which Anselm was treated by the
                    king as if he had been on trial for contumacy. The bishops sided with the king;
                    the laity took part mostly with the primate. Anselm refused to renounce
                    allegiance to the pope, but denied that this was incompatible with obedience to
                    the king. The assembly broke up without coming to a decision. William now tried
                    to win over the pope and received a legate who brought with him the pall. In the
                    hope of getting the legate to suspend Anselm, he consented to recognize Urban.
                    But, when he found that the pope had no intention of throwing over the
                    archbishop, he reconciled himself with Anselm and allowed him to take the pall
                    from the altar at Canterbury. But it was not long before he found an opportunity
                    of taking his revenge. A contingent of knights sent by the primate to aid the
                    king in his Welsh war (1097) was declared to be worthless, and Anselm was
                    summoned to explain his conduct at court. Tired of the persecution and
                    despairing of reform, Anselm again asked leave to go to Rome. William,
                    believing, whether rightly or not, that Anselm intended to appeal against him,
                    refused his request. Twice repeated, it met with the same answer. Anselm was
                    charged with having broken his oath to observe the laws of the kingdom in
                    threatening to leave England without the king’s permission. He answered that he
                    had only sworn to the laws subject to his duty to God and the verdict of his
                    conscience. This answer alienated many who had supported him on the previous
                    occasion. He was asked to swear that he would not appeal against the king, and
                    on his refusal was ordered to leave the country. In October 1097 Anselm left
                    England. William at once seized the archbishopric and kept possession of it till
                    his death.</p>
                <p>The unscrupulous tyranny which Rufus displayed in his quarrel with Anselm was
                    equally characteristic of his temporal government. The feudal customs of aids,
                    reliefs, escheats, &amp;c., were developed into a great system of extortion. The
                    townsfolk and the cultivators of the soil were weighed down by heavy taxes. The
                    forest laws were carried out with ruthless severity. On the other hand, order
                    was maintained, and the tyranny was to a certain extent veiled or limited by the
                    frequent use which William made of his great councils, in the trials of great
                    men like Odo, in the declaration of war, in the settlement of disputes such as
                    that with Anselm. It is clear that the national assembly was neither extinct nor
                    inefficient during this reign. It was in this period too that the office of
                    justiciar became permanent in the person of William’s chief minister, Ralph
                    Flambard, although in his hands its powers were used merely in support of
                    despotism.</p>
                <p>In his private character William was as vicious as in his public capacity he was
                    tyrannical. He was harsh and violent, extravagant and lustful, regardless of God
                    and pitiless to man. He had a strong vein of mockery and sarcasm, and no little
                    of the grim Norman humour. Almost the only redeeming feature of his character is
                    his chivalrous observation of his plighted word; but for ordinary promises or
                    obligations he had no respect. He died under mysterious circumstances in the New
                    Forest, Hampshire, on 2d August 1100. William II. was not married; he was
                    succeeded by his brother Henry.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Authorities.—</hi> Ordericus Vitalis, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historia Ecclesiastica;</hi> Geoffrey Gaiιnar, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Histoire</hi><hi rend="italic">des Angles;</hi> Eadmer, <hi rend="italic"
                    >Historia</hi><hi rend="italic">Novorwm;</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Anglo-Saxon
                    Chronicle;</hi> Freeman, <hi rend="italic">Reign of William Rufus.</hi> (G. W.
                    P.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
