<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0585-0550-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WHITEBAIT (9th edition, volume 24, page 550)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926650">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1028427">Mouth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150792">Tides</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:864963">Clupea</term>
                    <term ref="fast:804171">Albas</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x268">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f39x">Mouth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n585/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WHITEBAIT</label>, the vernacular name of a small Clupeoid
                    fish which appears in large shoals in the estuary of the Thames during the
                    summer months, and is held in great esteem as a delicacy for the table. As to
                    whether or not it is a distinct form, the opinions of naturalists have been
                    divided ever since their attention was directed to the question. Pennant and
                    Shaw believed it to be some kind of Cyprinoid fish, similar to the bleak, whilst
                    Donovan, in his <hi rend="italic">Natural History of British Fishes</hi>
                    (1802-8), misled by specimens sent to him as whitebait, declared it to be the
                    young of the shad. In 182Ó Yarrell proved conclusively that Donovan’s opinion
                    was founded upon an error; unfortunately he contented himself with comparing
                    whitebait with the shad only, and in the end adopted the opinion of the Thames
                    fishermen, whose interest it was to represent it as a distinct adult form; thus
                    the whitebait is introduced into Yarrell’s <hi rend="italic">History of British
                        Fishes</hi> (1836) as <hi rend="italic">Clupea</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >alba.</hi> The French ichthyologist Valenciennes went a step further,
                    declaring it to be not only specifically but also generically distinct from all
                    other Clupeoids. On examining the specimens of <hi rend="italic">Clupea</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">alba</hi> which passed from Yarrell’s collection into the
                    British Museum, the present writer found them to be the young of the common
                    herring <hi rend="italic">(Catal. Fish. Brit.</hi><hi rend="italic">Mus.,</hi>
                    vii. p. 416, 1868); and this conclusion was fully borne out by visits to the
                    Thames boats and by an examination of their captures on the spot. The bulk of
                    the whitebait caught consists, in May and June, chiefly of the fry of herring,
                    mixed with a number of shrimps, gobies, sticklebacks, pipe-fishes, young
                    flounders, and an occasional sprat. But, the Thames being unequal to the supply
                    of the large demand for this delicacy, large quantities of whitebait are now
                    brought to London and other markets from many parts of the coast. They
                    frequently consist of a much greater proportion of young sprats than the fish
                    obtained from the Thames; and they sometimes prove a valuable mine for the
                    collector, who may find mixed with them pelagic animals (such as the smaller
                    kinds of Cephalopods) which are not at all, or but rarely, met with at the mouth
                    of the Thames or on the south coast generally. In times past whitebait were
                    considered to be peculiar to the estuary of the Thames; and, even after the
                    specific identification of Thames whitebait with the young of the herring from
                    other localities, it was still thought that there was a distinctive superiority
                    in the condition and flavour of the former. It is possible that the young
                    herrings find in the estuary of the Thames a larger amount of suitable food than
                    on other parts of the coast, where the,water may be of greater purity, but
                    possesses less abundance of the minute animal life on which whitebait thrive.
                    Indeed, Thames whitebait -which have been compared with young herrings from the
                    mouth of the Exe, the Cornish coast, Menai Strait, and the Firth of Forth seemed
                    to be better fed; but, of course, the specific characteristics of the
                    herring,—into which we need not enter here,—were nowise modified.</p>
                <p>The fry of fishes is used as an article of diet in almost every country: in
                    Germany the young of various species of Cyprinoids, in Italy and Japan the young
                    of nearly every fish capable of being readily captured in sufficient numbers, in
                    the South Sea Islands the fry of <hi rend="italic">Teuthis,</hi> in New Zealand
                    young <hi rend="italic">Calaxias</hi> are consumed at certain seasons in large
                    quantities; and, like whitebait, these fry bear distinct names, different from
                    those of the adult fish.</p>
                <p>Whitebait fishing in the Thames lasts from the end of March to September. The
                    majority of the fish caught at the beginning of spring are about two inches
                    long; as the season advances the proportion of larger specimens becomes greater,
                    although very small ones occur abundantly throughout the season,— thus
                    apparently confirming the opinion of those who maintain that the herring is in
                    its spawning not bound to any particular month. Whitebait are caught on the
                    flood-tide from boats moored in from 3 to 5 fathoms of water. The net used is a
                    bag some 20 feet long, narrow and small-meshed towards the tail-end, the mouth
                    being kept open in the direction of the advancing tide by a framework 3 or 4
                    feet square. It is placed alongside the boat and sunk to a depth of 4 feet below
                    the surface; from time to time the end of the bag is lifted into the boat, to
                    empty it of its contents. The ‘ ‘ schools” of whitebait, advancing and retiring
                    with the tide for days and probably for weeks, have to run the gauntlet of a
                    dozen of these nets, and therefore eet verv much thinned in num·</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n586/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0586-0551"/>
                <p>ber by the end of the season. When the view commenced to gain ground that
                    whitebait were young herring, the question arose whether or not the immense
                    destruction of the young brood caused by this mode of fishing injuriously
                    affected the fishery of the mature herring. This undoubtedly it does; but, since
                    it has been ascertained that the herring is much more restricted in its
                    migrations than was formerly believed, and that it merely moves from the
                    feeding-grounds in the depth of the ocean to the shallower spawning-grounds of
                    the neighbouring coast, the injury, such as it is, must be local and limited to
                    the particular district in which the fishing for whitebait is methodically
                    practised.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
