<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0630-0593-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WILTS (9th edition, volume 24, page 593)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115460">Sheep</term>
                    <term ref="fast:828732">Baths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tv2w">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n630/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WILTS</label>, a south-western county of England, is bounded
                    N.W. and N. by Gloucestershire, E. by Berks and Hants, S. by Hants and Dorset,
                    and W. by Somerset. It is of an irregular oval form, its greatest length from
                    north to south being 54 miles and its greatest breadth from east to west 37. The
                    area is 866,677 acres, or about 1354 square miles.</p>
                <p>About two-thirds of the surface of Wilts is occupied by a great Chalk upland,
                    embracing the greater part of the wild wooded tract of Cranborne Chase, the
                    undulating elevation of Salisbury Plain, and the hilly district of the
                    Marlborough Downs, with Savernake Forest. In some cases the Chalk rises into
                    steep escarpments; and the scenery of the north-western region, bordering on the
                    lower ground, is varied and picturesque. A large portion of the Chalk region is
                    over 600 feet above sea-level, and several summits have an elevation of over 900
                    feet, the highest being Inkpen Beacon (1011 feet) at the junction of Wilts,
                    Hants, and Berks. Scattered over the surface of the northern downs are huge
                    blocks of silicious Tertiary grits, called sarsen stones or grey wethers, which
                    have been used in the formation of the Druidical circles of Stonehenge and
                    Avebury. The underlying Greensand is exposed in the deep valleys of the Chalk,
                    especially in the broad vale of Pewsey, separating the Marlborough Downs from
                    Salisbury Plain. It also appears as a narrow fringe between the Chalk and Oolite
                    formations on the north and west, and in Alfred’s Tower near Stourton on the
                    Somersetshire border reaches an elevation of 800 feet. Outliers of the London
                    Clay cap some of the hills in the neighbourhood of Great and Little Bedwin and
                    Savernake Forest; and the clays and sands of the Woolwich and Reading beds
                    appear in the south-eastern extremity of the county. About a third of the
                    surface of the county, to the north-west of the Chalk, including a portion of
                    the White Horse Vale, consists mainly of Oolite limestones and clays resting
                    chiefly on the Greensand. The Lower, Middle, and Upper varieties are all
                    represented. At one time the fuller’s earth of the Lower Oolite was dug for use
                    in the cloth-mills. In the Coral Rag of the Middle Oolite a useful bed of iron
                    is wrought near Westbury, the annual output of ore varying in value from £12,000
                    to £20,000. The valuable Portland stone of the Upper Oolite is quarried for
                    building purposes at Chilmark, Tisbury, and Swindon, and the famous Bath stone
                    of the Great Oolite is obtained at Corsham and Box on the Somersetshire border.
                    The Oolite yields a variety of interesting fossils: the pear encrinite <hi
                        rend="italic">(Apwcrinites</hi><hi rend="italic">rotundus)</hi> is found in
                    the Bradford clay; many fine corals are obtained in the Coral Rag; and <hi
                        rend="italic">Isastraea</hi><hi rend="italic">oblonga</hi> is very plentiful
                    at Tisbury.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n631/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0631-0594"/>
                <p>One of the most charming features of Wilts is its rich and finely wooded valleys.
                    The three principal rivers are the Kennet, the Lower or Bristol Avon, and the
                    Southern or Christchurch Avon. The Kennet, rising in the Marlborough Downs,
                    winds eastwards past Marlborough and Hungerford into Berkshire, to join the
                    Thames at Reading. The Lower Avon, which rises in Gloucestershire, flows
                    southwards by Malmesbury, Chippenham, Melksham, and Bradford, where it bends
                    north-westwards into Somersetshire. Besides several smaller streams, it receives
                    from the south the Frome, which forms for a short distance the boundary between
                    Wilts and Somersetshire. The Southern Avon, which rises near Bishop’s Cannings
                    in the centre of the county, flows southwards by Amesbury and Salisbury into
                    Hants. At Salisbury it receives from the west the Nadder, after its junction
                    with the Wily at Wilton, and from the north-east the Bourne. The Thames skirts
                    the north-eastern border of the county.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Agriculture.—</hi> According to returns made on 4th June 1887,
                    the total area of land occupied was 759,538 acres, of which 646,653 were rented
                    and 112,885 owned and occupied; 759,412 acres, or about seven-eighths of the
                    whole area, were under cultivation. Of this area 395,010 acres were permanent
                    pasture, a great portion consisting of sheep-runs on the Chalk downs. In some
                    places, especially in Salisbury Plain, tillage was in former years extensively
                    introduced in the Chalk districts, but much of this has again reverted to
                    pasture. There were 174,876 acres under corn crops, 99,388 under green crops,
                    79,049 under rotation grasses, and 11,086 under fallow. In north-west Wilts the
                    prevailing soil is a reddish chalky clay resting on a subsoil of broken stones,
                    whilst on the Chalk formation the arable land is of a lighter character. There
                    are also extensive tracts of richer soil well adapted for wheat and beans. In
                    1887 wheat occupied 67,357 acres, barley 50,928, oats 44,047, rye 1728, beans
                    7274, and pease 3542. The bulk of the green crops are grown for the feeding of
                    cattle and sheep, potatoes occupying only 3339 acres and carrots 237, while
                    54,869 acres were under turnips and swedes, 5673 mangold, 10,473 cabbage, rape,
                    &amp;c., and 24,527 vetches, &amp;c. The total area under nursery grounds in
                    1887 was 91 acres, while market gardens occupied 3525, and orchards 3346. Woods
                    in 1881 occupied 45,270 acres, a great part being comprised in the ancient
                    forests, including Cranborne Chase and Savernake Forest, which contain some
                    remarkable old oaks and beeches. The number of horses in 1887 was 23,616, of
                    which 18,980 were used solely for purposes of agriculture. Cattle numbered
                    106,020, 60,113 being cows and heifers in milk or in calf. Dairy farming is the
                    leading industry in the north-western districts, Wiltshire being famous for its
                    cheese. Of the cattle 15,505 were two years and above, and 30,402 under two
                    years, an indication that comparatively few cattle are kept for purposes of
                    feeding. Sheep in 1887 numbered 643,125, and pigs 66,422.</p>
                <p>According to the latest landowners’ <hi rend="italic">Return,</hi> Wiltshire was
                    divided among 14,013 owners, possessing 828,949 acres at an annual valuation of
                    £1,599,239, or about £1, 18s. 7d. per acre. There were 9635 owners possessing
                    less than one acre each, 1519 acres being divided amongst them. The estimated
                    extent of commons or waste lands was 1931 acres. The following proprietors owned
                    over 7000 acres each :—earl of Pembroke, 39,601 acres; marquis of Ailesbury,
                    37,994; marquis of Bath, 19,978; earl of Radnor, 17,173; Simon W. Taylor,
                    14,960; R. P. Long, 13,618; Sir John Neeld, 13,113; trustees of Sir H. Meux,
                    11,896; marquis of Lansdowne, 11,146; earl of Suffolk, 11,098; earl of
                    Normanton, 9812; Lord Ashburton, 9592; Sir E. Antrobus, 8374; Sir Francis D.
                    Astley, 7888; Sir Μ. E. Hicks Beach, 7200; and T. Fraser Grove, 7179.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Communication.—k</hi> considerable amount of traffic is carried
                    on in the northern districts by means of canals. The Thames and Severn Canal
                    crosses the north-west comer of the county. Between Cricklade and Swindon it is
                    joined by a branch canal to the Wilts and Berks Canal. This last has a
                    semicircular course southwestwards by Swindon, Wootton Basset, and Melksham, 2
                    miles beyond which it is joined by the Rennet and Avon Canal, which crosses the
                    centre of the county by Hungerford, Devizes, and Bradford. The railway
                    communication is supplied chiefly by the Great Western and the London and South
                    Western lines.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Manufactures and Trade.—</hi> Wiltshire has long been
                    celebrated for its cloths, the chief seats of the industry being Bradford and
                    Trowbridge, while among other places Melksham and Chippenham are perhaps the
                    most important. Wilton is still celebrated for its carpets.. Haircloth weaving
                    and the manufacture of cocoa-nut fibres are carried on at Melksham, and there
                    are silk works at Chippenham, Malmesbury, Mere, and Warminster. Iron-smelting
                    from the mines of the neighbourhood is carried on at Westbury; portable engines
                    are made at Devizes; and at Swindon are the enginee <hi rend="underline"
                        >rin</hi> g works of the Great·Western Railway. Various towns are associated
                    with different branches of the agricultural trade: Salisbury and Devizes have
                    important corn markets; Chippenham, besides a trade in cheese, has a condensed
                    milk manufactory; Wilton has a large sheep fair; and Caine is the centre of the
                    Wiltshire bacon trade.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Administration</hi><hi rend="italic">and Population.—</hi>
                    Wiltshire comprises 29 hundreds, the city of Salisbury or New Sarum (population
                    14,792 in 1881), and the municipal boroughs of Caine (2474), Chippenham (1352),
                    Devizes (6645), and Marlborough (3343). The county has one court of quarter
                    sessions and is divided into fifteen petty sessional divisions. The city of
                    Salisbury and the borough of Devizes have commissions of the peace and separate
                    courts of quarter sessions, and the borough of Marlborough has a commission of
                    the peace. Previous to the Act of 1885 the county was divided for parliamentary
                    purposes into North and South Wilts, each returning two members, and included
                    the following parliamentary boroughs—Caine, Chippenham, part of Cricklade,
                    Devizes, Malmesbury, Marlborough, Salisbury city, part of Shaftesbury, Westbury,
                    and Wilton. All these returned one member each, with the exception of Salisbury,
                    which returned two; by the Act of 1885 they were all merged in the county
                    divisions, with the exception of Salisbury, which was deprived of one member.
                    The county was reformed into five parliamentary divisions, each returning one
                    member,—north (Cricklade), into which the Wiltshire portion of Cricklade is
                    merged; north-west (Chippenham), into which Chippenham and Malmesbury are
                    merged; south (Wilton), into which Wilton is merged; east (Devizes), into which
                    Devizes and Marlborough are merged; and west (Westbury), into which Westbury is
                    merged. The county contains 340 civil parishes, with parts of seven others. It
                    is mostly in the diocese of Salisbury. From 183,820 in 1801 the population by
                    1821 had increased to 219,574, and by 1841 to 256,280, and, although by 1861 it
                    had diminished to 249,311, by 1871 it had again increased to 257,177; in 1881 it
                    was 258,965, of whom 128,114 were males and 130,851 females. The number of
                    persons to an acre is 0 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 30 and of acres to a
                    person 3 <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> 35.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History and Antiquities. —</hi> In the importance of its early
                    archaeo- 1ogical remains Wilts takes a foremost place among the counties of
                    England. In the river gravel-beds near Salisbury and elsewhere several specimens
                    of flint implements of the Palaeolithic age have been dug up, and the numerous
                    barrows of the Chalk downs have yielded a great variety of stone implements of
                    the Neolithic age, as well as of a later period. The ancient British boundary,
                    the Wans Dyke, passed westwards across the county from Great Bedwin; west of
                    Marlborough it still remains for many miles in a perfect condition. Traces of
                    several other boundaries of a somewhat similar character are met with in other
                    parts of the county. The British “ridgeway” runs north-eastwards from Avebury,
                    near the tumulus of Silbury Hill, to the ancient forts of Barbury and Bad bury;
                    other ancient British trackways have been converted into Roman roads. Among the
                    principal ancient defensive works are Battlesbury and Scratchbury near
                    Warminster; the entrenchments of Barbury and Badbury; Bratton, near Westbury,
                    defended by double ramparts, in some places 36 feet in height, to which Guthrum
                    the Dane is said to have retreated after his defeat by King Alfred; Casterly, on
                    a ridgeway about 7 miles south-east of Devizes, described by Sir R. C. Hoare as
                    “one of the most original and unaltered works of the British era which our
                    country can produce”; Figbury Ring, 3 miles north-east of Salisbury, sometimes
                    called Chlorus’s camp, from the tradition that it was made by the British
                    general Constantine Chlorus; Sidbury, 3 miles south-west of Collingbourne,
                    probably an ancient British town; Vespasian’s camp, between Amesbury and
                    Stonehenge; and Yarnbury camp, in very perfect preservation, to the north of
                    Wily. Ogbury camp, 6 miles north of Salisbury, is an undoubted British
                    entrenchment, but probably a sheep-fold. The stone circles of Avebury and
                    Stonehenge are the most remarkable megalithic structures in the kingdom; but
                    their origin and date are the subject of much dispute. Durrington “walls,” north
                    of Amesbury, are probably the remains of a British village; there are also
                    traces of others at several places on the slopes of the Marlborough Downs and
                    Salisbury Plain.</p>
                <p>There are no records of the Roman invasion, though many evi-detíces of Roman
                    occupation remain. The ancient Fosse Way crossed the north-west corner of the
                    county from Bath to Cirencester. From this last town another road passed
                    southwards to <hi rend="italic">Cunetro</hi> (Folly Farm near Marlborough),
                    joining the <hi rend="italic">Via Julia,</hi> which crossed the county from Bath
                    to Silchester. From Salisbury one went north-east to Silchester, another east to
                    Winchester, and another north-west to Bath. On the line of these roads remains
                    of Roman villages have been found at different places.</p>
                <p>After the departure of the Romans Wilts was the scene of frequent contests, first
                    between the Britons and the Saxons and afterwards between the Saxons and the
                    Danes. Badbury is the reputed <hi rend="italic">Mons Badonieus</hi> where King
                    Arthur defeated Cerdic in 520. In 552 Cynric inflicted a severe defeat on a
                    large army of Britons at Old Sarum, and in 556, after a great victory over them
                    at Barbury Hill, he incorporated the country of the Wilsaetas in the kingdom <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n632/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0632-0595"/> of Wessex. In 823 Egbert, king of the West
                    Saxons, gained a victory over Beornwulf, king of Mercia, at Ellandune near
                    Wilton. Wilton itself was the scene of Alfred’s defeat by the Danes in 871. In
                    878 the Danes plundered Chippenham, where Alfred had one of his residences, and
                    made the town their headquarters; but afterwards Alfred inflicted on Guthrum
                    such a severe defeat at Ethan-dune (supposed to be Edington near Westbury) that
                    the Danes came to terms with him, the south-western part of Mercia being
                    henceforth held by the Saxons and the north-eastern by the Danes. During the
                    Danish invasions at the close of the 10th and the beginning of the 11th century
                    the district was overrun by Sweyn, who pillaged and burned Wilton, as well as
                    Old Sarum. At the latter town Canute died in 1036. During the conflict between
                    Stephen and Matilda the strongholds of Sarum, Devizes, and Malmesbury were held
                    by Bishop Roger for Matilda, until he was compelled to surrender them. During
                    the Civil War Wiltshire sided chiefly with the Parliament. In 1643 Wardour
                    Castle near Tisbury was bravely defended by Lady Blanche Arundell against Sir
                    Edward Hungerford, and, although she was forced to capitulate, the castle was
                    again taken by her son in 1645. In 1643 Essex was routed by Charles I. and
                    Rupert at Aidbourn, and the same year Waller was defeated by Wilmot at Roundaway
                    near Devizes. After the storming of Devizes Castle by Cromwell in September 1645
                    the Cavaliers were wholly driven from the county.</p>
                <p>The church of St Lawrence, Bradford, converted at one time into cottages, is one
                    of the most perfect specimens of ancient Saxon architecture existing; and there
                    is also Saxon work in the churches of Britford (north and south door), Burcombe
                    (east end of the chancel), Manningford Bruce, and a few other places. There is a
                    large amount of Roman work in the church of Malmesbury abbey, much of it,
                    however, being Transition; the church of St John’s, Devizes, retains its
                    original Norman tower and exhibits Norman vaulting in the chancel; the chancel
                    of St Mary’s in the same town is also Norman, and its porch has characteristic
                    Norman mouldings; the churches of Preshute and Corsham contain interesting
                    examples of the same style. Salisbury cathedral is the finest and most perfect
                    example of Early English existing; and there is much good architecture of the
                    same style in the churches of Amesbury, Bishop’s Cannings, Cricklade,
                    Collingbourne-Kingston, Downton, Edington, and Purton. The prevailing
                    architecture is, however, Perpendicular, of which there are numerous fine
                    examples, especially in the districts where good building stone is found; but in
                    the Chalk districts, where the churches are constructed of flint, the
                    architecture is generally inferior. There are numerous interesting examples of
                    domestic architecture of the 14th, 15th, and 16th centuries. The only monastic
                    remains of importance within the county are the abbey church of Malmesbury; the
                    picturesque ruins of Lacock or Laycock abbey (3 miles south of Chippenham),
                    founded in 1232 by Ella, countess of Salisbury; the walls of Bradenstoke priory
                    (northeast of Chippenham), founded in 1142 by Walter d’Evreux for Augustinian
                    canons, now converted into a farmhouse; and slight remains of the Cluniae priory
                    of Monkton-Farleigh, founded in 1125. The fortress of Old Sarum is almost
                    completely demolished, but tho outlines of the defences remain; Devizes retains
                    a few fragments, “built up again,” according to Freeman, as “meaningless
                    ornaments in the midst of the most fearful piece of modern gim-crack that human
                    eyes ever beheld”; and the mound of Marlborough has been made into a “hill of
                    pleasure.” Trowbridge Castle, which was held for Matilda by Humphrey de Bohun,
                    has completely disappeared, its site being occupied by modern buildings; and
                    only a few small fragments remain of Ludgershall, which Matilda occupied on her
                    escape from Winchester.</p>
                <p>Wilts has an unusually long roll of illustrious persons. Among divines, Hugh
                    Latimer was rector of West Kington; Richard Hooker was rector of Boscombe;
                    George Crabbe was for eighteen years rector of Trowbridge, and was buried in the
                    chancel of the church; Dr Henry Sacheverell was the son of a Marlborough
                    clergyman; George Herbert and Archdeacon William Coxe were both rectors of
                    Bemerton (near Salisbury); and Dr Joshua Marshman, the Indian missionary, was
                    born at Westbury. Of persons who have distinguished themselves in some form of
                    literature we may mention Thomas Chubb, the Deist, who was a native of Harnham;
                    Hobbes of Malmesbury; Philip Massinger, who was born at Salisbury; Joseph
                    Addison, the son of the rector of Milston; Bryan Edwards, the historian; Aubrey
                    and Britton, the antiquaries; Edmund Ludlow, author of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Memoirs</hi> of the Restoration period; and Sir R. Colt Hoare, the
                    historian of Wilts. Statesmen are represented by “Orator” Hunt, Sir John Davies,
                    Bolingbroke, Hyde first earl of Clarendon, Harris first earl of Malmesbury, Fox
                    first Lord Holland, Protector Somerset, and Henry Fawcett. Other persons of
                    special distinction are Sir Christopher Wren, Sir B. Collins Brodie, and Thomas
                    Willis, one of the founders of the Royal Society.</p>
                <p>See Sir H. C. Hoare’s <hi rend="italic">Ancient Wiltshire,</hi> 1812-21, and <hi
                        rend="italic">Modern Wiltshire,</hi> 1822- 1844; Aubrey and Jackson’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Topographical Collections for Wilts,</hi> 1864; Britton's <hi
                        rend="italic">Beauties,</hi> 1801; Kite’s <hi rend="italic">Monumental
                        Brasses of Wilts,</hi> 1860; Jackson’s <hi rend="italic">Ancient Chapels of
                        Wilts,</hi> 1867; Jones’s <hi rend="italic">Early Annals,</hi> 1871; Saint
                    George's <hi rend="italic">Visitation of Wilts 1623,</hi> 1882; Stratford’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Wiltshire and its Worthies,</hi> 1882; and A. C. Smith's <hi
                        rend="italic">British and Roman Antiquities in North Wilts,</hi> 1884-85.
                    (T. F. H.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
