<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0364-0341-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WALTON, Brian (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    341)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mg7g36p">Rectors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg1r">Bachelors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:902475">Editors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825039">Bachelors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1163204">Ushers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n364/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WALTON, <hi rend="smallcaps">Brian</hi></label> (1600—1661),
                    bishop of Chester, and editor of the great London Polyglott Bible, was born at
                    Seymour, in the district of Cleveland, Yorkshire, in 1600. He went to Cambridge
                    as a sizar of Magdalene College in 1616, migrated to Peterhouse in 1618, was
                    bachelor in 1619, and master of arts in 1623. After holding a school mastership
                    and two curacies he was in 1626 made rector of St Martin’s Orgar in London
                    (1626), where he took a leading part in the contest between the London clergy
                    and the citizens about the city tithes, and compiled a treatise on the subject,
                    which is printed in Brewster’s <hi rend="italic">Collectanea,</hi> 1752. His
                    conduct in this matter displayed his ability, but his zeal for the exaction of
                    ecclesiastical dues was remembered to his hurt in 1641 in the articles brought
                    against him in parliament, which appear to have led to the sequestration of his
                    very considerable preferments.<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                        type="authorial"><p>He was from January 1635-36 rector of Sandon, in Essex,
                            where his first wife, Anne Claxton, is buried. He appears to have also
                            been a prebendary of St Paul’s, and for a very short time he had held
                            the rectory of St Giles in the Fields.</p></note> He was also charged
                    with Popish practices, but on frivolous grounds, and with aspersing the members
                    of parliament for the city. Up to this time he was perhaps more an active
                    ecclesiastic than an eager student. In 1642 he was ordered into custody as a
                    delinquent; thereafter he took refuge at Oxford, and ultimately returned to
                    London to the house of Dr Fuller, dean of Ely, whose daughter Jane was his
                    second wife. In this retirement he planned and executed his great work, a
                    Polyglott Bible which should be completer, cheaper, and provided with a better
                    critical apparatus than any previous work of the kind (see <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >Polyglott).</hi> The proposals for the Polyglott appeared in 1652, and the
                    book itself came out in six great folios in 1657, having been printing for five
                    years. England had at this time a band of Biblical and Oriental scholars of
                    unusual distinction, and Walton could reckon among his active helpers Usher,
                    Lightfoot, and Pococke, Castle, Wheelock, and Patrick Young, Hyde, Thomas
                    Greaves, and others of less note. The great undertaking was supported by liberal
                    subscriptions, and Walton’s political opinions did not deprive him of the help
                    of the Commonwealth; the paper used was freed from duty, and the interest of
                    Cromwell in the work was acknowledged in the original preface, part of which was
                    afterwards cancelled to make way for more loyal expressions towards that
                    restored monarchy under which Oriental studies in England immediately began to
                    languish. To Walton himself, however, the Reformation <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n365/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0365-0342"/> brought no disappointment. He was consecrated
                    bishop of Chester in December 1660. In the following spring he was one of the
                    commissioners at the Savoy Conference, but took little part in the business. In
                    the autumn of 1661 he paid a short visit to his diocese, and returning to London
                    he fell sick and died on 29th November.</p>
                <p>However much Walton was indebted to his helpers, the Polyglott Bible is a great
                    monument of industry and of capacity for directing a vast undertaking, and the
                        <hi rend="italic">Prolegomena</hi> (separately reprinted by Dathe, 1777, and
                    Wrangham, 1825) show judgment as well as learning. The same qualities appear in
                    Walton’s <hi rend="italic">Considerator Considered</hi> (1659), a reply to Dr
                    John Owen’s <hi rend="italic">Considerations,</hi> who thought that the
                    accumulation of material for the revision of the received text tended to
                    atheism. Among Walton’s works must also be mentioned an <hi rend="italic"
                        >Introductio ad Lectionem Linguarum Orientalium</hi> (1654, 2d ed. 1655),
                    meant to prepare the way for the Polyglott.</p>
                <p>See Henry J. Todd, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Life and Writings of
                        Walton,</hi> London, 1821, in 2 vols., of which the second contains a
                    reprint of Walton's answer to Owen.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
