<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0652-0615-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">WISBECH, or Wisbeach (9th edition, volume 24, page
                    615)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:852538">Charters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:836750">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878993">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1073379">Potatoes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039127">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r443">Journalism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4f18sf3s">Charters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41z41t5n">Boroughs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n652/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">WISBECH, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Wisbeach</hi></label>, a
                    municipal borough, markettown, and seaport of Cambridge, England, in the Isle of
                    Ely, is situated on the river Nene, on the Wisbech Canal, by which there is
                    connexion by the Ouse with Hertford, and on branches of the Great Eastern and
                    Midland Railways, 40 miles north of Cambridge, 21 east-north-east of
                    Peterborough, and about 90 from London. It possesses a spacious market-place, a
                    handsome crescent, and several good streets. There is a public park, 18 acres in
                    extent. The greater part of the town is situated on the south side the river,
                    which is crossed by an iron bridge. The church of St Peter and St Paul is very
                    singularly constructed, having two parallel naves, two aisles, and two chancels,
                    with a large square tower at the west end, originally dating from the 12th
                    century, but almost entirely reconstructed about the close of the 15th century.
                    The church contains some semicircular Saxon arches as well as some traces of
                    Early Norman. Among the other public buildings are the corn exchange (re-erected
                    1811), the public hall, the custom-house, the new cattle market, the working
                    men’s club and institute, and the museum and literary institute, with a library
                    of 12,000 volumes and a fine collection of Roman remains and other antiquities.
                    Besides the Cambridgeshire Hospital (1873) and the twelve corporation almshouses
                    there are a large number of other charities. A grammar-school was established in
                    the middle of the 16th century, and provision was made in the charter of Edward
                    VI. for its continuance. A Gothic monument was erected here to Thomas Clarkson,
                    the anti-slavery orator, in 1881. Vessels of 500 tons burden can enter the port,
                    and extensive wharfage has been erected at a cost of £60,000. The number of
                    vessels that entered the port in 1886 was 294, of 50,721 tons, and the number
                    that cleared 286, of 50,812 tons. The chief imports are corn, potatoes, wool,
                    timber, and iron, and the exports agricultural produce and salt. In the
                    neighbourhood immense quantities of fruit are grown, including apples, pears,
                    plums, gooseberries, and strawberries. Potatoes, asparagus, and other vegetables
                    are also largely grown for the London market. The town possesses agricultural
                    implement works, coach-building works, breweries, ropeworks, planing and sawing
                    mills, and corn and oil-cake mills, many of them driven by water, and others by
                    steam. The town is divided into two wards, and is governed by a mayor, six
                    aidermen, and eighteen councillors. It has a separate commission of the peace.
                    The corporation act as the urban sanitary authority. Water is obtained from
                    chalk springs near Norfolk. The population of the municipal borough in 1871 was
                    9362 and in 1881 it was 9249.</p>
                <p>Wisbech was most probably a fort of the Romans, who it is supposed constructed
                    the river banks in the neighbourhood. It takes its name from the river Ouse
                    (Wyse). It is first noticed in 664, in a charter of Wulfhere, son of Penda. In
                    the early part of the <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n653/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0653-0616"/> 11th century it was given by Oswy and
                    Leoflede to the convent of Ely, on the admission of their son Alwyn into that
                    monastery. After the subjugation of the Isle of Ely William erected a strong
                    castle at Wisbech to hold the district in subjection. At Domesday the manor was
                    held by the abbot of Ely, and possessed extensive fisheries, especially of eels.
                    In 1190 Richard I. granted to the tenants of the manor exemption from tolls at
                    all fairs and markets in England, a privilege confirmed by King John, who in
                    1216 visited the town. In 1236 the town and a great part of the castle was
                    destroyed by an inundation, and the castle lay in ruins till the 15th century,
                    when Morton, bishop of Ely, erected a new building of brick for an episcopal
                    residence. In the reign of Elizabeth it was appropriated to the confinement of
                    state prisoners, among others of Robert Catesby. During the Protectorate it was
                    purchased by Thurloe, afterwards secretary of state, who in 1660 erected an
                    entirely new one from designs of Inigo Jones, when some Roman bricks were
                    discovered. On the Restoration it again came into the possession of the bishops
                    of Ely, who sold it in 1793, and all remains of it have now disappeared.
                    Anciently the town possessed eight guilds in addition to that of the Holy
                    Trinity, to which they were subordinate. This guild received royal sanction from
                    Richard II. in 1393, and held its last meeting in 1557. The town received a
                    charter of incorporation from Edward VI. in 1549, which was renewed by James I.
                    in 1611, and confirmed by Charles II. in 1669, remaining in force till the
                    passing of the Municipal Act.</p>
                <p>See watson <hi rend="superscript"> -</hi> s <hi rend="italic">Historical Account
                        of Wisbech,</hi> 1827; <hi rend="italic">History of Wisbech,</hi> 1833; and
                    “Wisbech Castle,” in <hi rend="italic">Journal of Brit. Arch. Assoc.,</hi>
                    1879.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
