<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0708-6398-0251-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DUDLEY, Edmund (7th edition, volume 8, page
                    251)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cm39">Lawyers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kd1qn6g">Crowns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t18v">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pk7k">Museums</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106173">Saxons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198488">Dodo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:994346">Lawyers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:884318">Crowns</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193326398?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DUDLEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Edmund</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated lawyer and statesman in the reign of Henry VI1., who with Sir Richard
                    Ľmpson, another lawyer of the same stamp, assisted in filling that rapacious
                    monarch’s coffers by arbitrary prosecutions of the people on old penal statutes.
                    Dudley and Empson were beheaded on the accession of Henry VIII. in order to
                    pacify the clamours of the people for justice.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dudley,</hi><hi rend="italic">John,</hi> Duke of
                    Northumberland, son of the above, a statesman memorable in the English history
                    for his unsuccessful attempt to place the crown on the head of his
                    daughter-in-law, Lady Jane Grey, who fell a victim to his ambition, was born in
                    1502, and beheaded in 1553. Ambrose, his eldest son, was a brave general and
                    able statesman under Queen Elizabeth, and received the appellation of “the good
                    Earl of Warwick.” Henry, the duke’s second son, was killed at the siege of St
                    Quintin. Robert, the third son, a man of bad character, was created Earl of
                    Leicester, and became one of Queen Elizabeth’s favourites. His fourth son was
                    the unfortunate Lord Guildford Dudley, whose only crime was his being the
                    husband of Lady Jane Grey, an offence for which he was beheaded in 1554.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dudley,</hi><hi rend="italic">Sir Robert,</hi> as he was
                    called in England, and, as he was styled abroad, <hi rend="italic">Earl of
                    Warwick and Duke of</hi><hi rend="italic">Northumberland,</hi> was the son of
                    Robert above mentioned, by the Lady Douglas Sheffield, and born at Sheen in
                    Surrey in 1573, where he was carefully concealed, in order to prevent the queen
                    acquiring a knowledge of the earl’s engagement with his mother. He was entered
                    of Christ Church, Oxford, where he remained some time. In 1588 his father died,
                    and left him, after the decease of his uncle Ambrose, his castle of Kenilworth,
                    the lordships of Denbigh and Chirk, and the bulk of his estate, which before he
                    was of age he in a great measure enjoyed, notwithstanding the enmity borne him
                    by the Countess Dowager of Leicester. He was at this time one of the finest
                    gentlemen in England; and having a particular turn for navigation, he fitted out
                    a small squadron at his own expense, with which he sailed to the river Orinoco,
                    and took and destroyed nine sail of Spanish ships. In 1595 he attended the Earl
                    of Essex and the lord high admiral of England in their expedition against the
                    Spaniards, and, for his gallant behaviour at the taking of Cadiz, he received
                    the honour of knighthood. He now endeavoured to prove the legitimacy of his
                    birth, in order to be entitled to his hereditary honours. But being overpowered
                    by the interest of the Countess Dowager of Leicester, he applied for a license
                    to travel; and being well received at the court of Florence, he resolved to
                    continue there, notwithstanding his receiving a letter of recall; upon which his
                    whole estate was seized by King James I. and vested in the crown. At the court
                    of Cosmo II. great duke of Tuscany, he discovered those great abilities for
                    which he had been admired in England, and was at length made chamberlain to his
                    serene highness’s consort. Whilst in this situation, he contrived several
                    methods of improving shipping; introduced new manufactures; and by other
                    services obtained so high a reputation that, at the desire of the archduchess,
                    the Emperor Ferdinand, in 1620, created him a duke of the holy Roman empire. He
                    afterwards drained a vast tract of morass between Pisa and the sea, and raised
                    Leghorn, which was then a mean and insignificant place, into a large and
                    beautiful town, improving the haven by a mole, which rendered it both safe and
                    commodious; and having engaged his highness to declare it a free port, he by his
                    influence and correspondence drew many English merchants to settle and set up
                    houses there, which proved of very great service to his native country, as well
                    as to the Spaniards. He was also the patron of learned men, and held a high
                    place himself in the republic of letters. His most celebrated work is his <hi
                    rend="italic">Del</hi><hi rend="italic">Arcano</hi><hi rend="italic">del
                    Mare,</hi> Firenze, 1630, 1646, folio. This work, which has always been scarce,
                    has now become extremely rare. There is a copy in the British Museum, dated
                    1661, and called the second edition; but that which we have seen and examined
                    belongs to the Society of Writers to the Signet, Edinburgh, whose valuable and
                    well-selected library contains many works of the greatest merit, and literary
                    gems and rarities. The work, which consists of a collection of tracts,
                    comprehends a great number of projects for the improvement of navigation and
                    commerce, with the charts and plans relative thereto; all of them schemes which,
                    considering the time when they were devised, are quite remarkable for the
                    boldness and originality with which they are conceived, and the extent of
                    scientific acquirements which they exhibit.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Dudley,</hi> a large town of the hundred of Halfshire, in
                    the county of Worcester, 130 miles from London. It contains two parishes, with
                    their respective churches. The country around it abounds with coal and iron. The
                    chief employment consists in making nails and other hardware. It is a very
                    ancient town, the castle of which is reported to have been built in the seventh
                    century, by a Saxon prince Dodo or Duddo. There is a large market held every
                    Saturday. The inhabitants in 1801 amounted to <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193326411?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0708-6411-0252"/> 10,107, in
                    1811 to 13,925, in 1821 to 18,211, and in 1831 to 23,043.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
