<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0721-0056-0042-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">SWITZERLAND</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140558">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="fast:893284">Diet</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208963">Turkey</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207312">Russia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41n7xp3p">Cimbri</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q23r39q">Franks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649x27">Gall</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p527">Basel</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=56" org="uniform" part="N"
                sample="complete" type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">SWITZERLAND</label>.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Switzerland</hi> is situate in western Europe,
                    having France on the west, Germany on the north, Austria on the east and
                    south-east, and Savoy and Piedmont on the south-west. This country was anciently
                    called Helvetia, from its first known inhabitants: its more modem name is
                    supposed to be derived from the canton of Schwytz, the cradle of Swiss
                    independence. Little is known of the inhabitants of Switzerland till about one
                    hundred years before Christ, when the Cimbri, a race of barbarians inhabiting
                    the northern regions now known as Friesland and Sweden, crossed the Rhine and
                    extended their conquests into Gaul. Several of the Helvetian tribes, tempted by
                    the immense spoils gained by the Cimbri, entered into an alliance with them, and
                    carried their united ravages nearly to the mouths of the Rhone. In this
                    extremity the Gauls applied for assistance to the Romans, who speedily sent a
                    powerful army to their assistance, under the command of the consul Lucius
                    Cassius. This force, however, was suddenly attacked on the banks of the lake of
                    Geneva, by the Tigurini, a tribe of the Helvetii, led by a young general named
                    Divico. The Romans were totally defeated, the consul and his lieutenant Piso
                    left dead on the field, and the survivors only permitted to retreat after they
                    had given hostages and marched under the yoke. Emboldened by this success,
                    Divico rejoined the Cimbri, and with their united forces crossed the Alps and
                    entered Italy itself, where, however, they were defeated by Marius with
                    tremendous slaughter, and the few who escaped sought refuge among the fastnesses
                    of the Helvetian mountains.</p>
                <p part="N">For nearly half a century after this decisive defeat, the Helvetii
                    confined themselves to their own country. But the recollection of the rich
                    pastures and fertile plains of Gaul outlived the terror of the Roman arms, and
                    made them resolve once more to quit their rocky fastnesses. After spending three
                    years in preparation, they set out with their wives and families, cattle and
                    possessions, led by the same Divico who had commanded their fathers fifty years
                    before. The number who marched out on this expedition is computed at 368,000
                    souls, of whom 92,000 were ablebodied warriors.</p>
                <p part="N">The Roman province of Gaul was at that time under the government of
                    Julius Caesar, and that consummate general no sooner heard of the emigration of
                    the Helvetians than he took effectual measures to defeat their plans. After some
                    abortive attempts at negociation, he attacked and defeated them in two
                    engagements with tremendous slaughter. Their strength and spirit were completely
                    broken, and, overwhelmed with shame and grief, their numbers reduced to scarcely
                    110,000, they returned to their desolated country and rebuilt their ruined
                    habitations. In order to watch and overawe them, Caesar erected a fortress at
                    Noviodunum (Nyon), on the banks of the lake of Geneva, and established several
                    other garrisons in different parts of the country.</p>
                <p part="N">The Helvetii were at first the allies of the Roman people, but in the
                    reign of Augustus they were reduced to complete subjection, and their country
                    remained in the condition of a Roman province for upwards of three centuries,
                    and underwent various reverses of fortune, according to the prosperous or
                    adverse fortune of the empire to which it was subject. When the innumerable
                    swarms of barbarians issuing from the unknown regions of the north and east
                    overran Italy and destroyed the Roman empire, Switzerland also became their
                    prey. The Goths established themselves in that portion of the country which
                    bordered on Italy; the Burgundians fixed their residence on both sides of the
                    Jura, on the lake of Geneva, and in the lower Valais, as far as the Aar; and the
                    Allemanni took possession of the country to the eastward of that country, and of
                    great part of Germany.</p>
                <p part="N">After this state of affairs had continued about a century, a new swarm
                    of adventurers obtained the ascendency. These were the Franks, another German
                    race, who, after traversing the Netherlands, gained possession of the whole of
                    Gaul, and pouring their resistless myriads into Switzerland, forcibly
                    dispossessed the inhabitants, and at length, after various changes, succeeded in
                    obtaining exclusive dominion over the whole of Rhaetia and Helvetia. Rhaetia and
                    the country between the lake of Constance and the Rhine, the Aar and St Gothard,
                    in which German was the current language, were united to Suabia, while Geneva,
                    the Valais, Neuchâtel, and the present country of Berne, Soleure, Freyburg, and
                    Vaud, the districts in which Romance was the prevailing language, were united to
                    Savoy, under the denomination of Little Burgundy. The Franks introduced into
                    Helvetia the feudal system and other peculiar institutions and laws of the
                    Germanic tribes. To them also the inhabitants were indebted for the blessings of
                    the Christian religion, which contributed powerfully to the progress of
                    civilization, and the revival of the country from its waste and desolate state.
                    Switzerland remained subject to the Franks till after the death of Charlemagne,
                    when, in consequence of the feuds of that monarch’s successors, the vast empire
                    which he had founded was entirely dismembered, and Switzerland was portioned out
                    among France, Italy, and Germany. But this arrangement was of short duration,
                    for the disorders and confusion produced by the continued wars enabled the
                    provincial governors to throw off all allegiance to their feudal superiors, or
                    to secure real independence while yielding nominal obedience. Switzerland was
                    thus divided into a great number of petty states, generally engaged in
                    hostilities with each other, and seldom uniting among themselves unless when
                    menaced by some great and common danger. Such a case presented itself in the
                        reign<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=61"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0061-0043"/> of the emperor Henry I. surnamed the Fowler.
                    An immense horde of barbarians, known by the name of Hungarians, issued from the
                    east and the shores of the Black Sea, and overran Italy and Germany, burning and
                    destroying wherever they came. In order to protect the inhabitants from the fury
                    of these ruthless invaders, Henry built walls around a number of defensible
                    places, to which all, in case of need, might fly for the security of their lives
                    and property. In this manner Zurich, St Gall, Basel, and various other places,
                    rose from petty hamlets to towns of considerable strength and numerous
                    population. About the same period the bailifs of the emperor built and fortified
                    Berne, Freyburg, and various other towns. A ninth of the free and nobler class
                    of inhabitants were required to occupy these national fortresses, and they
                    received the same political organization and rights as the more ancient cities
                    of Germany. This was the first foundation of the class of burghers, who in
                    process of time came to be a third estate in the kingdom. In proportion as the
                    wealth and importance of the towns augmented, the citizens were eager to extend
                    their rights and privileges. They availed themselves of every opportunity to
                    purchase their emancipation from the feudal dominion of the bishops, abbots, and
                    monasteries, to whose authority they had long been subjected; and in a short
                    time the burghers were able to bid defiance to the nobles, and even to balance
                    the political weight of the clergy.</p>
                <p part="N">The affairs of Switzerland continued in this state without any material
                    alteration until the year 1290, when Rudolp of Hapsburg, whose castle was
                    situated in the canton of the Aar, and who, besides possessing manorial rights
                    and great influence in Schwytz, had held the office of imperial bailif of
                    several towns, was elected emperor of Germany. This prince, though inhabiting a
                    distant country, continued throughout his life to be strongly attached to
                    Switzerland. He conferred new honours on its nobles, and granted additional
                    privileges to its towns, or confirmed those which they already enjoyed. Rudolp
                    was succeeded by his son Albert, whose ambition and rapacity soon alienated the
                    affections of both his German and his Swiss subjects. Two of the imperial
                    bailifs, Herman Gessler and Berin-guer of Landenberg, who were appointed over
                    the Waldstätten (the three cantons of Schwytz, Unterwalden, and Uri), subjected
                    the inhabitants to every species of insolence and oppression. Gessler, in
                    particular, was guilty of so many acts of wanton cruelty that he was at length
                    put to deatli by the famous William Tell, w ho thus paved the way for the
                    deliverance of his countrymen. Three patriots, whose names are still revered
                    throughout the republic, Werner from the canton of Schwytz, Walter Hurst from
                    Uri, and Arnold from Unterwalden, formed a conspiracy against the Austrian
                    governors; and their measures were concerted with such wisdom, and executed with
                    so much courage and intrepidity, that they obtained possession of every fortress
                    of any considerable strength or importance. The three cantons formerly mentioned
                    having thus achieved their independence, held a meeting on the 7th of January
                    1315, and laid the foundation of the Swiss confederation. Shortly after this
                    revolt of the forest cantons, the emperor Albert was murdered by his nephew and
                    some other nobles; but his son Duke Leopold marched against the cantons with a
                    powerful army. The Schwytzers waited his arrival at Morgarten, on the slope of
                    the mountain Sattel, and, notwithstanding the disparity of their forces, routed
                    the Austrians with great slaughter; and it was with no small difficulty that the
                    duke himself escaped, leaving most of his officers and an immense number of his
                    soldiers dead upon the field.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1332 the inhabitants of Lucerne formed a perpetual league with the
                    Waldstätten; and in 1351 the citizens of Zürich, having thrown off the yoke of
                    the aristocracy, joined the Swiss republic, and on account of the power and
                    wealth of the town it was promoted to the chief rank. Zug joined the
                    confederation in 1352, and Berne in the following year. To the latter, in
                    consideration of its importance, was assigned the second place of
                    precedence.</p>
                <p part="N">Duke Leopold III. of Austria viewed the extending confederation with
                    jealousy and alarm, and various quarrels having taken place between him and the
                    cantons, hostilities were at length commenced. The duke, with a numerous force,
                    chiefly composed of cavalry, marched rapidly towards the interior of the
                    country, and on the 9th of July 1386 encountered the Swiss in the neighbourhood
                    of Sempech. The battle was long and fiercely contested, but at length the Swiss
                    patriots gained a complete victory; the duke himself was slain, and more than
                    600 of the higher and lower nobility, with about 2000 of their less
                    distinguished adherents, were left dead on the field.</p>
                <p part="N">Two years after the battle of Sempech, the Austrians stormed Naefels, a
                    small town in the canton of Glaris. The garrison retreated from the town as far
                    as Mount Rute, where they took up a strong position, and awaited the approach of
                    the enemy. The Austrians maintained the fight for some time with great ardour,
                    but were in the end overthrown and put to flight. The bridge of Weser was broken
                    down by the weight of the fugitives, and above 3000 common soldiers, and 183
                    knights, were slain in the battle, or drowned in the lake and in the river.
                    These defeats induced Duke Leopold IV. to enter into a truce with the cantons
                    for seven years, during which the Swiss contrived by various means to extend
                    their territory and to increase their power.</p>
                <p part="N">With the exception of the disputes which took place between the people
                    of the canton Appenzell, and of the Valais and Rhaetian Alps, with their lords,
                    and of the civil war which arose between Zürich and Schwytz relative to the
                    right to some lands, no event of much importance occurred in the history of
                    Switzerland till the year 1474, when Louis XI. of France induced the Swiss to
                    make a diversion in his favour, by falling on the territory of Charles the Bold,
                    duke of Burgundy, who had advanced to the very walls of Paris, and threatened
                    Louis with the loss of his throne. This unprovoked attack induced the duke to
                    offer terms of peace to the king of France, and the emperor of Germany, with
                    whom he was at the same time at war; and these monarchs accepted his offer,
                    leaving their late allies to meet his whole vengeance as they best might. Peace
                    was no sooner concluded, than Charles determined to inflict condign punishment
                    on them for their unjustifiable aggression, and in the spring of 1476 crossed
                    the Jura with an army of sixty thousand men. He encountered the army of the
                    confederates near the town of Grandson, and after a desperate conflict was
                    totally defeated with the loss of a thousand men. His camp, with an immense
                    booty, fell into the hands of the Swiss. A few months after, he was defeated,
                    with prodigious slaughter, in a second action, near the little town of Morat;
                    and two years later, when the duke was slain in the battle of Nancy, the
                    Burgundians paid the confederates the sum of 150,000 florins to make peace with
                    them.</p>
                <p part="N">These repeated victories procured for the Swiss the reputation of being
                    the best soldiers in Europe; and a considerable number of them were hired to
                    fight the battles of foreigners. The sudden wealth acquired by plunder and
                    pensions excited its possessors to profusion and extravagance; their morals
                    became corrupted, and the simple republican spirit almost disappeared. A spirit
                    of cupidity and pride displayed itself among the rulers, and dissipation and
                    love of plunder among the people; and the Swiss became notorious throughout
                    Europe as the hirelings of any potentate who had battles to fight and gold to
                    squander. Domestic troubles and feuds generally prevailed; the peace and
                    security of the country were disturbed to such a degree by an armed and
                    desperate banditti of disbanded soldiers and idle vagabonds, that in 1480,
                    during the short<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=62"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0062-0044"/> space of three months, nearly 1500 assassins
                    and robbers were condemned to death.</p>
                <p part="N">The confederates had been faithfully supported in their wars by the
                    towns of Freyburg and Soleure, and in 1481 these requested to be admitted into
                    the confederation. Their request was warmly supported by the town cantons; but
                    the mountaineers of the forest cantons objected to it, and the dispute ran so
                    high, that at a general congress of all the confederates, the deputies were at
                    the point of coming to blows, and the confederation was threatened with
                    dissolution. This catastrophe was happily averted by the eloquent remonstrances
                    of a pious hermit, called Nicholas Laven-brugen. His simple but pathetic appeal
                    had the effect of removing their differences, and Soleure and Freyburg were
                    received into the Swiss confederation.</p>
                <p part="N">In the year 1497, the Grisons entered into a treaty offensive and
                    defensive with the confederate cantons. This alliance gave great offence to the
                    emperor Maximilian, who immediately collected his troops, and marched both
                    against the Grisons and their Swiss allies. Battle after battle took place, in
                    all of which the Austrians were defeated; and the emperor having lost 20,000 of
                    his troops in eight months, and finding further exertions useless, concluded a
                    peace with the Swiss at Basel in September 1499, by which he acknowledged their
                    unconditional independence as a nation. This war, called the Suabian war, was
                    the last the Swiss had to sustain for their independence. For three centuries
                    after this date no farther attempts were made against the liberties of the Swiss
                    cantons, which assumed their station as an independent power in Europe. The
                    towns of Basel and Schaffhausen were received into the confederation in 1501,
                    and Appenzell was added in 1513, and completed the number of thirteen cantons,
                    which have constituted the Helvetic body till within our own times, namely,
                    Zürich; Schwytz, Uri, Unterwalden, the three Waldstätten or forest cantons;
                    Lucerne, Claris, Zug, Berne, Freyburg, Soleure, Basel, Schaffhausen, and
                    Appenzell. Besides these, there were various confederates and associates who
                    were in alliance with the cantons, and entitled to assistance in case of foreign
                    attack. These were the abbot of St Gall, the city of the same name, the towns of
                    Mulhausen and Bienne, the Grisons and the Valais, the republic of Geneva, and
                    the county of Neuchâtel.</p>
                <p part="N">Switzerland had scarcely obtained rest from her political wars, when
                    religious disputes arose among the cantons, and converted into fierce enemies
                    those who had lately fought side by side in defence of their liberties. The
                    unscrupulous sale of indulgences by the agents of Pope Leo X. in Germany,
                    Switzerland, and the other countries, led to a searching inquiry into the whole
                    of the papal system, and caused vast multitudes to renounce altogether the
                    authority of the church of Rome. In no country did the doctrines of the
                    Reformation create a greater excitement, or meet with more zealous supporters,
                    than in Switzerland. The inhabitants of Zürich, Berne, Schaffhausen, Basel, St
                    Gall, and the Grisons, as well as of many parts in the neighbourhood of Geneva
                    and Neuchâtel, eagerly adopted the opinions of Calvin and Zuinglius, while the
                    people of the Waldstätten, and of Soleure and Freyburg, being more secluded and
                    ignorant, and more under the control of the priests, continued staunch in their
                    support of the papal authority. Fierce animosities speedily arose between the
                    reformed and the popish cantons, and various sanguinary wars were carried on for
                    many years. During these internal broils, the territory of the confederation was
                    violated and their rights infringed without remonstrance; and such was the
                    divided state of the cantons, that Austria, their ancient enemy, might easily
                    have subdued them, but for the jealousy of the other great powers. To prevent
                    this danger, they, in concluding the treaty of Westphalia in 1648, formally
                    recognised the independence of the Swiss confede ration. But though Switzerland
                    was thus secured against the invasion of any of the greater powers, it continued
                    to be torn by internal dissensions. The arbitrary manner in which the large
                    towns levied taxes upon the people of the country, and of the smaller towns and
                    villages, caused great dissatisfaction, especially in the territories of Berne
                    and Lucerne, and at length the peasantry rose up in rebellion against their
                    rulers; and it was not until after considerable bloodshed that the revolt was
                    quelled, and several of the chiefs who were taken alive were tried, condemned,
                    and executed. Scarcely had this insurrection terminated when religious quarrels
                    again broke out between the Protestants and the Romanists. Till near the close
                    of the seventeenth century, Switzerland was distracted by the dissensions
                    arising from this cause; and in 1703, the whole of the Protestant and of the
                    Catholic cantons were openly arrayed against each other, and a civil war of
                    several years’ duration ensued. The immediate cause of the war was a quarrel
                    between the people of Toggenburg and their superior the abbot of St Gall, who
                    had endeavoured in a fraudulent manner to deprive them of their privileges.
                    Zürich and Berne took part with the people, while the Catholic cantons espoused
                    the cause of the abbot. Several battles were fought, and at length an army of
                    Catholics, 12,000 in number, encountered 8000 Bernois at Villmergen. The
                    conflict lasted six hours, and in the end the Catholics were completely routed,
                    leaving 2000 of their number dead upon the field. A peace was soon after
                    concluded on terms advantageous to the victors.</p>
                <p part="N">From this period till towards the close of the eighteenth century, the
                    state of Switzerland underwent no material alteration; and their internal
                    discord paved the way for external aggression, and rendered them an easy prey to
                    the grasping ambition of the French republic,. In 1797, the French government,
                    which had previously interfered in the affairs of Switzerland, manifested a
                    determination to take possession of that country, and evidently sought for a
                    pretence to come to an open rupture. The Swiss government placed their only hope
                    in a passive neutrality, which in the end proved their ruin. For the sake of
                    peace they submitted with the utmost servility to the imperious and insulting
                    demands of the directory; but their humiliation did not save them from
                    destruction. The emissaries of France laboured but too successfully to incite
                    dissensions among the people, and the French rulers made these dissensions a
                    pretext for their interference with the constitution of the country. In this way
                    the bailiwicks of Valtelina, Chiavenna, and Bormio, which had been for centuries
                    dependent on the Grisons, were incorporated with the Cisalpine republic.
                    Insurrections broke out in several of the cantons, and were rendered triumphant
                    by the assistance of the French arms. The inhabitants of Berne, Soleure,
                    Freyburg, and especially of the Waldstätten, made a brave but ineffectual stand
                    in defence of their rights and liberties. The most horrible excesses were
                    committed by the French soldiers; the towns were successively rifled of their
                    public property, and great part of the country was laid waste, and many of the
                    inhabitants reduced to utter destitution. A new constitution was framed by the
                    French directory, which provided that Switzerland should form a single republic,
                    one and indivisible, under a central government to be established at Aarau. The
                    country was divided into twenty-two cantons, and the supreme authority was
                    committed to two councils and an executive directory, in whom was vested the
                    appointment of prefects and other authorities for the various cantons, which
                    were thus transformed into departments, with the loss of their independence as
                    separate states. After this new constitution was established, a treaty was made
                    with France, by one of the articles of which the Swiss republic was bound to
                    furnish to its new ally a force of 18,000 men; and thus all the miseries of the
                        conscription<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=63"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0063-0045"/> were made familiar to the Swiss, as they had
                    previously been to the French population. Great miseries were suffered by the
                    people, from the excesses of every kind committed by the French troops, and
                    their heavy requisitions and exactions. The small canton of Unterwalden refused
                    to swear fidelity to the new constitution of the Helvetic republic, but after a
                    desperate struggle it was subdued; the inhabitants were massacred without
                    distinction of sex or age; and that district, once peaceful and happy, was left
                    a scene of horrible desolation. During the campaign of 1799, Switzerland was the
                    theatre of the struggle between the great powers of Austria, Russia, and France.
                    The mountain cantons were in consequence utterly ruined, a considerable part of
                    the country rendered uncultivated, and the population reduced to little short of
                    actual starvation. The Helvetic directory was suppressed in 1800, and an
                    executive commission substituted in its room; and about seven months after, this
                    commission dissolved the councils and convoked a new legislature. A general diet
                    was called in September 1801, for the purpose of re-organizing the constitution
                    of the country. Meanwhile the treaty which was signed at Luneville between
                    France and Austria, guaranteed the independence of the Helvetic republic, and
                    the French troops were consequently ordered to evacuate Switzerland. Their
                    departure was the signal for a general revolt. All the old factions were
                    awakened afresh. The Pays de Vaud formed itself into a single republic; Uri,
                    Schwytz, and Unterwalden took up arms against the Helvetian government; and the
                    towns of Zürich, Basel, and Schaffhausen renounced their allegiance. A civil war
                    appeared inevitable, when Napoleon Bonaparte offered himself as arbitrator
                    between the contending parties, and ordered Marshal Ney to advance with a body
                    of troops to the frontiers of Switzerland to enforce compliance with his
                    mandates. The existing government was dissolved, a provisional government
                    established, and deputies from all the cantons were ordered to assemble at Paris
                    to deliberate upon a constitution for their country. Several months were spent
                    in debates; and Napoleon, after he had heard and reflected on their
                    representations, promulgated an act of mediation, which appears to have been
                    drawn up with a view of reconciling opposite factions, and of fairly meeting
                    various interests. It restored the old federative system, but introduced very
                    considerable improvements. The act of mediation was promulgated 19th February
                    1803; and the Helvetic general government having been dissolved, and the new
                    constitution put in force, the French troops finally evacuated the country.</p>
                <p part="N">From that time till 1814 Switzerland enjoyed internal peace; and during
                    the gigantic wars which at that momentous period raged throughout Europe, this
                    country rested in security amid the din of battles and the crash of falling
                    empires, and made rapid progress in the arts of industry, and in the career of
                    intellectual and social improvement. On the downfall of Napoleon the act of
                    mediation was dissolved. The integrity of the country was guaranteed by the
                    congress of Vienna in 1815. The territories formerly dependent on the bishop of
                    Basel, which had been annexed to France, together with Valais, Neuchâtel, and
                    Geneva, were ceded to it as new cantons, and a constitution, based on the act of
                    mediation, was framed for the whole cantons, now amounting to twenty-two. On the
                    7th of August 1815 the federal compact was finally signed by all the deputies in
                    the diet assembled at Zürich. The deputies then repaired in procession to the
                    cathedral, where they bound themselves by a solemn oath, and in the name of
                    their constituents, to the faithful observance of its enactments.</p>
                <p part="N">During the fifteen years which elapsed from 1815 to 1830, Switzerland
                    enjoyed profound tranquillity. The general condition of the country was
                    prosperous, and education was improved in several districts; but the civil and
                    criminal laws remained in a defective state; the press was under a strict
                    censorship, and various anomalies existed in the institutions of many of the
                    cantons. Petitions were from time to time presented for the revision of the
                    constitution of 1814, but were everywhere rejected by the councils. The first
                    alteration of this state of things took place in the canton of Ticino in May and
                    June 1830, and the example was speedily followed by all the other representative
                    cantons of Switzerland. The new constitution established equality of political
                    rights among all the citizens of the state; the direct system of electing all
                    the members of the legislature, the elections to take place every four years;
                    separation of the three powers, legislative, executive, and judicial; publicity
                    of debates; liberty of the press, subject to fixed laws against libels;
                    inviolability of person and property, and the right of petition. No tax can be
                    imposed unless it is sanctioned by a majority of two thirds in the great
                    council. The present constitution cannot be modified until twelve years shall
                    have elapsed from its enactment, and then any alterations proposed in it must be
                    submitted to the approval of the primary assemblies of the people. These
                    alterations in their constitution were peaceably adopted by the most of the
                    cantons; but in some of them popular tumults arose, which however were speedily
                    suppressed by the firmness and prudence of the diet.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1834 the tranquility of Switzerland was endangered by a considerable
                    body of Polish, German, and Italian refugees, who had taken up their residence
                    in Switzerland. In the month of January, some hundreds of these refugees made a
                    sudden attack on the dominions of the king of Sardinia, in expectation of
                    combined attacks and insurrections in other parts of the Sardinian monarchy. The
                    Sardinian government made strong remonstrances to the confederation concerning
                    this violation of the neutrality of the Swiss territory; and the courts of
                    Austria, Prussia, and other German states, whose territories border on
                    Switzerland, joined in these remonstrances. After some negociations, the matter
                    was brought to an amicable termination by the Swiss governments promising in
                    future to send away from their territory all those who sliould attempt to
                    disturb the tranquillity of the states.</p>
                <p part="N">An attempt was made in the diet of 1832, and again in that of 1834, to
                    procure a revision of the federal pact, but it terminated without any result.
                    The last eight years have been years of severe trial for Switzerland, but she
                    has safely passed through them, and has succeeded in maintaining both lier
                    internal tranquillity and her external independence.</p>
                <p part="N">Switzerland lies between 45° 50' and 47° 40' north latitude, and 6° and
                    10° 30' east longitude. Its extent from east to west is about 210 miles, and
                    from north to south about 130 miles. Its area is estimated to contain about
                    11,000 square geographical miles. Switzerland forms part of the high land of
                    central Europe. It rises above the plains of Lombardy on the south, and the
                    plains of Dijon or Burgundy on the west. On the east it is connected by the Alps
                    with the high lands of Tyrol and Bavaria, and on the north it adjoins the
                    elevated plain of Suabia; from which it is separated only by the bed of the
                    Rhine. It is bounded by mountains on the west, south-west, and east, but is open
                    to the north on the side of Germany. The lower parts of Switzerland are
                    generally more than 1200 feet above the level of the sea, and nearly 1000 feet
                    higher than the plains of Lombardy, but the greater part of the surface is much
                    higher. In point of romantic and picturesque scenery, Switzerland is reckoned
                    the finest country in Europe. It is a singular assemblage of high mountains,
                    deep valleys, rivers, and lakes. Two distinct ranges of mountains traverse
                    Switzerland; the chain of the Jura, which stretches from south-west to
                    north-east, and is about 240 or 250 miles in length, and from thirty-five to
                    forty in breadth; and the chain of the Alps, which is much more extensive, and
                    covers the greater part of the country with its nume-<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=64" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0064-0046"
                    /> rous branches. The former occupies the western part of Switzerland,
                    stretching from near the western extremity of the lake of Geneva along the
                    boundary between France and the Pays de Vaud, and then enters the canton of
                    Neuchâtel, which it almost entirely covers, as well as the north-west part of
                    Berne and the greater part of Soleure and Basel, and the north-west part of
                    Aargau. The range of the Jura is divided from the mountains of the Black Forest
                    by the vale of the Rhine; and its eastern boundary is marked by the lakes of
                    Neuchâtel and Bienne, and the valley of the Lower Aar from the confluence of the
                    Thiele to the junction of the Aar with the Rhine. The Jura consists of several
                    parallel ridges, of which the most eastern is generally the highest. It is
                    precipitous and abrupt towards Switzerland, but becomes gradually lower on the
                    side of France. It does not attain above one third of the height of the Alps,
                    its principal summit in Switzerland being from 5500 to 5300 feet high, but in
                    proportion to its height it is colder than the region of the Alps. The valleys
                    formed by the Jura run parallel with the direction of the chain, are narrow and
                    short, and some of them very elevated and cold. The Jura is principally formed
                    by calcareous rocks of a grayish ash or bluish colour, and in some places mixed
                    with marble.</p>
                <p part="N">The great chain of the Alps forms the highest part of the continent. The
                    main ridge, called the Pennine Alps, forms the boundary between Switzerland and
                    Italy, and separates the basin of the Upper Rhone on the north from that of the
                    Po on the south. To the south of Mont Blanc the Alps consist of a single chain,
                    with many lateral projections or spurs, chiefly on the west side. Eastward they
                    are divided into two great ranges, which enclose the valley of the Upper Rhone,
                    and meet at Mount St Gothard, which may be regarded as the centre of the Alpine
                    system of Swit-zcrland. Four ranges diverge from this point; the Bernese Alps to
                    the west; the Alps of Glaris; and the northern Grisons to the north-east; the
                    south-east branch, which forms the southern boundary of the Grisons on the side
                    of Italy; and the south-west branch, which connects the St Gothard with the
                    Pennine Alps. Between these ranges there are four large valleys, those of the
                    Rhone, the Reuss, the Upper Rhine, and the Ticino. To the north-east of the
                    group of St Gothard is the country of the Grisons, the whole surface of which is
                    studded with elevated ridges and peaks. In this Alpine region there are not less
                    than sixty deep valleys. The mean breadth of the highest portion of the Alps
                    does not exceed 100 miles, but it widens considerably as they proceed eastward.
                    (For an account of these mountain masses, their geology, climate, and natural
                    history, see <hi rend="smallcaps">Alps.)</hi></p>
                <p part="N">North of the Alpine region and east of the Jura lies the table-land of
                    Switzerland, which is the finest and most productive of the whole. It slopes
                    from south to north, from the foot of the Alps to the Rhine and the lake of
                    Constance, and includes the cantons of Vaud and Freyburg, the greater part of
                    Berne, Lucerne, and Aargau, the whole of Zürich, Zug, Thurgau, and part of St
                    Gall. The elevation of the table-land varies from 1200 to 1800 feet above the
                    sea. Its surface is furrowed by numerous valleys, which generally run from
                    south-east to north-west. Each of these valleys is divided by its river, and
                    various ranges of wooded hills follow the course of the streams.</p>
                <p part="N">The Rhine, the chief river of Switzerland, is formed by the streams
                    which rise in the Alps of the Grisons, and receive the waters of all the
                    glaciers of that lofty region. After leaving the country of the Grisons, it
                    receives on its left bank the Tamina from the canton of St Gall, and on its
                    right bank the Ill from the Austrian territory. It then flows through or rather
                    forms the lakes of Constance and Untersee. On issuing from the latter, at the
                    town of Stein, it flows in a general west direction, but by a tortuous course,
                    as far as Basel, forming the natural boundary of Switzer land on the north side
                    for a direct distance of about seventy miles. By means of the Thur, the Aar, and
                    the Birs, it receives the waters of three fourths of Switzerland. At Basel the
                    Rhine is about 500 feet broad; here it turns to the north, and soon after leaves
                    the Swiss territory. The Rhone is formed by different streams from Mount Furca,
                    at the north-eastern extremity of the Valais, at the height of 5500 feet above
                    the sea. Descending rapidly to Oberwald, it proceeds in a south-west direction
                    as far as Martigny, where it turns abruptly to the north-west, and continues in
                    that course to its entrance into lake Leman. It issues out of this lake again at
                    Geneva, below which it receives the Arve from the valley of Chamouny, and quits
                    the Swiss territory near Chanci, the last village of the canton of Geneva. The
                    Inn descends from Mount Bermina. The Adda rises from the base of Mount Gallo,
                    and falls into the lake of Como. The Ticino issues from Mount Gries, and
                    traverses the lake Maggiore in Italy. The Aar flows through the lakes of Brientz
                    and Thun, and forms lofty cataracts before its junction with the Rhine. The
                    Limmat, a rapid stream, which rises in the Alpsof Glaris, flows through the lake
                    of Wallerstadt: after marking the limits between the Schwytz and St Gall it
                    forms the lake of Zürich, and, flowing through part of the cantons of Zürich and
                    Aargau, enters the Aar below the confluence of the Reuss. The Thur rises in the
                    mountains of High Toggenburg, in the canton of St Gall, and enters the Rhine
                    below Rheinau.</p>
                <p part="N">The Leman lake, or lake of Geneva, the great reservoir of the Rhone,
                    spreads in the form of a crescent, its northern bank being about fifty-four
                    miles in length, and its southern bank about forty-six. Its breadth near the
                    middle is about nine miles, but it becomes much narrower towards Geneva. The
                    surface of the lake is 1200 feet above the level of the sea. Its greatest depth
                    is about 1800 feet, and its area 340 square miles. It receives several streams,
                    the principal of which are the Dranse from the Alps of Savoy, and the Vevayse
                    and Venoge from the Swiss side. Lake Leman is known to have been frozen over
                    only twice, in <hi rend="smallcaps">a. d</hi>. 762 and 805. The lake of
                    Constance, or Boden See, is about forty-five miles long and ten miles wide. Its
                    area is about 290 square miles, and its greatest depth is 1800 feet. One or two
                    steam-boats run upon the lake of Constance. The Waldstätten See, or lake of the
                    four cantons, is about twenty-six miles in length. The southern part of it,
                    called the lake of Uri, is a sheet of deep water, eight miles long and between
                    one and two broad, running from south to north between two ranges of mountains
                    almost perpendicular; a narrow channel unites it with the middle basin, which is
                    about nine miles in length and about two wide. Another narrow strait leads from
                    the middle into the western basin, called the lake of Lucerne, which is the
                    widest and finest of the three. The lake is about 1400 feet above the level of
                    the sea, and its greatest depth is 1000 feet. The country around the Waldstätten
                    See is the cradle of Swiss independence, and is full of recollections of the
                    exploits of its heroes. A steam-boat plies between Lucerne and Fluellen, the
                    port of Altorf. The lake of Zurich, formed by the Limmat, is twenty-four miles
                    long, and from one mile to two miles wide. Its greatest depth is 600 feet, and
                    its surface is about 1300 feet above the level of the sea. A steam-boat plies on
                    this lake between Zürich and Rapperswyl. The lake of Neuchâtel is about
                    twenty-five miles in length, and five miles broad throughout one half of its
                    length. It is about 1400 feet above the sea, and its greatest depth is about 350
                    feet. A steam-boat plies daily on this lake. Besides these there are several
                    other lakes of considerable dimensions, such as the lake of Wallerstadt, formed
                    by the Limmat, eleven miles in length, and the lakes of Brientz and Thun, both
                    formed by the Aar; the latter thirteen miles long, its greatest depth 800 feet,
                    and more than 1900<pb break="no" facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=65"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0721-0065-0047"/> feet above the sea. A steam-boat plies on
                    this lake, which is much visited by tourists from Berne. The fish which these
                    lakes contain are pike, trout, salmon, lato, and umber, a very delicate fish,
                    occasionally exported to Paris, and sold at a very high price.</p>
                <p part="N">The minerals and metals most abundant in Switzerland are porphyry,
                    marble, and alabaster; iron, lead, zinc, cobalt, and bismuth. Arsenic and
                    antimony are found in veins and in masses, rock-crystals are very common,
                    sulphur is collected in many places, and particles of gold are found in the
                    sands of some rivers, as the Rhine, the Aar, the Adda, and the Reuss; strata of
                    bituminous wood are worked in several valleys, and the inhabitants use it for
                    fuel.</p>
                <p part="N">Switzerland contains a greater number of mineral springs than any other
                    country in Europe. The most frequented of these are the springs at Pfeffers and
                    Leuk. The acidulated springs of St Maurice, in the canton of the Grisons, the
                    baths of Gurnigel in Berne, and those at Baden, are also well known.</p>
                <p part="N">Switzerland is the central point where three great European races and
                    languages meet, and is not more remarkable for the variety of its physical
                    features, than for the moral and religious diversities of its population. The
                    Deutsch or German Swiss occupy the cantons of Zurich, Lucerne, Uri, Schwytz,
                    Unterwalden, Glaris, Zug, Appenzell, St Gall, Thurgau, Schaffhausen, and Aargau,
                    a great part of Basel and Berne, a considerable portion of Soleure, Freyburg,
                    Valais, and Grisons, some communes of the canton of Vaud, and the commune of
                    Bosco in the canton of Ticino, forming about two thirds of the whole population
                    of Switzerland. The French Swiss occupy the cantons of Neuchâtel and Geneva,
                    nearly the whole of Vaud, part of Freyburg, Soleure, and Valais, and the Jura
                    portions of Basel and Berne, and form about one fifth of the entire population.
                    The Italian Swiss inhabit the canton of Ticino, some valleys of the Grisons, and
                    a few places in the Valais. To these are to be added the Romans or Rhse-tians,
                    who are found in small numbers in the Grisons, the Oberland, towards the sources
                    of the Rhine, and the upper part of the Engardine. Their language more nearly
                    resembles Latin, or ancient Roman, than that of their Italian neighbours.</p>
                <p part="N">Before 1798 Switzerland consisted of a confederation of states of three
                    very different kinds: 1. Thirteen cantons; 2. the subjects or vassals of these
                    cantons; and, 3. the allies of these cantons. The federal bond which united the
                    various cantons and their allies was very loose. There was not in Switzerland
                    any permanent sovereign body, or central government, or standing federal
                    magistrate, equally acknowledged by all. No important question could be decided
                    in the general diets, unless it had been previously debated and decided on in
                    the councils of each of the cantons. The cantons were not even allied to all;
                    the three forest cantons alone were allied to every one of the other cantons.
                    The subjects of the Swiss were either subjects of certain particular cantons, or
                    common bailiwicks subject to all the cantons. The whole population of the
                    thirteen cantons at the close of last century was about 1,000,000; that of their
                    subjects was about 250,000; and that of their associates and confederates, and
                    the subjects of these confederates, amounted to nearly half a million more.
                    Altogether the territory belonging to the Helvetic federal body contained a
                    population of about 1,700,000.</p>
                <p part="N">Switzerland now forms a confederation of twenty-two cantons, united for
                    the defence of their common liberty and independence, and security against
                    attacks from abroad, as well as for the preservation of order and tranquillity
                    in the interior. They guarantee each other reciprocally their respective
                    territories. For these purposes a contingent of troops is furnished by each
                    canton when required, in the proportion of one to fifty of its population; and a
                    pecuniary quota, for defraying the military and other general expenses of the
                    confederacy, is paid by each canton in proportion to its property and resources.
                    A war-fund is also formed to meet exigencies; and for this purpose a federal
                    duty is levied on foreign goods imported into Switzerland which are not articles
                    of first necessity. The diet fixes the tariff as well as the rates to be paid by
                    each canton. The united federal contingents of all the cantons, which must be
                    disciplined and furnished with clothes and arms, ready to march when required,
                    amount to about 34,000 men, and the reserve, in case of need, to as many more.
                    The general affairs of the confederation are intrusted to a council or diet,
                    composed of deputies from the cantons, who vote according to the instructions of
                    their respective governments. Each canton has only one vote, although it may
                    send more than one deputy to the diet. The diet meets for two successive years
                    by turns, at the capital of each of the directing cantons of Lucerne, Zurich,
                    and Berne, the burgomaster or avoyer of which acts as president for the turn,
                    with the title of Landmann. The diet usually meets on the first Monday of July,
                    at the capital of the directing canton, and has the power of making war and
                    peace, alliances with foreign powers, appointing diplomatic agents, and
                    disposing of the military force. The ordinary sessions of the diet last about
                    five weeks. Before closing its yearly session, it gives its instructions to the
                    directing canton, to which the management of the general affairs is intrusted
                    when the diet is not sitting. The directing canton is assisted in its duties by
                    a federal chancery, consisting of a chancellor and secretary, both appointed by
                    the diet. An extraordinary meeting of the diet may be convoked by the directing
                    canton, whenever urgent circumstances may require it, or simply on the demand of
                    five cantons.</p>
                <p part="N">The provisions of the federal pact are liberal and equitable in their
                    spirit. One of them states, that “the enjoyment of political rights can never in
                    future be the exclusive privilege of any one class of citizens in any one
                    canton. Free importation and exportation of provisions, or merchandise, or
                    cattle, shall be allowed from one canton to another without any import or export
                    duties. The property of chapters and convents which exist in several cantons is
                    guaranteed, but at the same time it is liable to the public charges and taxes,
                    like any other private property.” It will be seen by the above statements that
                    the federal government of Switzerland has, properly speaking, no permanent
                    executive, and the diet is merely an assembly of delegates from the various
                    cantons, who decide according to the instructions given by their respective
                    governments. Many attempts have been made to give more influence to a central
                    authority; but the resistance to any system of centralization and unity has been
                    so strong, and the apprehensions of encroachments on the part of any general
                    government upon the sovereign independent authority of the different cantons so
                    widely spread, that all proposals for modifying the federal convention have
                    hitherto failed. The independence of the different cantons has been singularly
                    preserved. Revolutions which have completely changed the constitution and the
                    laws of one district have had little or no influence upon another. The boundary
                    of a canton has bounded the most marked and violent political commotions. Civil
                    war itself has not spread beyond the narrow sphere of local interests. Though in
                    the different cantons the inhabitants enjoy an almost absolute equality of
                    rights and privileges, yet these advantages cease as soon as they pass the
                    narrow local territory to which they belong; and the general character of a
                    Swiss citizen has no immunities spreading over the whole of Switzerland.<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">Bowring's
                            Report, p. 5.</p></note><pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=66" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0066-0048"
                    /> The constitutions of the twenty-two cantons may be ranged into three classes.
                    The first class is that of the pure democracies, consisting of the old mountain
                    cantons, Scliwytz, Uri, Unterwalden, Glaris, Zug, and Appenzell. To these may be
                    added the Grisons and the Valais, which at first were only allies of the Swiss,
                    but are now integral parts of the confederation. The second class of cantons
                    consists of those in which aristocratic privileges had been enjoyed for
                    centuries by the principal town of the canton. These cantons are Zürich, Berne,
                    Freyburg, Soleure, Lucerne, Basel, and Schaffhausen; but their constitutions
                    underwent a thorough change in 1830, and the country districts were then
                    admitted to the enjoyment of equal privileges with the towns. The third class is
                    that of the new cantons formed since 1803, out of the former bailiwicks; namely,
                    Aargau, Thurgau, Vaud, Ticino, and St Gall. The constitutions of these cantons
                    were also rendered more popular in 1830, and framed on the principle of equality
                    of rights among all classes of the citizens. Two cantons have not been
                    enumerated in any of the above classes, Geneva and Neuchâtel. The institutions
                    of the former at one time resembled those of the aristocratic cantons, but they
                    have now been established on a popular basis. The latter is a constitutional
                    monarchy, of which the king of Prussia is prince. In the representative cantons
                    of Berne, Lucerne, Aargau, Ticino, and Geneva, a property qualification is
                    required for members of the legislature.</p>
                <p part="N">The different branches of agriculture are well understood in
                    Switzerland. The extent and fertility of the pastures are favourable to the
                    breeding of cattle. The oxen are remarkable for their size; and the cows,
                    particularly the short-horned breed in the valleys of Gruyères, are much prized
                    in different countries. The horses are strong and hardy, but the mule is the
                    most common beast of burden in the mountains. The central and south-eastern
                    cantons are chiefly dependent on their agricultural productions.</p>
                <p part="N">The commercial relations of Switzerland are of great importance, and her
                    manufactures have gradually forced their way into all the markets of the world,
                    however remote or seemingly inaccessible. This result is the more remarkable, as
                    Switzerland neitlier produces the raw material which she manufactures, nor, when
                    manufactured, has she any port of outlet, except on such conditions as her
                    maritime neighbours impose upon her; and yet, in spite of these obstacles, her
                    progress has been almost unexampled in manufacturing prosperity. Capital is
                    rapidly increasing, through the influence of unrestricted industry. Activity is
                    everywhere visible both in the trading and the agricultural districts. Wages are
                    comparatively low in many of the departments of industry, the necessary result
                    of the general cheapness of most of the articles of consumption; a cheapness
                    which again is the cause and consequence of the free egress and ingress of all
                    commodities. The land is for the most part released from tithes and taxes, and
                    the people subject to very trifling fiscal burthens. The great secret of the
                    commercial prosperity of Switzerland is,—industry has been left to itself.
                    Capital has not been diverted by legislative interference from its natural
                    tendencies. The consumer has been allowed to go to the cheapest market, the
                    producer to the dearest; and the present position and prospects of Swiss
                    industry furnish abundant evidence of the wisdom of this policy. The prohibitory
                    system adopted by the surrounding states excited at first some alarm among the
                    manufacturers of Switzerland; but their anxieties on this subject have now
                    ceased, and the narrow policy of their neighbours has only had the effect of
                    forcing the Swiss into a wider and more profitable field, which they have been
                    able successfully to explore to the extent of their capitals and their means of
                    production. Many of the manufacturers, who had formerly been strenuous advocates
                    for heavy custom-house duties on foreign articles, are now convinced by
                    expcrience that their views were erroneous.</p>
                <p part="N">The various forms of government in Switzerland have proved to some
                    extent a cause of embarrassment and difficulty to her national commerce. No
                    prohibition is laid by any of the states on the import, export, or transit of
                    any article; but each canton maintains the right to stipulate the conditions of
                    ingress and egress, and the transport of merchandise is necessarily impeded by
                    the collection of tolls at the different frontiers. Many attempts have been made
                    by the most intelligent merchants to equalize the transit-duty, and to remove
                    the charges and embarrassments of so many local administrations, by some general
                    plan; but as the tolls are one of the main sources of local revenue, the cantons
                    have been unwilling to abandon them for any national and general object.</p>
                <p part="N">A very considerable amount of trade is carried on between France and
                    Switzerland, the frontier territory being extensive, the language in those
                    districts identical, and the customs of the adjacent provinces substantially the
                    same. On an average of fourteen years the annual imports into France from
                    Switzerland amount to L.454,345, the annual exports from France to Switzerland
                    to L.1,094,554. The principal articles imported from France are wine, oil,
                    madder, brandy, alcohol, salt, fruit, sugar, coffee, and colonial produce, silk,
                    woollen, and cotton manufactures, and articles of fashion in great variety.
                    There is no duty, except a nominal one, on any of these articles, while France
                    receives from Switzerland some horned cattle and cheese, both of which pay
                    enormous duties; and ribbands, linens, and threads, all subject to large
                    custom-house imposts. There is also a considerable export of watches and
                    jewellery, which is principally in the hands of contraband traders. The
                    unfriendly and hostile tariff of France has naturally produced much discontent
                    in Switzerland, while it is a notorious fact, that the protection afforded to
                    French manufactures, by highly raised or prohibitory tariffs, has not produced
                    its intended results; that no manufacturing industry has suffered such violent
                    shocks, or seen such terrible reverses, as the industry of France.</p>
                <p part="N">The Prussian commercial league caused at its origin a considerable
                    alarm, and appeared to menace Switzerland with a serious reduction of exports to
                    Germany. But time and experience have diminished these apprehensions.</p>
                <p part="N">The imports from England are cast iron, steel, pewter, tin, fine hard
                    ware, a small quantity of printed cottons, woollen stuffs, tea, pottery, India
                    and China silk, dyeing ingredients, and colonial productions, when they are
                    cheaper in England than in the continental ports of Europe. Switzerland, on the
                    other hand, furnishes very few articles to England; and these principally
                    consist of embroidered muslins, Turkey-red calicoes, and a few printed goods
                    upon the same red ground.</p>
                <p part="N">After the peace of 1815, the Swiss merchants, finding themselves
                    precluded, by the prohibitive system, from almost the whole of the European
                    markets, directed their attention to the United States of America, and gradually
                    extended their relations with the southern parts of that continent. Throughout
                    the whole of that hemisphere, the consumption of their manufactures has
                    increased from year to year. Besides this new market for the sale of their
                    goods, they have made some experiments in the East Indies, and these have now
                    acquired some importance. They have likewise a few consumers in the states of
                    Barbary, Egypt, Illyria, Greece, Turkey, and Persia.</p>
                <p part="N">The Swiss cantons which are the most distinguished for their wealth and
                    industry, and for tlieir general prosperity, are Zürich, Basel, Geneva, St Gall,
                    Neuchâtel, Appenzell, and Aargau. The canton of Appenzell has manufactories of
                    muslins, cottons, and silks, and receives a considerable quantity of cotton
                    yarns from England. Neuchâtel exports con-<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=67" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0067-0049"
                    /> siderable quantities of wines and cheeses, and has very extensive
                    manufactories of watches and jewellery, lace and printed cottons. Within these
                    few years the making of sparkling wine has been greatly extended. The principal
                    manufactures are watches, printed cottons, and lace. The probable production of
                    printed cottons in Neuchâtel is now about 80,000 pieces per annum, each
                    containing about thirty-two English yards. Watch-making is carried on to an
                    immense and increasing extent in the mountainous districts of this canton, in
                    the French portion of the canton of Berne, and in the town and neighbourhood of
                    Geneva. It has been a source of wealth and comfort to many thousands of the
                    inhabitants, who, in the remote villages of the Jura, have gathered around them
                    a large portion of the enjoyments of life. Switzerland has long furnished the
                    markets of France; and though the names of certain French watchmakers have
                    obtained a European celebrity, yet an examination into this trade has elicited
                    the fact, that not ten watches are made in Paris in the course of a year, the
                    immense consumption of France being furnished from Switzerland, and the Swiss
                    works being only examined and rectified by the French manufacturers. The
                    contraband trade into France was immense, but they are now admitted into that
                    country at six per cent. for gold, and ten per cent. for silver watches; and a
                    considerable quantity pays regularly this moderate duty. The Jura Mountains have
                    been the cradle of the most exquisite productions of the mechanical arts. During
                    the winter, which lasts from six to seven months, the inhabitants are almost
                    imprisoned in their dwellings, and occupy themselves in those works which
                    require the utmost development of skilful ingenuity. Nearly 120,000 watches are
                    produced annually in the elevated regions of Neuchâtel. The largest proportion
                    of these is exported to the United States of America. It is not easy to state
                    the exact number of workmen who are engaged in watchmaking, because nearly the
                    whole of the population are more or less occupied in this branch of industry,
                    which they carry on in their own houses and amidst their own families. The
                    manufactures of Neuchâtel are admitted into Prussia on diminished duties.
                    Watches and such articles pay only one half of the duty stipulated by the
                    tariff.</p>
                <p part="N">The main source of the trade in the canton of Thurgau is the manufacture
                    of cotton, flax, and silk, with their various establishments for weaving,
                    printing, and dyeing. The exports are principally wine, fruit, and cider, oats,
                    brandy, linen, cattle, &amp;c. The imports principally consist of iron,
                    iron-wares, and metal manufactures, salt, woollen goods, fine cloths, sugar,
                    coffee, chicory, madder, drugs, and dye-stuffs, tobacco, wheat, fine cotton
                    yarns, &amp;c.</p>
                <p part="N">The canton of Schaffhausen possesses a considerable transit trade, which
                    is facilitated by the navigation of the Rhine. This canton has suffered more
                    than any other from the Prussian commercial league, its principal export being
                    wine, of which the German markets were the main seats of consumption. Nature has
                    blessed this small district with a fertile soil, which places it in the class of
                    the agricultural rather than that of the commercial cantons of Switzerland.</p>
                <p part="N">Basel is almost entirely a commercial and manufacturing territory; its
                    industry is principally engaged in the production of ribbands and some silks.
                    The former are exported to the value of about 10,000,000 of French francs. About
                    one half of these goes to the United States, the remainder is sent to Germany,
                    France, Holland, Denmark, Sweden, &amp;c. Since 1814, and particularly within a
                    few years, the progress of Basel has been very great, both as regards the
                    quantity and the quality of its manufactures.</p>
                <p part="N">The manufactures of Zurich are of ancient date. The silk manufacture of
                    this town dates as far back as the thirteenth century, and it still forms a very
                    important article in the trade of this canton. The silk manufactures of Zurich
                    consist of florentines, gros de Naples, gros de Berlin, marcelines, taffetas,
                    serges, levantines, silk handkerchiefs, a few shawls, &amp;c. The number of
                    looms at present employed in the silk trade may be reckoned at 10,000; and the
                    total annual produce of the silk manufacture of Zürich has been estimated at
                    L.600,000 sterling. The silk manufacture of Switzerland is constantly
                    increasing, and it is in the town and canton of Zürich that it is most
                    extensively carried on. Great improvements have been made, and are constantly
                    making, in this branch of industry. Zürich also possesses some cotton
                    manufactures. About 800,000 pieces of cotton are manufactured yearly. The
                    imports of Zürich consist mainly of cotton yarns from England, woollen cloths,
                    bark, straw hats, linens, furs, glass, stationery, wheat principally from
                    Suabia, wine from France, Neuchâtel, and Vaud, brandy, fruits, tobacco,
                    fir-wood, cotton and silk, wool and colonial cattle, butter and cheese,
                    minerals, &amp;c.</p>
                <p part="N">The principal manufacture of Aargau is cotton in its various branches;
                    the second in importance is that of silk. The exportation of these articles is
                    principally to Italy, Piedmont, the northern states of Germany, Turkey, and
                    North and South America. The principal articles of import are wheat, wine, salt,
                    and leather, iron and other metals, hard ware, tobacco and snuff, hemp and flax,
                    chicory, oil, raw cotton, cotton twist, fine cotton manufactures from England,
                    woollen cloths, raw silk, spices, drugs, dye-stuffs, dry goods, indigo,
                    &amp;c.</p>
                <p part="N">The canton of Geneva, for its small extent of surface, presents a
                    remarkable scene of manufacturing industry. Jewellery, watches, and musical
                    boxes, are three of the most important branches of trade, employing a great
                    number of hands, and imparting the utmost activity to a commerce which conveys
                    these productions to all quarters of the globe. The watchmakers of Great Britain
                    buy largely both in Geneva and Neuchâtel. The average annual export to England
                    is from 8000 to 10,000 watches, and the average price about L.10 sterling. The
                    jewellery sent from Geneva to England represents a value of about L.60,000 per
                    annum. In an article of such small bulk as a watch, it has been found impossible
                    to guard against illicit introduction; the contraband trade is consequently very
                    large, and scarcely a single watch pays the duty of twenty-five per cent. The
                    smuggling is carried on almost wholly by French houses, who reap the profits of
                    the smuggling premium, and who, it appears by the small amount of seizures,
                    really run scarcely any risk. The English consumer pays the gains of the French
                    smuggler, and pays too for that damage, delay, and risk which accompany
                    fraudulent transactions. Of other sorts of merchandise Geneva exports annually
                    about 120,000 quintals. The amount of British manufactures sold in the canton is
                    estimated at about L.200,000 per annum. One half of this is supposed to be
                    consumed in the town and neighbourhood, the other half is smuggled into
                    France.</p>
                <p part="N">There are several striking peculiarities in the condition and
                    employments of the labouring classes of Switzerland. There are few weaving
                    factories or buildings in which the labouring weavers are congregated together.
                    Their looms are in their own abodes, which are scattered over the country. They
                    receive from the manufacturer the chain and the woof, and return to him the
                    woven article. Weaving can hardly indeed be called a manufacturing industry; it
                    is a sort of domestic labour, associated with, and often subordinate to,
                    agricultural employment. It is in fact but one of two means of existence, the
                    labouring population being only in part dependent on it. It is very common to
                    find many looms in the cottage of a small farming labourer, the whole of which
                    may be worked by its members when the weather, or the seasons, or other
                    circumstances, withdraw them from the field. In the common apartment of the
                    family of the country people, one or two members of the family may be seen
                    weaving, and carrying on at the same<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=68" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0068-0050"
                    /> time their household occupation; sometimes working in their gardens, and
                    contributing in turns their assistance in the cultivation of their fields, and
                    the labour of agriculture in general. The quality and neatness of the articles
                    produced are evidently rendered inferior by this custom; but, on the other hand,
                    it is more economical, and during a slackness of trade the workman who possesses
                    a garden and a little ground suffers less. In almost every part of Switzerland,
                    with the exception of those mountain heights which are incapable of cultivation,
                    agricultural labour affords resources when wages fall or markets are glutted, so
                    that the pressure of want is generally light and temporary.</p>
                <p part="N">The working classes in Switzerland are divided into four different
                    sections, viz. manufacturers, weavers, winders, and embroiderers. There are
                    manufacturers of every order and description, from the individual who only
                    manufactures the quantity which himself and his family can weave, up to those
                    who employ a hundred weavers or embroiderers; for the manufacturer who employs
                    embroiderers does not engage in weaving. These manufacturers, who either sell
                    their goods unbleached to the traders at home, or bleached to foreigners,
                    breakfast upon coffee and milk, butter, honey, or green cheese. Their dinner is
                    composed of soup and bouilli, potatoes, or porridge. Their beverage is cider or
                    milk. Many of them sup upon coffee, and they seldom drink wine. This class is in
                    general very economical. They take a great interest in public affairs, and pride
                    themselves particularly upon their probity and honour. They furnish the greatest
                    number of magistrates, and from among them are principally chosen all the
                    parochial authorities.</p>
                <p part="N">The weaver, as soon as it is possible for him to do so, purchases a
                    piece of ground, or at least a small house; and very frequently the manufacturer
                    furnishes him with the means. The acquisition of landed property is greatly
                    promoted in Switzerland, by the facility with which money may be borrowed upon
                    mortgage. This class of working proprietors forms the great mass of voters in
                    the popular assemblies.</p>
                <p part="N">All the weavers in Switzerland make use of coffee, milk, oatmeal, and
                    potatoes, which compose their principal food. They work from thirteen to
                    fourteen hours a day. They earn from 1s. 10d. to 9s. 2d. a week; but the
                    greatest number only earn from 3s. 8d. to 5s. per week. The winders, many of
                    whom are old people of both sexes, earn from 1d. to 3d. sterling a day. The
                    embroiderers, who are generally women or young lads, earn on an average about
                    6½d. a day. In Neuchâtel the ordinary rate of wages is, for male domestics, from
                    L.8 to L.12 sterling, and for females, from L.4 to L.6 sterling, per annum. The
                    average wages of agricultural labourers are from ls. ld. to ls. 8d. per day. The
                    wages of artisans vary extremely, the lowest being about 9d. and the highest
                    11d. per day. The wages of watchmakers may be calculated at from L.55. 10s. to
                    L.83. 5s. per annum; but workmen are generally paid by the job.</p>
                <p part="N">Provisions are very cheap in Switzerland. In the canton of Appenzell, a
                    pound of bread weighing 20 ounces is worth 4 kreutzers, rather less than 1½d. In
                    Neuchâtel, the loaf of white bread is from 2d. to 2½d.; meat, from 4d. to 5¼d.;
                    butter, from 9½d. to 10d. the pound of 17 ounces. The measure of potatoes
                    weighing from 33 to 34 pounds, is worth from 10d. to 1s. 1¼d.; milk, l¼d.; and
                    wine from 3d. to 6d. the bottle.</p>
                <p part="N">In Switzerland the clergy are supported by the state. The cost of the
                    church establishment in Zürich is L.8000 per annum, being 9d. for each
                    individual. The clergy amount to 271. In Neuchâtel the maximum salary of a
                    clergyman is L.121, the minimum L.72, and the average L.83. There are 34
                    clergymen in this canton, which gives one to every 1647 persons. The Protestant
                    religion is professed by the cantons of Basel, Berne, Vaud, Schaffhausen,
                    Zürich, Geneva, and Neuchâtel. Soleure, Freyburg, Lucerne, Zug, Schwytz,
                    Unterwalden, Uri, Ticino, and Valais, have continued Romanists. The cantons of
                    Aargau, Glaris, Thurgau, St Gall, Appenzell, and the Grisons, contain a mixture
                    of Romanists and Protestants.</p>
                <p part="N">Education is very generally diffused throughout Switzerland. In
                    Appenzell every one is instructed; and for many years past the law does not
                    allow any person to be admitted to the sacrament who cannot read; and the
                    greater part of the population can also write, and have acquired the rudiments
                    of arithmetic and singing. In Neuchâtel a considerable sum is paid by the state
                    for the purpose of education. Every commune is required to provide a
                    schoolmaster, and education is made obligatory throughout the principality.
                    There is no person under the age of forty who is unable to read and write; and
                    it is extremely difficult to find a person who does not also know how to
                    calculate, and who is not well acquainted with his civil and political rights.
                    To religious instruction much attention is paid. Before being admitted to the
                    sacrament, the young men are obliged to attend for a certain number of years on
                    the public ordinances, as well as to receive private lessons from their own
                    pastors. In Basel both the primary and superior schools are good; and for many
                    years the poor have been obliged to send their children to school for a course
                    of elementary instruction, which occupies them until their tenth or twelfth
                    year. The means for educating them are furnished by the poor-fund. In this
                    manner children are prevented from entering too young into the factories, or
                    from being employed in too laborious occupations.</p>
                <p part="N">At Hofwyl, in the canton of Berne, the establishments of Mr de
                    Fellenberg for the maintenance and education of poor children, and his
                    institution for the instruction of schoolmasters, have been attended with that
                    success which might have been expected from efforts prompted by pure benevolence
                    and guided by sound judgment.</p>
                <p part="N">In Aargau every district of 120 children must have at least one primary
                    and one superior sch∞l. In every circle, the population being from 15,000 to
                    20,000 souls, there are from five to six secondary schools, and in the capital a
                    gymnasium and a school of art. Besides this, there is a normal school for the
                    instruction of teachers. The cost of these establishments is paid partly by the
                    communes, and partly from the state funds. In Thurgau, every child, on reaching
                    the age of five years, must be sent to school. Of the whole proceeds of the
                    land-tax, two fifths have been applied to the purposes of education. A
                    model-school for the education of teachers, established at Krutzlingen in 1833,
                    under the superintendence of Mr Wehrlea, a pupil of Fellenberg, has had great
                    success. Funds are cheerfully and liberally voted by the legislature. In 1834
                    more than one fifth of the whole population was attending the schools.</p>
                <p part="N">The poor in Switzerland are supported by a poor-law, greatly assisted
                    however by voluntary contributions. The general law is that each parish shall
                    take care of its own poor, but the arrangements in the different parishes
                    respecting paupers are very various.</p>
                <p part="N">The administration of justice in Switzerland is prompt and economical.
                    In Neuchâtel, for example, a verdict obtained in the Court of First Instance,
                    might be pressed through all its stages, even to the confiscation of property to
                    any amount, at a cost of less than 6s. 8d. sterling, and with a delay of only
                    three weeks, there being three stages of appeal, each one allowing of a week for
                    appearance and answer. While the cost to suitors is small, the cost to the
                    public is equally so. In the district of Valangin, consisting of 6104 souls, the
                    expenses for the administration of civil justice for 1834 amounted to less than
                    five sixths of a farthing per individual; yet there are 122 trusteeships of
                    minors, lunatics, &amp;c., committed to the charge of the civil tribunals. There
                    are on an average seventy causes per<pb break="no"
                        facs="ht:chi.12945678&amp;view=1up&amp;seq=69" xml:id="kp-eb0721-0069-0051"
                    /> annum, the average cost of which to the suitors was about 4s. 6d. per suit.
                    The cost of the criminal tribunals of the same district was about L.140
                    sterling.</p>
                <p part="N">The taxes in Switzerland are extremely light. In Neuchâtel tliey amount
                    on an average to about 4s. 8d. per inhabitant yearly; in Aargau, to 2s. 6d.; in
                    the canton of Vaud, to 4s. 8d. The whole amount of taxes paid per individual in
                    Thurgau, is not more than one fifth of what is paid in England per individual
                    for the poor-rates alone. In Zürich the poor-rates are less than 2½d. per annum
                    for each inhabitant. The civil expenditure is little more than 10d. and the
                    military expenses less than 6d. for each.</p>
                <p part="N">Savings banks are very generally established in Switzerland, but the
                    working classes seldom deposit in them any of their earnings. They are
                    principally made use of by the children, for whom their parents deposit their
                    savings, in order to purchase for them an equipment when their first attendance
                    at the Lord’s Supper gives them the rights of citizens. Servants and artists
                    also place their savings in these banks; but the ambition of the workmen is to
                    invest the fruits of their economy in the acquisition of a house, or of a small
                    portion of land.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1817 the population of Switzerland amounted to 1,687,900, in 1827 to
                    1,916,000, in 1836 to 2,177,420, of whom 130,500 were Protestants, 870,000 Roman
                    Catholics, about 3000 Jews, and a few Moravians and Anabaptists. German is
                    spoken by about 1,560,000 people, French by 450,000, Italian by 124,000,
                    Rumonsch and Ladin by about 42,000 in the Grisons. The following table exhibits
                    an account of the population, &amp;c. in 1838. <hi rend="smallcaps">(b.
                    q.</hi>)</p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Cantons.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Area in Square Geographical
                            Miles.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Citizens of the Can tons.</cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">Citizens of other Strangers,
                                Cantons.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Total Population. 1838.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Roman Catholics.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Protestants.</cell>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1">Contingent to the</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Capitols.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Federal Revenue.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Federal Army.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Aargau</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">379</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">174,992</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">5,965</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,798</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">182,755</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">67,500</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">79,800</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">£3,016</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2,410</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Aarau.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Appenzell,</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Ausserrhoden</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">115</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">38,701</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,898</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">481</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">40.080</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">9,796</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">40,080</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">∫ 482</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">772</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Trogen and Herisau.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Innerrhoden.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">9,671</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">89</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">36</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">9,796</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1 93</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">200</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Appenzell.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Basel City</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">139</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">10,611</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">8,481</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">5,229</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">24,321</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">6,000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">49,590</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,309</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">918</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">∫ Basel or Bale*</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">35,990</p><p part="N"
                                >381,200</p><p part="N">83,234</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3,952</p><p part="N"
                                >13,954</p><p part="N">6,010</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1,161</p><p part="N"
                                >4,846</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">41,103</p><p part="N"
                                >400,000</p><p part="N">91,145</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Liechstall or Liestall Berne.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Berne</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1,933</p><p part="N"
                            >374</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">50,000</p><p part="N"
                                >82,745</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">358,860</p><p part="N"
                                >8,400</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">6,505</p><p part="N"
                                >1.162</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">5,824</p><p part="N"
                                >1,240</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Freyburg</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,901</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Freyburg or Fribourg.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Geneva</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">69</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">38,156</p><p part="N"
                                >28,217</p><p part="N">4,670 120,012</p><p part="N">40,808</p><p
                                part="N">144,359</p><p part="N">29,462</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">8,677</p><p part="N"
                            >821</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">11,833</p><p part="N"
                                >310</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">58,666</p><p part="N"
                                >29,348</p><p part="N">88,506</p><p part="N">124,521</p><p part="N"
                                >58,616</p><p part="N">158,853</p><p part="N">31,125</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">17,000</p><p part="N">3,800
                                24,000 124,468</p><p part="N">2,400</p><p part="N">99,300</p><p
                                part="N">600</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">41,666</p><p part="N"
                                >25,548</p><p part="N">62,000</p><p part="N">53</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,375</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">880</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Genf or Geneva.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Claris.</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">211</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">226</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">482</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Glarus or Giaris. Chur or Coire.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Grisons</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,938</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2,412</p><p part="N"
                                >3,383</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1,424</p><p part="N"
                            >626</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">750</p><p part="N"
                                >1,625</p><p part="N">1,200</p><p part="N">2,465</p><p part="N"
                                >676</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1,600</p><p part="N"
                                >734</p><p part="N">960</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Lucerne</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">443</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Luzern or Lucerne. Neuenburg or
                            Neuchâtel. St Gallen or St Gali. Schaffhausen.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Neuchâtel</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">211</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">14,534</p><p part="N"
                                >11,139</p><p part="N">1,409</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3,214</p><p part="N"
                                >3,355</p><p part="N">254</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">54.400</p><p part="N"
                                >58,400</p><p part="N">35,125</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">St Gall</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">565</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">2,630</p><p part="N"
                            >466</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Schaffhausen</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">86</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Schwytz</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">256</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">12,948</p><p part="N"
                                >59,214</p><p part="N">110,445</p><p part="N">78,160</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">537</p><p part="N"
                                >3,274</p><p part="N">299</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">34</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">13,519</p><p part="N"
                                >63,186</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">13,519</p><p part="N"
                                >63,196</p><p part="N">113,923</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">188</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">602</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Schweitz or Schwytz. Solothurn or
                            Soleure.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Soleure</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">192</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">708</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">847</p><p part="N"
                            >1,128</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">904</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Ticino</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">781</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3,179</p><p part="N"
                                >1,501</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">113,923</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1,804</p><p part="N"
                                >1,520</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Bellenz or Bellinzona.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Thurgau</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">203</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">4,463</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">84,124</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">18,500</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">72,191</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,425</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Frauenfeld.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Unterwalden,</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Obwalden</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">198</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">11,857</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">500</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">11</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">12,368</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">22,671</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">69</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">221</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Sarnen.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Nidwalden...</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">9,804</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">388</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">11</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">10,203</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">...</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1 50</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">161</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Stanz.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Uri</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">318</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">39,326</p><p part="N"
                                >73,673</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,128</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">196</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">40,650</p><p part="N"
                                >75,798</p><p part="N">183,582</p><p part="N">15,322</p><p part="N"
                                >231,576</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">40,650</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">73</p><p part="N"
                            >600</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">236</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Λltorf.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Valais</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,254</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">778</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">1,347</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">75,798</p><p part="N"
                                >3,000</p><p part="N">15,322</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">1,280</p><p part="N"
                                >2,964</p><p part="N">250</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Sitten or Sion.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Vaud</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">893</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">164,686</p><p part="N"
                                >14,193</p><p part="N">217,219</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">14,931</p><p part="N"
                                >1,019</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3,965</p><p part="N"
                            >110</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">180,582</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p part="N">3,705</p><p part="N"
                                >79</p><p part="N">4,625</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Lausanne. Zug. Zürich.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Zug</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">64</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">7,991</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">6,366</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">223,240</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">3,700</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">Zürich</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">517</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2,000</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">11,039</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2,012,168</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">118,032</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">53,896</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">2,184,096</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">33,673</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1">32,758</cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p part="N">*Switzerland being both a German and a French country, most of the
                    principal places have both a German and a French name. Sometimes, however, there
                    is also an Italian name, as <hi rend="italic">Bellinzona;</hi> and some of them
                    have even three forms, as <hi rend="italic">Chiavenna, Cleven, Cleves,</hi> the
                    first of which is the Italian, the second the German, and the third the French
                    form of the same name.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
