<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0705-2437-0721-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">BURNET, Thomas</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 5, page 721</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="10" ref="fasttopic:881747">Courts</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term><term n="9" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:899678">Dutch</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term><term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term><term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="9" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1243607">Earth</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193742437" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">BURNET, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label>, a
                    distinguished writer, was born at Croft in Yorkshire about the year 1635, but is
                    supposed to have been descended of a Scotish family. His early education he
                    received at the free-school of Northallerton, in the same county, under Thomas
                    Smelt, who used to propose him as an example to the rest of his scholars. On the
                    26th of June 1651, he was admitted a pensioner of Clare Hall at Cambridge, under
                    the tuition of Tillotson, who continued to remember him with kindness; but in
                    the year 1654, he removed to Christ’s College, on the election of Dr Cudworth to
                    the mastership, and there he obtained a fellowship in the year 1657. In 1661 he
                    became senior proctor of the university. He was successively domestic tutor to
                    Charles duke of Bolton, and to James earl of Ossory, afterwards duke of Ormonde,
                    grandson to the first duke; and by the interest of the latter nobleman he was
                    chosen master of the Charter-house in 1685. Among the electors, some of the
                    bishops opposed him on account of his wearing a lay-habit; but the duke was
                    satisfied that he possessed the more essential qualifications of a life and
                    conversation suitable to his clerical character. After this appointment, he took
                    the degree of D. D. In his capacity of master, he made a noble stand against the
                    admission of a papist named Andrew’ Popham, as a pensioner of the house: on the
                    26th of December 1686, the king addressed to the governors a letter dispensing
                    with the statutes; but the opposition of the master being vigorously supported
                    by other governors, James deemed it prudent to desist from this illegal
                    attempt.</p><p>Dr Burnet had already published his <hi rend="italic">Telluris Theoria</hi><hi rend="italic">sacra.</hi> Lond. 1681, 4to. This work attracted an unusual share
                    of the public attention, and he was afterw ards encouraged to exhibit it in an
                    English dress. His <hi rend="italic">Sacred Theory of the Earth</hi> was printed
                    in folio, the first part in 1684, and the conclusion in 1689. Addison commended
                    the author in a Latin ode. His fanciful theory was however attacked by Dr Keill,
                    Mr Whiston, and Mr Warren, to all of whom he returned an answ∙er. He had now
                    acquired a high reputation as a man of talents; and after the revolution, he was
                    introduced at court by Archbishop Tillotson, whom he succeeded as clerk of the
                    closet to King William.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Birch’s Life of Tillotson, p. 2Ĵ8. Lond. 1752, 8vo.</p></note> He seemed
                    already to be on the direct road to much higher preferment, when he suddenly
                    marred his own prospects by the publication of a learned and ingenious work,
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Archoeologiae Philosophicae</hi><hi rend="italic">:</hi><hi rend="italic">sive Doctrina antiqua</hi><hi rend="italic">de</hi><hi rend="italic">Rerum Originibus.</hi> Lond. 1692, 4to. The mode in which he
                    discussed the history of the fall of man, excited a great clamour against him;
                    and the king was obliged to remove him from his office at court. Of this book an
                    English translation was executed by Mr Foxton. Lond. 1729, 8vo. Dr Burnet next
                    published <pb break="no" facs="nls:193742450" xml:id="kp-eb0705-2450-0722"/>“Remarks upon an Essay concerning Human
                    Understanding, in a Letter address’d to the Author.” Lond. 1697, 4to. “Second
                    Remarks, &amp;c. being a Vindication of the first Remarks against the Answer of
                    Mr Locke, at the end of his Reply to the Lord Bishop of Worcester.” Lond. 1697,
                    4to. “Third Remarks,” &amp;c. Lond. 1699, 4to. These remarks were answered by
                    Catherine 1 rotter, afterwards Mrs Cockburn, in her “Defence of Mr Locke s
                    Essay, written when she was twenty-three years of age, and printed at London in
                    1702. He died at the Charterhouse on the 27th of September 1715, at a very
                    advanced age. Two of his works were published several years after his death. <hi rend="italic">De Fide</hi><hi rend="italic">et Officiis Christianorum</hi><hi rend="italic">Liber</hi><hi rend="italic">posthumus.</hi> Lond. 1722, 4to. <hi rend="italic">De Statu</hi><hi rend="italic">Mortuorum</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">Resurgentium Tractatus.</hi> Lond. 1723, 4to. Of the
                    first of these works, there are several other editions, one of which was
                    published by Dr Teller of Berlin. Halae Magdeburg. 1786, 8vo. The second has
                    likewise been more than once reprinted; and two English translations were
                    published by Matthias Earbery and John Dennis. The author was evidently a man of
                    genius and learning; but his fancy being sometimes more vigorous than his
                    judgment, he is not on all occasions a very safe guide. In this work he
                    maintains the doctrine of the middle state, the Millennium, and the limited
                    duration of future punishment. Mura tori, an Italian writer of great eminence,
                    published copious animadversions upon it, under .the subsequent title: “De
                    Paradiso Regnique Caelestis Gloria, non expectata Corporum Resurrectione, Justis
                    a Deo conlata; adversus Thomae Burneti Britanni Librum de Statu Mortuorum.”
                    Veronae, 1738, 4to. The name of Burnet appears in the following publication, but
                    his only contribution consists of a few pages translated from his treatise on
                    the faith and duties of Christians: “The Judgment of Dr Thomas Burnet, late
                    Master of the Charter-House, concerning the Doctrine of the Trinity: and the
                    Judgment of Dr Samuel Clarke, late Rector of St James’s, concerning 1. the
                    Satisfaction, 2. the Merits, 3. the Mediation and Intercession of Christ, 4. the
                    ordinary Influence and Assistance of the Holy Spirit, 5. the two Sacraments.
                    With a preface concerning Mr Lock, Sir Isaac Newton, and Mr Wollaston.” Lond.
                    1732, 8vo. (x.)</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Burnet,</hi><hi rend="italic">Gilbert,</hi> bishop of
                    Salisbury, was born at Edinburgh in 1643, but was descended of an ancient family
                    in the county of Aberdeen. His father being bred to the law, was, at the
                    restoration of King Charles IL, appointed one of the lords of session, by the
                    title of Lord Crimond, as a reward for his constant attachment to the royal
                    party during the civil wars. Gilbert, the youngest son of his father, was
                    instructed by him in the Latin tongue; and at ten years of age he was sent to
                    Marischal College, Aberdeen, where he was admitted A. Μ. before he was fourteen
                    years of age. His own inclination led him to the study of the civil and feudal
                    law; and he used to say that it was from this study he had received more just
                    notions concerning the foundations of civil society and government, than those
                    which some divines maintain. He afterwards changed his views, and, to the great
                    satisfaction of his father, began to apply to divinity. He received ordination
                    before the age of eighteen; and Sir Alexander Burnet, his cousin-german, offered
                    him a benefice, but he refused to accept of it.</p><p>In 1663, about two years after the death of his father, he came into England; and
                    after six months stay at Oxford and Cambridge, returned to Scotland; which he
                    soon left again to make a tour of some months, in 1664, in Holland and France.
                    At Amsterdam, by the help of a Jewish rabbi, he perfected himself in the Hebrew
                    language; and likewise became acquainted with the leading men of the different
                    persuasions tolerated in that country, Calvinists, Arminians, Lutherans,
                    Anabaptists, Brownists, Papists, and Unitarians; among each of which sects he
                    used frequently to declare he met with men of such unfeigned piety and virtue,
                    that he became fixed in a strong principle of universal charity, and an
                    invincible abhorrence of all severities on account of religious dissensions.</p><p>Upon his return from his travels, he was admitted minister of Saltoun; in which
                    station he served five years in the most exemplary manner. He drew up a
                    memorial, in which lie took notice of the principal errors in the conduct of the
                    Scotish bishops, which he observed not to be conformable to the primitive
                    institution; and sent a copy of it to several of them. This exposed him to their
                    resentments; but to show he was not actuated by a spirit of ambition, he led a
                    retired course of life for two years, which so endangered his health that he was
                    obliged to abate his excessive application to study. In the year 1668 he was
                    appointed professor of divinity in the university of Glasgow; and, according to
                    the usual practice, he read his lectures in the Latin language. It was
                    apparently at this’ period that he laid the chief foundation of that theological
                    learning for which he became so distinguished. In 1669 lie published his “Modest
                    and free Conference between a Conformist and Nonconformist.” He became
                    acquainted with the Duchess of Hamilton, who communicated to him all the papers
                    belonging to her father and her uncle; upon which he drew up the “Memoirs of the
                    Dukes of Hamilton,” afterwards printed at London, in folio, in the year 1677.
                    The Duke of Lauderdale, hearing he was engaged in this work, invited him to
                    London, and introduced him to King Charles II. He returned to Scotland, and
                    married Lady Margaret Kennedy, daughter of the Earl of Cassillis, a lady of
                    great knowledge, and highly esteemed by the Presbyterians, to whose sentiments
                    she was strongly inclined.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Some degree of attention has lately been directed to this lady in
                    consequence of the publication of a collection of <hi rend="italic">Letters
                    fa&gt;m Lady Margaret Burnet to John Duke of Lauderdale.</hi> Edinb. 1828,
                    4to.</p></note> As there was some disparity in their ages, that it might be
                    sufficiently evident that this match was wholly owing to inclination, and not to
                    avarice or ambition, the day before their marriage he delivered to the lady a
                    deed, by which he renounced all pretensions to her fortune, which was very
                    considerable, and must otherwise have fallen into his hands, she herself having
                    no intention to secure it. His “Vindication of the Authority, Constitution, and
                    Laws of the Church and State of Scotland,” was printed at Glasgow, in octavo, in
                    the year 1673. This was considered as so material a service to the government,
                    that he was again offered a bishopric, with a promise of the next vacant
                    archbishopric; but he did not accept of it, because he could not approve of the
                    measures of the court, the great vifew of which he perceived to be the
                    advancement of popery. The publication itself was one of those which the author
                    could not afterwards recollect with much satisfaction. ,</p><p>His intimacy with the Dukes of Hamilton and Lauderdale procured him frequent
                    messages from the king and the Duke of York, who. had conversations with him in
                    private. But Lauderdale, who was the most unprincipled man of the age,
                    conceiving a resentment against him on account of the freedom with which he
                    spoke to him, represented at last to the king that Dr Burnet was engaged in an
                    opposition to his measures; and on his return to London he perceived that these
                    suggestions had entirely deprive him of the king’s favour, though the Duke of
                    fork treated him with greater civility than ever, and dissuaded him from going
                    to Scotland. He accordingly resigned his professorship<pb break="no" facs="nls:193742463" xml:id="kp-eb0705-2463-0723"/> at Glasgow,
                    and settled in London. About this time the living of Cripplegate being vacant,
                    the dean and chapter of St Paul’s (in whose gift it was), hearing of his
                    circumstances, and the hardships which he had undergone, made him an offer of
                    the benefice; but, as he had been informed of their first intention of
                    conferring it on Dr Fowler, he generously declined it. In 1675, at the
                    recommendation of Lord Hollis, whom he had known in France as ambassador at that
                    court, he was by Sir Harbottle Grimstone, master of the rolls, appointed
                    preacher at the Rolls chapel, notwithstanding the opposition of the court; and
                    he was soon afterwards chosen lecturer at St Clement’s, and became one of the
                    most popular preachers in town. The first volume of his <hi rend="italic">History of the Reformation of the Church of England</hi> was published in folio
                    in 1681, the second in 1683, and the third in 1715. For this great work he
                    received the thanks of both houses of parliament. Of the first two volumes he
                    published an abridgment in the year 1683.</p><p>Dr Burnet about this time happened to be sent for to a woman in sickness, who had
                    been engaged in an amour with the Earl of Rochester. The manner in which he
                    treated her during her illness gave that profligate nobleman a great curiosity
                    for being acquainted with him; and during a whole winter, he spent one evening
                    of the week with Dr Burnet, who discussed with him all those topics upon which
                    sceptics and men of loose morals attack the Christian religion. The happy
                    effects of these conferences occasioned the publication of his account of the
                    life and death of that nobleman. In 1682, when the administration was changed in
                    favour of the Duke of York, being much resorted to by persons of all ranks and
                    parties, in order to avoid returning visits, he built a laboratory, and for
                    above a year pursued a course of chemical experiments. Not lon*g after he
                    refused a living of three hundred pounds a year offered him by the Earl of
                    Essex, on the terms of his not residing there, but in London. When the enquiry
                    concerning the popish plot was on foot, he was frequently sent for and consulted
                    by King Charles with relation to the state of the nation. His majesty offered
                    him the bishopric of Chichester, then vacant, if he would engage in his
                    interests; but he refused to accept it on these terms. He preached at the Rolls
                    till 1684, when he was dismissed by order of the court.</p><p>About this period he published various works, among which we must not overlook
                    the following seven. “Some Passages of the Life and Death of John Earl of
                    Rochester.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p><hi rend="superscript"> t’í</hi> Which,” says Dr Johnson, <hi rend="superscript">
                    ςζ</hi> the critick ought to read for its elegance, the philosopher for its
                    arguments, and the saint for its piety.” (TJvcÿ <hi rend="italic">of English
                    Poets,</hi> vol. i∙ p. 303.) . ∙* <hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> ∏ τ&gt; <hi rend="subscript"> tλ tλ</hi></p></note> Lond. 1680, 8vo. “The Life and Death of
                    Sir Matthew Hale, Kt. sometime Lord Chief Justice of his Majesties Court of
                    Kings Bench.” Lond. 1682, 8vo. “The History of the Rights of Princes in
                    disposing of Ecclesiastical Benefices and Church Lands.” -Loud. 1682, 8vo. “The
                    Life of William Bedell, D. D. Bishop of Kilmore in Ireland.” Lond. 1685, 8vo.
                    “Reflexions on Mr Varillas’s History of the Revolutions that have happened in
                    Europe in matters of Religion, and more particularly on his ninth book, that
                    relates to England.” Amst. 1686, 12mo. “A Defence of the Reflections on the
                    ninth book or the first volum of Mr Varillas’s History of Heresies; being a
                    Reply to his Answer.” Amst. 1687, 12mo. “A Continuation of Reflections on Mr
                    Varillas’s History of Heresies, particularly on that which relates to English
                    Affairs in his third and fourth tomes.” Amst. 1687, 12mo. He bore a very
                    conspicuous part in the controversy which at that time was so ably maintained
                    against the papists; and a complete catalogue of his works would occupy no small
                    space. The following translations deserve to be mentioned in this very brief and
                    inadequate notice. “Utopia, written in Latin by Sir Thomas More, Chancellor of
                    England: translated into English.” Lond. 1685, 8vo. “A Relation of the Death of
                    the primitive Persecutors, written originally in Latin by L. C. F. Lactantius:
                    Englished by Gilbert Burnet, D. D. to which he hath made a large preface
                    concerning persecution.” Amst. 1687,12mo.</p><p>On King James’s accession to the throne, having obtained leave to quit the
                    kingdom, he first went to Paris, and lived in great retirement, till,
                    contracting an acquaintance with Brigadier Stouppe, a Protestant gentleman in
                    the French service, he made a tour with him into Italy. He met with an agreeable
                    reception at Rome. Pope Innocent XI. hearing of his arrival, sent the captain of
                    the Swiss guards to acquaint him he would give him a private audience in bed, to
                    avoid the ceremony of kissing his holiness’s slipper; but Dr Burnet excused
                    himself as well as he could. Here, with more zeal than prudence, he engaged in
                    some religious disputes; and, on receiving an intimation from Prince Borghese,
                    he found it necessary to withdraw from this stronghold of priestcraft, and
                    pursued his travels through Switzerland and Germany. He afterwards came to
                    Utrecht, with an intention to settle in some of the seven provinces. There he
                    received an invitation from the prince and princess of Orange (to whom their
                    party in England had recommended him) to come to the Hague, and of this
                    invitation he accepted. He was soon acquainted with the secret of their
                    councils, and advised the preparation of a fleet in Holland sufficient to
                    support their designs and encourage their friends. This, and the account of his
                    travels,<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Some Letters,
                    containing an Account of what seemed most remarkable in Switzerland, Italy,
                    &amp;c. written by G. Burnet, D. D. to T. H. R. B. Rotterdam, 168G,
                    8vo.</p></note> in which he endeavoured to blend popery and tyranny together,
                    and represent them as inseparable, with some papers reflecting on the
                    proceedings of England, that came out in single sheets, and were dispersed in
                    several parts of England, of most of which Dr Burnet owned himself the author,
                    alarmed King James, and were the occasion of his writing twice against him to
                    the princess of Orange, and insisting, by his ambassador, on his being forbidden
                    the court; which, after much importunity, was done, though he continued to be
                    trusted and employed as before, the Dutch minister daily consulting him. To put
                    an end to these frequent conferences with the ministers, a prosecution for high
                    treason was commenced against him both in England and Scotland; but receiving
                    the intelligence before it reached the states, he avoided the storm, by
                    petitioning for, and obtaining without any difficulty, a bill of naturalization,
                    in order to his intended marriage with Mary Scott, a Dutch lady of considerable
                    fortune, who, with the advantage of birth, united those of a fine person and
                    understanding.</p><p>After his marriage with this lady, being legally under the protection of Holland,
                    when Dr Burnet found King James plainly subverting the constitution, he omitted
                    no •method to support and promote the design which the prince of Orange had
                    formed of delivering Great Britain; and, having accompanied him in quality of
                    chaplain, he was in the year 1689 advanced to the see of Salisbury. He declared
                    for moderate measures with regard to the clergy who scrupled to take the oaths,
                    and many were displeased with him for declaring for the toleration of
                    nonconformists. As my lord of Salisbury, says the Earl of Shaftesbury, “has done
                    more than any man living for the good and <pb break="no" facs="nls:193742476" xml:id="kp-eb0705-2476-0724"/>honour of the
                    church of England and the reform’d religion, so he now suffers more than any man
                    from the tonguesand slander of those ungrateful church-men; who may well call
                    themselves by that single term of distinction, having no claim to that of
                    Christianity or Protestant, since they have thrown off all the temper of the
                    former, and all concern or interest with the latter.” The same noble writer has
                    elsewhere mentioned him in the following terms of commendation: “The bishop of
                    Salisbury’s Exposition of the Articles is, no doubt, highly worthy of your
                    study. None can better explain the sense of the church, than one who is the
                    greatest pillar of it since the first founders; one who best explain’d and
                    asserted the reformation its self; was chiefly instrumental in saving it from
                    popery before and at the Revolution; and is now the truest example of laborious,
                    primitive, pious, and learned episcopacy.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Shaftesbury’s <hi rend="italic">Letters,</hi> p. 28,
                    3Ĵ.</p></note></p><p>His pastoral letter concerning the oaths of allegiance and supremacy to King
                    William and Queen Mary, 1689, happening to touch upon the right of conquest,
                    gave such offence to both houses of parliament, that it was ordered to be burnt
                    by the hands of the common executioner. He soon afterwards published a very
                    valuable work, entitled <hi rend="italic">A Discourse of the Pastoral Cure.</hi>
                    Lond. 1692, 4to. In 1698 he lost his wife by the small-pox; and as he was almost
                    immediately after appointed preceptor to the Duke of Gloucester, of whose
                    education he took great care, this employment, and the tender age of his
                    children, induced him the same year to supply her loss by a marriage with Mrs
                    Berkeley, a widow, who was eldest daughter of Sir Richard Blake. In 1699 he
                    published his <hi rend="italic">Exposition of the thirty-nine Articles</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> which occasioned a representation against him in the lower
                    house of convocation in the year 1701, but he was vindicated in the upper house.
                    His speech in the House of Lords in 1704 against the bill to prevent occasional
                    conformity, was severely attacked. He formed a scheme for augmenting the small
                    livings; which he pressed forward with such success, that it ended in an act of
                    parliament passed in the second year of Queen Anne, for the augmentation of the
                    livings of the poor clergy. He died in 1715, and was interred in the church of
                    St James, Clerkenwell, where a monument was erected to his memory.</p><p>Bishop Burnet’s <hi rend="italic">History of his own Time,</hi> consisting of two
                    large volumes in folio, was not published till several years after the author’s
                    death; the first volume appeared in 1724, an I the second in 1734. An account of
                    his life was added by his youngest son Sir Thomas Burnet, one of the judges of
                    the court of common pleas. The history itself was not printed without
                    mutilations; but after an interval of nearly a century, an edition, containing
                    all the passages which had formerly been suppressed, was published under the
                    superintendence of the learned Dr Routh. Oxford, 1823, 6 vols. 8vo. This is a
                    work of great and intrinsic value: it exhibits many curious and interesting
                    delineations of character, and many striking views of the causes and progress of
                    events. The first volume, which relates to the reigns of Charles II. and his
                    brother James, we consider as the more interesting of the two. His materials are
                    not always very carefully digested, and his style is sometimes supposed to be
                    too familiar; but these defects are abundantly compensated by the copiousness of
                    his information, the benevolence of his sentiments, and the earnestness of his
                    manner. The <hi rend="italic">Conclusion</hi> displays superior dignity of
                    composition, and cannot be perused without the most favourable impression of the
                    author’s intellectual attainments and moral worth. He uniformly evinces his
                    attachment to the cause of freedom, nor is this the least conspicuous part of
                    his character: the church of England, in its collective capacity, has always
                    been hostile to civil as well as religious liberty; and its annals exhibit very
                    few names which tend to remove the general stigma. Those of Burnet and Hoadley
                    ought never to be forgotten.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Burnet,</hi><hi rend="italic">James, Lord Monhoddo,</hi> a
                    senator of the college of justice, was born about the year 1714. He was the son
                    of Mr Burnet of Monboddo in Kincardineshire. After passing through the usual
                    course of school education, he prosecuted his studies at the universities of
                    Aberdeen, Edinburgh, and Leyden, with distinguished reputation. He was admitted
                    an advocate in 1737; and on the 12th of February 1767, he was raised to the
                    bench by the title of Lord Monboddo.</p><p>A journey to London became a favourite amusement of his periods of vacation from
                    the business of the court; and for a time he made this journey once a year. A
                    carriage, a vehicle that was not in common use among the ancients, he considered
                    as an engine of effeminacy and sloth, which it was disgraceful for a man to make
                    use of in travelling. To be dragged at the tail of a horse, instead of mounting
                    upon his back, seemed, in his eyes, to be a truly ludicrous degradation of the
                    genuine dignity of human nature: in all his journeys, therefore, between
                    Edinburgh and London, he was wont to ride on horseback, with a single servant
                    attending him. He continued this practice, without finding it too fatiguing for
                    his strength, till he was upwards of eighty years of age.</p><p>Lord Monboddo is well known to the world as a man of letters. His first
                    publication was <hi rend="italic">The Origin and Progress of Language,</hi> in
                    two vols. 8vo, 1773, which were followed by four more volumes, the last being
                    published not long before his death. In this work, intended chiefly to vindicate
                    the honour of Grecian literature, he ascribes the origin of alphabetical writing
                    to the Egyptians; and strenuously maintains that the ourang-outang is a class of
                    the human species, and that his want of speech is merely accidental. He also
                    endeavours to establish the reality of the existence of mermaids, and other
                    fictitious animals. He was induced to undertake another work for the purpose of
                    defending the cause of Grecian philosophy, and published, in five vols. 4to, a
                    work entitled <hi rend="italic">Ancient Metaphysics,</hi> which, like the other,
                    is remarkable for a surprising mixture of erudition and genius, with the most
                    absurd whim and conceit.</p><p>As a judge his decisions were sound, Upright, and learned, marked with acute
                    discrimination, and free from those paradoxes and partialities which appear in
                    his writings. He attended his judicial duty with indefatigable diligence till
                    within a few days of his death, which happened at his house in Edinburgh on the
                    26th of May 1799, at the advanced age of eighty-five.</p></div></body></text></TEI>