<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-0772-0593-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BROUSSONET, Pierre Marie Auguste</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 5, page 593</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1205592">Morocco</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208401">Angola</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1034543">Naturalists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:921865">Fathers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vs35">Naturalists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x63b58d">Kindness</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193740772" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BROUSSONET, <hi rend="smallcaps">Pierre Marie
                    Auguste</hi></label>, a distinguished French naturalist, born at Montpellier on
                    the 28tb February 1761. His father was a respectable schoolmaster in that town,
                    who, perceiving the avidity with which he received instruction of every kind,
                    took pains to store his mind with knowledge at an early age. It appears from his
                    writings that he was at first educated for the medical profession. The opinion
                    entertained in the university of the success with which he pursued his studies,
                    was proved by his being appointed to fill a professor’s chair when he was only
                    eighteen years of age. So great, indeed, was the reputation he had acquired,
                    that when he offered himself as candidate a few years afterwards for a seat in
                    the Aca-lemy of Sciences, he was elected a member by an unanimous vote; a
                    circumstance which had hitherto been without example since the foundation of
                    that learned body. Botany seems to have been the science to which be was at
                    first chiefly devoted; and he laboured with much zeal to establish the system of
                    Linnaeus in France. In pursuit of this great object, and with the view of
                    extending his mowledge of the science, he visited Paris, and studied θ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> ver</hi> y museum and collection from which he could derive
                    obstruction in the different branches of natural history.</p>
                <p><hi rend="superscript"> e neχ</hi> t came to England, where he was admitted in
                    1782 an honorary member of the Royal Society. It was also at this period that he
                    published at London his work on <hi rend="superscript smallcaps"> s</hi><hi
                    rend="smallcaps">. -s,</hi> describing the most rare species of this class of
                    animals, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Ichthyologia,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">seu Piscium</hi><hi rend="italic">De-</hi><hi rend="italic
                    superscript"> scr</hi><hi rend="italic">}Ρti°nes</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >et</hi><hi rend="italic">leones.</hi> On his return to Paris he was appointed
                    perpetual secretary to the Society of Agriculture, an office which the intendant
                    Berthier de Sauv⅛n <hi rend="subscript"> v</hi> purposely resigned that it might
                    be filled by Broussonet.</p>
                <p>A life thus dedicated to the pursuits of science was not likely to be chequered
                    by any remarkable vicissitude. But the revolution, which soon broke out in
                    France, and for a long time unhinged all the ordinary relations of society, had
                    already involved in its vortex not only the ambitious and the turbulent spirits
                    of the nation, but also the peaceful votaries of science. In 1789 he was
                    nominated a member of the Electoral College of Paris, an office which required
                    him to serve as magistrate whenever his colleagues were in need of assistance in
                    the exercise of their functions. On the first day when he was called upon this
                    duty, as he was proceeding to the Hotel de Ville, he had the misfortune to see
                    his friend and protector Berthier barbarously murdered by the populace. His own
                    life was frequently exposed to great danger during the tumults that ensued, and
                    when he had the charge of superintending the supply of provisions for the
                    capital. In 1791 he had a seat in the legislative assembly; but, disgusted with
                    politics, he quitted Paris the year following, and repaired to his native city.
                    Persecution followed him in his retreat, and he was glad to effect his escape to
                    Madrid, after encountering many dangers. But though well received and liberally
                    assisted by the literati of that city, the malignity of the French emigrants,
                    who could not. pardon his having held any office under the revolutionary
                    government, still pursued him, and drove him from Spain, and afterwards from
                    Lisbon, where he had sought another asylum. He at last went out as physician to
                    an embassy which the United States sent to the emperor of Morocco. He was
                    furnished with the means of equipping himself by the generous assistance of Sir
                    Joseph Banks, who, informed of his distresses, nobly sent him a credit for
                    L.1000. After residing for some time at Morocco, during which he lost no
                    opportunity of pursuing his favourite science, be obtained from the French
                    directory permission to return to France; and he was appointed by them consul at
                    the Canaries, in which capacity he resided for two years at Teneriffe. On his
                    return in 1797 lie was chosen member of the institute, and was reinstated in his
                    botanical professorship at Montpellier, with the direction of the botanical
                    garden. He was afterwards elected a member of the legislative body, and died of
                    apoplexy on the 27th July 1807. France is indebted to him for the introduction
                    of the Merino sheep and Angola goats.</p>
                <p>Besides the work on fishes, already noticed, the following are his principal
                    productions: 1. Variae Positiones circa Respirationem, Montpellier, 1788. 2.
                    Essai sur 1 Histoire</p>
                <p>Naturelle de quelques espèces de Moines, décrite à la manière de Linné, 8vo,
                    1784, which is a translation of a Latin satire on the monks, the original of
                    which appeared in Germany in 1783. 3. Année rurale, ou Calendner a l’usage des
                    Cultivateurs, in 2 vols. 12mo. Pans 1(8/-ö. 4. Notes pour servir à ľHistoire de
                    ľĽcole de Médécine de Montpellier pendant l’an VI. 8vo, Montpellier, 179o. He
                    was also a conductor, conjointly with Parmentier, Dubois, and Lefebure, of La
                    Feudle du Cultivateur, in 8 vols. 4to, published in 1788 and the following
                    years, <hi rend="smallcaps">(y.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
