<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0705-0902-0603-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">BROWNE, Sir Thomas</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 5, page 603</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4fj29h67">Hebrews</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m6299t">Urns</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v00z">Travelers</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4rr1pw5q">Travels</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b49p2wf9z">Travel</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:795344">Accountants</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:795379">Accounting</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:795510">Accounts</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1155691">Travelers</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1155558">Travel</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239509">Africa</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1240495">Asia</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1212489">Bulgaria</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193740902" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">BROWNE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir Thomas</hi></label>, an
                    eminent physician and celebrated writer, was born at London on the 19th of
                    Oetober 1605. Having studied at Winchester College, and afterwards at Oxford, he
                    travelled through France and Italy; and returning by the way of Holland, he took
                    his degree of doctor of physic at Leyden. In 1636 he settled at Norwich, and the
                    year following was incorporated as doctor of physic at Oxford. His <hi rend="italic">Religio</hi><hi rend="italic">Medici</hi> made a great noise; and
                    being translated into Latin, instantly spread throughout Europe, and gained him
                    a prodigious reputation. It <hi rend="subscript"> was</hi> ti <hi rend="subscript"> ιen</hi> translated into almost every language m Europe. This
                    book has been heavily censured by some <hi rend="superscript"> as</hi>. tending
                    to infidelity, and even atheism; whilst others, with much more reason, have
                    applauded the piety, as well as the parts and learning, of the author. His
                    Treatise on</p><p>Vulgar Errors was read with equal avidity; he also published <hi rend="italic">Hydriotapliia,</hi> or a Discourse of Sepulchral Urns lately found in Norfolk.
                    His reputation in his profession was equal to his fame for learning in other
                    respects; and therefore the college of physicians were pleased to take him into
                    their number as an honorary member; and King Charles II. coming to Norwich in
                    his progress in 1671, was pleased to knight him, with singular marks of favour
                    and respect. He died on his birthday in 1681, leaving several manuscripts behind
                    him, which were published under the title of The Posthumous Works of the learned
                    Sir Thomas Browne, Knt. Μ. D.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Browne,</hi><hi rend="italic">Edward,</hi> the son of the
                    former, physician to King Charles II. and president of the Royal College of
                    London. He was born in the year 1642; and studied at Cambridge, and afterwards
                    at Merton College, Oxford. He then travelled; and on his return published a
                    brief account of some travels in Hungary, Servia, Bulgaria, Macedonia, Thessaly,
                    Austria, Styria, Carinthia, Carniola, Friuli, and other parts. He also published
                    an account of several travels through great part of Germany, and joined his name
                    to those of many other eminent men in a translation of Plutarch’s Lives. He was
                    acquainted with Hebrew, was a critic in Greek, and no man of his age wrote
                    better Latin. High Dutch, Italian, Freneb, and other modern languages, he spoke
                    and wrote with as much ease as his mother tongue. King Charles said of him, that
                    he was as learned as any of the college, and as well bred as any at court. He
                    died on the 27th August 1708.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Browne,</hi><hi rend="italic">William George.</hi> This
                    eminent traveller was born on Great-Tower-Hill, London, on the 25th July 1768.
                    His father was a respcetable wine merchant, clescended from a good family in
                    Cumberland. His constitution being originally so weak as to require constant
                    attention, he was educated privately under Dr Whalley, editor of Ben Jonson’s
                    works, a man of considerable parts and learning, who inspired him with a taste
                    for study. At seventeen he was sent to Oriel College, Oxford; and, though he
                    complained of the want of encouragement and assistance, he there went through an
                    extensive course of classical reading, studying often from twelve to fifteen
                    hours a day. On leaving the university lie hesitated for some time between the
                    three learned professions, but at length determined to remain contented with the
                    moderate competence left to him by his father, and applied himself entirely to
                    the pursuit of knowledge. He embarked deeply in political questions, embracing
                    with ardour the popular cause. He republished some political tracts, among which
                    was part of Buehanan, <hi rend="italic">J)e Jure</hi><hi rend="italic">Regni
                    apud Scotos,</hi> and formed the plan of reprinting a regular series of such
                    writings. But the fame of Mr Bruce’s travels, and of the first discoveries made
                    by the African Association, inflamed his ardent mind, and he determined to
                    devote himself to the cause of discovery on that continent.</p><p>Mr Browne left England at the close of 1791, and arrived at Alexandria in January
                    1792. He spent a few months in visiting Siwah, the supposed site of the temple
                    of Jupiter Ammon; and employed the remainder of the year in examining the whole
                    of Egypt. In the spring of 1793 he visited Suez and Sinai, and in May set out
                    for Darfur. This was his most important journey, in which he acquired a great
                    variety of original information. He endured much hardship, and was unable to
                    effect his purpose of returning by Abyssinia. He did not reach Egypt till 1796,
                    after which he spent a year in Syria, and did not arrive in London till
                    September 1798. In 1800 he published his travels in Africa, Egypt, and Syria,
                    from the year 1792 to 1798, in one volume 4to. The work was highly esteemed, and
                    is classed by Major Rennell among the first performances of the kind; but, from
                    the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193740915" xml:id="kp-eb0705-0915-0604"/>abruptness and dryness of the style, it never
                    became very popular.</p><p>In 1800 Mr Brown again left England, and spent three years in visiting Greece,
                    some parts of Asia Minor, and Sicily. He had made some progress in preparing for
                    the press an account of this journey, but gave up his intention, for some reason
                    unknown.</p><p>Mr Browne now spent some years in retirement, employed in oriental studies, and
                    showing indifference to British objects and scenery, though he enjoyed greatly
                    an excursion into Ireland.</p><p>Tired of this inactivity, in 1812 he set out on a more extensive journey than
                    formerly, proposing to penetrate to Samarcand, and survey the most interesting
                    regions of Central Asia. He spent the winter in Smyrna, and in the spring of
                    1813 proceeded through Asia Minor and Armenia, made a short stay at Erzerum, and
                    arrived on the first of June at Tabriz, where he met with Sir Gore Ouseley.
                    About the end of the summer of 1813 he left Tabriz for Teheran, intending to
                    proceed thence into Tartary; but unhappily he never reached that destination.
                    Near the banks of the Kizil-Ozan his party were attacked by banditti, and,
                    according to the report of the survivors, Mr Browne was dragged to a short
                    distance from the road, where he was plundered and murdered. Suspicion attached
                    to his companions, and even to the Persian government, but nothing occurred to
                    confirm these surmises. Some bones, believed to be his, were afterwards found
                    and interred near the grave of Thevenot, the celebrated French traveller.</p><p>Mr Browne, in his person, was thin, rather above the middle size, with a grave
                    and pensive cast of countenance. He entertained an extraordinary predilection
                    for the manners and character of the orientals. Like them, he was in general
                    society silent, reserved, and even repulsive. Even among his most intimate
                    friends he would remain long gloomy and reserved; but after indulging in a pipe
                    his eye brightened, and he related with great animation the interesting scenes
                    through which he had passed. His disposition was friendly, liberal, and
                    generous, and he was distinguished by a strict regard to veracity. Under a cold
                    exterior he cherished an ardent desire to distinguish himself by some memorable
                    achievement, in pursuit of which he was ready to brave danger and death.</p><p>His volume of travels in Africa has already been mentioned. Mr Walpole, in the
                    second volume of his Memoirs relating to European and Asiatic Turkey (4to,
                    1820), has published, from papers left by him, the account of his journey in
                    1802 through Asia Minor to Antioch and Cyprus; also Remarks written at
                    Constantinople. No account is preserved of his last journey, except what is
                    contained in a letter to Mr Smithson Tennant.</p></div></body></text></TEI>