<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-1331-0636-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BUDDHA or Buddiiu</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 5, page 636</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gk13">Vedas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b44q7qq38">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k877">Research</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sx64f56">Mayas</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="16" ref="fasttopic:840025">Buddhas</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:840028">Buddhism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:957175">Hindus</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:939025">Gautamas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:840320">Buddhists</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1093898">Religions</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193741331" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BUDDHA or <hi rend="smallcaps">Buddiiu</hi></label>, one of
                    the two appearances of Vishnu, assumed for the purpose of deluding the enemies
                    of the gods, and effecting their destruction by leading them to profess
                    heretical opinions, and thus to reject the Hindu religion. In the Bhagawat, a
                    work held in high esteem by the great majority of the Hindus, it is expressly
                    declared, “that, at the commencement of the Kali Yug, Vishnu became incarnate in
                    Kikata, under the name of Buddha, the son of Jina, for the purpose of deluding
                    the enemies of the gods ;” that “the Undiscernible Being, having assumed a
                    mortal form, preached heretical doctrines in the three cities founded by Maya,
                    for the purpose of destroying, by deluding, the enemies of the gods, stedfast in
                    the religion prescribed by the Vedas ;” that praise is due to “the pure Buddha,
                    the deluder of the Daityas and Dana was ;” and that, “by his words, as Buddha,
                    Vishnu deludes the heretics.” The same legend is related in a more detailed
                    manner in the Kashi Khand of the Skanda Purana, and also in the Ganesha
                    Upa-Purana, in which the appearance of Buddha is described as a manifestation
                    rather than an incarnation of Vishnu; and an account is given of the
                    circumstances under which it is alleged to have been made. According to the
                    Puranas, Divodasa, a king of the solar race, finding Kashi unoccupied, took
                    possession of the place, and there established the religion of Vishnu on so firm
                    a foundation, and rendered his people so virtuous and happy, that the gods
                    having become alarmed lest they should lose their supremacy, which they
                    maintained by the use of very different means, applied to Vishnu and Shiva to
                    relieve them from their anxieties on this head. The two incarnations of the
                    Supreme Being, however, declared at first that it would be unjust to deprive so
                    virtuous a prince of his kingdom; but Divodasa, having obtained as a boon from
                    Brahma that none of the deities should remain in his kingdom, or exercise any
                    power over it, Shiva at length waxed wroth at being so long banished from his
                    favourite residence, and consented to fulfil the malignant wishes of the
                    deities. But how was this to be accomplished? As long as Divodasa and his
                    subjects remained stedfast in their religion, they were secure from injury; it
                    therefore became necessary to lead them into error as a pretext for destroying
                    them; and with this view Devi, the twelve suns, and Ganesha, were employed, but
                    without success. At last, when these minor tempters had failed, Vishnu appeared,
                    as Buddha, and effected their apostacy.</p>
                <p>From the tenor of this legend may be divined, <hi rend="italic">a priori,</hi>
                    the doctrines which it was necessary for Buddha to propagate, in order to induce
                    Divodasa and his subjects to apostatize from the religion of the Vedas. These in
                    fact were,—that no credit whatever is due to the Vedas or Shastras; that it is
                    vain to worship the images of gods; that sacrifices are cruel and sinful; that
                    there is no such thing as transmigration of souls; that at death the five
                    elements in the body dissolve never to reunite; that pleasure is the grand
                    object of life, and that all acts of abstinence, piety, and charity, are
                    unprofitable; that the body is man’s real god, and should alone be worshipped;
                    that pleasant food, fine clothes, and handsome women, form the grand felicity of
                    man; that this world is without beginning, and consequently owes its existence
                    neither to creator nor cause; and that Brahma, Vishnu, Shiva, Budra, and all the
                    other gods, are mere creatures of fancy an fear, and never had a being, except
                    in the imaginations of their worshippers. In short, the ancient Brahmimca
                    Buddha, whether a manifestation of Vishnu according to <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193741344" xml:id="kp-eb0705-1344-0637"/>the Shaivas, or an
                    incarnation according to the Vaishnavas, was the propagator of a system of
                    universal scepticism, embracing not only a disbelief of all religion, but also a
                    disregard for all virtue, and indeed for every thing except mere sensual
                    gratification. He was a false teacher and impostor, who came to deceive and to
                    mislead, in order to destroy; not a kind and merciful being, adorned with the
                    attributes of wisdom and benevolence, and worthy to receive all praise and
                    worship, as some have erroneously supposed. Moreover, his appearance was for a
                    temporary and local purpose, namely, to render Divodasa the voluntary cause of
                    his own downfal, and thus to gratify the malice of the deities who had conceived
                    an aversion to that virtuous potentate. But the sceptical doctrines which he
                    disseminated in the course of his delusive manifestation became afterwards
                    blended and intermixed with a variety of others of a totally different
                    description; so that, although Buddhism has ever continued more or less distinct
                    from the faith of which originally it formed the negation, it is exceedingly
                    difficult to trace its progress, and by no means easy to ascertain its precise
                    character at any given period, of time. The rejection of the λ <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 7</hi> edas, and of the religion founded upon them, seems,
                    however, to be common to all forms of Buddhism; and although the Brahmins
                    nevertheless recognise Buddha as an object of worship or reverence, it is only
                    as a manifestation of Vishnu, one of the emanations of Brahm, or the Supreme
                    Being, and not as a false teacher and an impostor, whose object was to deceive
                    and delude, that he is acknowledged by the sacred caste of the Hindus. By not
                    perceiving or not attending to this distinction, all the writers on the subject
                    whose works we have consulted have entangled themselves in the mazes of
                    inextricable perplexity and contradiction, and thickened the darkness which they
                    laboured to dispel. M. Guigniaut, indeed, has attempted to cut the knot which he
                    could not unloose. “Bouddha ne jouit d’aucun culte dans l’Inde,” says he; “ses
                    temples, ses idoles y sont renversés ou abandonnés; one ténébreuse horreur, one
                    ignorance feinte ou réelle, one haine non moins violente qu’irréfléchie, regnent
                    chez les Brahmanes, sur tout ce qui concerne sa doctrine.” But in another part
                    of his work <hi rend="italic">(Religions de</hi><hi rend="italic">l</hi><hi
                    rend="italic superscript"> ,</hi><hi rend="italic">Antiquité,</hi> vol. i. p.
                    294), the same author admits that Buddha has not ceased to be revered by the
                    Hindu nation; an admission wholly irreconcilable with the statement contained in
                    the passage just quoted. This confusion of ideas, however, proceeds from
                    incorrect notions as to the character of Buddha; for as long as he is considered
                    merely as a manifestation of Vishnu, he is held to be an object of reverence,
                    not as Buddha, but as the divinity who chose to appear in that form. The Hindus
                    have never acknowledged him in any other character; and consequently all that
                    has been written concerning him with reference to the religion of India, is
                    wholly irrelevant, and foreign· to the subject.</p>
                <p>According to the fable, Buddha, when he had effected the apostacy of Divodasa,
                    was prevailed upon by the Brahmins and holy men to terminate the propagation of
                    heretical doctrines, upon which he disappeared in a deep well at Gaya, leaving
                    neither writings nor disciples behind him; and it is further believed, upon the
                    credit of tradition, that no Buddhists were known in India, until their sect was
                    established by Gautama or Godama, with whom Buddha is frequently confounded.
                    Now, in this mythic account, which is supported by a legend in the Shiva Purana,
                    we have the true genius of Buddhism displayed. Its character throughout is
                    essentially negative. When reduced to its elements or first principles, it
                    consists merely of the rejection of the Vedas and of the religion founded upon
                    them. It is not the Hindu faith; but under this denomination of Buddhism there
                    may be, and in point of fact there has been included the most various, not to
                    say incongruous, tenets and superstitions which it is possible to imagine; and
                    although its negative character is everywhere the same, its positive character
                    differs in different countries. Hence the Buddhism of China, allied to the
                    institutions, laws, and maxims of Fo and Confucius, is in many respects as
                    different from the Buddhism of the Burman empire as the latter is from the
                    system of religion founded on the Vedas and the Shastras. But, nevertheless, it
                    has some positive general characteristics. The principles of this sect, as
                    established by Gautama, its founder, about five hundred years before Christ, are
                    unknown; but those now ascribed to him, and professed as his alleged
                    revelations, may be very briefly stated. The doctrine and law of Gautama consist
                    chiefly in observing five commandments, and abstaining from ten sins. The five
                    commandments contain prohibitions against killing any animal whatsoever, from
                    the meanest insect up to man; against the commission of theft; against the
                    violation of another man’s wife or concubine; against falsehood; and against the
                    use of wine, or any intoxicating liquor or drug, as opium: and an exemption from
                    poverty, misfortune, and calamity is promised to those who keep these
                    commandments during all successive transmigrations. The ten sins consist in the
                    killing of animals, theft, adultery, falsehood, discord, contumelious language,
                    idle and superfluous talk, covetousness, envy or malice, and the following of
                    false gods: and he who abstains from all these sins is said to obtain Sila,
                    while every one who observes Sila, in all successive transmigrations, becomes at
                    last worthy of beholding a god, and of hearing his great voice, and is exempted
                    from the four known miseries, namely, weight, old age, disease, and death. There
                    are also certain positive good works which ought to be practised, such as Dana,
                    which consists in giving alms, and Bavana, which consists in repeating solemnly
                    the three words Aneizza, Docha, and Anatta; the first indicating liability to
                    vicissitude, the second exposure to misfortune, and the third the impossibility
                    of obtaining exemption from these evils. From this statement it appears that the
                    two scales of commandments and prohibitions are singularly ill adjusted to each
                    other; inasmuch as the duties enjoined are only half the number of the sins
                    forbidden, and as the negative and the positive in morals are blended in
                    both.</p>
                <p>The worshippers of Buddha contend with the disciples of Brahma for the honour of
                    a high antiquity; and this pretension has been countenanced by some European
                    writers of high reputation. Sir William Jones, for instance, fixes the first
                    appearance of Buddhism about a thousand years before Christ; but his argument
                    rests upon very weak grounds, and, if the Puranas are admitted to be of any
                    authority, it is wholly untenable; for whatever antiquity may be ascribed to
                    Buddha, considered as a manifestation of Vishnu for the purpose of local and
                    temporary delusion, there arc clearly no grounds, mythological, traditional, or
                    historical, for placing the origin of this sect higher than the period of
                    Gautama, or about five hundred years before Christ, as already mentioned. What
                    we know with certainty is, that Buddhism, so called doubtless from its peculiar
                    character, once predominated throughout a great part of India; that the
                    doctrines and system of belief adopted by its votaries were in direct opposition
                    to the religion founded on the Vedas; that a deadly hatred arose between the
                    followers of Brahma and the Buddhists, which ended in the expulsion of the
                    latter; that, nevertheless, the Brahmins continued to reverence Buddha as the
                    manifestation of Vishnu, however much they might have detested the sect which
                    called itself by his name; that Buddhism appears to have diffused itself over
                    all the countries from Bengal to China inclusive; that in its character <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193741357" xml:id="kp-eb0705-1357-0638"/> and genius it is
                    extremely flexible and accommodating; and that, in the different countries which
                    it overspread, it appears to have become amalgamated with indigenous local
                    superstitions of almost every description. (See Kennedy’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Researches into the Nature and Affinity of Ancient and Hindu Mythology,</hi> p.
                    248, <hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">seqq.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >;</hi><hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Bombay Literary Society,</hi> part
                    iii. p. 532; Guigniaut, <hi rend="italic">Religions de ι</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Antiquité,</hi> tom. i. p. 300; Heeren, <hi rend="italic">Ideen über</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">die</hi><hi rend="italic">Politik,</hi> &amp;c. vol. viii. p. 127,
                    4th edit.; <hi rend="italic">Asiatic Researches,</hi> vol. viii. p. 474.) . .
                    <hi rend="smallcaps">(a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
