<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-2281-0709-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BURGER, Godfrey Augustus</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 5, page 709</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1126120">Songs</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1004072">Lutherans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:953493">Heart</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1112660">Sentimentalism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:888613">Death</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4xp6v41r">Heart</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193742281" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BURGER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Godfrey Augustus</hi></label>, a
                    celebrated German poet, born on the 1st of January 1748, at Wolmerswende, a
                    village in the principality of Halberstadt, where his father was Lutheran
                    minister. In his childhood he discovered little inclination to study; the Bible
                    and the Canticles alone had any attraction for him: these he knew by heart; and
                    his first attempts in versification were imitations of the Psalms, which,
                    notwithstanding their defects, gave proofs of feeling and a correct ear. It is
                    to this first direction of his studies that we are to attribute the biblical
                    phrases, the allusions to Christianity, and the theological style, if we may be
                    allowed the expression, which we find even in his amatory poetry. He was fond of
                    solitude, and indulged in all the romantic sentiments which deserts and the
                    gloom of forests inspiret. From the school of Aschersleben, where his maternal
                    grandfather resided, and which he quitted in consequence of a severe
                    chastisement which had been inflicted on him for composing an epigram, he was
                    sent to the institution at Halle; but at neither of these places did he make any
                    very sensible progress. He discovered a taste only for the lessons in prosody
                    and versification which were given to the scholars of the institution, in which
                    his friend Gökingk was a class-fellow with him, who afterwards distinguished
                    himself by his epistles and songs, and who has lamented the premature death of
                    Bürger in an elegy to his memory. In 1764 Bürger, who was intended for the
                    clerical office, began to attend the course of lectures given by the professors
                    of the university. Klotz, a learned classical scholar, admitted him of the
                    number of young people whose talents he took a pleasure in cultivating; but this
                    society appears not to have produced the same favourable effect on the moral
                    character of Bürger as on his genius. His conduct prejudiced his grandfather
                    Bauer against him; and it was with difficulty that he obtained from him some
                    further assistance, with permission, in the year 1768, to repair to Göttingen to
                    prosecute the study of the law instead of that of theology. This change did not
                    make him more regular in his studies; his manners became corrupted; and his
                    grandfather withdrew his protection. Bürger contracted a number of debts; and
                    his situation would have become altogether desperate had it not been for the
                    assistance of some friends. An association, memorable in the annals of German
                    literature, had just been formed at Göttingen: it reckoned among its members
                    Boje, Biester, Sprengel, Hölty, Müller, Voss, the two Counts Stolberg, C. F.
                    Cramer, and Leisewitz. Bürger was admitted into it. All of these persons were
                    versed in the Greek and Roman literature, and, at the same time, all of them
                    idolized Shakspeare. The Germans are the only foreigners who seem to relish or
                    understand the merits of this great genius in the same degree as his own
                    countrymen profess to do; and they do not seem to like his genius the less on
                    account of the irregularities objected to it by other nations. Bürger, in a
                    great measure, owed his style to the enthusiasm which he showed, in common with
                    his literary friends, for our celebrated tragic writer. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Reliques</hi><hi rend="italic">of Ancient English Poetry,</hi> published about
                    this time by Dr Percy, gave an additional impulse to the direction which his
                    mind had taken, and suggested to him some of the productions which his
                    countrymen admire the most. Of all his friends, Boje was the one who exercised
                    the greatest influence over him in the choice and management of his
                    compositions. He taught him to make easy verses by taking pains; and it is to
                    his severe observations that the poetical stanza of Bürger owes a great part of
                    that elegance and roundness which characterize it. To the same friend he was
                    indebted also for some improvement in his circumstances, which, till the year
                    1772, had been very uncomfortable. On the recommendation of Boje he was
                    appointed to the collectorship of Alvenglei-chen, in the principality of
                    Calenberg. The winter following, some fragments of a ghost story, which he heard
                    a peasant girl singing by moonlight, caught his imagination, and his <hi
                    rend="italic">Leonora</hi> appeared, which soon became popular in all parts of
                    Germany. Soon after the publication of this ballad, a circumstance occurred to
                    give him still greater confidence in his talents. Going a journey to his native
                    place, he one evening heard the schoolmaster of the village, in the room next to
                    that in which he lay, reading to the assembled audience collected at the inn the
                    ballad of <hi rend="italic">Leonora,</hi> which had just come out, and which was
                    received with the liveliest marks of admiration. This proof of success flattered
                    him more than all the compliments of his friends. About this time he married a
                    Hanoverian lady, named Leonhart; but this union proved only a source of
                    bitterness to him, an unhappy attachment to her younger sister having sprung up
                    in his heart. The loss of a sum of money, of which his grandfather had made him
                    a present, was the first commencement of the embarrassment of his circumstances.
                    The taking of a large farm, which he did not know how to manage, increased it;
                    and the dismissal from his place, which he was obliged to submit to in 1784, in
                    consequence of suspicions (probably ill-founded) raised against the fidelity of
                    his accounts, gave the finishing stroke to his misfortunes. He had, a little
                    before, lost his wife; and it is but too certain that her death was hastened by
                    the culpable passion which Bürger cherished in his heart. Left with two
                    children, and reduced to the inconsiderable emoluments of <hi rend="italic">The
                    Almanack of the Muses,</hi> published at Göttingen, which he had edited since
                    1779, he removed to this city, with a view to give private lessons there, and in
                    the hope of obtaining from the <pb break="no" facs="nls:193742294"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0705-2294-0710"/>Hanoverian government a professor’s chair in the
                    belles-lettres. Five years afterwards, the title was conferred on him, but
                    without a salary; yet this was the only public recompense obtained during his
                    Whole life by a man who was one of the favourite authors of his nation, and who,
                    while yet young, had enjoyed the highest reputation. Scarcely were the ashes of
                    his wife cold when he espoused her sister Molly, whose name his poems have made
                    but too famous, and who had embittered the existence of his first wife; but he
                    did not long enjoy the happiness after which he had sighed. She died in childbed
                    in the beginning of 1786. From that moment his own life only lingered on; and
                    the fire of his genius seemed extinguished with the passion which had so long
                    nourished it. He had scarcely strength enough, in the intervals of his
                    dejection, to finish his <hi rend="italic">Song of Songs,</hi> a sort of
                    dithyrambic or nuptial hymn, intended to celebrate his second marriage, and
                    which is a strange mixture of frantic passion, religious devotion, and the most
                    bombastic expression. It was the last production of Bürger. Having studied the
                    philosophy of Kant, he had an idea of deriving some advantage from it at
                    Göttingen, where it had not yet been taught. He undertook to explain it in a
                    course of lectures, which were attended by a great number of young people. The
                    satisfaction which the university expressed to him for two cantatas which he
                    composed in 1787, at the period of the fifty years’ jubilee of this illustrious
                    institution, and his nomination to the situation of-professor extraordinary,
                    reanimated his spirits. Fortune appearing to smile on Him once more, he formed
                    the design of marrying again, in order to provide a mother for his children.
                    During one of the moments when he was most occupied with this idea, he received
                    a letter from Stuttgard, in which a young woman, whose style indicated a
                    cultivated mind, and her sentiments an elevated and feeling heart, after
                    describing to him, with enthusiasm, the impression which his poetry had made
                    upon her, offered him her hand and heart. Bürger spoke of the thing at first
                    only in jest, but the information which he received respecting the character,
                    the fortune, and personal accomplishments of his correspondent having excited
                    his curiosity, he took a journey to Stuttgard, and brought back with him a wife
                    who embittered and dishonoured the rest of his days. In less than three years he
                    saw himself under the necessity of obtaining a divorce from her; and the ruin of
                    his health aggravated the absolute disorder of his finances. Confined to a small
                    chamber, the favourite poet of Germany wasted the remainder of his strength in
                    translations ordered by foreign booksellers; but sickness and grief soon
                    deprived him even of this resource, and he must have died in the most frightful
                    state of want, if the government of Hanover had not extended some kindness to
                    him. He died on the 8th of June 1794, of a disorder of the bowels, which he had
                    never believed to be dangerous.</p>
                <p>Bürger is only remarkable as a lyric poet. He has tried all the different species
                    of this class of the productions of genius; but he succeeded eminently only in
                    the song and the ballad. We shall, perhaps, characterize his genius sufficiently
                    by saying that his imagination is more fresh than rich,—that he has more
                    sensibility than elevation, more naivete and good nature than delicacy or taste.
                    His style sparkles by its clearness, its energy, and from an elegance which is
                    rather the result of labour than of natural grace; he possesses, in short, all
                    the qualities which please the multitude. Allowing the title of poet only to
                    those whose writings were calculated to become popular, he early habituated
                    himself to reject whatever appeared to him not sufficiently intelligible and
                    interesting to all classes of readers. Always clear and forcible, he is never
                    either low or trivial; and if at certain times there appears a want of selection
                    and care in the details, yet the sentiments are uniformly noble, and the moral
                    intention of the majority of his pieces altogether irreproachable. Some breathe
                    the loftiest piety and the purest love of virtue. Wieland said of him (see the
                    <hi rend="italic">German Mercury,</hi> 1778), that in composing his poem
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">Mcennerheuschheit</hi> (on Chastity), Bürger had
                    deserved better of the present and future generations, than if he had written
                    the finest treatise of morality. This little piece has been inserted in most of
                    the collections of hymns for the use of the Lutheran church.</p>
                <p>There are three editions of Bürger’s works. The first two appeared in his
                    lifetime, in 1778 and 1789, in 3 vols. 8vo; and the third, after his death, was
                    published by his friend Ch. Reinhard, in 4 vols. 1796. All three were printed at
                    Göttingen. The last contains some posthumous pieces, and miscellanies in prose.
                    We must confine ourselves to a short notice of those for which their merit or
                    the singularity of the subject has procured the greatest degree of celebrity. 1.
                    A translation, or rather an imitation, of the <hi rend="italic">Vigil of Venus
                    {Pervigilium Veneris.')</hi> It is a fine piece of poetic diction and rythmical
                    harmony. 2. <hi rend="italic">Leonora,</hi> a romance; which belongs to the
                    class which Bürger himself called the <hi rend="italic">epic lyric.</hi> This
                    story is borrowed from a popular tradition, of which the traces are to be found
                    in the different countries of the north. <hi rend="italic">Leonora</hi> was
                    translated into Danish in 1788, six times into English, by Stanley, Pyc,
                    Spencer, Taylor, &amp;c·, and from English into French by De la Madelaine in
                    1811. The translation by Mr Spencer is accompanied with engravings after designs
                    by Lady Diana Beauclerc∙ Two German composers have set it to music. Bürger often
                    appeared very ill contented with the vast success of this production of his
                    youth. He preferred a great number of his other poems, and was himself the first
                    to blame the puerile trick of the play upon sounds which he has here indulged
                    in. 3. <hi rend="italic">The Ministers Daughter of</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Taubenhain</hi> is the story of the seduction and tragical end of a young girl.
                    There are in this, as in the other productions of the same author, some
                    objectionable details, but the whole leaves a deep impression. 4. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Inhuman Huntsman.</hi> 5. <hi rend="italic">The Song of the
                    Brave</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> in which the heroism of a peasant, who saves
                    a family from the fury of the waves, is related with admirable feeling. 6. <hi
                    rend="italic">The Song of Songs, conceived at the foot of the altar.</hi> This
                    is a hymn or ode in praise of his Molly. 7. <hi rend="italic">A</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Travestie</hi><hi rend="italic">of the Fable of Jupiter and
                    Europa.</hi> This is a piece of humour of the most clumsy kind, and in a taste
                    the most wretched, yet it had a great run when it first appeared. 8. <hi
                    rend="italic">A translation in iambic verse, of some boohs of the Iliad.</hi>
                    The choice of the measure is by no means happy. He was accordingly requested
                    ironically, to set about translating Anacreon into hexameters, when he had
                    finished his version of Homer into German iambics. 9. An excellent <hi
                    rend="italic">Translation of Shakspeards Macbeth,</hi> lθ∙ <hi rend="italic"
                    >Pieces of Poetry and of Rhetorical Prose.</hi> He had begun to write critical
                    observations on his own works, with equal severity and sagacity; but he has only
                    left some fragments of this work. 11. He was editor of the Göttingen <hi
                    rend="italic">Almanach</hi><hi rend="italic">of the Muses,</hi> from 1779 to
                    1794. Vetterlein, Politz, and Engel, have published a selection of the poetry of
                    Bürger, with notes; and celebrated composers, such as Schulz and Reichardt, have
                    set a great number of his songs to music. Bürger’s third wife, whom German
                    biography has thought worthy to have her name associated with his on account of
                    her taste for literature, and particularly poetry, is author of several pieces
                    in verse i <hi rend="superscript"> ns</hi> ξR' ed in the collections. The one
                    having for its title <hi rend="italic">Th</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                    e</hi><hi rend="italic">Raillery of a Mother,</hi> is sufficient to prove her
                    poetica talent.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
