<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0705-4935-0144-03" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">BOUGUER, Peter</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 5, page 144</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="16" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term><term n="13" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rn70">Snow</term><term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20m0w">Mess</term><term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4xw48182">Invalids</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210572">Iceland</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1211700">Mexico</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="16" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term><term n="13" ref="fasttopic:1121907">Snow</term><term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1042815">Objectivity</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:961111">Hospitalers</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:977967">Invalids</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193734935" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">BOUGUER, <hi rend="smallcaps">Peter</hi></label>, an eminent
                    French mathematician, was born in 1698. His father was king’s professor of
                    hydrography at Croisic in Lower Brittany, one of the best hydrographers of his
                    time, and author of an excellent treatise on navigation. Young Bouguer was bred
                    to mathematics from his infancy, and made rapid progress in that science. At an
                    early age he was appointed to succeed his father in the chair of professor of
                    hydrography, after having undergone a strict examination in mathematics, so as
                    completely to satisfy his examiners. In 1727 he gained the prize given by the
                    Academy of Sciences of Paris for his paper “On the best manner of forming and
                    distributing the masts of ships.” He got two other prizes from the academy in
                    the course of four years: the one was bestowed on him for his dissertation “On
                    the best method of observing the altitude of stars at sea the other for his
                    paper “On the best method of observing the variation of the compass at sea.”
                    These papers are published in the <hi rend="italic">Prix de l’Academie des
                    Sciences.</hi> In 1729 he published a work entitled <hi rend="italic">Essai
                    d</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">Optique sur la Gradation de la Lumière,</hi> the
                    object of which is to define the quantity of light which is lost by passing
                    through a given extent of the atmosphere. He finds the light of the sun to be
                    300 times more intense than that of the moon.</p><p>He was soon after made professor of hydrography at Havre, whereby he had the
                    advantage of being nearer Paris than before; and he was chosen associate
                    geometer of the Academy of Sciences, an office which did not require residence
                    in Paris. In this office he was the successor of Maupertuis. Afterwards he was
                    promoted in the academy to the place of pensioned astronomer, and came to reside
                    in Paris.</p><p>It was resolved in France to send an expedition to South America for the purpose
                    of measuring a degree of the meridian near the equator. From that measurement,
                    compared with the length of a degree of the meridian in other latitudes, the
                    deviation from sphericity in the figure of the earth might be known. The academy
                    made choice of four of its members to proceed on this voyage; they were Godin,
                    Bouguer, and De la Condamine, for the geodetical operation, and the younger
                    Jussieu for observations in natural history. Bouguer and his fellow-travellers
                    sailed from La Rochelle in 1735, and it was ten years before he returned to
                    France. The account of his operations during the expedition is given by him in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of the Academy of Sciences,</hi> 1744, and in a
                    separate work entitled <hi rend="italic">La Figure de la Terre determinee par
                    les Observations de MM. Eouguer et De la Condamine.</hi> There is likewise<pb break="no" facs="nls:193734948" xml:id="kp-eb0705-4948-0145"/> an
                    account of this expedition published by Don George Juan and Don Antonio de
                    Ulloa, two scientific naval officers, who accompanied the expedition by order of
                    the Spanish government. The length of a portion of the meridian was measured on
                    the ground by means of a base and a set of triangles. Then, by observing the
                    altitude of the <hi rend="italic">s</hi> of Orion which passed near the zenith
                    simultaneously at the two ends of the meridian line that had been measured, that
                    line was found to contain 3° 7' of latitude. A star near the zenith was
                    employed, to the end that the observation might not be affected by refraction;
                    <hi rend="italic subscript"> l</hi> of Orion passed the meridian in the zenith
                    near the middle of the line measured, so that the distance of that star <hi rend="italic">south of</hi> the zenith of the northern extremity of the line was
                    1° 25' 46"; and its distance <hi rend="italic">north</hi> of the zenith of the
                    southern extremity of the line was 1° 41' 13", the sum of these two numbers
                    making 3° 7'. The altitude was taken by zenith sectors of a long radius. The
                    ground on which these operations were performed was elevated 12,000 feet above
                    the level of the sea, and 420Ö feet above the neighbouring city of Quito, and
                    situate in a plain extending from north to south, between the two ridges of the
                    Cordillera. The northern extremity of the arc was on the equator. The length of
                    the degree resulting was 56,767 toises; but this was the degree of a curve
                    circumscribed round the earth at the height of 12,000 feet above the level of
                    the sea; and the length of the degree at the level of the sea deduced from this,
                    with some other corrections, is 56,753 toises. This length of the degree of the
                    meridian at the equator was compared with the degree of the meridian measured in
                    France, with the degree measured in Lapland, and with the degree of longitude
                    deduced in the south of France. From this comparison it was concluded that the
                    equatorial diameter of the earth is to the polar diameter as 179 to 178, and
                    that the equatorial radius of the earth was about eight leagues longer than the
                    polar. Since the time of Bouguer, degrees have been measured in different
                    climates with more accurate instruments than he possessed; but the precise
                    proportion of the equatorial and polar diameters of the earth is not yet finally
                    ascertained. Bougucr makes the excess of the equatorial diameter above the polar
                    to be <hi rend="subscript"> τ</hi>-∣-g∙; Sir Isaac Newton made it <hi rend="smallcaps">j+ĳ·;</hi> Laplace, calculating from the lunar motion, j-ŗŗ;
                    Melanderhielm and Svanberg, from a degree measured anew in Lapland in 1783,
                    compared with the degree measured in the province of Quito, Bouguer found the
                    seconds pendulum of a line shorter at the summit of Pichincha than at the level
                    of the sea; that is, the force of gravity was less by one 1200th part at that
                    elevation.</p><p>He made some observations on the limit of perpetual snow, a subject which has
                    been elucidated since his time by the researches of Humboldt, Von Buch,
                    Wahlenberg, and others. At the equator the limit of perpetual snow is at 14,760
                    feet above the sea, a height equal to that of Mont Blanc. In Mexico in the
                    latitude of 19° 20', it is at 13,800 feet, according to Humboldt. In latitude
                    28° 15', where the Peak of Teneriffe is situate, it is supposed to be 11,700
                    feet: the Peak is only 11,454 feet, and has no perennial snow. On Etna, in
                    latitude 37° 30', the edge of the perennial snow is at the height of 9000 feet.
                    On Mount Caucasus, in latitude 42° 30', the limit is at 9900 feet; whilst on the
                    Pyrenees, in latitude 42° 45', it descends to 1400 above the sea; and on the
                    Swiss Alps, in latitude 46°, to 8220 feet. In Iceland, in latitude 65°, the edge
                    of the perennial snow is at the perpendicular height of 2892 feet from the sea.
                    In Lapland, in latitude 67°, where the summers are warmer than in Iceland,
                    though the winters are colder, the perennial snow does not descend so low,
                    attaining only to 3300 French feet from the sea, as Von Buch and Wahlenberg
                    ascertained by barometrical observations. When the latitudes arc the same, a
                    solitary mountain will have the edge of the perennial snow higher than a
                    mountain surrounded by others, on account of the warm winds from the
                    neighbouring plains. A mountain in an inland situation will have the border of
                    the perennial snow higher than a mountain in the same latitude, and situated in
                    an island, the summers which reduce the limits of the snow being warmer in the
                    inland situation. When the mass of perennial snow is large, glaciers are formed
                    which descend below the limit of perennial snow. Chimboraço has 5400 feet of its
                    height covered with perpetual snow, according to Humboldt. Bouguer thought he
                    could perceive that the clouds do not ascend higher than 2400 feet above the
                    summit of Chimboraço. If there were mountains whose height reached beyond the
                    greatest height to which the clouds attain, all the part of the mountain above
                    the region of the clouds would be free from snow, although exposed to intense
                    cold. On Bouguer’s supposition of the height to which the clouds ascend, the
                    upper limit of snow at Chimboraço would be at the height of 22,200 feet above
                    the sea; and the distance between the upper limit of snow and the lower limit
                    would be there about 7800 feet.</p><p>Bouguer, whilst he was at the equator, made observations to ascertain the
                    obliquity of the ecliptic, which he found to be 23° 28' 28". He also made some
                    experiments on the deviation of the plumb-line from the vertical, occasioned by
                    the attraction of a neighbouring mountain, a phenomenon afterwards investigated
                    by Dr Maskelyne on the mountain Schehallien.</p><p>The number of Bouguer’s papers contained in the printed Memoirs of the Academy of
                    Sciences, is a proof of the assiduity with which he performed his duty in the
                    academy. His <hi rend="italic">Heliometer</hi> is described in the Memoirs of
                    the Academy for 1748. It is an object-glass micrometer, and its essential parts
                    consist of an astronomical dioptric telescope, with two object-glasses of the
                    same, focal length placed side by side. When this instrument is directed to the
                    sun, each object-glass gives an image of that luminary; and the object-glasses
                    are so placed that the limbs of the two images touch when the diameter of the
                    sun is greatest, and when the diameter is less there is an interval between the
                    limbs of the two images.</p><p>Some experimenters maintained that the plumb-line had a diurnal oscillation;
                    Bouguer showed that it remains at rest. He employed for this purpose a
                    telescope, attached to the end of a chain 187 feet long, suspended within the
                    dome of the church of the Hospital of Invalids at Paris: the telescope was
                    directed to a distant mark, so that any motion in this long pendulous system
                    might be seen by the deviation of the wires of the telescope from the mark. The
                    particulars of this experiment are to be found in the <hi rend="italic">Mém. de
                    l’Academic des Sciences,</hi> 1754.</p><p>In the volume for 1739 and 1749 there are papers of his on the astronomical
                    refraction in the torrid zone, particularly in cases where the star is seen at
                    more than 90° from the zenith, in consequence of the observer being in a high
                    situation. In the volume for 1747, he proposed, a log of a new construction for
                    measuring a ship’s way.</p><p>In the same collection there are papers of his on the length of the pendulum, on
                    the form of the prow which suffers least resistance in passing through the
                    water, and on a variety of other subjects. He bestowed great pains on his works,
                    and his health at length became impaired by a sedentary life, and too constant
                    application to scientific pursuits. He died in 1758, aged sixty. His disposition
                    was naturally mild, and the dissensions that arose between him and his
                    fellow-traveller De la Condamine caused him great vexation. He was impressed,
                    from his earliest years, with a conviction of the truths of Christianity<pb break="no" facs="nls:193734961" xml:id="kp-eb0705-4961-0146"/>. By
                    economy he had acquired a moderate fortune, a part of which he bequeathed to the
                    poor.</p><p>The following is a list of his principal works: <hi rend="italic">Traité cľ
                    Optique sur la Gradation de la Eumiere,</hi> 1729 and 1760. <hi rend="italic">Entretiens sur la Cause de l’inclinaison des Orbites des Planètes,</hi> 1734;
                    another edition in 1749. <hi rend="italic">Traité de Navire, de sa construction,
                    et de ses mouvemens,</hi> 1746,4to. <hi rend="italic">Ta Figure de la Terre
                    déterminée, par les Observations de Mess. Bouguer et de la Condamine, envoyés
                    par ordre du Poy au Pérou;</hi> par M. Bouguer, 1749,4to. <hi rend="italic">Nouveau Traite de Navigation, contenant la Théorie et la Pratique du Pi~
                    lotage,</hi> 1753. A new edition by De la Caille, 1761. <hi rend="italic">Solution des Principaux Problèmes sur la Manoeuvre des Vaisseaux,</hi> 1757.
                    <hi rend="italic">Operations faites pour la Verification du Degré du Méridien
                    entre Paris et Amiens;</hi> par Mess. Bouguer, Camus, Cassini, et Pingré,
                    1757.</p><p>After his return from South America he was editor of the <hi rend="italic">Journal des Savans.</hi> Some of his papers in the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of
                    the Academy of Sciences</hi> have been mentioned in this article; his <hi rend="italic">Eloge</hi> is contained in the volume for 1758. <hi rend="smallcaps">(b b.)</hi></p></div></body></text></TEI>