<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0705-6833-0290-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BRISSOT, Peter</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 5, page 290</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b40z70z6b">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47s7hw9j">Girondists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4610vs0f">Archbishops</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4c53f41h">Physicians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4f47gx2h">Physics</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1095066">Republicanism</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:864940">Clubs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:942930">Girondists</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1170328">War</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:874582">Conducting</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1062841">Physicians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193736833" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BRISSOT, <hi rend="smallcaps">Peter</hi></label>, one of the
                    ablest physicians of the sixteenth century, was born at Fontenay-le-Comte, in
                    Poitou, in 1478. He studied at Paris, and, having taken his doctor’s degree,
                    bent his thoughts on reforming physic, by restoring the precepts of Hippocrates
                    and Galen, and exploding the maxims of the Arabians; for which purpose he
                    publicly explained Galen’s works, instead of those of Avicenna, Rhases, and
                    Mesvé. He afterwards resolved to travel to acquire the knowledge of plants; and
                    going to Portugal, he practised physic in the city of Evora. His new method of
                    bleeding in pleurisies, on the side where the pleurisy was situated, raised a
                    kind of civil war among the Portuguese physicians, and was brought before the
                    university of Salamanca, which at last gave judgment, that the opinion ascribed
                    to Brissot was the pure doctrine of Galen. The partisans of Denis, his opponent,
                    appealed in 1529 to the emperor, to prevent the practice, as being attended with
                    destructive consequences; but Charles III. duke of Savoy happening to die at
                    this time of a pleurisy, after having been bled on the opposite side, the
                    prosecution dropped. He wrote an Apology for his practice, but died before it
                    was published, in 1552, by his friend Anthony Luceus. Renatus Moreau printed a
                    new edition at Paris in 1622, and annexed to it a treatise entitled <pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:193736846" xml:id="kp-eb0705-6846-0291"/><hi rend="italic"
                    >De Sanguinis Missione in Pleuritide,</hi> together with a life of Brissot.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Brissot, John Peter,</hi> the chief of the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Brissotine</hi> or pure republican party in France during the early stages of
                    the revolution, was born at the village of Ouaroille, near Chartres, in the
                    Orleannois, on the 14th of January 1754. His father, who was a pastry-cook, gave
                    his son a liberal education, and Brissot became an author when he had scarcely
                    left college. He exhibited a decided predilection for politics, and displayed an
                    early zeal for republican principles. The boldness of his writings against the
                    inequality of ranks excited the displeasure of the government, and subjected him
                    to a prosecution and imprisonment in the Bastile. Having been restored to
                    liberty through the influence of the Duke of Orleans, at the solicitation of
                    Madame de Genlis, he married one of the duchess’s women, and soon afterwards
                    went to England, with secret instructions, it is said, from the lieutenant of
                    the police. Others assert that he came over to London to avail himself of the
                    freedom of the press in conducting a periodical publication, the design of which
                    was to enlighten the people of France on the subject of civil liberty. It is
                    certain that he endeavoured to maintain himself in London by his literary
                    talents; but the failure of this attempt subjected him to embarrassments, from
                    which he was relieved by the liberality of a friend, and he then returned to his
                    native country.</p>
                <p>Having again rendered himself obnoxious to the government by an attack on the
                    administration of the Archbishop of Sens, he escaped a second imprisonment by a
                    journey to Holland. During a temporary residence at Mecklin he published a
                    periodical paper called <hi rend="italic">Le Courrier Belgique.</hi> In the
                    beginning of the year 1788 he repaired to America; but on the approach of the
                    revolution he returned to Paris, resolved to take an active part in the scenes
                    which were just preparing. He commenced his revolutionary career in 1789, by the
                    publication of some pamphlets, and particularly of a journal entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Le Patriote François.</hi> He belonged to the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Representation des Communes,</hi> which was formed in the capital a short time
                    previous to the memorable 14th of July. On the storming of the Bastile, the keys
                    were deposited with him. He was elected president of the Jacobin Club; and, in
                    consequence of his zeal and activity in the revolutionary cause, he was
                    appointed by his colleagues a member of the <hi rend="italic">Comité des
                    Recherches,</hi> which served as the model of all those committees which were
                    afterwards successively formed under similar denominations, and with similar
                    objects; such as the <hi rend="italic">Comités de Surveillance, de Surete
                    Generale, de Salιιt Public,</hi> &amp;c. Of this committee Brissot was the
                    president; and, while in this situation, he acquired a number of enemies. A
                    French writer of the name of Morande published at Paris, in 1791, a periodical
                    pamphlet, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Argus,</hi> in which he assailed
                    the character of Brissot with great bitterness, representing his conduct in the
                    most odious colours, and even accusing him of robbery; an accusation which,
                    there is reason to believe, was utterly calumnious.</p>
                <p>On the flight of the royal family in 1791, Brissot, in concert with the Chevalier
                    de Laclos, drew up the famous petition of the <hi rend="italic">Champ de
                    Mars,</hi> demanding the abdication of the king, which became the signal for a
                    dangerous insurrection, that was with difficulty quelled by the interposition of
                    the national guard. This circumstance is said to have been the occasion of his
                    quarrel with Μ. de Lafayette, to whom he had previously been zealously attached.
                    At this period the republican faction began to a'ssum'e∙a consistent-form, and
                    to utter their Sentiments with ’ freedom and boldness. Brissot, who had been one
                    of its first and most zealous apostles,-was re turned a member to the National
                    Assembly, in spite of the opposition of the court, to whom he had become
                    extremely formidable; and from this time he displayed an implacable enmity to
                    the king. The National Assembly attributing to Brissot talents which he does not
                    appear to have possessed, appointed him a member of the diplomatic committee, of
                    which he became the habitual organ; and in this capacity he was the constant
                    advocate of the most violent public measures, and never ceased to demand a
                    declaration of war against all the powers of Europe. In order to attain this
                    object, it was necessary to remove the ministers, whose dispositions were
                    favourable to peace. Brissot accordingly attacked them all, but particularly M.
                    Delessart, who was at the head of the department of foreign affairs; and, by
                    repeated denunciations, he at length succeeded in obtaining a decree of
                    accusation against him. His place was supplied by Dumouriez, under whose
                    administration war was declared against the emperor of Germany, on the 20th of
                    April 1792. From this period, however, the political influence of Brissot began
                    to decline. Robespierre, with whom he had previously been intimately connected,
                    now declared himself his enemy, denounced him at the Jacobin Club as a traitor
                    to his country and an enemy of the people, and continued to persecute him with
                    unrelenting rancour, until he finally effected his destruction. Alarmed at the
                    storm which was gathering around him, Brissot, in concert with the other leaders
                    of his party, attempted to form a reconciliation with the constitutional
                    royalists; but this attempt having proved abortive, he reverted to his former
                    opinions and line of conduct, and continued to denounce to popular vengeance all
                    those whom he knew to be attached to the king. But although his writings may
                    naturally be supposed to have excited those dispositions among the people which
                    gave rise to the atrocities of the times, he had no direct influence on the
                    revolution of the I0th of August, which appears to have been planned and
                    directed by Danton. He was chosen a deputy to the National Convention for the
                    department of the Eure, where he played only an inferior part, and was
                    continually exposed to the rancorous attacks of Robespierre. It was Brissot,
                    however, who, as the organ of the diplomatic committee, obtained the declaration
                    of war against England and Holland, on the 1st of February 1793. This may be
                    considered as the last act of his political life; for from thenceforth he was
                    only occupied in defending himself against his numerous enemies.</p>
                <p>The party distinguished by the name of the <hi rend="italic">Mountain</hi> had
                    now acquired a complete ascendancy, and meditated the destruction of their
                    opponents, the <hi rend="italic">Girondists,</hi> to which latter party Brissot
                    was attached. Having at length been proscribed, after the revolution of the 31st
                    of May, he was arrested at Moulins while attempting to make his escape into
                    Switzerland, sent to Paris, subjected to a mock trial before the revolutionary
                    tribunal, and beheaded on the 31st of October 1793, at the age of
                    thirty-nine.</p>
                <p>Brissot was somewhat below the middle size, a little deformed, and of a feeble
                    constitution. His countenance was pale and melancholy, and he affected an
                    extreme simplicity in his dress. With regard to his intellectual character, his
                    talents appear to have been much beneath his reputation, and he certainly
                    possessed more zeal than judgment. Notwithstanding the violence of his writings,
                    declamations, and public conduct, however, he was not deficient in humanity;
                    and, in the intercourse of private life, his manners are said to have been mild
                    and accommodating. As an author, Brissot has not much merit; his style is
                    monotonous, verbose, and tedious; and, upon the whole, it is wonderful that,
                    with such slender abilities, he should have acquired so great an ascendancy in
                    public <pb break="no" facs="nls:193736859" xml:id="kp-eb0705-6859-0292"
                    />opinion. The best articles of his journal are said to have been written by his
                    secretary Dupre. The following are the principal productions of his pen :—1.
                    Moyens d’Adou-cir la Rigueur des Lois Penales en France, Chalons, 1781, 8vo; 2.
                    Un 1ndependant'de l’Ordre des Avocats sur la Decadence du Barreau en France,
                    1781, 8vo; 3. De la Vérité, ou Méditations, &amp;c. 1782, 8vo; 4. Le
                    Philadelphien à Geneve, 1783, 8vo; 5. Théorie des Lois Criminelles, 1781, 2
                    vols. 8vo; 6. Bibliothèque Philosophique du Législateur, du Politique, du
                    Jurisconsulte, 1782—1786, 10 vols. 8vo; Tableau de la Situation Actuelle des
                    Anglais dans les Indes Orientales, &amp;c. 1784-5, 8vo; 8. Journal du Lycée de
                    Londres, &amp;c. published in monthly numbers,</p>
                <p>1784, 8vo; 9. Un Défenseur du People à l’Empereur Joseph IL, sur son Règlement
                    concernant l’Emigration, &amp;c.</p>
                <p>1785, !2mo; 10. Examen Critique des Voyages dans l’Amérique Septentrionale, par
                    le Marquis de Chatellux,</p>
                <p>1786, 8vo; 11. Voyages en Europe, en Asie, et en Afrique, translated from the
                    English, with notes, 1786 and 1790, 2 vols. 8vo; 12. Nouveau Voyage dans les
                    Etats-Unis de l’Amerique Septentrionale, 1791, 3 vols. 8vo. To the first volume
                    of this work was prefixed a life of Brissot, which was translated into English,
                    and published separately in 1794. Besides these works, Brissot wrote a variety
                    of pamphlets, and articles inserted in periodical publications, which it is
                    unnecessary to enumerate. See the life of Brissot, above mentioned, and the <hi
                    rend="italic">Biographie Universelle.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
