<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0816-0767-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ZANTE</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 767</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rm1n">Plains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d50g08p">Groups</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rq88">Growth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1065075">Plains</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:948571">Growth</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n816/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZANTE</label>, the ancient <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Zacynthus,</hi> an island of Greece, one of the Ionian group, in the Ionian
                    Sea, in 37° 40' N. lat. and 21° E. long., is 25 miles long, about 12 broad, and
                    64 miles round, with an area of 277 square miles, and a population in 1879 of
                    44,522, and estimated in 1887 at 48,000. Zante lies 8 miles south of Cephalonia,
                    forming with it, Leucas, and Ithaca a crescent-shaped insular group, which
                    represents the crests of a submerged limestone ridge facing the Gulf of Patras.
                    At Ithaca, its northernmost member, the ridge almost touches the adjacent coast
                    of Acarnania, with which it is geologically connected; and at Zante, its
                    southernmost member, it recedes about 15 miles from the coast of Elis in Morea.
                    Zante is of somewhat irregular oval shape, with its main axis disposed in the
                    direction from north-west to south-east, and indented by a deep inlet at its
                    southern extremity. The surface is mainly occupied by an extensive and highly
                    productive central plain, skirted on the west side by a range of bare limestone
                    hills from 1000 to 1200 feet high, which fall gently landwards, but present bold
                    steep cliffs towards the sea, and which culminate northwards in Mount Skopos
                    (1500 feet ?), the highest point in the island. On the east side the plain is
                    also limited by a low ridge, which still justifies the epithet of <hi
                    rend="italic">nemorosa,</hi> or the “wooded,” applied by Virgil to Zacynthus.
                    These hills are densely clothed to their summits with an exuberant growth of
                    olives, figs, myrtles, laurels, oranges, aloes, vines, and other sub-tropical
                    plants. Travellers sailing between this coast and the mainland describe in
                    enthusiastic language the charming effect produced by these masses of evergreen
                    vegetation rising in long terraces above the surrounding waters, and everywhere
                    interspersed with pleasant homesteads and hamlets embowered in verdure.
                    Nevertheless Zante, notwithstanding its Italian title of “Fior di Levante,” is
                    inferior in picturesque beauty to Corfu, owing to the less elevation of its
                    hills and the somewhat monotonous character of the great central plain. This
                    plain, however, is highly cultivated, forming an almost continuous stretch of
                    gardens and vineyards, varied here and there with a few patches of cornfields
                    and pasture lands. Here is grown a peculiar dwarf vine, whose fruit, the
                    “currant” (from “Corinth ”) of commerce, forms the chief resource and staple
                    export of Zante, as well as of the neighbouring mainland. In 1886 the currant
                    crop for the whole of Greece was valued at £2,000,000, of which nearly one-fifth
                    was raised in Zante, chiefly for the English market. The vine, which grows to a
                    height of 3 feet, begins to yield in seven years and lasts for over a century.
                    From the grape, which has a pleasant bitter-sweet taste, a wine is also
                    extracted, which is said to excel all others in flavour, fire, and strength.
                    Besides this species, there are nearly forty different kinds of vine and ten of
                    the olive, including the <hi rend="italic">karudolia,</hi> which yields the best
                    edible olive berry. For size, vigorous growth, and productiveness the olive tree
                    of Zante is rivalled only by that of Corfu.</p>
                <p>The island enjoys a healthy climate; and, although there are no perennial
                    streams, an abundant supply of good water is obtained from the numerous springs,
                    occurring especially in the eastern aud central districts. But earthquakes are
                    frequent and at times disastrous. During recent times the most destructive were
                    those of 1811, 1820, and 1840; and, although the prevailing geological
                    formations are sedimentary, chiefly calcareous, there seems no doubt that these
                    disturbances are of igneous origin. Other indications of volcanic agency are the
                    oil springs occurring on the coast, and even in the bed of the sea near Cape
                    Skinari on the north side, and especially the famous pitch or bituminous wells
                    already mentioned by Herodotus (<hi rend="italic">Hist.,</hi> bk. iv.). These
                    have been productive throughout the historic period and still yield a
                    considerable supply of pitch. They are situated in a swamp near the coast
                    village of Chieri, and comprise two basins, with alternate layers of water and
                    bitumen, the lower sheet of water apparently communicating with the sea.</p>
                <p>Zante, capital of the island, is a considerable seaport on the east side, with a
                    population of 16,250 (1879). It occupies the site of the ancient city of
                    Zacynthus, said to have been founded by Zacynthus, son of a legendary Arcadian
                    chief, Dardanus, to whom was also attributed the neighbouring citadel of
                    Psophis. But of this, as well as of the temple of Diana that formerly crowned
                    the summit of Mount Scopus, no vestiges can now be discovered.</p>
                <p>Traditionally the island formed part of the territory of Ulysses, king of Ithaca,
                    and at one time it appears to have also received a colony of Achaeans from
                    Peloponnesus. Later it joined the Athenian hegemony; but after the fall of
                    Athens the democratic party was replaced by an oligarchy, which ruled in the
                    interests of Sparta. Under the Romans Zacynthus was included in the province of
                    Epirus, and passed in mediaeval times successively from Byzantium to the Normans
                    (11th century), the Orsini, counts of Cephalonia (after the 4th crusade), and
                    the Tocco family, who held it with Cephalonia as vassals of the Neapolitan
                    Angevine dynasty. In the 15th century it was occupied by the Venetians, and was
                    held by them till the fall of the republic in 1797. Wrested in 1799 by the
                    Russians from the French, it was soon after seized by the English, and in 1815
                    constituted with the other Ionian Islands a “septinsular republic” under British
                    protection, till the union with Greece in 1864.</p>
                <p>The long Venetian occupation is reflected in the appearance, character, and to
                    some extent even the language and religion of the Zantiots. Nearly all the
                    aristocracy claim Venetian descent; most of the upper classes are bilingual,
                    speaking both Greek and Italian; and a considerable section of the population
                    are Roman Catholics of the Latin rite. Even the bulk of the people, although
                    mainly of Greek stock, form in their social usages a connecting link between the
                    Hellenes, whose language they speak, and the Western nations by whom they were
                    so long ruled. They have the reputation of being industrious and enterprising,
                    but passionate and revengeful. But no more high-minded, enlightened, and
                    courteous people can anywhere be found than in the circle of the Maddalenas,
                    Terzettis, Mercatis, and other families of Venetian lineage.</p>
                <p>See Balthazar Raimondini, <hi rend="italic">De Zacynthi Antiquitatibus;</hi> C.
                    Parrigopoulo, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de la Civilisation Hellénique;</hi> S.
                    de Nolhac, <hi rend="italic">La Dalmatie, les Îles Ioniennes,</hi> &amp;c.,
                    Paris, 1882.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
