<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0924-0811-0762-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">ZACHARIAE VON LINGENTHAL, Karl Salomo</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 24, page 762</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4m90280p">Law</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:993678">Law</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:994346">Lawyers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n811/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZACHARIAE VON LINGENTHAL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Karl
                    Salomo</hi></label> (1769-1843), German jurist, was born on 14th September 1769
                    at Meissen in Saxony. His family came from Austria. His father was a lawyer; his
                    mother, a Hessian, was the daughter of a pastor. Of feeble health and long the
                    only child of his parents, Karl did not go to school until the age of fifteen.
                    He afterwards studied philosophy, history, mathematics, and philology at the
                    university of Leipsic. In 1792 he went to Wittenberg as tutor to Count zur
                    Lippe, and whilst there he began to study law. There he came greatly under the
                    influence of Kant, traces of whose teaching remain even in his latest writings.
                    In 1794 Zachariae became a privat-docent, lecturing on canon law, in 1798
                    extraordinary professor, and in 1802 ordinary professor of feudal law. From that
                    time to his death in 1843, with the exception of a short period in which public
                    affairs occupied him, he poured out a succession of works covering the whole
                    field of jurisprudence and extending into other adjoining regions. He was also
                    indefatigable in the labour of his chair, and he was the editor of, or a copious
                    contributor to, more than one periodical. In 1807 he went to Heidelberg, then
                    beginning its period of splendour as a school of law. There, resisting many
                    calls to Göttingen, Berlin, and other universities, he remained until his death.
                    In 1811 he married under romantic circumstances. His wife died in four
                    years.</p>
                <p>In 1820 he was elected representative of the university in the first Baden
                    chamber, and four years later was made a member of the second. From 1825 to 1829
                    he devoted much time to political affairs and to the preparation of a code. He
                    was a constitutional reformer, averse to great or violent changes. He loved to
                    cite the saying of the Roman emperor to his adopted son,—“Imperaturus es
                    hominibus qui nec totam servitutem pati possent nec totam libertatem,”—“a
                    truth,” he observes in one of his many brochures <hi rend="italic">(Die
                    Souverainetätsrechte der Krone Würtemberg,</hi> Ac.), “which no Government and
                    no people should ever forget.” In 1842 he was ennobled with the title of Von
                    Lingenthal. To the last days of his life he toiled with the ardour of a young
                    student. His fame extended beyond Germany. The German universities then enjoyed
                    by tacit consent a jurisdiction in regard to legal questions of international
                    importance which had come down from the Middle Ages; and Zachariae was often
                    consulted as to questions arising in Germany, France, and England. Elaborate
                    “opinions,” some of them forming veritable treatises,— <hi rend="italic"
                    >e.g.,</hi> on Sir Augustus d’Este’s claim to the dukedom of Sussex, Baron de
                    Bode’s claim as an English subject to a share in the French indemnity, the
                    famous dispute as to the debts due to the elector of Hesse-Cassel, confiscated
                    by Napoleon, and the constitutional position of the Mecklenburg landowners,—were
                    composed by Zachariae. He died on 27th March 1843, leaving a son who has
                    worthily continued his father’s labours in jurisprudence.</p>
                <p>Zachariae’s true history is in his writings, which are extremely numerous and
                    multifarious. They deal with almost every branch of jurisprudence; they are
                    philosophical, historical, and practical; they relate to Boman, canon, German,
                    and French law; and his curiosity extended to the writings of his
                    contemporaries, Bentham and Austin. A work on Sulla, in whom he sees another
                    Napoleon, and an unpublished translation of his favourite Tacitus were some of
                    the fruits of his restless activity. The first book of much consequence whieh he
                    published was <hi rend="italic">Die Einheit des Staats und der Kirche mit
                    Rücksicht auf die Deutsche Reichsverfassung</hi> (1797), one of the most
                    original of his works, displaying the writer’s power of analysis, his skill in
                    making a complicated set of facts appear to be deductions from a few
                    principles,—a study even now well worth reading. His theme is the relation of
                    religion to the state. Zachariae undertakes to show that with Christianity three
                    systems only are possible, — (1) what he calls the system of hierarchy,
                    according to which the state is under the power of the church, the object of the
                    former being subordinated to that of the latter; (2) the territorial system,
                    according to which the church is subject to the power of the state; and (3) what
                    he terms the collegiate system, according to which neither of the two societies
                    is subject to the other, and both have different objects in view. The
                    consequence of the adoption of these various systems—the principles of law which
                    must be accepted according as one or the other of them is supreme—he deduces
                    with much acumen. While much of his work has lost its interest, it remains a
                    luminous example of the application of the deductive process to historical
                    investigation, a proof that legal conceptions may often serve to give unity to
                    the complex facts of history. In 1805 appeared <hi rend="italic">Versuch einer
                    allgemeinen Hermeneutik des Rechts.</hi> Neither in English nor in Scotch legal
                    literature is there any book, so far as known to the present writer, covering
                    the field to which it relates. It is an attempt to found on the rules of grammar
                    and logic a system of interpretation applicable to all systems of law. The weak
                    part of the book is that, like so many of Zachariae’s works, it stops short at
                    the point where the inquiry would be most fruitful. Illustrations are taken from
                    Roman law; we miss any adequate treatment of the problems which the forms of
                    modern legislation raise. In 1806 appeared <hi rend="italic">Die Wissenschaft
                    der Gesetzgebung,</hi> a fragment, which is a curious outcome of the French
                    Revolution. Impressed by the overthrow or decay of the forces which had hitherto
                    held society together, he looked about for a better substitute for them than <hi
                    rend="italic">politique de circonstance</hi> offered. Many of Zachariae’s maxims
                    seem fanciful; there are divisions which do not elucidate, and distinctions made
                    apparently for their own sake. But the work is interesting; it shows that the
                    author was groping after the principle of utility as the guide of the
                    legislator; the study of very different facts had brought him independently to
                    much the same conclusion as Bentham had reached. Zachariae’s last work of
                    importance was <hi rend="italic">Vierzig Bucher vom Staate,</hi> published in
                    1839-42, with the motto <hi rend="italic">non omnis moriar.</hi> This was his
                    favourite work, and is the one to which his admirers point as his enduring
                    monument. Undoubtedly it contains much erudition and, what is rarer, many
                    original ideas as to the future of the state and of law. It has been compared to
                    <hi rend="italic">L'Esprit des Lois,</hi> and Zachariae, in spite of his
                    pedantry, has some tincture of the discursive brilliancy of Montesquieu. It
                    covers no small part of the field of Buckle’s first volume of the <hi
                    rend="italic">History of Civilisation.</hi> The reader will, however, seek in
                    vain for any order or system in some of the chapters of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Vierzig Bücher vom Staate.</hi> He was recasting many of his ideas as he wrote,
                    and the book ends before the process is completed. Among the most esteemed of
                    the works of Zachariae is that on <hi rend="italic">Staatsrecht,</hi> of the
                    originality of which he was proud, and his treatise on the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Code Napoléon,</hi> a marvellous work, considering it was composed by a German
                    professor who did not much concern himself with this subject till somewhat late
                    in life. There are no fewer than three French editions of his book, and it has
                    been translated into Italian. Zachariae edited with Mittermaier the <hi
                    rend="italic">Kritische Zeitschrift für Rechtswissenschaft und Gesetzgebung des
                    Auslandes,</hi> and the introduction which he wrote illustrates his wide reading
                    and his constant desire for new light upon old problems.</p>
                <p>Zachariae exhibits the best and the worst sides of German jurisprudence: there is
                    the desire not to base generalizations or conclusions on the peculiarities of
                    any one system, but to master the whole facts. He does not assume a distinction
                    or classification of Roman law to be necessarily scientific. He seeks real
                    reasons; he avoids the English lawyer’s favourite fallacy of proving <hi
                    rend="italic">idem per idem,</hi> of seeking to show the reasonableness of
                    anything by saying the same thing again in different language. Though a scholar,
                    Zachariae has not the weakness of exaggerating the importance of whatever is
                    rare or unpublished, and he has no delight in barren erudition. Himself a
                    learned pandectist, he had cast aside his countrymen’s proneness to find all
                    things in the <hi rend="italic">Corpus Juris.</hi> His books, however, have the
                    failings of so many German works on law. They want actuality; they have little
                    relation to the facts of life. They are leavened by metaphysics—often very bad
                    metaphysics, and not always by the same system. Nor is he a clear thinker. We
                    are never sure what is his notion of the province of jurisprudence; his
                    favourite idea appears to be that law creates among men an order similar to that
                    which exists in the physical world, and that it is a security for the freedom of
                    man’s will. The influence of Kant is observable in all his works. In his later
                    that of Hegel also appears; <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n812/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0924-0812-0763"/> and his mental changes do not end there. He does
                    not indeed say, “Back to Montesquieu; study facts, the simplest and primitive
                    facts above all; adopt his method, and improve upon it;” but that is the wise
                    spirit of some of his later works. Unfortunately he &lt;lid not fulfil the
                    promise which they contain. He had not learned to distinguish sharply between
                    the science and the practical art of jurisprudence, and we are never certain in
                    what capacity he speaks. He had not conceived clearly the truth that society
                    forms one whole, that the phenomena of law at any given time or place are not
                    accidents but the outcome of a long train of events, that, so regarded, they are
                    as much susceptible of scientific treatment as the facts of language, and that a
                    treatise on botany or, still more, one on comparative philology is a better
                    guide to what jurisprudence may yet be than a volume of Hugo or even Austin. It
                    was made a reproach to Zachariae that he changed his opinions. He did so; it was
                    a sign of his single-mindedness and restless curiosity. It is also one of the
                    reasons why his works are now little read. They opened paths, and they were
                    superseded by others which could not have existed without them.</p>
                <p>There is no adequate account of Zachariae and his works; the best are Robert von
                    Mohl’s <hi rend="italic">Geschichte u. Literatur der Staatswissenschaften</hi>
                    (1855-58) and Charles Brocher’s <hi rend="italic">K. S. Zachariae, sa Vie et ses
                    Oeuvres</hi> (1870). (J. M†.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
