<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0924-0831-0782-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ZEUS (9th edition, volume 24, page 782)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1243607">Earth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc0b">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r50f">Phoenicians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vj0c">Ritual</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44x54q60">Ritualism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1938968">Aryans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:818281">Aryanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120260">Sky</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098241">Ritual</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098260">Ritualization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098258">Ritualism</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n831/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ZEUS</label>, the chief deity of ancient Greek religion,
                    bears a name which almost certainly means “sky.” His title is identified by
                    etymologists with the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">Hyaus,</hi> the “bright one,”
                    “sky,” though his legend and place in religion are not closely akin to those of
                    the Vedic deity. It seems nearly certain that the peoples who speak Aryan
                    languages had at some remote time a common word for the sky, and nothing can be
                    more probable than that they also worshipped the vault of heaven. In what sense
                    the sky may have been an Aryan deity before the distant and obscure process
                    called the Aryan dispersion, it is not possible with certainty to say. The
                    followers of Mr Herbert Spencer might not inconsistently suppose that there was
                    once an Aryan medicine-man or chief named Sky, and that on his death his ghost
                    was worshipped and his cult finally blended with that of the actual natural
                    phenomenon. Or, again, it might be argued that the sky was originally adored as
                    a symbol of the Infinite, and that men, losing the original conception, and
                    misled by the personal appearance of the name as other words for sky became more
                    familiar, were deceived into the belief that “sky” was a personal deity. Or,
                    once more, theorists might urge that Sky was first worshipped at a stage of
                    early fancy, when all things in nature were looked on as personal and of human
                    parts and passions, while later the sky sank back into the category of lifeless
                    things, leaving Zeus as a distinct personal being and deity. Other hypotheses
                    might, no doubt, be invented, but unhappily we have no means of proving their
                    historical accuracy. It is a common thing among backward races, for example on
                    the Gold Coast, to find Sky worshipped as a god, or regarded as the
                    dwelling-place of gods. How and in what manner such conceptions were attained by
                    the ancestors of the ancient Greeks we can never know as a matter of fact</p>
                <p>Coming to historical and documentary evidence, our earliest knowledge of Zeus is
                    derived from the Homeric and Hesiodic poems. It is very probable that in the
                    legend and ritual of remote towns and temples in Greece we have traces of a
                    conception of Zeus much older than that which meets us in Homer. But Homer and
                    Hesiod are the most ancient literary testimonies; next to these come the
                    speculations of the early philosophers and the writings of the lyric poets,
                    Pindar, Herodotus, and the tragedians. Finally, we have the Zeus of the
                    philosophers of the central period,—Plato and Aristotle,—and the Zeus of the
                    later philosophic periods down to the prevalence of Christianity.</p>
                <p>By the time that Zeus meets us in Homer he has wandered far from the original
                    conception of him. Whatever that may have been, Zeus cannot have been first
                    imagined in an age of advanced society on the heroic system, that is, in an age
                    of the fully developed monogamous family of city states each governed by a king,
                    and of a general loose confederation, with a kind of upper and lower house,—the
                    prince’s council and the assembly of the people. It is, however, on the model of
                    such a society that the Olympian consistory is organized in Homer, with Zeus for
                    the bretwalda, the principal chief of the gods. Such a position Zeus holds in
                    Homer. The poet represents him as anthropomorphic,—a powerful, humorous, amorous
                    ruler, sometimes troubled by disputes among his younger brethren, —Hades and
                    Poseidon,—his wife, and his children. His claim to supreme authority is based on
                    primogeniture (77., XV. 187), whereas in Hesiod Zeus is the successful youngest
                    son of Cronus. Both poets agree that he has overthrown the paternal dynasty, and
                    established his own power after violent struggles. The legends in Hesiod are
                    full of ugly and puerile fables and conceits, dating doubtless from remote and
                    uncivilized antiquity. Though Zeus be so much of a magnified man in Homer, there
                    are probably traces of the elemental conception, and his union with Hera (<hi
                        rend="italic">Il.</hi>, xiv. 152) on the crest of Ida may be a poetic memory
                    of the old story of Heaven wedding Earth, though Hera cannot as a rule be
                    regarded as a form of Gaea or of Demeter. While among the gods Zeus is a father,
                    brother, and emperor, Homeric men sometimes use his name as we might use that of
                    God, in a religious rather than in a mythological sense. Now regarded as subject
                    to Fate, so that he cannot save even his own children from her decree, elsewhere
                    he seems to hold the gifts of Fate in his own hand: from two vast jars he deals
                    out good and evil to mankind. Where morals are concerned, he sanctions the oath
                    (ZZ., iii. 227) both in this world and the next, and he is the friend of
                    strangers and suppliants, the patron of the hospitable hearth. In Homer Zeus
                    does not assume the form of the lower animals, and in the strange passage where
                    he recounts his loves, the Leporello of his own Don Juan, he says nothing of
                    those well-known disguises. In Hesiod the old wild tales revive, and we learn,
                    for example (<hi rend="italic">Theog.,</hi> 886; compare the scholiast), that
                    Zeus swallowed his own wife, Metis, after inducing her to take the shape of a
                    fly, just as Puss-in-Boots got rid of the ogre who turned himself into a mouse.
                    In Hesiod, too, we have the tale of Prometheus and Pandora, a tale which
                    afforded such an admirable theme for moral handling by Aeschylus. Zeus tempted
                    Epimetheus by the aid of the woman Pandora; hence came death into the world and
                    all our woe. Then Prometheus pitied and aided men, whom Zeus had intended to
                    destroy, and the hero was fixed to a rock in Caucasus by order of the god. The
                    myth may be allegorized in a dozen ways, and perhaps may be taken to mean that
                    man does not increase happiness by increasing <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit24newyrich/page/n832/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0924-0832-0783"/> knowledge, science, and the arts of life.
                    Without the gifts of Prometheus, carried to what Horace would have thought a
                    profane pitch of perfection, we should not have reached modern industrialism and
                    the horrors of modern war. In Hesiod Prometheus may stand for humanity vainly
                    struggling to be powerful and happy against that inflexible and ruthless law
                    which is Zeus And what shall the end be? How shall the ways of Zeus be justified
                    to men, and man’s rebellion be justified to Zeus? We no more know how Aeschylus
                    solved the problem mythically than we can discover the actual solution. The idea
                    that another shall voluntarily take the place of Prometheus (Aesch., <hi
                        rend="italic">Prom. Vinct.</hi> 1026) naturally recalls the theory of the
                    Atonement. To such mysteries does the Greek mind attain, and in such ultimate
                    perplexities is the conception of Zeus, the <hi rend="italic">Bon Dieu</hi> of
                    the Homeric Olympian festivals, involved.</p>
                <p>At the opposite pole from the Hesiodic Zeus is the Zeus who practically means the
                    unknown god, as Terpander sings, <hi rend="italic">Zeυ πάντων άρχά, πάντων
                        άγήτωρ,</hi> or, as the Orphic hymn (whatever its date) proclaims him, Zeύς
                        <hi rend="italic">κεφαλή,</hi> Zeύs μέ <hi rend="italic">σσa,</hi> ∆ιός δ' έ
                        <hi rend="italic">κ πάντα τέτυκτaι.</hi></p>
                <p>Thus Zeus becomes a shorthand symbol for the pantheistic deity.</p>
                <p>The Zeus of pure religion and of speculation is very different from the Zeus of
                    ritual and of local myth. To ritual, and to the local myths treasured by
                    priests, which often tried to explain the ritual, we owe the unbecoming
                    anecdotes of Zeus as the god who, in the form of ant, snake, bull, eagle, and so
                    forth, made love to the daughters of men. On this point reference may be made to
                    the work of the present writer, <hi rend="italic">Myths, Ritual, and
                        Religion</hi> (ii. 189). The hypothesis there offered is that the Greeks in
                    their early uncivilized state, dwelling in tribes and in scattered kraals or
                    villages, retained traditions like the totemic and magical beliefs of Red
                    Indians or Australians. When they became more united and more civilized, they
                    did not drop wholly the faith that they were descended from animals, nor wholly
                    forget such tales as the Indians tell of Manibozho and the Australians of
                    Punjel, but they transferred the old anecdotes to Zeus. In place of saying, “We
                    descend from a bull,” they said, “We descend from Zeus, who for purposes of
                    amorous disguise took the shape of a bull,” or a swan, or an ant, as the case
                    might be. Probably some foreign legends, Phoenician or African, were also
                    borrowed and attached to Zeus. If this be a correct, as it seems a possible,
                    hypothesis, then it will be well to be cautious in explaining the myths about
                    Zeus as if they were all of elementary origin, and all expressed in images some
                    natural process or series of natural phenomena. We must regard Zeus as an
                    extremely difficult complex, in which elemental myths, myths of savage fancy,
                    myths of perverted history, theories of early natural philosophy, and the ideas
                    of pantheistic speculation are all confusedly mingled. He is the sum of the
                    religious thought of Hellas, formed in the numberless ages between savagery and
                    complete civilization. He received human sacrifices even after the Christian
                    era; yet long before it he all but corresponded to the Unknown Substance of
                    Spencerian philosophy. (See Plato, <hi rend="italic">Rep.,</hi> viii. 565 D;
                    Suidas, <hi rend="italic">s.v.</hi> “Laphystius.”) A summary of the Zeus myths
                    will be found in Dr William Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Classical
                        Mythology.</hi> For a comparison between the character and attributes of
                    Jupiter and Zeus, see the article <hi rend="smallcaps">Jupiter.</hi></p>
                <p>Among modern works in which the character and legend of Zeus are discussed may be
                    recommended Welcker’s <hi rend="italic">Griechische Götterlehre</hi> (Gottingen,
                    1857); Preller’s <hi rend="italic">Griechische Mythologic</hi> (Berlin, 1872);
                    the <hi rend="italic">Selected Essays</hi> of Mr Max Miiller; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Le Sentiment Religieux en Grèce</hi> of Μ. Jules Girard (3d ed., Paris,
                    1887); and C. O. Müller’s <hi rend="italic">Introduction to a Scientific System
                        of Mythology</hi> (Eng. transl., London, 1844). The subject has not yet been
                    reached (1888) in Rosscher’s great <hi rend="italic">Lexikon.</hi> The
                    authorities named will introduce the reader in turn to other authors, their
                    researches and speculations. Heyne’s <hi rend="italic">Apollodorus</hi>
                    (Göttingen, 1803) is also useful. (A. L. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
