<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-9569-0208-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NICOTIANA, or Tobacco (7th edition, volume 16, page
                    208)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1432109">Tobacco</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1065823">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1122050">Snuff</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1037543">Nicotiana</term>
                    <term ref="fast:885683">Cutting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1128153">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gm3d">Tobacco</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6pc2x">Planting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q79t">Plants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qf8jt00">Snuff</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r47q">Cuttings</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ks6jd02">Spaniards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1211575">Jamaica</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207170">Malta</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194559569?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NICOTIANA, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Tobacco</hi></label>, a
                    plant so called from Nicot above mentioned. There are seven species of
                    nicotiana, of which the most remarkable is the <hi rend="italic">tabacum,</hi>
                    or common tobacco plant. This was first discovered in America by the Spaniards
                    about the year 1560, and by them imported into Europe. It had been used by the
                    inhabitants of America long before, and was called by those of the islands <hi
                    rend="italic">yoli,</hi> and by the inhabitants of the continent <hi
                    rend="italic">paetun.</hi> It was sent into Spain from Tabaco, a province of
                    Yucatan, where it was first discovered, and from which it takes its common name.
                    Sir Walter Raleigh, it is generallv said, first introduced it into England about
                    the year 1585, and taught his countrymen how to use it. Dr Cotton Mather,
                    however, in his Christian Philosopher, says, that in the above year one Mr Lane
                    brought over some of it from Virginia, which was the first time it had ever been
                    seen in Europe. Tobacco is commonly used by the oriental nations, though it is
                    uncertain by whom it was introduced amongst them. Considerable quantities of it
                    are cultivated in the Levant, on the coasts of Greece and the Archipelago, in
                    Italy, and also in the island of Malta.</p>
                <p>There are two varieties of that particular species of nicotiana which is
                    cultivated for common use, and which are distinguished by the names of <hi
                    rend="italic">Orinoko</hi> and <hi rend="italic">sweet-scented tobacco.</hi>
                    They differ from each other only in the figure of their leaves, those of the
                    former being somewhat longer and narrower than those of the latter. They are
                    tall herbaceous plants, growing erect with fine foliage, and rising with a
                    strong stem from six to nine feet in height. The stalk near the root is above an
                    inch in diameter, and surrounded with a kind of hairy or velvet clammy substance
                    of a yellowish-green colour. The leaves are rather of a deeper green, and grow
                    alternately at the distance of two or three inches from each other. They are
                    oblong, of a spear-shaped oval, and simple; the largest being about twenty
                    inches long, but decreasing in size as they ascend, till they come to be only
                    ten inches long, and about half as broad. The face of the leaves is much
                    corrugated, like those of spinage when fully ripe. Before they attain maturity,
                    when they are about five or six inches in length, the leaves are generally of a
                    full green, and rather smooth; but as they increase in size they become rougher,
                    and acquire a yellowish cast. The stem and branches are terminated by large
                    bunches of flowers, collected into clusters, of a delicate red, the edges, when
                    full blown, inclining to a pale purple. They continue in succession till the end
                    of the summer, when they are succeeded by seeds of a brown -colour and a kidney
                    shape. These are very small, each capsule containing about 1000; and the whole
                    produce of a single plant is reckoned at about 350,000. The seeds ripen in the
                    month of September.</p>
                <p>The following extract, which is copied from a manuscript of Dr Barham,<note
                    anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>This gentleman was
                    contemporary with Sir Hans Sloane. He was a man of great probity, an able
                    physician, and a skilful natura ist. He collected and arranged a number of the
                    plants of Jamaica, which he presented to Dr Sloane, and made several commu∙
                    nιcatιons to the Royal Society.</p></note> containing directions for raising,
                    cultivating, and curing tobacco in Jamaica, is perhaps worthy of the attention
                    of those who wish to be further acquainted with this subject.</p>
                <p>“Let the ground or woodland wherein you intend planting tobacco be well burned,
                    as the greater the quantity of wood ashes the better. The spot you intend
                    raising your plants on must be well strewed with ashes, laid smooth and light;
                    then blow the seed from the palmof your hand gently on the bed, and cover it
                    over with palm or plantain leaves.</p>
                <p>“When your plants are about four inches high, draw them and plant them out about
                    three feet asunder; and when they become as high as your knee, cut or pluck off
                    the top; and if there are more than twelve leaves on the plant, take off' the
                    overplus, and leave the rest entire.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:194559582?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-9582-0209"/>
                <p>“The plant should now be daily attended to, in order to destroy the caterpillars
                    that are liable to infest it; as also to take off every sprout or sucker that
                    puts out at the joints, in order to throw the whole vegetable nourishment into
                    the large leaves.</p>
                <p>“When the edges and points of the leaves begin to turn a little yellow, cut down
                    the stalks about ten o’clock in the morning, taking the opportunity of a fine
                    day, and be careful the dew is fully off the plant; and do not continue this
                    work after two in the afternoon. As fast as it is cut let it be carried into
                    your tobacco-house, which must be so close as to shut out all air (on this much
                    depends), and hung up on lines tied across, for the purpose of drying.</p>
                <p>“When the stalks begin to turn brownish, take them off the lines and put them in
                    a large binn, and lay on them heavy weights for twelve days; then take them out,
                    and strip off the leaves, and put them again into the binn, and let them be well
                    pressed, and so as no air gains admission, for a month. Take them out; tie them
                    in bundles about sixty leaves in each, which are called <hi rend="italic"
                    >monocoes,</hi> and are ready for sale. But observe to let them always be kept
                    close till you have occasion to dispose of them.</p>
                <p>“Let your curing house be well built, and very close and warm. If a boarded
                    building, it will not be amiss, in a wet situation, to cover the whole outside
                    with thatch and plantain trash, to keep off the damps; for by this care you
                    preserve the fine volatile oil in the leaves. Observe, no smoke is to be made
                    use of, or admitted into your curing house.”</p>
                <p>In 1790, the quantity of tobacco retained forborne consumption in Great Britain
                    and Ireland was 11,860,661 pounds, and the nett amount of revenue derived from
                    it was L.645,579. 5s. lid. The quantity entered for home consumption in the year
                    ending the 5th of January 1836 was 22,116,759 pounds, and the amount of duty
                    received thereon was L.3,354,459. Is. 5d. The quantity imported in 1834 was
                    39,477,907 pounds; in 1835, 25,818,965 pounds: the quantity exported in 1834 was
                    13,264,614 pounds; in 1835, 13,492,000 pounds: the quantity retained for
                    consumption in 1834 was 21,193,860 pounds; in 1835, 21,945,589 pounds.</p>
                <p>The price of tobacco in bond in the London market ranges from 3d. to 5d. per
                    pound. The rates of duty per pound on tobacco in the year ending 5th of January
                    1836 was, for unmanufactured of any British possession in America, 2s. 9d.; of
                    any other place, 3s.; for manufactured tobacco and segars, 9s.; snuff, 6s.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">An Account of the Number of Pounds Weight of Leaf Tobacco,
                    Manufactured Tobacco, Segars, and Snuff, upon which Duty was paid quarterly from
                    the year</hi> 1835, <hi rend="italic">ending 5th of January</hi> 1836; <hi
                    rend="italic">also the rate of Duty, and the total amount of the same.</hi></p>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Quarter ending</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"><p>Quantity entered for Consumption in
                            the United Kingdom in the several quarters of the year ended 5th January
                            1836.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="4" role="data" rows="1"><p>Gross Amount of Duty received
                            thereon.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Unmanufactured Tobacco.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Manufactured Tobacco,
                            &amp;c.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Snuff.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Unmanufactured Tobacco.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Manufactured Tobacco,
                            &amp;c.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Snuff.</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>Total.</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>5th April 1835.</p><p>5th July 1835..
                            10th Oct. 1835.</p><p>5th Jan. 1836..</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>5,660,167</p><p>5,284,269</p><p>5,652,943</p><p>5,377,543</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>34,023</p><p>34,863</p><p>39,730</p><p>33,027</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>40</p><p>34</p><p>97</p><p>23</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"
                            ><p>5,694,230</p><p>5,319,166</p><p>5,692,770</p><p>5,410,593</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">?</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">L.</hi> j. <hi rend="italic">d.</hi></p><p>848,108 9 6
                            790,071 7 0 846,490 19 6 805,983 13 0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">L. s.
                            d.</hi></p><p>15,310 9 3</p><p>15,690 3 11</p><p>17,882 1
                            10</p><p>14,863 6 4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>A. <hi rend="italic">s ∙
                            d.</hi></p><p>12 3 7</p><p>10 4 7</p><p>29 4 11</p><p>6 18 0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p><hi rend="italic">L. s. d.</hi>
                            863,431 2 4 805,771 15 6 864,402 6 3 820,853 17 4</p></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>21,974,922</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>141,643</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>194</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>22,116,759</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3,290,654 9 0</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>63,746 1 4</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>58 11 1</p></cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"><p>3,354,459 1 5</p></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
