<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0833-0798-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DANCE (9th edition, volume 6, page 798)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1030269">Music</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1030814">Musicals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1170328">War</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1173194">Weavers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:891104">Dervishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:924133">Fijians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198518">Samoans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42v2ch0v">Music</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rf5kg1k">Dancers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p843w5c">Hand</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xw4857c">Weavers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rx93h41">Fijians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gx4522p">Peruvian</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7f28s">Zulus</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208479">Fiji</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205154">Guatemala</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1209332">Madagascar</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206536">Tasmania</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n833/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DANCE</label>. The term dancing in its widest sense includes
                    three things :—(1) the spontaneous activity of the muscles under the influence
                    of some strong emotion, such as social joy or religious exultation; (2) definite
                    combinations of graceful movements performed for the sake of the pleasure which
                    the exercise affords to the dancer or to the spectator; (3) carefully trained
                    movements which are meant by the dancer vividly to represent the actions and
                    passions of other people. In the highest sense it seems to be for prose-gesture
                    what song is for the instinctive exclamations of feeling. Pantomime in the
                    emphatic form of dancing scarcely exists in this century, but it has had an
                    important history. Regarded as the outlet or expression of strong feeling,
                    dancing does not require much discussion, for the general rule applies that such
                    demonstrations for a time at least sustain and do not exhaust the flow of
                    feeling. The voice and the facial muscles and many of the organs are affected at
                    the same time, and the result is a high state of vitality which among the
                    spinning Dervishes or in the ecstatic worship of Bacchus and Cybele amounted to
                    something like madness. Even here there is traceable an undulatory movement
                    which, as Mr Spencer says, is “habitually generated by feeling in its bodily
                    discharge.” But it is only in the advanced or volitional stage of dancing that
                    we find developed the essential feature of <hi rend="italic">measure,</hi> which
                    has been said to consist in “the alternation of stronger muscular contractions
                    with weaker ones,” an alternation which, except in the cases of savages and
                    children, “is compounded with longer rises and falls in the degree of muscular
                    excitement.” In analyzing the state of mind which this measured dancing
                    produces, we must first of all allow for the pleasant glow of excitement caused
                    by the excess of blocd sent to the brain. But apart from this, there is an
                    agreeable sense of uniformity in the succession of muscular efforts, and in the
                    spaces described, and also in the period of their recurrence. If the steps of
                    dancing and the intervals of time be not precisely equal, there is still a
                    pleasure depending on the gradually increasing intensity of motion, on the
                    undulation which uniformly rises in order to fall. As Florizel says to Perdita,
                    “When you do dance, I wish you a wave of the sea” (<hi rend="italic">Winter's
                        Tale,</hi> iv. 3). The mind feels the beauty of emphasis and cadence in
                    muscular motion, just as much as in musical notes. Then, the figure of the dance
                    is frequently a circle or some more graceful curve or series of curves,—a fact
                    which satisfies the dancer as well as the eye of the spectator. But all such
                    effects are intensified by the use of music, which not only brings a perfectly
                    distinct set of pleasurable sensations to dancer and spectator, but by the
                    control of dancing produces an inexpressibly sweet harmony of sound and motion.
                    This harmony is further enriched if there be two dancing together on one plan,
                    or a large company of dancers executing certain evolutions, the success of which
                    depends on the separate harmonies of all the couples. The fundamental condition
                    is that throughout the dance all the dancers,keep within their bases of gravity.
                    This is not only required for the dancers’ own enjoyment, but, as in the famous
                    Mercury on tiptoe, it is essential to the beautiful effect for the spectator.
                    The idea of much being safely supported by little is what proves attractive in
                    the modern posturing ballet. But this is merely one condition of graceful
                    dancing, and if it be made the chief object, the dancer sinks into the acrobat.
                    These psychological principles have still to be applied to the phenomena
                    presented by the dances of different nations. (See Read’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Characteristic National Dances,</hi> 1853).</p>
                <p>We shall first consider the varieties of dance which without any apparent mimetic
                    object seem to be suggested by the mere pleasure of movement felt by the
                    performer or by the spectator. In Tigre the Abyssinians dance the <hi
                        rend="italic">chassee</hi> step in a circle, and keep time by shrugging
                    their shoulders and working their elbows backwards and forwards. At intervals
                    the dancers squat on the ground, still moving the arms and shoulders in the same
                    way. The Bushmen dance in their low-roofed rooms supporting themselves by
                    sticks; one foot remains motionless, the other dances in a wild irregular
                    manner, while the hands are occupied with the sticks. The Gonds, a hill-tribe of
                    Hindustan, dance generally in pairs, with a shuffling step, the eyes on the
                    ground, the arms close to the body, and the elbows at an angle with the closed
                    hand. Advancing to a point, the dancer suddenly erects his head, and wheels
                    round to the starting point. The women of the Pultooah tribe dance in a circle,
                    moving backwards and forwards in a bent posture. The Santal women, again, are
                    slow and graceful in dance; joining hands, they form themselves into the arc of
                    a circle, towards the centre of which they advance and then retire, moving at
                    the same time slightly towards the right, so as to complete the circle in an
                    hour. The Kukis of Assam have only the rudest possible step, an awkward hop with
                    the knees very much bent. The national dance of the Kamchadale is one of the
                    most violent known, every muscle apparently quivering at every moment. But
                    there, and in some other cases where men and women dance together, there is a
                    trace of deliberate obscenity; the dance is, in fact, a rude representation of
                    sexual passion. It has been said that some of the Tasmanian <hi rend="italic"
                        >corrobories</hi> have a phallic design. The Yucatan dance of <hi
                        rend="italic">naual</hi> may also be mentioned. The Andamans hop on one foot
                    and swing the arms violently backwards and forwards. The Veddahs jump with both
                    feet together, patting their bodies, or clapping their hands, and make a point
                    of bringing their long hair down in front of the face. In New Caledonia the
                    dance consists of a series of twistings of the body, the feet being lifted
                    alternately, but without change of place. The Fijians jump half round from side
                    to side with their arms akimbo. The only modulation of the Samoan dance is one
                    of time—a <hi rend="italic">crescendo</hi> movement, which is well-known in the
                    modern ball-room. The Javans are perhaps unique in their distinct and graceful
                    gestures of the hand and fingers. At a Mexican feast called Huitzilopochtli, the
                    noblemen and women danced tied together at the hands, and embracing one another,
                    the arms being thrown over the neck. This resembles the dance variously known as
                    the Greek Bracelet or Brawl, ’Opp.os, or Bearsfeet; but all of them<note
                        anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Compare the Chica of
                            South America, the Fandango of Spain, and the Angrismene or la Fach^e of
                            modern Greece. See also <hi rend="italic">Romaunt de la Hose,</hi>
                            v.776.</p></note> probably are to a certain extent symbolical of the
                    relations between <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n834/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0834-0799"/> the sexes. Actual contact of the partners,
                    however, is quite intelligible as matter of pure dancing <hi rend="italic">;
                        for,</hi> apart altogether from the pleasure of the embrace, the harmony of
                    the double rotation adds very much to the enjoyment. In a very old Peruvian
                    dance of ceremony before the Inca, several hundreds of men formed a chain, each
                    taking hold of the hand of the man beyond his immediate neighbour, and the whole
                    body moving forwards and backwards three steps at a time as they approached the
                    throne. In this, as in the national dance of the Coles of Lower Bengal, there
                    was perhaps a suggestion of “l’union fait le force.” In Yucatan stilts were
                    occasionally used <hi rend="superscript"> r</hi> or dancing.</p>
                <p>It seldom happens that dancing takes place without accompaniment, either by the
                    dancer or by others. This is not merely because the feelings which find relief
                    in dancing express themselves at the same time in other forms; in some cases,
                    indeed, the vocal and instrumental elements largely predominate, and form the
                    ground-work of the whole emotional demonstration. Whether they do so or not will
                    of course depend on the intellectual advancement of the nation or tribe, and
                    upon the particular development of their aesthetical sensibility. A striking
                    instance occurs among the Zulus, whose grand dances are merely the accompaniment
                    to the colloquial war and hunting songs, in which the women put questions which
                    are answered by the men. So also in Tahiti there is a set of national ballads
                    and songs, referring to many events in the past and present lives of the people.
                    The fisherman, the woodsman, the canoe-builder, has each his trade song, which
                    on public occasions at least is illustrated by dancing. But the accompaniment is
                    often consciously intended, by an appeal to the ear, to regulate and sustain the
                    excitement of the muscles. And a close relation will be found always to exist
                    between the excellence of a nation’s dancing and the excellence or complexity of
                    its music and poetry. In some cases the performer himself sings or marks time by
                    the clanking of ornaments on his person. In others the accompaniment consists
                    sometimes of a rude chant improvised by those standing round, or of music from
                    instruments, or of mere clapping of the hands, or of striking one stick against
                    another or on the ground, or of “marking time,” in the technical sense. The
                    Tasmanians beat ou a rolled up kangaroo-skin. The Kamchadales make a noise like
                    a continuous hiccough all through the dance. The Andamans use a large hollow
                    dancing-board, on which one man is set apart to stamp. Sometimes it is the
                    privilege of the tribal chief to sing the accompaniment while his people dance.
                    The savages of New Caledonia whistle and strike upon the hip.</p>
                <p>The rude imitative dances of early civilisation are of extreme interest. In the
                    same way, the dances of the Ostyak tribes (Northern Asiatic) imitate the
                    habitual sports of the chase and the gambols of the wolf and the bear and other
                    wild beasts, the dancing consisting mainly of sudden leaps and violent turns
                    which exhaust the muscular powers of the whole body. The Kamchadales, too, in
                    dancing, imitate bears, dogs, and birds. The <hi rend="italic">Kru</hi> dances
                    of the Coast Negroes represent hunting scenes; and on the Congo, before the
                    hunters start, they go through a dance imitating the habits of the gorilla and
                    its movements when attacked. The Damara dance is a mimic representation of the
                    movements of oxen and sheep, four men stooping with their heads in contact, and
                    uttering harsh cries. The canter of the baboon is the humorous part of the
                    ceremony. The Bushmen dance in long irregular jumps, which they compare to the
                    leaping of a herd of calves, and the Hottentots not only go on all-fours to
                    counterfeit the baboon, but they have a dance in which the buzzing of a swarm of
                    bees is represented. The Kennowits in Borneo introduce the mi as and the deer
                    for the same purpose. The Australians and Tasmanians in their dances called <hi
                        rend="italic">corrobories</hi> imitate the frog and the kangaroo (both
                    leaping animals). The hunt of the emu is also performed, a number of men passing
                    slowly round the fire and throwing their arrows about so as to imitate the
                    movements of the animal’s head while feeding. The Gonds are fond of dancing the
                    bison hunt, one man with skin and horns taking the part of the animal. Closely
                    allied to these are the mimic fights, almost universal among tribes to which war
                    is one of the great interests of life. The Bravery Dance of the Dahomans and the
                    Hoolee of the Bhil tribe in the Vindhya Hills are illustrations. The latter
                    seems to have been reduced to an amusement conducted by professionals w ho go
                    from village to village,— the battle being engaged in by women with long poles
                    on the one side, and men with short cudgels on the other. There is here an
                    element of comedy, which also appears in the Fiji club-dance. This, although no
                    doubt originally suggested by war, is enlivened by the presence of a clown
                    covered with leaves and wearing a mask. The monotonous song accompanying the
                    club-dance is by way of commentary or explanation. So also, in Guatemala there
                    is a public <hi rend="italic">baile</hi> or dance, in which all the performers,
                    wearing the skins and heads of beasts, go through a mock battle, which always
                    ends in the victory of those wearing the deer’s head. At the end the victors
                    trace in the sand with a pole the figure of some animal; and this exhibition is
                    supposed to have some historical reference. But nearly all savage tribes have a
                    regular war-dance, in which they appear in fighting costume, handle their
                    weapons, and go through the movements of challenge, conflict, pursuit or defeat.
                    The women generally supply the stimulus of music. There is one very picturesque
                    dance of the Natal Kaffirs, which probably refers to the departure of the
                    warriors for the battle. The women appeal plaintively to the men, who slowly
                    withdraw, stamping on the ground and darting their short spears or <hi
                        rend="italic">assegais</hi> towards the sky. In Madagascar, when the men are
                    absent on war, the women dance for a great part of the day, believing that this
                    inspires their husbands with courage. In this, however, there may be some
                    religious significance. These wardances are totally distinct from the
                    Institution of military drill, which belongs to a later period, when social life
                    has become less impulsive and more reflective.<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Greek <hi rend="italic">Kapireia</hi>
                            represented the surprize by robbers of a warrior ploughing a field. The
                            gymnoptedic dances imitated the sterner sports of the palsestra. . .
                            ,</p></note> There can be little doubt that some of the characteristic
                    movements of these primitive hunting and war-dances survive in the smooth and
                    ceremonious dances of the present day. But the early mimetic dance was not
                    confined to these two subjects; it embraced the other great events of savage
                    life— the drama of courtship and marriage, the funeral dance, the consecration
                    of labour, the celebration of harvest or vintage;<note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>The Greek Lenaia and Dionysia had a
                            distinct reference to tne seasons.</p></note> sometimes,too, purely
                    fictitious scenes of dramatic interest, while other dances degenerated into
                    games. For instance, in Yucatan one man danced in a cowering attitude round a
                    circle, while another followed, hurling at him <hi rend="italic">bohordos</hi>
                    or canes, which were adroitly caught on a small stick. Again, in Tasmania, the
                    dances of the women describe their “clamber for the opossum, diving for
                    shellfish, digging for roots, nursing children, and quarrelling with husbands.”
                    Another dance, in which a woman by gesture taunts a chieftain with cowardice,
                    gives him an opportunity of coming forward and recounting his courageous deeds
                    in dance. The funeral dance of the Todas (another Indian hill tribe), consists
                    in walking backwards and forwards, without variation, to a howling tune of <hi
                        rend="superscript"> u</hi> ha! hoo !” The meaning of this is obscure, but it
                    can <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n835/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0835-0800"/> scarcely be solely an outburst of grief. In
                    Dahomey the blacksmiths, carpenters, hunters, braves, and bards, with their
                    various tools and instruments, join in a dramatic dance. We may add here a form
                    of dance which is almost precisely equivalent to the spoken incantation. It is
                    used by the professional devil-dancer of the wild Veddahs for the cure of
                    diseases. An offering of eatables is put on a tripod of sticks, and the dancer,
                    decorated with green leaves, goes into a paroxysm of dancing, in the midst of
                    which he receives the required information. This, however, rather belongs to the
                    subject of religious dances.</p>
                <p>It is impossible here to enumerate either the names or the forms of the sacred
                    dances which formed so prominent a part of the worship of antiquity. A mystic
                    philosophy found in them a resemblance to the courses of the stars. This
                    Pythagorean idea was expanded by Sir John Davies, in his epic poem <hi
                        rend="italic">Orchestra,</hi> published in 1596. They were probably adapted
                    to many purposes,—to thanksgiving, praise, supplication, and humiliation. It is
                    only one striking illustration of this wide-spread practice, that there was at
                    Rome a very ancient order of priests especially named Salii, who struck their
                    shields and sang <hi rend="italic">assamenta</hi> as they danced. The practice
                    re-appeared in the early church, special provision being made for dancing in the
                    choir. Scaliger, who astonished Charles V. by his dancing powers, says the
                    bishops were called <hi rend="italic">Pr</hi><hi rend="italic">ae</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">sules,</hi> because they led the dance on feast days.
                    According to some of the fathers, the angels are always dancing, and the
                    glorious company of apostles is really a <hi rend="italic">chorus</hi> of
                    dancers. Dancing, however, fell into discredit with the feast of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Agap</hi><hi rend="italic">ae</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi> St
                    Augustine says, “Melius est fodere quam saltare;” and the practice was generally
                    prohibited for some time. No church or sect has raged so fiercely against the
                    cardinal sin of dancing as the Albigenses of Languedoc and the Waldenses, who
                    agreed in calling it the devil's procession. After the middle of the 18th
                    century, there were still traces of religious dancing in the cathedrals of
                    Spain, Portugal, and Roussillon,—especially in the Mussarabian Mass of Toledo.
                    An account of the numerous secular dances, public and private, of Greece and
                    Rome will be found in the classical histories, and in Mr Weaver’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Essay towards a History of Dancing,</hi> London, 1712, which,
                    however, must be revised by more recent authorities. The Pyrrhic (derived from
                    the Memphitic) in all its local varieties, the Bacchanalia, and the Hymensea
                    were among the more important. The name of Lycurgus is also associated with the
                    Trichoria. Among the stage dances of the Athenians, which formed interludes to
                    the regular drama, one of the oldest was the Delian dance of the Labyrinth,
                    ascribed to Theseus, and called Τ <hi rend="italic">έρα</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >vos,</hi> from its resemblance to the flight of cranes, and one of the most
                    powerful was the dance of the Eumenides. A farther development of the art took
                    place at Rome, under Augustus, when Pylades and Bathyllus brought serious and
                    comic pantomime to great perfection. The subjects chosen were such as the labour
                    of Hercules, and the surprise of Venus and Mars by Vulcan. The state of public
                    feeling on the subject is well shown in Lucian’s amusing dialogue <hi
                        rend="italic">De Saltatione.</hi> Before this Rome had only very inferior
                    buffoons, who attended dinner parties, and whose art traditions belonged not to
                    Greece, but to Etruria.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>The Pantomimus was an outgrowth from the <hi rend="italic"
                                >canticum</hi> or choral singing of the older comedies and <hi
                                rend="italic">fabul</hi><hi rend="italic">ae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                                >Atellan</hi><hi rend="italic">ae</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >.</hi></p></note> Apparently, however, the Romans, though fond of ceremony
                    and of the theatre, were by temperament not great dancers in private. Cicero
                    says, “Nemo fere saltat sobrius, nisi forte insanit.” But the Italic Dance of
                    the imperial theatre, supported by music and splendid dresses, supplanted for a
                    time the older dramas. It was the policy of Augustus to cultivate other than
                    political interests for the people; and he passed laws for the protection and
                    privilege of the pantomimists. They were freed from the <hi rend="italic">jus
                        virgarum,</hi> and they used their freedom against the peace of the city.
                    Tiberius and Domitian oppressed and banished them; Trajan and Aurelius gave them
                    such titles as decurions and priests of Apollo; but the pantomime stage soon
                    yielded to the general corruption of the empire.</p>
                <p>The modern ballet seems to have been first produced on a considerable scale in
                    1480, at Tortona, before Duke Galeazzo of Milan. It soon became a common
                    amusement on great occasions at the European courts. The ordinary length was
                    five acts, each containing several <hi rend="italic">entrees,</hi> and each <hi
                        rend="italic">entree</hi> containing several quadrilles. The accessories of
                    painting, sculpture, and movable scenery were employed, and the representation
                    often took place at night, The allegorical, moral, and ludicrous ballets were
                    introduced to France by Baϊf in the time of Catherine de’ Medici. Balthasar of
                    Beaujeu appears also as a director of court ballets, in which amusement the
                    royal families of France continued for long to take an active part. The complex
                    nature of these exhibitions may be gathered from the title of one played at
                    Turin in 1634— <hi rend="italic">La verita nemica della apparenza, sollevata dal
                        tempo.</hi> Of the ludicrous, one of the best known was the Venetian ballet
                    of <hi rend="italic">La verita raminga.</hi> Now and then, however, a high
                    political aim may be discovered, as in the “Prosperity of the Arms of France,”
                    danced before Richelieu in 1641, or “Religion uniting Great Britain to the rest
                    of the World,” danced at London on the marriage of Princess Elizabeth to the
                    Elector Frederick. Outside the theatre, the Portuguese revived an ambulatory
                    ballet which was played on the canonization of Carlo Borromeo, and to which they
                    gave the name of the Tyrrhenic Pomp. During this time also the ceremonial ball
                    (with all its elaborate detail of <hi rend="italic">courante,</hi> minuet, and
                    saraband) was cultivated. The fathers of the church assembled at Trent gave a
                    ball in which they took a part. Masked balls, too, resembling in some respects
                    the Roman Saturnalia, became common towards the end of the 17th century. In
                    France a ball was sometimes diversified by a masquerade, carried on by a limited
                    number of persons in character-costume. Two of the most famous were named “au
                    Sauvage” and “des Sorciers.” In 1715 the regent of France started a system of
                    public balls in the opera-house, which did not succeed. Dancing, also, formed a
                    leading element in the <hi rend="italic">Opéra Fran</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ç</hi><hi rend="italic">ais</hi> introduced by Quinault. His subjects were
                    chiefly marvellous, drawn from the classical mythologies; and the choral dancing
                    was not merely <hi rend="italic">divertissement,</hi> but was intended to assist
                    and enrich the dramatic action of the whole piece. The ideas of military
                    evolution and of magic incantation reappear. Although Lully wrote the music, and
                    the representation was supported by splendid decoration and mechanical effects,
                    the success of this new “tragedy” was short-lived, and since then the modern
                    ballet has never been more than a lyrical interlude. In this humbler function,
                    however, it was greatly improved by La Motte, whose piece <hi rend="italic"
                        >L'Europe Galante</hi> (1697) is a sparkling and elegant production. The
                    lyrical ballet draws much from Fairyland and Arcadia. The possibility of
                    theatrical dance has been strenuously maintained by M. de Cahusac in his <hi
                        rend="italic">La Danse, Ancienne et Moderne,</hi> 3 vols., 1751; by M. de
                    Noverre in his <hi rend="italic">Lettres sur les Arts Imitateurs;</hi> and by
                    Diderot in the <hi rend="italic">Encyclopédie Méthodique,</hi> 1786. It was
                    illustrated by the performance of <hi rend="italic">Pygmalion</hi> by Mdlle.
                    Sallé in London (1732).<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                            ><p>Among the last <hi rend="italic">demi-caractére</hi> ballets may be
                            mentioned the <hi rend="italic">Fills mal gardée</hi> of Dauberval;
                            among the anacreontic, the <hi rend="italic">Dansomanie</hi> of
                            Gardel.</p></note></p>
                <p>Among the antiquities of this subject chorography, or orchesography, the art of
                    dancing notation, deserves a place. The idea is as old as 1598; but about 1700
                    M. Feuillet published a complicated system, which was twice translated <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n836/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0836-0801"/> into English at the beginning of the 18th
                    century by Mr Weaver and Mr Essex. A separate sign was used for each position,
                    bend, rising, step, leap, cabriole, falling, slide, turn, and cadence; and the
                    track of the dance was represented by curved lines. These were sometimes printed
                    along with the music. Such diagrams as still exist are interesting enough as
                    visible history of extinct dances; but as a practical aid in teaching or
                    composing dances chorography was entirely thrown aside as too cumbrous by
                    Noverre, and by Sir John Gallini, the proprietor of the ancient concert rooms in
                    Hanover Square, who wrote on this subject in 1726. The difficulty of the process
                    may be seen by applying it to so comparatively simple a dance as the Scotch
                    reel, which contains no less than 10 single steps—the ceum-siubhaile (forward
                    step), the ceum-coisiche (footing step), the leum-trasd (cross-spring,—French,
                        <hi rend="italic">sissonne),</hi> the siabadh-trasd (chasing step), the
                    aiseag-trasd (cross-passes), the fosgladh (open step), the cuartag (turning
                    step), and others. As may be seen from the technical language of dancing
                    (assemblée, jetée, chassée, glissada, contre-danse, contre-temps, coupé,
                    entrechat, bourrée, gaillarde, fleuret, &amp;c.) it has undoubtedly been brought
                    to greatest perfection in France. But space does not permit us to explain the
                    steps or to describe the picturesque forms of dance which are still practised in
                    town and country.</p>
                <p>One sentence in conclusion upon dancing or musical gymnastics as an important
                    branch of physical education. Long ago Locke pointed out (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Education,</hi> secs. 67,196) that the effects of dancing are not confined
                    to the body; it gives to children, he says, not mere outward gracefulness of
                    motion, but manly thoughts and a becoming confidence. Only lately, however, has
                    the advantage been recognized of making gymnastics attractive by connecting it
                    with what Homer calls “the sweetest and most perfect of human enjoyments.” The
                    practical principle against heavy weights and intense monotonous exertion of
                    particular muscles is thus stated by Mr Smiles <hi rend="italic">(Physical
                        Education,</hi> p. 148) :— “The greatest benefit is derived from that
                    exercise which calls into action the greatest number of muscles, and in which
                    the action of these is intermitted at the shortest intervals.” It required only
                    one further step to see how, if light and changing movements were desirable,
                    music would prove a powerful stimulus to gymnastics. It touches the
                    play-impulse, and substitutes a spontaneous flow of energy for the mechanical
                    effort of the will. The force of imitation or contagion, one of the most
                    valuable forces in education, is also much increased by the state of
                    exhilaration into which dancing puts the system. This idea was embodied by
                    Froebel in his <hi rend="italic">Kindergarten</hi> plan, and has been developed
                    by Jahn and Schreber in Germany, by Dio Lewis in the United States, and by Ling
                    (the author of the <hi rend="italic">Swedish Cure Movement}</hi> in Sweden. It
                    is of course not merely on aesthetic grounds (though these are sufficient) that
                    musical gymnastics, as distinguished from the process of manufacturing a shell
                    of muscle, are invaluable, They are, according to the testimony of all competent
                    persons, indispensable to complete development and general health.</p>
                <p>For the old division of the <hi rend="italic">Ars Gymnastica</hi> into <hi
                        rend="italic">pal</hi><hi rend="italic">oe</hi><hi rend="italic">strica</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">saltatoria,</hi> and of the latter <hi rend="italic">into
                        cubistica, sph</hi><hi rend="italic">ae</hi><hi rend="italic">ristica,</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">orchestica,</hi> see the learned work of Hieronymus
                    Mercurialis, <hi rend="italic">De arte Gymnastica,</hi> Amsterdam, 1572.
                    Cubistic was the art of throwing somersaults, and is described minutely by
                    Tuccaro in his <hi rend="italic">Trois Dialogues,</hi> Paris, 1599. Sphaeristic
                    included several complex games at hall and tilting—the Greek <hi
                        rend="italic                     smallcaps"> k</hi><hi
                        rend="italic smallcaps"> ώρν</hi><hi
                        rend="italic                     smallcaps"> kos,</hi> and the Roman <hi
                        rend="italic">trigonalis</hi> and <hi rend="italic">paganica.</hi>
                    Orchestic, divided by Plutarch into <hi rend="italic">latio, figura,</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">indicatio,</hi> was really imitative dancing, the “silent
                    poetry” of Simonides. The importance of the Χερο or hand-movement is indicated
                    by Ovid :—“Si vox est, canta; si mollia brachia, salta.” For further information
                    as to modem dancing, see Rameau’s <hi rend="italic">Le Ma</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ît</hi><hi rend="italic">re</hi><hi rend="italic">à</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Danser,</hi> 1726, and Querlon’s <hi rend="italic">Le Triomphe des
                        Graces,</hi> 1774. In the earlier part of this article considerable use has
                    been made of the Aesthetic Products” of Mr Spencer’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sociological Tables.</hi> (W. C. S.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
