<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0879-0844-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DAVIES, Sir John (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    844)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49z90b98">Epigrams</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914131">Epigrams</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914130">Epigram</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n879/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DAVIES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Sir John</hi></label>
                    (1569-1626), philosophical poet of the age of Elizabeth, was baptized on the
                    16th of April 1569, at Tisbury, in Wiltshire, where his parents lived in the
                    manor-house of Chicksgrove. He was sent first to Winchester College, and
                    afterwards to New College, Oxford. In 1585 he became a commoner of Queen’s
                    College, Oxford, and in 1587 entered at the Middle Temple. Bereft of both his
                    parents at a very early age, he seems to have plunged into all the dissipations
                    that London could offer in those days to a rich young man of fashion. It is
                    amusing to find the future attorney-general of Ireland, and grave Christian
                    poet, connected, beyond all concealment, with one of the worst literary scandals
                    of the period. One would be very glad to know what circumstances led to the
                    publication of the notorious and now excessively rare little volume that bears
                    the title <hi rend="italic">All Ovid's Elegies,</hi> 3 <hi rend="italic">Bookes,
                        by C. M. Epigrams by J. D. At Middleburgh,</hi> in which Marlowe had a
                    share, and which was condemned by the archbishop to be burned. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Epigrams</hi> are far from edifying or promising, and we may,
                    in the absence of a date, be permitted to put the earliest possible, 1592 or
                    1593, on their unseemly boisterousness. In 1593 was ready for the printer,
                    though not, it would seem, published till 1596, a far more worthy work, the
                    charming and singular fragment called <hi rend="italic">Orchestra,</hi> a little
                    epic written in praise of dancing, in fifteen consecutive days. The poet seeks
                    to prove that every harmonious movement of nature, every action of the elements,
                    every motion in the firmament, is a conscious and well-ordered dance; also that
                    plants in growing, men in all their familiar and noble exercises, the angels
                    themselves, and all the mysterious translunary world effect a solemn dancing in
                    their motion. <hi rend="italic">Orchestra</hi> was dedicated to the author’s
                    “very friend,” Master Richard Martin, a riotous youth whom, in the winter of
                    1597, Davies, the friendshaving quarrelled, attacked with a cudgel in the hall
                    of the Middle Temple. For this offence he was expelled and degraded. Rusticating
                    at Oxford, he spent the first year after his expulsion in the composition of his
                    great philosophical poem, <hi rend="italic">Nosce Teipsum,</hi> which appeared
                    in 1599. It is on this work that his fame mainly rests. The style was entirely
                    novel in that age; and its force, eloquence, and ingenuity, no less than the
                    modern and polished tone of the periods, made it at once extremely popular. It
                    was to its own age all that Pope’s <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi> was to
                    the Georgian period. In the same year, 1599, there saw the light a little book
                    of exquisite lyrics from the same hand, <hi rend="italic">Hymns to A
                        strata,</hi> twenty-six acrostics on the words <hi rend="italic">Elisabetha
                        Regina,</hi> which all warble with the most delightful sweetness. In 1601
                    Davies was restored to his position at the bar, without loss of seniority. About
                    the same time he sat in Elizabeth’s last Parliament, as member for C’orfe
                    Castle. At Elizabeth’s death he was instantly received with great favour by
                    James I., and sent to Ireland as solicitor-general in 1603. On December 18 of
                    that year he was knighted at Dublin. From this time forth he abandoned poetry in
                    favour of the most active statesmanship. His activities in Ireland were almost
                    ubiquitous. In 1606 he was further promoted to be attorney-general for Ireland,
                    and created sergeant-at-arms. In the disordered condition of the country he was
                    required to be stirring at all times, and his abilities seem to have been as
                    conspicuous as his trustworthiness and uprightness. He married Eleanor, daughter
                    of the earl of Castlehaven, but she unfortunately became insane. In 1612 Davies
                    published his valuable prose work, <hi rend="italic">A Discourse of the True
                        Reasons why Ireland has never been entirely subdued.</hi> The same year he
                    represented the county of Fermanagh in the Irish Parliament, and was elected
                    speaker. In 1614 he represented Newcastle-under-Lyne in the English Parliament,
                    and in 1619 he threw up his appointments in Ireland. In 1622 he issued a
                    collected edition of his poetical works. In 1626 Davies was appointed lord chief
                    justice of England, but ere he could enter on the office, he was found dead in
                    his bed (December 8), the victim, it was supposed, of apoplexy.</p>
                <p>The prose writings of this remarkable man were mainly posthum ous, and no attempt
                    was made to collect them, until they were republished in four volumes by the
                    Rev. A. B. Grosart, in 1876, with a full and interesting biography. The poetical
                    works have often been reproduced since the author’s lifetime.</p>
                <p>Sir John Davies is not to be confounded with <hi rend="smallcaps">John
                        Davies</hi> of Hereford, a contemporary author of a great quantity of verse,
                    of which <hi rend="italic">The Holy Roode</hi> (1609), <hi rend="italic">The
                        Scourge of Folly</hi> (1611), and <hi rend="italic">The Muses'
                        Sacrifice</hi> (1612) are fair typical examples. Gifted with extraordinary
                    volubility and self-confidence, but with no delicacy or taste the writings of
                    this John Davies have survived more by reason of their bulk and their accidental
                    interest of reference or dedication than from any intrinsic merit.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
