<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0855-0820-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">D’ANVILLE, Jean Baptiste Bourguignon</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 820</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:830322">Benedictionals</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:830317">Benediction</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1008726">Maps</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4g15tc6x">Maps</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n855/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">D’ANVILLE, <hi rend="smallcaps">Jean Baptiste
                    Bourguignon</hi></label> (1697— 1782), a French geographer of the highest
                    eminence, was born at Paris on the 11th July 1697. His passion for geographical
                    research displayed itself from his earliest years. At the age of twelve, while
                    reading the Latin authors at college, he amused himself with drawing maps of the
                    countries which they described. While he was thus busily employing himself one
                    day in the class, his master observed and was about to punish him; but upon
                    casting his eye upon the performance, he immediately judged him to be deserving
                    rather of encouragement. After leaving college he derived much instruction from
                    intercourse with the Abbd Longuerue, the celebrated antiquarian. D’Anville from
                    this time devoted himself entirely to geography, particularly that of the
                    ancient world. His first map, that of Ancient Greece, was published when he was
                    fifteen, and at the age of twenty-two he was appointed one of the king’s
                    geographers, and began to delineate maps which attracted the attention of the
                    most eminent authorities.</p>
                <p>The course of study on which D’Anville entered was of great extent. Works
                    professedly geographical formed the least part of it; those of all the ancient
                    and modern historians, travellers, narrators of every description, were
                    assiduously examined. He studied also the philosophers, orators, and poets, but
                    only for the sake of the occasional<pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n856/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0856-0821"/> geographical lights which they afforded, for it
                    was remarked that in perusing their works he was totally indifferent to
                    everything which did not tend to fix a geographical position. The object of this
                    immense labour was to effect a complete reform in the science of geography by
                    banishing the system of copying blindly from preceding maps, and never fixing a
                    single position without a careful examination of all the authorities upon which
                    it rested. By this process he detected many serious errors in the works of his
                    most celebrated predecessors, while his own accuracy was soon attested on all
                    sides by the travellers and mariners who had taken his works as their guide. His
                    principles led him also to another innovation, which was that of omitting every
                    name for which there existed no sufficient authority. Vast spaces, which had
                    before been covered with countries and cities, were thus suddenly reduced to a
                    perfect blank; but it was speedily perceived that this was the only accurate
                    course, and that the defect lay in the science, not in the geographer.</p>
                <p><hi> D’Anville</hi> was at first employed in the humbler taslj of illustrating by
                    maps the works of different travellers, such as Marchais, Charlevoix, Labat, and
                    Duhalde. For the history of China by the last-named writer he was employed to
                    make an atlas, which was published by itself at the Hague in 1737. The question
                    respecting the figure of the earth coming to be much agitated, he published in
                    1735 and 1736 two treatises, with a view to illustrate it. But this attempt to
                    solve a geometrical problem by historical materials was eminently unsuccessful.
                    Maupertuis having gone to measure a degree within the polar circle, the result
                    was fouud directly opposite to D’Anville’s prediction. Any loss of reputation
                    which this failure might have occasioned was completely retrieved by his map of
                    Italy, published in 1743. It was marked by a method of investigation often
                    employed by D’Anville with peculiar success, which consisted in the application
                    of ancient materials to correct the existing geography. By the diligent study of
                    the Latin authors he was enabled to trace numerous errors which had crept into
                    the delineation of that country. A trigonometrical survey which Pope Benedict
                    XIV. almost immediately after caused to be made in the States of the Church
                    confirmed, in a surprizing degree, all these alterations. On this occasion he
                    first set the example of accompanying the map with a memoir exhibiting the data
                    on which it had been constructed.</p>
                <p>He now applied himself to ancient geography, always his favourite department, the
                    aspect of which, under his hands, was soon completely changed. He illustrated
                    successively, by maps, all the countries known to the ancients, among which
                    Egypt attracted his peculiar attention. To render these labours more extensively
                    useful, he published in 1768 his <hi rend="italic">Geographic Ancienne
                    Abregee,</hi> of which an English translation, entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Compendium, of Ancient Geography,</hi> appeared in 1791. His attention was
                    fiually turned to the Middle Ages, which were illustrated by his <hi
                    rend="italic">fitats formes en Europe apres la Chute de VEmpire Romain en
                    Occident</hi> (1771), and by some other works equally learned. Entirely devoted
                    to geographical inquiries, the appearance of his successive publications formed
                    the only events by which his life was diversified. From causes which are not
                    explained, he was late in being admitted into the literary societies. In 1754,
                    at the age of sixty, he became a member of the Academy of Inscriptions and
                    Belles Lettres, whose transactions he enriched with many papers. In 1775 he
                    received the only place in the Academy of Sciences which is allotted to
                    geography; and in the same year he was appointed, without solicitation, first
                    geographer to the king. But these honours came too late to gladden a life which
                    was now drawing to its utmost verge. His last employment consisted in arranging
                    his collection of maps, plans, and geographical materials. It was the most
                    extensive in Europe, and had been purchased by the king, who, however, left him
                    the use of it during his life. This task performed, he sunk into a total
                    imbecility both of mind and body, which continued for two years, and ended only
                    with his death in January 1782.</p>
                <p>D Anville’s published memoirs and dissertations amounted to 78, and his maps to
                    211. A complete edition of liis works was announced in 1806 by De Manne in 6
                    vols. quarto, only two of which had appeared when the editor died in 1832. See
                    Dacier’s <hi rend="italic">Eloge de D'Anville</hi> (Paris, 1802).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
