<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0906-0818-0783-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">DALMATIA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 6, page 783</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fastgeo:1212674">Croatia</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1692600">Montenegro</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1226682">Albania</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="6" ref="fasttopic:850620">Cent</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:950823">Hand</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1028334">Mountaineering</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:821579">Austrians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1120771">Slavs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:804157">Albanians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4h41jw08">Servians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4w669847">Slavs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g03">Cent</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b48s4jt2v">Heights</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43b5w92m">Salts</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n818/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DALMATIA</label>, a crownland of the Austrian empire,
                    stretching in a narrow strip along the eastern shores of the Adriatic from
                    Austrian Croatia on the N. to Albania in the S., end bounded towards the
                    interior by Turkish Croatia, Herzegovina, and Montenegro. It has an area oi 4937
                    square miles, and its population in 1869 was 456,961.</p>
                <p>The boundary towards Austrian Croatia is marked by the Velebitch Mountains, which
                    trend to the east and reach a height of 5350 feet in Vizerunaand 5774 in
                    Sveto-Brdo, or the Holy Mountain; and the Turkish frontier coincides with the
                    line of the Dinarian Alps, which run parallel with the Adriatic and attain an
                    elevation of 5940 feet in Mount Dinara. The highest mountain in the country is
                    Orjen, in the district of Cattaro, 6225 feet. The coast is for the most part
                    steep and rocky, and fronted by a large number of islands. Towards the north,
                    opposite the Croatian coast, are Pago and Arbe, of which the former rises to a
                    height of 885 feet and the latter to 1338; next come Isola Grossa, Ugliana,
                    Isola Incoronata, and others of less importance; then to the south of the
                    promontory of Osorich, Brazza, with Monte St Vito, 2574 feet high; Lesina, with
                    Monte St Nicola, 2078; and Curzola, with a maximum elevation of 1879, forming a
                    prolongation of the promontory of Sabioncello. To tile south of Curzola lies
                    Lagosta, and to the south of Sabioncello, Meleda. The chief natural harbours are
                    Tajer, Zara, Sebenico, Lesina, Lissa, Curzola, Sabioncello, Meleda, Gravosa, and
                    Cattaro.</p>
                <p>Dalmatia is not well supplied with water. The lakes are for the most part
                    temporary rain-pools, and the only streams of importance are the Kerka <hi
                    rend="italic">(ffitius)</hi> and the Cettina <hi rend="italic">(Pilurus),</hi>
                    which rise in the Dinara mountains. The former constitutes the boundary between
                    Croatia and Dalmatia, and is interesting for its falls and the wildness of its
                    scenery. The Narenta <hi rend="italic">(Naro),</hi> which belongs mainly to
                    Herzegovina, disembogues between the peninsula of Sabioncello and the mainland,
                    and forms an extensive marsh.</p>
                <p>The climate is warm and healthy, the mean temperature at Zara being 57° Fahr., at
                    Lesina 62°, and at Ragusa 63°. The prevailing wind is the sirocco, or S.E.; but
                    the terrible Bora, or N.E., may blow at any season of the year. The average
                    annual rainfall is about 28 inches, but a dry and a wet year usually alternate.
                    The greater proportion of the surface is devoted to pasture,—only 18 per cent,
                    being under the plough, 5| per cent, in vineyards, and 22 per cent, in forest.
                    Barley, wheat, maize, oats, rye, millet, beet-root, hemp, and potatoes are all
                    grown, but in small quantities. Asses are largely used as beasts of burden;
                    goats are strikingly numerous; and sheep are reared for the sake of their
                    mutton, which is almost the only animal food freely consumed in the country.
                    Asphalt, lignite, and bay-salt from Dernis and Sign are now the only mineral
                    products of commercial importance; and there is no manufacturing industry except
                    the distillation of liqueurs, oil-pressing, and tile-burning. The peasant still
                    grinds his corn with his own hands, weaves his own cloth, and prepares his own
                    furniture. The principal exports are olive-oil, wine, salt, and rosoglio.</p>
                <p>Dalmatia is sparsely peopled, the neighbourhoods of Cattaro and of Ragusa being
                    the areas of maximum density. About 89 per cent, of the inhabitants are the
                    so-called Morlacks, or Dalmatians proper, who belong to the Servian race, and
                    speak a Slavonic dialect usually distinguished as the Illyric; about 10| per
                    cent, are of Italian origin; and the remainder consist mainly of Albanians and
                    Jews. The pre <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi>- vailing religion is Roman
                    Catholicism, to which no fewer than 82 per cent, of the population are attached;
                    and the Greek Church comprises almost all the rest. The Roman Catholic
                    archbishop has his seat at Zara; and Spalato, Ragusa, Sebenico, Lesina, and
                    Cattaro are bishoprics. Education is still in a backward state, but has made
                    considerable advances since 1862. The political constitution is based on the law
                    of the 26th February 1861. The diet is composed of 43 members, including the
                    Roman Catholic archbishop, the Greek bishop of Zara, and representatives of the
                    chief <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n819/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0906-0819-0784"/> tax-payers, the towns, and the communes. To the
                    imperial diet Dalmatia furnishes five delegates. Zara is the capital of the
                    country; and Benkovacz, Cattaro, Curzola, Imoski, Knin, Lesina, Macarsca,
                    Ragusa, Sebenico, Sign, and Spalato give names to the administrative districts.
                    With the exception of Zara, Spalato, and Sebenico, most of the towns are very
                    small, and the great proportion of the population is distributed in petty
                    hamlets.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">History.—</hi> The history of Dalmatia may be said to begin
                    with the year 180 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.,</hi> when the tribe from which it
                    takes it name declared their independence of Gentius the king of Illyria, and
                    established a republic with its capital at Delminium or Dalminium, which was
                    probably situated in Dalen in the Herzegovina. In 156 <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >b.c.</hi> the Dalmatians were for the first time attacked by the Romans, and
                    compelled to pay tribute, but it was not till the reign of Augustus that their
                    country was made a Roman province. A formidable revolt was suppressed by
                    Tiberius in 9 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.d.</hi> Under the later empire Dalmatia was
                    thoroughly Romanized, and it had the honour of giving to the world an emperor in
                    the person of Diocletian, who retired, after resigning the purple, to Salona,
                    the new Dalmatian capital, where he erected those buildings which still bear
                    witness to his magnificence. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Spalato).</hi> After the
                    fall of the Western Empire, in which it was included, Dalmatia was successively
                    in the hands of Odoacer, Theodoric, and Justinian; and in the 7th century it
                    received the dominant element of its present population by the immigration of
                    the Slavs, who had been invited by Heraclius. In the 9th century we find
                    Croatian influence at its height, and Croatian princes recognized as kings of
                    Dalmatia; but in the course of the 10th Venice extended her power over most of
                    the towns, and about 1018 the doge took the title of duke of Dalmatia. During
                    the 11th century the struggle went on between Croatia and Venice, till in 1091
                    the Hungarians took the place of the Croatians. Meanwhile the maritime cities
                    Zara, Trau, Ragusa, &amp;c., had each almost a separate history of its own, and,
                    like the free cities of Northern Italy, attained no small prosperity through
                    commerce and industry. As was natural from their position and affinities, they
                    rather sided with Venice, and in fact were sometimes really under Venetian
                    control; but the treatment they received from the great republic alienated their
                    affection, and in 1357-8 they opened their gates to Louis of Hungary, who became
                    for a time master of all Dalmatia. Venetian authority was, however, again
                    restored through most of the country, and it was not till the treaty of Campo
                    Formio, in 1797, that Dalmatia was finally incorporated with the Austrian
                    dominions. Since that date, with the exception of the Napoleonic period from
                    1805-1814, the Austrian supremacy has never been questioned, though during a
                    considerable time the feeling of the country towards its masters was extremely
                    hostile, and in 1869 an insurrection had to be put down by force of arms.</p>
                <p>The literature relating to Dalmatia is very extensive. See Lucius of Trau, De
                    regno Dalmatiae et Croatia, 1668; Gio. Louvich, Dei Costumi del Morlaecki, 1776;
                    Cattalinich, Memorie degli Avvenimenti successi in Dalmatia; A. Fortis, Travels
                    in Dalmatia, 1778; Schmidl, Das Königreich Dalmatien, 1843; Cusani, Dalmatia,
                    1846; Wilkinson, Dalmatia and Montenegro, 2 vote. 1848; Paton, Highlands and
                    Islands of the Adriatic, 1849; Kohl, Reisen in Istrien, Dalmatien, &amp;c.,
                    1850; Neigebauer, Die Südslaven, 1851; Petter, Compendio geografico della
                    Dalmatia, and Dalmatien in seinen verschiedenen Vertiehungen dargestellt, Gotha,
                    1857; W. F. Wingfield, Tour in Dalmatia, 1859; Hecquard, “Géographie pol. et.
                    phys. de la Dalmatia,” in Bulletin de la soc. de géogr. 1862; Noe, Dalmatien und
                    seine Inselwelt, 1870; Maschek, Manuale del regno di Dalmatia per l'anno 1875;
                    Schiff, Cultur-bilder aus Dalmatien, Vienna, 1875.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
