<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0906-0832-0797-04" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">DANBY, Francis (9th edition, volume 6, page
                    797)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:835564">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110280">Sealing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1183341">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1183692">Youthfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:817721">Arts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:815177">Art</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17ss11">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz5d">Youth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gq6r76k">Martins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b6k">Bohemianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nj3s">Sealing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1208755">Egypt</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n832/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">DANBY, <hi rend="smallcaps">Francis</hi></label> (1793-1861),
                    a painter of poetical landscape, who possesses some significance and importance
                    in the English school, was born in the south of Ireland, November 16, 1793. His
                    father farmed a small property he owned near Wexford, and Francis began life in
                    the country, but the death of his father caused the family to remove to Dublin,
                    while he was still a schoolboy, and there his bias to art very quickly developed
                    itself, and superseded any other education. He began to practise drawing at the
                    Royal Dublin Society’s schools; and under a Mr O’Connor, an erratic youth of his
                    own age with national peculiarities, he began painting landscape. The capital of
                    Ireland has never shown very much interest in the arts, but there was a youth
                    then rising who afterwards made his mark in archaeology, if not in his
                    profession of landscape painting, George Petrie, with whom Danby formed an
                    acquaintance; and all three left for London together in 1813. This expedition,
                    undertaken with very inadequate funds, and no aid, quickly came to an end and
                    they had to get home again by walking all the way. At Bristol they made a pause,
                    and Danby finding he could get trifling sums for water-colour drawings, remained
                    there working diligently and sending to the London exhibitions pictures of
                    importance. There his large pictures in oil quickly attracted attention. They
                    were very powerful in effect and imaginative in invention; and, had his Upas
                    Tree and the Delivery of the Israelites from Egypt been produced before a
                    greater man, John Martin, had shown the way to express multitude, vastness, and
                    fabulous wonders in architecture, Danby would be properly considered one of the
                    great men in modern painting. The Upas Tree (1820), his most independent and
                    original picture, is, however, a very noble work, not only in invention but in
                    execution; the poison tree, surrounded by the remains of slaves who have been
                    sent to gather its gum, grows alone in a valley of rocks lit by a ghastly
                    moonlight, which is itself a triumph of art. The Delivery of the Israelites
                    (1825) is much more strictly a derivation from Martin. The Royal Academy,
                    however, elected him into their body on the strength of it, thinking by his
                    means to checkmate that master, who did not aspire to Academic honours. He now
                    left Bristol for London, and in 1828 exhibited his Opening of the Sixth Seal at
                    the British Institution, receiving from that body an honorary premium of 200
                    guineas; and this picture, which was admirably painted, was followed by two
                    others from the Apocalypse, both productions of surprising power, though
                    certainly indebted to the works of a similar species of invention appearing a
                    few years earlier. These were the last of his important and large pictures. He
                    suddenly left London, declaring that he would never live there again, and that
                    the Academy, instead of aiding him, had, somehow or other, used him badly. Some
                    insurmountable domestic <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit06newyrich/page/n833/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0906-0833-0798"/> difficulty overtook him also, and for eleven
                    or twelve years he lived on the Lake of Geneva, a Bohemian with boat-building
                    fancies, painting only now and then. He returned to England in 1841, when his
                    sons James and Thomas, who have both followed the art with considerable
                    advantage, were growing up. The only additional pictures it is necessary to
                    mention are the Golden Age, and the Evening Gun, the first begun before he left
                    England, the second painted after his return, when he had taken up his abode at
                    Exmouth, where he died February 9, 1861, in his sixty-eigh th year. His Upas
                    Tree is now i n the South Kensington National Collection by the Townshend
                    bequest, and is held in general respect, but such of his other works as have
                    been lately seen have not maintained his reputation. They have the hot tone and
                    opacity of bronze, and reveal the secret that they have been produced in a
                    darkened studio, and irrespective of the facts and even of the sentiment of
                    living nature. Notwithstanding these drawbacks they must be always interesting
                    from their imaginative motives, and undoubtedly play a noticeable part in the
                    history of English landscape art.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
