<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0712-5849-0619-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">JONES, Inigo</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 619</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4db7vr13">Stone</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b43n20g8z">Schools</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bh84">Gardens</term><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jg6k">Gardening</term><term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4dn3zz3k">Design</term><term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p65z">Architects</term><term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b47659q39">Surveyors</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:891345">Designers</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:891253">Design</term><term n="6" ref="fasttopic:1198505">Life</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:813114">Architects</term><term n="3" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1133812">Stone</term><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1133955">Stoning</term></keywords><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1204558">Denmark</term><term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1754964">Rome</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term><term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term><term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1207649">Wales</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:192945849" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">JONES, <hi rend="smallcaps">Inigo</hi></label>, a celebrated
                    English architect, the son of a cloth-worker of London, was born in 1572. He was
                    at first put as apprentice to a joiner; but having early distinguished himself
                    by his inclination for drawing or designing, he was particularly noticed for his
                    skill in landscape-painting. This afterwards recommended him to the favour of
                    William earl of Pembroke, who sent him abroad with a handsome allowance, in
                    order to perfect himself in that branch. He had no sooner arrived at Rome, than
                    he found himself in his proper sphere; he felt that nature had not formed him to
                    decorate cabinets, but to design palaces. He accordingly dropped the pencil, and
                    conceived Whitehall. In the state of Venice he saw the works of Palladio, and
                    learned that refined taste may be exerted on a less theatre than the capital of
                    an empire. How he distinguished himself in a place where he had no opportunity
                    to display his talents, we are not informed, though it would not be the least
                    curious part of his history. Certain it is, however, that, on the strength of
                    his reputation at Venice, Christian IV. invited him to Denmark, and appointed
                    him his architect; but on what buildings he was employed in that country we have
                    yet to learn. James I. found him at Copenhagen, and Queen Anne took him, in the
                    capacity of her architect, to Scotland. He served Prince Henry in the same
                    capacity, and the place of surveyor-general of the works was granted to him in
                    reversion. On the death of that prince, Jones travelled once more into Italy,
                    and, assisted by maturity of judgment, perfected his taste. To the interval
                    between these voyages Mr Walpole is inclined to attribute those buildings of
                    Jones which are less pure, and border too much upon the bastard style. Inigo’s
                    designs of that period are not Gothic, but have a littleness of parts, and a
                    weight of ornament, with which the revival of the Grecian taste was encumbered,
                    and which he shook off in his grander designs. The surveyor’s place having
                    become vacant, he returned to England; and, as if architecture was not all he
                    had learned at Rome, he disinterestedly gave up the profits of his office, which
                    he found extremely in debt, and prevailed upon the comptroller and paymaster to
                    imitate his example, until the whole arrears were cleared off.</p><p>In 1620 he was employed in a manner very unworthy of his genius, King James
                    having set him upon discovering, or rather guessing, who were the founders of
                    Stonehenge. But his ideas were all Roman; consequently, his partiality to his
                    favourite people, which ought rather to have prevented him from charging them
                    with that mass of barbarous clumsiness, made him conclude that it was a Roman
                    temple.</p><p>In the same year Jones was appointed one of the commissioners for the repair of
                    St Paul’s; but this was not commenced till the year 1633, when Laud, then bishop
                    of London, laid the first stone, and Inigo the fourth. In the restoration <hi rend="italic">of</hi> that cathedral he made two capital faults. He first
                    renewed the sides with very bad Gothic; and then added a Roman portico
                    magnificent indeed, but which had no affinity to the ancient parts that
                    remained, and made his own Gothic appear ten times heavier. He committed the
                    same error at Winchester, thrusting a screen in the Roman or Grecian taste into
                    the middle of that cathedral. Jones indeed was by no. means successful when he
                    attempted Gothic. The chapel of Lincoln’s-Inn has none of the characteristics of
                    that architecture. The cloister beneath seems oppressed by the weight of the
                    building above.</p><p>The authors of the life of Jones place the erection of the Banqueting House in
                    the reign of King Charles; but it appears, from the accounts of Nicholas Stone,
                    that it was begun in 1619, and finished in two years, being a small part of the
                    pile designed for the palace of our kings, but so complete in itself, that it
                    stands as a model of its kind. Several plates of the intended palace at
                    Whitehall have been given, but, Mr Walpole thinks, from no finished design. The
                    four great sheets are evidently made up from general hints; nor could such a
                    source of invention and taste as the mind of Inigo ever produce so much
                    sameness. The whole fabric, however, was so great an idea, that, according to
                    Walpole, one forgets for a moment, in the regret for its not being executed, the
                    confirmation of our liberties, obtained by a melancholy scene that passed before
                    the windows of that very Banqueting House.</p><p>In 1623 he was employed at Somerset House, where a chapel was to be fitted up for
                    the Infanta, the intended bride of the prince. The chapel is still in existence.
                    The front to the river, part only of what was designed, and the water-gate, were
                    afterwards erected on the designs of Inigo, as was the gate at York Stairs.</p><p>On the accession of Charles, Jones was continued in his posts under both king and
                    queen. His fee as surveyor was eight shillings and fourpence a day, with an
                    allowance of L.46 a year for house-rent, besides a clerk, and incidental
                    expenses. What other remuneration he received, or whether he received any at
                    all, we have not been informed.</p><p>During the prosperous state of the king’s affairs, the pleasures of the court
                    were indulged in with much taste and magnificence. Poetry, painting, music, and
                    architecture, were all called in to contribute rational amusements. Mr Walpole
                    is of opinion, indeed, that the celebrated festivals of Louis XIV. were copied
                    from the shows exhibited at Whitehall, in his time the most polite court in
                    Europe. Ben Jonson was the laureate; Inigo Jones the inventor of the
                    decorations; Laniere and Ferabosco composed the symphonies; whilst the king, the
                    queen, and the young nobility, danced in the interludes. We have accounts of
                    many of those entertainments called “masques,” which had been introduced by Anne
                    of Denmark. Lord Burlington had a folio of the designs for these solemnities, by
                    Inigo’s own hand, consisting of habits, masks, scenes, and so forth. The harmony
                    of these masks was a little interrupted by a war which broke out between the
                    composers, Inigo and Ben, in which, whoever was the aggressor, the turbulent
                    temper of Jonson took care to put him most in the wrong.</p><p>The works of Inigo Jones are not scarce; and Surgeons’ Hall is one of his best
                    performances. One of the most admired is the arcade of Covent-garden, and the
                    church; “two structures,” says Mr Walpole, “of which I want taste to see the
                    beauties. In the arcade there is nothing remarkable; the pilasters are as arrant
                    and homely stripes as any plasterer could make. The barn-roof over the portico
                    of the church strikes my eyes with as little idea of dignity and beauty as it
                    could do if it covered nothing but a barn. It must be owned, that the defect is
                    not in the architect, but in the order. Who ever saw a beautiful Tuscan
                    building? Would the Romans have chosen that order for a temple ?” The expense of
                    building the church amounted to L.4500.</p><p>Ambresbury in Wiltshire was designed by Jones, but executed by his scholar Webb.
                    Jones was one of the first who observed the same diminution in pilasters as in
                    pillars. Lindsay House in Lincoln’s-Inn Fields, which he built, owes its chief
                    grace to this singularity. In 1618, a <pb break="no" facs="nls:192945862" xml:id="kp-eb0712-5862-0620"/>special
                    commission was issued to the Lord Chancellor, the Earls of Worcester, Pembroke,
                    Arundel, and others, to plant and reduce to uniformity Lincoln’s-Inn Fields, as
                    it should be drawn by way of map or ground-plot, by Inigo Jones,
                    surveyor-general of the works. That square is laid out with a regard to so
                    trifling a singularity, as to be of the exact dimensions of one of the Pyramids;
                    a conceit which would have been admired in those ages when the keep at
                    Kenilworth Castle was erected in the form of an horse-fetter, and the Escurial
                    in the shape of St Laurence’s gridiron.</p><p>Coleshill in Berkshire, the seat of Sir Matthew Pley-deD, built in 1650, and
                    Cobham Hall in Kent, were works of Jones. He was employed to rebuild Castle
                    Ashby, and finished one front; but the civil war interrupted his progress there
                    and at Stoke Park in Northamptonshire. Shaftesbury House, now the London
                    Lying-in Hospital, on the east side of Aldersgate Street, is a beautiful front
                    of his. The Grange, the seat of Lord Henley, in Hampshire, is entirely of this
                    master. It is by no means a large house, but one of the best proofs of his
                    taste. The hall, which opens to a small vestibule with a cupola, and the
                    staircase adjoining, are beautiful models of the purest and most classic
                    antiquity The gate of Beaufort Garden at Chelsea, designed by Jones, was
                    purchased by Lord Burlington, and transported to Chiswick. He also drew a plan
                    for a palace at Newmarket. One of the most beautiful of his works is the queen’s
                    house at Greenwich. The first idea of the hospital is said to have been taken
                    from his papers by his scholar Webb. Heriot’s Hospital in Edinburgh, and the
                    improvements made in his time on Glammis Castle, Forfarshire, Scotland, are
                    specimens of the designs of Inigo Jones.</p><p>Inigo tasted early the misfortunes of his master. Being not only a favourite, but
                    a Roman Catholic, he in 1646 paid L.545 for his delinquency and sequestration.
                    Whether it was before or after this fine, it is uncertain, that he and Stone the
                    mason buried their joint stock in Scotland yard; but an order being published to
                    encourage the informers of such concealments, and four persons being privy to
                    the spot where the money was hidden, it was taken up, and reburied in Lambeth
                    marsh. Grief, misfortunes, and age, put a period to his life, at Somerset House,
                    on the 21st of July 1651. Several of his designs have been published by Mr Kent,
                    Mr Colin Campbell, and Mr Isaac Ware. He left in manuscript some curious notes
                    on Palladio’s architecture, which are inserted in an edition of Palladio
                    published in 1714.</p><p><hi rend="smallcaps">Jones,</hi><hi rend="italic">Sir William,</hi> the son of
                    William Jones, Esq. an eminent mathematician, contemporary with the great
                    Newton, was born in London on the 28th of September 1746, and received the
                    rudiments of his education at Harrow School, under the tuition of Dr Robert
                    Sumner, whom he has celebrated in an elegant and affecting enlogium. From Harrow
                    School he went to University College, Oxford, where the rapidity of his literary
                    acquisitions excited universal admiration.</p><p>He travelled through France at the age of twenty-three, taking up his residence
                    for some time at Nice, where society, and the various forms of government,
                    became the favourite objects of his investigation. A wish to relieve his mother
                    from the burden of his education made him long for a fellowship in his college;
                    but having no immediate prospect of obtaining it, he, in 1765, became tutor to
                    young Lord Al-ţhorp, afterwards Earl Spencer, in which situation he was
                    introduced to the best of company, and had also leisure to prosecute the
                    acquisition of knowledge, and the further cultivation of his intellectual
                    powers, which were objects ever dear to him.</p><p>He obtained next year the fellowship he expected, and was thus raised to a state
                    which he could not help viewing as independent. Being at Spa with his pupil in
                    the year 1767, he employed much of his time in making himself acquainted with
                    the German language; and in the follow ing year he was requested, by the Duke of
                    Grafton’s under-secretary, to undertake a translation of a Persian manuscript of
                    the life of Nadir Shah into the French language, of which the king of Denmark
                    was anxious to have a version. This, his first publication, appeared in 1770,
                    with the addition of a treatise on oriental poetry, which was very much admired
                    on account of the elegance of the French style and the accuracy of the,
                    translation. For this excellent publication it appears that he received nothing
                    more than a diploma from his Danish majesty, constituting him a member of the
                    Royal Society of Copenhagen, with a warm recommendation to the notice of his own
                    sovereign.</p><p>That he might be enabled to gratify his commendable ambition, he now began to
                    think seriously of some profession ,∙ and, as he had conceived an early
                    predilection for the law, he made that the object of his choice, and, in the
                    month of September 1770, entered himself at the Temple. Yet the studies of his
                    profession did not prevent him from making those literary advances in which he
                    so much delighted; and oriental literature still continued a favourite object.
                    When the life of Zoroaster by Anquetil Duperron made its appearance, in the
                    preliminary discourse to which the university of Oxford had been attacked, our
                    author defended it in a pamphlet written with equal severity and elegance. In
                    1772, he published a small volume of poems, being translations from the Asiatic
                    poets, remarkable for the grace and brilliancy of their style; and in 1774
                    appeared his work <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Poesi
                    Asiatica,</hi> the beauty and purity of the Latin in which it is composed
                    exciting the admiration of men of taste and learning both at home and abroad. He
                    was called to the bar in the beginning of 1774, but declined to act in that
                    capacity without a previous knowledge of the actual business of the profession.
                    He was appointed a commissioner of bankrupts in 1776, about which period he
                    addressed a letter to Lord Althorp, in which he expresses his ardent wish to
                    have constitutional liberty established by constitutional means.</p><p>His translation of the speech of Isaeus, on account of the elegant style and the
                    profound critical and historical knowledge it displayed, commanded the
                    admiration of every competent judge. Soon after this his practice at the bar
                    increased with rapidity; but he had little reason to flatter himself with the
                    prospect of advancement in professional rank and dignity, because he was known
                    to be convinced of the injustice of the British cause respecting the American
                    war, which he was at no pains to conceal; and an opponent of the measures of
                    those who had then the direction of public affairs, had little preferment to
                    look for. In 1780 he became a candidate to succeed to Sir Roger Newdigate as
                    representative in parliament for the university of Oxford, in which he was
                    respectably supported; but his political sentiments were ill suited to secure
                    him a majority, a circumstance which made him decline the contest prior to the
                    election. He soon afterwards published a pamphlet entitled “An Inquiry into the
                    legal mode of suppressing Riots, with a Constitutional Plan of future Defence,”
                    recommending the propriety of making every citizen a soldier in cases of
                    imminent danger. He next published a translation of seven ancient poems of the
                    highest reputation in Arabia, which, with an ode on the marriage of Lord
                    Althorp, procured for him the highest reputation. His essay on the law of
                    bailment was also much admired, as was his speech at the London Tavern in
                    defence of a parliamentary reform in 1782. At Paris he drew up a dialogue
                    between a farmer and a country gentleman on the principles of government, which
                    was published in Wales by the dean of St Asaph, and for which a bill of
                    indictment was preferred against <pb break="no" facs="nls:192945875" xml:id="kp-eb0712-5875-0621"/>that clergyman.
                    In a letter to Lord Kenyon, Mr Jones avowed himself the author, and asserted the
                    principles it contained to be perfectly agreeable to the British constitution;
                    but it appears that he afterwards relaxed considerably in his political
                    ardour.</p><p>After the resignation of Lord North, and the appointment of Lord Shelburne, Mr J
                    ones was nominated one of the judges in the British territories of India; an
                    appointment which he had long wished for, as it would afford him an opportunity
                    of prosecuting his favourite researches into oriental literature. He was
                    appointed a judge in March 1783, and on the 20th of that month the honour of
                    knighthood was conferred upon him. He arrived at Calcutta in September, and
                    entered upon his office in December, opening the sessions with a very elegant
                    charge to the grand jury. Here he planned the institution of a society similar
                    to the Royal Society of London, the valuable labours and researches of which are
                    already in the hands of the public. He collected materials for a complete digest
                    of the Hindu and Mahommedan laws, which interesting work he did not live to
                    bring to a conclusion. The publication of the <hi rend="italic">Asiatic
                    Researches</hi> occupied much of his attention. In 1789 he translated an ancient
                    Indian drama called <hi rend="italic">Sacontala,</hi> which has been considered
                    as an interesting curiosity. In 1794 he gave the world his Ordinances of Menu, a
                    famous Indian legislator, containing a system of duties both civil and
                    religious.</p><p>The climate of India having proved unfavourable to the health of Lady Jones, she
                    was obliged to return to England, whither Sir William designed soon to follow
                    her. But, on the 20th of April 1794, he was seized at Calcutta with an
                    inflammation of the liver, which set the powers of medicine at defiance, and on
                    the 27th of the same month he expired without pain or struggle.</p><p>It may be fairly asserted that few men have died more respected or regretted, as
                    few have passed a more useful and irreproachable life. The uncommon extent of
                    his erudition has been displayed in all his writings, and hardly any subject of
                    human research escaped his notice. He has scarcely ever been equalled as a
                    linguist, for he is said to have been more or less acquainted with about
                    twenty-eight different languages. Taste and elegance marked all his exertions,
                    and he might have risen as a poet to the very first rank. Great as his knowledge
                    was, his virtue and religion were not inferior. In whatever light we think
                    proper to view him as standing in relation to society, he was undoubtedly a
                    pattern worthy of imitation.</p><p>As a permanent monument to his memory, his affectionate lady published his whole
                    finished works in six quarto volumes, in the year 1799; and a marble monument to
                    his memory by the same endeared friend was placed in the anti-chamber of
                    University College, Oxford. The East India Company also voted a monument to his
                    memory in St Paul’s Cathedral, and a statue of him to be sent out to Bengal.
                    Memoirs of his life were published by Lord Teignmouth; and a society of
                    gentlemen in Bengal, who had been educated at Oxford, subscribed a sum for a
                    prize dissertation on his character and merits, by students of that
                    university.</p></div></body></text></TEI>