<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0712-5407-0585-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">JIDDA, or D Jidda</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 12, page 585</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"                     replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">                     <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4xs5jj0k">Merchants</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b40c4st3m">Shopping</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dz24">Caravans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c62w">Bedouins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="10" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1017057">Merchants</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:1116884">Shopping</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="fasttopic:846714">Caravans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:829496">Bedouins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:812571">Arabism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1208755">Egypt</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208757">Syria</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1208963">Turkey</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:192945407" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">JIDDA, or D <hi rend="smallcaps">Jidda</hi></label>, a
                    considerable commercial town, the port of Mecca, situated on the eastern shore
                    of the Red Sea. It is built on a slightly rising ground, the lowest side of
                    which is washed by the sea, and extends along the shore, in its greatest length,
                    about 1500 paces, and is about half that space in breadth. It was encompassed
                    with a wall in 154-0; but as this ancient defence has long since fallen into a
                    state of ruin, a new wall has been constructed on the land side, by the joint
                    labours of the inhabitants, to guard against the incursions of the Wahabees. It
                    is in a tolerable state of repair, but is of no strength; though it is a
                    sufficient barrier against the Arabs, who have no artillery. Watch-towers, with
                    a few rusty guns, are erected at the distance of forty or fifty paces; a narrow
                    ditch is carried round it to increase the means of defence; and it enjoys
                    throughout Arabia the reputation of an impregnable fortress. At the northern
                    extremity stands the governor’s residence; and on the southern is a small
                    castle, mounting eight or ten guns. The whole harbour is commanded by a battery,
                    in which is mounted an immense old piece of ordnance, which carries a ball of
                    500 pounds, and, says Burckhardt, “is so celebrated all over the Red Sea, that
                    the very fame of it is a protection to the port.” The approach to the town by
                    the sea is by two quays, where small boats discharge the cargoes of large ships;
                    these last being obliged to anchor in the roadstead, about two miles from the
                    shore. The quays being shut every evening after sun-set, all communication is
                    prevented at night between the town and the shipping. On the land-side Jidda has
                    two gates, the Bab-Mekka on the east side, and the Bab-el-Medina on the north.
                    Along the area enclosed by the modern wall, and by the sea on the west, a broad
                    piece of open ground extends the whole length of the interior wall; there is
                    also a good deal of waste ground near the Medina gate, and on the southern
                    extremity. The suburbs consist of miserable huts of reeds, rushes, and
                    brushwood, inhabited by Bedouins or poor peasants and labourers, who live after
                    the Arab fashion. The most respectable inhabitants reside near the sea, where
                    there is a long street parallel with the shore, lined with shops, and containing
                    many khans, exclusively frequented by merchants. Jidda is well built; the
                    streets, though unpaved, are spacious and airy; and the houses are high,
                    consisting mostly of two stories, with many small windows and wooden shutters,
                    and wholly constructed of stone, mostly brought from the sea-shore, but
                    consisting of madrepores and other marine fossils. They have generally a
                    spacious hall at the entrance, where, at noon, the master, with all his male
                    attendants and slaves, may be seen enjoying a siesta. No attention is paid to
                    uniformity of architecture. Some houses are built with small, others with large
                    square stones; sometimes the walls are entirely of stone, whilst at other times
                    layers of plank are placed at intervals in the wall. When the walls are
                    plastered, the dazzling white, during the glare of the sun, is extremely
                    distressing to the eye. There are no buildings of ancient date, owing to the
                    rapid decay of the madrepore, of which they are constructed, when it is exposed
                    to the rain and the moist atmosphere prevalent on the shores of the Red Sea. The
                    town contains, besides many small mosques, two of considerable size. The
                    governor’s habitation is a paltry building, as also that of the collector of the
                    customs. The khans are, many of them, well built, and have good accommodation
                    for the foreign merchants, whose residence they are during their short stay in
                    the town. Water is scarce in Jidda, as in most of the Arabian towns. Several of
                    the wells are private property, and yield their owners a considerable income.
                    Every town of moderate size has its cisterns; but the rains not falling in
                    sufficient abundance to afford an adequate supply to the town, the inhabitants
                    are forced to have recourse to pools formed outside of the town in the rainy
                    season. This water is not so good as the rain-water, which is esteemed a
                    delicacy; and though water is everywhere found at the depth of fifteen feet, it
                    is of a bad quality, and scarcely fit for use. There are only two wells that
                    afford sweet water, which is wholly consumed by the rich. The poorer classes use
                    the water supplied by the other wells, to which, being of indifferent quality,
                    their ill health is ascribed. The town of Jidda is surrounded by a barren
                    desert, without gardens or vegetation of any kind, except a few date-trees
                    adjoining one of the mosques, or a few shrubs and low acacia trees. Beyond the
                    Mecca wall; and on the road to this place, are huts inhabited by poor Bedouins,
                    camel-drivers, and negro hadjis or pilgrims, who gain a livelihood by cutting
                    wood in the mountains. About a mile beyond these huts, eastward of the town, is
                    the principal burial-ground, containing the tombs of several sheiks. There are
                    also several cemeteries within the walls.</p>
                <p>The inhabitants of Jidda, like those of Mecca and Medina, are almost exclusively
                    foreigners, and consist, in many cases, of rich merchants, who come on their
                    pilgrimage to Mecca with large adventures of goods, and, not being able to
                    settle their accounts immediately, they wait another year. In the mean time,
                    cohabiting with Abyssinian slaves, whom they marry, and finding themselves with
                    a family, they at last settle in the country. Every pilgrimage thus adds to the
                    population of Jidda, as of the other Arabian towns, and recruits the waste
                    occasioned by the surplus of the deaths over the births. The natives of Jidda
                    are only a few families of Sherifs, who are all of the learned order, and are
                    attached to the mosques or the courts of justice. All the others are foreigners,
                    or their descendants. Colonies from every town and province of Hadramaut and
                    Yemen are settled in Jidda, and maintain an intercourse with their native
                    places. There are upwards of a hundred Indian families from Surat, and a few
                    from Bombay; also Malays, and people from Muskat. The settlers from Egypt,
                    Syria, Barbary, European Turkey, and Anatolia, may be still recognised in the
                    features of their descendants. No Christians are settled in Jidda; but a few
                    Greeks from the islands of the archipelago occasionally bring merchandise to
                    this market from Egypt. Jews were formerly the chief brokers of the town, but
                    they were all expelled about fifty or sixty years ago by some of the
                    governors.</p>
                <p>Jidda is a great emporium of maritime commerce, and well merits the Arabian
                    appellation of Djidda, or rich, being probably richer than any town of the same
                    size in the Turkish dominions. The inhabitants are mostly all engaged in
                    commerce, and pursue no manufactures or trades but those of immediate necessity.
                    They are all either sea-faring people, traders by sea, or engaged in trading
                    with Arabia. Jidda not only derives its riches from being the port of Mecca,
                    through which numerous bands of pilgrims pass in their journey to the holy
                    place, but it is an entrepôt of eastern commerce, through which all the exports
                    of India and Arabia destined for Egypt first pass. All bargains are chiefly for
                    ready money, the bad faith of the <pb break="no" facs="nls:192945420"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0712-5420-0586"/>eastern merchants not being favourable to credit.
                    Sales and purchases are made of entire ships’ cargoes in the course of half an
                    hour, and the next day the money is paid down. Its commerce may be divided into
                    two principal branches, namely, the coffee trade and the Indian trade. Ships
                    laden with coffee arrive from Yemen all the year round, and dispose of their
                    cargoes for cloths, linen stuffs, and beads, but chiefly for dollars, which they
                    take back to their own country. The demand for Arabian coffee in European
                    Turkey, Asia Minor, and Syria, has been in a great degree superseded, since the
                    termination of the war in Europe, by West India coffee.</p>
                <p>The fleets from India, from Calcutta, Surat, and Bombay, reach Jidda in the
                    beginning of May; their cargoes of Indian goods are immediately bought up by the
                    merchants of Jidda, or on account of Cairo merchants, who send money to Jidda
                    for the purpose. The greater part of the merchandise is shipped for Suez, and
                    sold at Cairo, whence it finds its way into the Mediterranean. The returns are
                    made either in goods or in dollars and sequins, large quantities of which are
                    carried off annually by the Indian fleet. There are several rich merchants in
                    Jidda. Burckhardt, on whose accurate information this account is chiefly
                    founded, mentions two merchants whose grandfathers were the original settlers,
                    and who had each a capital of from L.150,000 to L.250,000. Several Indians, he
                    adds, had acquired capitals nearly equal; and there were about a dozen of houses
                    possessing from L.40,000 to L.50,000 sterling. The vessels belonging to Jidda
                    amount to about 250. It trades by land only with Mecca and Medina. A caravan, of
                    from sixty to a hundred camels, departs for Medina every forty or fifty days,
                    principally with India goods and drugs, and is always augmented by a crowd of
                    pilgrims, who wish to visit Mahommed’s tomb. There is another caravan for Mecca
                    every evening, or at least twice a week, with goods and provisions. During the
                    pilgrimage these caravans set out regularly every evening after sun-set from the
                    Mecca gate; also a caravan of asses, which perform the journey in fifteen or
                    sixteen hours. It is by this caravan that letters are conveyed between the two
                    towns. There are twenty-seven coffee-shops in Jidda, where coffee, as in most
                    parts of Arabia, is drunk to excess, and various other shops for the sale of
                    butter, which is a chief article of Arabian cookery; honey, oil, vinegar,
                    fruits, dates, beans, &amp;c.; sweet-meats, sugar-plums, bread, milk; corn,
                    consisting of Egyptian wheat, beans, lentils, dhourra, Indian and Egyptian rice;
                    biscuits, salt, tobacco, soap, drugs, spices, sugar, perfumery, incense, &amp;c.
                    There are also shops for articles of Indian manufacture, for the sale of clothes
                    chiefly after the Turkish fashion, carpets, Indian piece goods. There are,
                    besides, bankers, bakers, tailors, and one watch-maker. The number of
                    inhabitants may be estimated in general at from 12,000 to 15,000; but during the
                    months preceding the pilgrimage, and the summer months, when the Indian fleets
                    arrive with the monsoons, the influx of strangers swells the population one half
                    above its usual number. Long. 39. 15. E. Lat. 21. 29. N.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
