<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0208-0197-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">INTESTACY (9th edition, volume 13, page 197)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204622">Georgia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pn8xd98">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659j0m">Descent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qv3c374">Blood</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:796146">Acting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839665">Brothers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:921865">Fathers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115271">Sharing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:888385">Dead</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n208/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">INTESTACY</label>. In dealing with the property of a person
                    who dies without making a will, the law of England distinguishes sharply between
                    his real and his personal estate. The devolution of the former is regulated by
                    the rules of <hi rend="smallcaps">Inheritance</hi><hi rend="italic">(q.υj).</hi>
                    The destination of the latter is marked out by the Statute of Distributions. The
                    proper conditions of a testamentary disposition of property will be found under
                    the heading <hi rend="smallcaps">Will.</hi></p>
                <p>The distribution of an intestate’s personal estate is carried out under the
                    authority of administrators, whose duties are generally the same as those of
                    executors under a will. Administration was until quite recently a matter
                    cognizable by the ecclesiastical courts, and the ordinary was in fact the
                    administrator until the passing of the 31 Edw. III. st. i. c. 11. An earlier
                    statute (Westminster 2) directed against the abuses, of the system required the
                    ordinary, instead of applying the residue of the estate to “pious uses,” to pay
                    the debts of the intestate. The Act of Edward III. went further in providing
                    that “in case where a man dieth intestate, the ordinaries shall depute of the
                    next and most lawful friends of the dead person intestate to administer his
                    goods,” with power to sue for debts due to the deceased, and under obligation to
                    pay debts due by him, and to answer to the ordinary like executors in the case
                    of testament. Administrators remained on this footing of deputies appointed by
                    the ordinary until the Probate Act transferred the jurisdiction in
                    administration of the ecclesiastical courts to the new court of probate.</p>
                <p>The courts of law having held that by the grant of administration the authority
                    of the ecclesiastical courts was exhausted, the administrator became entitled to
                    the privilege, similar to that formerly enjoyed by the ordinary, of dealing as
                    he pleased with residue of the estate. The next of kin of the same degree of
                    relationship with the deceased were thus aggrieved by the preference of the
                    administrator, and it was to remedy this grievance that the Statute of
                    Distributions (22 and 23 Charles II. c. 10) was passed. It empowered the
                    ordinary to take a bond from the administrator binding him to make a fair and
                    complete distribution of the estates among the next of kin. Such distribution is
                    to be in the following manner: —one-third to the wife of the intestate, and all
                    the residue by equal portions to and amongst the children, and their
                    representatives if any of such children be dead, exclusive of children who shall
                    have any estate by the settlement of the intestate, or shall be advanced by the
                    intestate in his lifetime by portions equal to the shares allotted to the other
                    children under the distribution. If such advancement should be less than the
                    share of the other children in distribution, then it shall be made equal
                    thereto. But the “heir-at-law, notwithstanding any land that he shall have by
                    descent or otherwise from the intestate, is to have an equal part in
                    distribution with the rest of the children” (§ 5). By § 6, if there be no
                    children nor any legal representatives of children, one moiety of the estate <pb
                        break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n209/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0913-0209-0198"/> is to be allotted to the wife of the
                    intestate, the residue “to be distributed equally to any of the next of kindred
                    of the intestate who are equal in degree and those who legally represent them.”
                    By § 7 there shall “be no representation admitted among collaterals after
                    brothers’ and sisters’ children; and in case there be no wife, then all the said
                    estate to be distributed equally to and among the children; and in case there be
                    no child, then to the next of kindred in equal degree of or unto the intestate
                    and their legal representatives as aforesaid, and in no other manner
                    whatsoever.” For the protection of creditors it is enacted that there shall be
                    no distribution till a full year after the intestate’s death, and if any debts
                    should be discovered after distribution, the persons sharing the estate shall
                    refund the amount of the same ratably. Finally, by § 4 it is provided that
                    nothing in the Act shall prejudice the customs of London, York, and other places
                    having customable rules of succession; but these have been since abolished.</p>
                <p>With reference to the above rules the following points may be observed:—(1) The
                    husband’s absolute right to administer his wife’s estate is not affected by the
                    Act. This was made clear by a later Act of the same reign (29 Charles II. c. 3).
                    Administration is now granted to the representatives of the husband, where he
                    has died without taking out administration to his wife, unless it can be shown
                    that the wife’s next of kin are beneficially interested. (2) The widow, in the
                    event of there being no children or next of kin, takes only her half. The other
                    half goes to the crown. (3) The child or children take equally two-thirds if the
                    widow be alive, and the whole if she be dead. If the children of the intestate
                    be all dead, the grandchildren will take equally amongst themselves as next of
                    kin; if there be neither child nor grandchild alive the great-grandchildren
                    would likewise take equally as a class <hi rend="italic">(per capita).</hi> But
                    if some of the children be alive, some dead leaving issue, the children of a
                    deceased child take their father’s share <hi rend="italic">(per stirpes).</hi>
                    Thus, for example, the ten children of a deceased son would only take between
                    them their father’s share if any brother or sister of their father were alive;
                    if not, they would share equally with the other grandchildren. (4) The next of
                    kin must be ascertained according to the rules of consanguinity, which are the
                    same in English as in the civil law. Degree is calculated from the intestate,
                    through the common ancestor if any, to the kindred. Thus from son to father is
                    one degree, to grandfather two degrees, to brother two degrees, to uncle three
                    degrees, and so on. The statute ordains distribution to be made “to the next of
                    kindred in equal degrees <hi rend="italic">pro</hi><hi rend="italic">suo
                        cuique</hi><hi rend="italic">jure,</hi> according to the laws in such cases
                    and the rules and limitations hereafter set down.” Equality in degree is
                    therefore not in all cases accompanied by equality in rights of succession.
                    Neglecting the cases of wife and children already noticed, the father excludes
                    all other next of kin. So would a mother, in default of a father surviving, but
                    the Act 1 James II. c. 17 enacted that in such a case the brothers and sisters
                    of the intestate should share equally with the mother. The language both of this
                    and of the principal statute is very inapt, and has given rise to complicated
                    questions of interpretation. In the absence of brothers or sisters and their
                    representatives, the mother in the case supposed would take the whole.
                    Mothers-in-law and stepmothers are not within the rules of consanguinity. As
                    between a brother and a grandfather who are both in the second degree,
                    preference is given to the brother; but a grandfather, being in the second
                    degree, will exclude an uncle, who is in the third. An uncle and a nephew, both
                    being in the third degree, take together. Brothers or sisters of the half blood
                    take equally with brothers and sisters of the whole blood. The rule which
                    prohibits representations after brothers’ and sisters’ children would, in a case
                    where the next of kin were uncles or nephews, wholly exclude the children of a
                    deceased uncle or nephew. Also, as between the son of a brother and the grandson
                    of a brother, the latter would not be admitted by representation. Where a
                    brother and the children of a deceased brother are the next of kin, they will
                    take <hi rend="italic">per stirpes, i.e.,</hi> the brother will take one half,
                    and the children of the other brother will take the other half between them.
                    When the next of kin are all children of the deceased brothers or sisters, they
                    will take equally <hi rend="italic">per capita.</hi> Subject to these
                    modifications, the personal estate will be divided equally among the next of kin
                    of equal degree, <hi rend="italic">e.g.,</hi> great-grandfathers would share
                    with uncles or aunts, as being in the third degree. Failing next of kin, under
                    these rules, the estate goes to the crown as <hi rend="italic">ultimus</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">hseres,</hi> a result which is more likely to happen in the
                    case of illegitimate persons than in any other.</p>
                <p>Personal or movable property takes its legal character from the domicile of the
                    owner, and the distribution of an intestate’s goods is therefore regulated by
                    the law of the country in which the intestate was domiciled. A domiciled
                    Scotchman, for example, dies intestate in England, leaving personal property in
                    England; the administrator appointed by the court of probate will be bound to
                    distribute the estate according to the Scotch rules of succession.</p>
                <p>In the law of Scotland the free movable estate of the intestate is divided
                    amongst the nearest of kin, the full blood excluding the half blood, and neither
                    mother nor maternalrelations being originally admitted. The heir of the
                    heritable property if one of the next of kin must collate with the next of kin
                    if he wishes to share in the movables. Proximity of kin is reckoned in the same
                    order as in the case of inheritance. The Intestate Movable Succession Act, 1855,
                    among other changes, allows the issue of a predeceasing next of kin to come in
                    the place of their parent in succession to an intestate, gives the father of an
                    intestate dying without issue one-half of the movable estate in preference to
                    brothers and sisters, and to the mother if the father be dead a similar
                    preference to the extent of one-third, and admits brothers and sisters uterine
                    in the absence of brothers and sisters german or consanguineam</p>
                <p>In the United States the English Statute of Distribution has been taken as the
                    basis of the law for the distribution of personal property in intestacy, and its
                    principles have been applied to real property also. “Ina majority of the States
                    the descent of real and personal property is to the same persons and in the same
                    proportions, and the regulation is the same in substance as the English Statute
                    of Distribution. In Georgia the real and personal estate of the intestate is
                    considered as altogether of the same nature and upon the same footing. . . . The
                    English Statute of Distribution, being founded on justice and on the wisdom of
                    ages, was well selected as the most suitable and judicious basis on which to
                    establish our American law of descent and distribution.” See <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">Inheritance.</hi> (E. R. )</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
