<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0913-0448-0433-05" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ISTRIA (9th edition, volume 13, page 433)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>387 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n29p91c">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47h1dv6c">Rye</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44t6f430">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669847">Slavs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z56c">Goths</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1056939">Peninsulas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1174325">Wheat</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102628">Rye</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150988">Timber</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120771">Slavs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:967439">Illyrians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204901">Austria</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n448/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">ISTRIA</label> (anciently also <hi rend="italic"
                        >Histria,</hi> in German <hi rend="italic">Istrien,</hi> and formerly <hi
                        rend="italic">Histerreicli),</hi> a margraviate of Austria, forming the
                    southern part of the Küstenland crownland, is contained in the peninsula which,
                    bounded on the north by the districts of Trieste, Görz, and Carniola, stretches
                    southwards into the Adriatic Sea, between the Gulf of Trieste <hi rend="italic"
                        >(Sinus</hi><hi rend="italic">Tergestinus),</hi> and the Gulf of Quarnaro
                        <hi rend="italic">(Sinus Flanaticus).</hi> The area of the official
                    district, which includes Veglia, Cherso, Lussino, and other smaller islands on
                    the south-east coast, is 1908 square miles, of which 1545 belong to the
                    peninsula itself. The surface is mountainous, especially in the north and east
                    regions, which are occupied by offshoots from the Julian Alps. Monte Maggiore
                    (4573 feet) in the north-east is the highest summit. The Quieto in the west and
                    the Arsa in the east, neither of which is navigable, are the principal streams.
                    The west coast abounds in convenient bays and harbours, of which Pola, an
                    imperial naval station, is the chief; but the steep and rocky east coast is
                    beset with shallows and islets, and is much exposed to the prevailing winds, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Sirocco</hi> from the south-south-east and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Bora</hi> from the north-east. The climate of Istria, although
                    it varies with the varieties of surface, is on the whole warm and dry. The soil
                    is not unfertile, but its resources are far from being fully developed. About
                    one half of the total area is occupied with scanty grass and pasture land, while
                    timber and the various annual crops divide the remainder in different
                    proportions. Wheat, oats, potatoes, and rye are grown in the north, and in the
                    south wheat, maize, rye, olives, vines, and melons. The harvest of 1872 yielded
                    46,410 bushels of wheat, 157,385 of rye, 165,800 of oats, and 158,200 of maize;
                    and the value of the total agricultural produce was £950,000. Beech and oak
                    timber (good for shipbuilding), gall-nuts, oak-bark, and cork are also produced.
                    The minerals include coal, alum, quartz, and good building stone. Many of the
                    inhabitants are engaged in a seafaring life, in fishing, and in preparing salt
                    for fishcuring. Shipbuilding, sheep and cattle rearing, and the manufacture of
                    oil, wine, and bricks are also noteworthy industries. The best sorts of wine are
                    made near Capo d’Istria, Muggia, Isola, Parenzo, and Dignano; and the oil of
                    Istria was famous even in Roman times. The trade of the peninsula is
                    unimportant. The roads are fairly numerous, and a railway, lately opened, with a
                    branch to Rovigno, connects Pola with Trieste. Istria is divided into the six
                    government districts of Capo d’Istria, Parenzo, Pisino, Pola, Volosca, and, for
                    the islands, Lussino. The estates of Istria, which meet at Parenzo, consist of 3
                    bishops, 5 representatives of the landed proprietors, 8 representatives of the
                    towns, 12 representatives for the other and rural communities, and 2
                    representatives of the chamber of commerce at Rovigno. Two-thirds of the people
                    are Slavs, although among these there are many differences of dress and dialect.
                    The remaining third, on the coast and in the towns, is almost entirely Italian.
                    The population in 1869 was 254,905, of whom 35,917 belonged to the islands:
                    278,218 was the official estimate at the end of 1879.</p>
                <p>The modern Istria occupies the same position as the ancient Istria or Histria,
                    known to the Romans as the abode of a fierce tribe of Illyrian pirates. It owed
                    its name to an old belief that the Danube (Ister, in Greek) discharged some of
                    its water by an arm entering the Adriatic in that region. The Istrians,
                    protected by the difficult navigation of their rocky coasts, were only subdued
                    by the Romans in 177 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> after two wars. Under
                    Augustus the greater part of the peninsula was added to Italy, and, when the
                    seat of empire was removed to Ravenna, Istria reaped many benefits from the
                    proximity of the capital. After the fall of the Western empire it was pillaged
                    by the Longobardi and the Goths; it was annexed to the Frankish kingdom by
                    Pippin in 789; and about the middle of the 10th century it fell into the hands
                    of the dukes of Carinthia. Fortune after that, however, led it successively
                    through the hands of the dukes of Meran, the duke of Bavaria, and the patriarch
                    of Aquileia, to the republic of Venice. Under this rule it remained till the
                    peace of Campo Formio in 1797, when Austria acquired it, and added it to the
                    north-eastern part which had fallen to her share so early as 1374. By the peace
                    of Pressburg, Austria was in 1805 compelled to cede Istria to France, and the
                    department of Istria was formed; but in 1813 Austria again seized it, and has
                    retained it ever since. <hi rend="italic">Sαggiο di bibliοgrafa Istriaηa</hi>
                    (Capodistria, 1864) contains a classified bibliography of the province.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n449/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0449-0434"/>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
