<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0913-0200-0189-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">INTERNATIONAL</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 13, page 189</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>19kp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1355303">Wars</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1079934">Protestants</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1047771">Organisms</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:918096">Exhibitionism</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942100">Germans</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:942099">Germanization</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b44j09z32">Founding</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4k931f29">Ruins</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4br8mh3x">Organ</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b45m62b4v">Germans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4rn30b7z">Freemasons</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3m81r">Swiss</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b42v2c962">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="4" ref="fastgeo:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206891">Poland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n200/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">INTERNATIONAL</label>. The International Working Men’s
                    Association, commonly called the “International,”’ was formed at London in 1864.
                    It was a society of working men of all nations, somewhat like a cosmopolitan
                    trades union, but bearing a still closer resemblance to an international social
                    science association for discussing and furthering the rights of labour. At first
                    moderate in its tone, it soon began to endorse advanced views respecting
                    property and industrial organization. Shortly after it had attained to the
                    height of its power about 1869, it became more and more allied with the most
                    destructive socialism of western Europe. Weakened by internal disunion, and
                    discredited by its approval of the commune at Paris and its alliance with the
                    communal risings in southern Spain, the International died a natural death
                    before it was quite ten years old.</p>
                <p>The occasion of the formation of the International was the visit of some French
                    workmen to the London Exhibition of 1862. This visit had the approval and even
                    the pecuniary support of the emperor, and was warmly commended by some of the
                    leading Parisian organs as a means, not only of acquainting them with the
                    industrial treasures of the exhibition, but of removing from the relations of
                    the two countries the old leaven of international discord and jealousy. In the
                    course of their visit the French delegates were cordially welcomed at an
                    entertainment at the Freemasons’ Tavern, where the labour question was
                    discussed, and a desire for the further interchange of ideas expressed. Nothing
                    decisive, however, was done till 1864, when a great public meeting of working
                    men of all nations was held at St Martin’s Hall, at which Professor Beesly
                    presided. Here a provisional committee was appointed to draft the constitution
                    of the new association. In this constitution, which was approved at the first
                    congress held at Geneva in 1866, and in a remarkable address issued by the
                    committee the aim of the International is defined in clear and able terms. It
                    was set forth that, notwithstanding the vast development of industry and the
                    enormous accumulation of national wealth, the lob of the working class was as
                    hard as ever. All the recent revolutions and political reforms had been achieved
                    only in the interest of the middle classes, leaving the position of the working
                    man unimproved. The emancipation of the working men must be the task of the
                    working men themselves. With this view the International was founded, which,
                    while recognizing truth, justice, and morality as the basis of its action,
                    without distinction of creed, nationality, and colour, would serve as a common
                    centre for the efforts of working men towards their complete deliverance from
                    the tyranny of capital. A general council having its seat at London was
                    appointed, which was to hold annual congresses and exercise a general control
                    over the affairs of the association, while local societies were allowed free
                    play in all local questions. The working men of a district or trade were to form
                    a section, several sections formed a federation, and all the societies of each
                    nation were if possible to form a national association; but all were to be in
                    communication with the International headquarters.</p>
                <p>The first four congresses of the International, held at Geneva (September 1866),
                    Lausanne (1867), Brussels (1868), and Basel (1869), marked the rapid development
                    of the association. It gained its first triumph in the effectual support of the
                    bronze-workers at Paris during their lock-out in 1867; and it repeatedly gave
                    real help to the English unionists by preventing the importation of cheap labour
                    from the Continent. In the beginning of 1868 one hundred and twenty-two
                    societies of South Germany assembled at Nuremberg declared their adhesion to the
                    International. In 1870 Cameron announced himself as the representative of
                    800,000 American workmen who had adopted its principles. It soon spread as far
                    east as Poland and Hungary, and it had affiliated societies with journals
                    devoted to its cause in every country of western Europe. The leading organs of
                    the European press became more than interested in its movements; the <hi
                    rend="italic">Times</hi> published four leaders on the Brussels congress. It was
                    supposed to be concerned in all the revolutionary movements and agitations of
                    Europe, gaining a world historic notoriety as the rallying point of social
                    overthrow and ruin. Its prestige, however, was always based more on the vast
                    possibilities of the cause it represented than on its actual power. Its
                    organization was loose, its financial resources insignificant; the Continental
                    unionists joined it more in the hope of borrowing than of contributing support.
                    At the successive congresses its socialistic tendencies became more and more
                    pronounced; it declared its opposition to private property not only in railways
                    but in mines and the soil, holding that these should revert to the community.
                    Even the principle of inheritance was saved only by a narrow majority. Tn 1869
                    Bakunin the Russian socialist or nihilist with his party joined the association,
                    and at once asserted his character as the “apostle of universal
                    destruction.”</p>
                <p>In 1870 the International resolved to establish itself at the very hearth of the
                    revolutionary movement by holding its annual congress at Paris. This plan was
                    rendered abortive by the Franco-German conflict. That war, however, helped to
                    bring the principles of the association more decidedly before the world. On
                    general grounds, and during the Λustro-Prussian struggle of 1866, it had
                    declared its emphatic condemnation of war; and now the societies of France and
                    Germany as well as the general council at London uttered a solemn protest
                    against this renewal of the scourge. Some of its German adherents likewise
                    incurred the wrath of the authorities by venturing to protest against the
                    annexation of Alsace and Lorraine. In this way the International appeared as the
                    champion of a wider principle against the abuse of the principle of
                    nationality.</p>
                <p>The relation of the association to the communal rising at Paris in the spring of
                    1871 has been the subject of much dispute. It is now agreed that the
                    International as such had no part either in originating or conducting it; some
                    of its French members joined it, but only on their individual responsibility.
                    Its complicity after the event is equally clear. After the fall of the commune
                    the general council of London, Karl Marx included, issued a long and trenchant
                    manifesto, approving its action and extolling the “glorious vanquished.” From
                    this point the decline and <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit13newyrich/page/n201/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0913-0201-0190"/> fall of the association is to be dated. The
                    English unionists, intent on more practical concerns at home, never took a deep
                    interest in its proceedings; the German socialists were hindered by law from
                    corporate action; America was too remote. But it found its worst enemies amongst
                    its own friends; the views of Marx and his school were too moderate for the
                    universally subversive principles of Bakunin, and the radical Swiss federation
                    of the Jura led by Guillaume. It came to a rupture at the congress of 1872, held
                    at the Hague, when Bakunin, being outvoted and “excommunicated” by the Marx
                    party, formed a rival International, which found its chief support in Spain and
                    Italy, Wearied of its European contentions and desirous to form a basis of
                    operation in America, the Marx International now transferred the seat of its
                    general council to New York; but it survived just long enough to hold another
                    congress at Geneva in 1874, and then quietly expired. The party of destruction
                    styling themselves “autonomists” had a bloodier history. The programme of this
                    party was to overturn all existing institutions, with the view to reconstructing
                    them on some vague communal basis such as had been tried at Paris in 1871. It
                    endeavoured to realize this in the great communal risings in southern Spain in
                    1873, when its adherents set up their peculiar form of government at Barcelona,
                    Seville, Cadiz, and Cartagena,— at the last-mentioned place also seizing on part
                    of the ironclad fleet of Spain. As at Paris, they failed in leadership and
                    organization, and were suppressed, though not without difficulty, by the
                    national troops. The “autonomists” lingered on till 1879. At present there is no
                    society that has any claim to the name and prestige of the International. The
                    collapse has thus been complete of an association which once extended from
                    Hungary to San Francisco, and alarmed the minds of men with visions of universal
                    ruin.</p>
                <p>See Villetard, <hi rend="italic">Histoire de l'internationale,</hi> Paris, 1871;
                    Testut, <hi rend="italic">L'Internationale,</hi> Paris, 1871; Onslow Yorke, <hi
                    rend="italic">Secret History of the International,</hi> London, 1871; Emile de
                    Laveleye, <hi rend="italic">Revue des Deux Mondes,</hi> April 1880; Professor
                    Beesly, <hi rend="italic">Fortnightly Review,</hi> 1870. (T. K.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
