<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-3462-0319-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BALLAD (7th edition, volume 4, page 319)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106456">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1106459">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825857">Ballade</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825864">Ballads</term>
                    <term ref="fast:825860">Ballades</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126120">Songs</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sf2mc29">Ballads</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68967">Songs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47941291">Scandinavians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81x15">Scandinavianism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204556">Norway</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193193462?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BALLAD</label> is a word frequently used as synonymous with
                    <hi rend="italic">song:</hi> but it properly denotes an historical song, or a
                    song containing a narrative of adventures or exploits, either serious or comic.
                    It is one of the most ancient species of composition, and still constitutes a
                    great portion of the literature of the more uncivilized tribes of mankind.
                    Giovanni Finati, who supplies us with much information respecting the manners
                    and customs of the East, has recorded the following anecdote of
                    ballad-literature among the Benysackr Arabs, whom he found encamped near the
                    shores of the Dead Sea. Their chief, Ibn Fays, he states, “had strangers with
                    him from Damascus, and feasted his guests so plentifully, that the wooden dish
                    out of which we all fed had four iron handles to it, and required three persons
                    to lift it and set it before us. Afterwards, a great earthen pan of grease was
                    lighted as a lamp for the company, and Ibn Fays himself, and his brother, sung a
                    sort of slow plaintive ballad to an instrument with one string, the purport of
                    which was the tragic account of a battle against a neighbouring tribe, in which
                    their own father perished·”<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Narrative of the Life and Adventures of Giovanni
                    Finati,</hi> translated by William John Bankes, Esq. vol. ii. p. 272. Lond.
                    1830, 2 vols. 8vo.</p></note> The leader of this wandering horde might himself
                    be the author, as well as tlιe reciter, of the ballad which thus regaled his
                    guests.</p>
                <p>Most of the nations of modern Europe have considerable collections of the ballads
                    which delighted their forefathers; and in some countries the political influence
                    of such compositions has been found to be very powerful. “Of these,” says Dr
                    Aikin, <hi rend="superscript"> ζζ</hi> the most copious source is party; and
                    there has seldom been an occasion of political contest in countries permitting
                    such freedoms, in which appeal has not been made to the popular feelings by
                    means of comic and satirical ballads, often with great effect. The share that
                    <hi rend="italic">Lilliburlero</hi> had in producing the Revolution in this
                    country has been noticed by grave historians. In the war of the Fronde in
                    France, ballads were a weapon as much employed as muskets, and those written for
                    and against Cardinal Mazarin filled several volumes. The French give to these
                    compositions the appropriate title of <hi rend="italic">Vaudeville,</hi>
                    implying their fitness to walk the streets; and indeed street-poetry iñ general
                    belongs to the ballad class.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Aikin’s <hi rend="italic">Essay on Song-Writing</hi> (p.
                    xviii.) prefixed to Vocal Poetry, or a Select Collection of English Songs. Bond.
                    1810, 8vo.</p></note> The Spaniards<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p><hi rend="italic">See the introduction to Depping’s</hi>
                    Sammlung der besten alten Spanischen Historischen llittcr-und Maurischen
                    Romanzen. <hi rend="italic">Altenburg und Leipzig, 1817, 12mo.</hi></p></note>
                    and other nations of the south have preserved ample collections of their early
                    ballads; but the affinity of our own nation and tongue with those of the
                    northern tribes, renders their literary reliques an object of more particular
                    interest. The various tribes of Scandinavians have generally been distinguished
                    for their love of poetry. Many ancient reliques of Islandic poetry are still
                    preserved, and are regarded as very curious specimens of the literature of the
                    different ages to which they belong; nor are the kindred nations of Sweden and
                    Denmark without their early and recent poets, some of whom have attained to high
                    reputation. Of the ballad-poetry of these northern nations, many remnants have
                    descended to our times; and ample collections of Danish, Swedish, and even
                    Feroese ballads have recently been published by respectable editors, “The songs
                    mentioned by Tacitus in his account of the Germans,” says Mr Jamieson, “those
                    collected by the order of Charlemagne, and those which the Goths brought with
                    them out of the East, are now not to be found; yet it is more than probable that
                    much more of them is preserved, in however altered a form, than we are aware of;
                    in the elder northern and Teutonic romances, the Danish and Swedish, Scottish
                    and English popular ballads, and those which are sung by old women and nurses,
                    and hawked about at fairs, in Germany.”<note anchored="true" place="bottom"
                    type="authorial"><p>Illustrations of Northern Antiquities, <hi rend="italic">p.
                    245. Edinb. 1814, 4to.</hi></p></note> The same ingenious and well-informed
                    writer has elsewhere expressed his conviction, that many of the traditionary
                    ballads still current in this kingdom have been preserved in the north of
                    England and the lowlands of Scotland, ever since the arrival of the Cimbri in
                    Britain.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Jamieson’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Popular Ballads and Songs,</hi> vol. ii. p. 87∙ Edinb. 180G, 2
                    vols. 8vo.—See however Mr Finlay’s <hi rend="italic">Scottish Historical and
                    Romantic Ballads,</hi> vol. i. p. xxv. Edinb. 1808, 2 vols. 8vo.</p></note> Many
                    of our historical ballads may at all events be considered as the productions of
                    a remote period; but it is not to be supposed that they have been transmitted
                    from one generation to another without innumerable transformations. A great
                    proportion of them have doubtless been preserved by oral tradition; and they
                    seem in general to have undergone such changes as brought them nearer to the
                    current speech of each successive generation; for, without this progressive
                    adaptation, the lapse of a few centuries would have rendered them unintelligible
                    to the great body of the people; nor is it usual for any combination of words to
                    be retained in the memory without being understood. Thus, for example, we have
                    reason to believe that the ballad of Sir Patrick Spence derives its origin from
                    a very early age; but the variations to which it must gradually have been
                    subjected, may easily be inferred from a comparison of the different copies
                    which are now to be found.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Percy’s</hi> Reliques of Ancient English Poetry, <hi
                    rend="italic">vol. i. p. 81. Scott’s</hi> Minstrelsy of the Scottish Border, <hi
                    rend="italic">vol. i. p. 7∙ Jamieson’s</hi> Popular Ballads. and Songs, <hi
                    rend="italic">vol. i. p. 157—See Mr Motherwell’s</hi> Minstrelsy, Ancient and
                    Modern, <hi rend="italic">p. xliv. Glasgow, 1827, 4to.</hi></p></note> A story
                    may thus be preserved, when most of the original words have been changed. The
                    close affinity between the old Danish and the old Scotish and English ballads
                    has been noticed by various writers, by Pinkerton, Jamieson, Nyerup, Geijer, and
                    Grimm:<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Pinkerton’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Enquiry,</hi> vol. i. p. 3G4. Jamieson’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ballads,</hi> vol. ii. p- 87∙ Nyerup, <hi rend="italic">Danske Viser,</hi> Bind
                    v. S. 12. Geįjer, <hi rend="italic">Svcnska Folk-Visor,</hi> del. i. s. liv—The
                    affinity between the old English and the old Danish ballads is noticed in the
                    preface (S. xxxi.) to <hi rend="italic">Altdii-nische Heldenlieder, Balladen,
                    und Märchen,</hi> übersetzt von Wilhelm Carl Grimm. Heidelberg, 1811, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> -</hi> 8vo.</p></note> their resemblance is to be traced in
                    the general spirit and contrivance of the poems; while some of the Danish and
                    Scotish ballads exhibit a remarkable coincidence in their particular stories.
                    Whether these effects <pb break="no" facs="nls:193193475?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-3475-0320"/> are to be imputed to so remote a cause as the
                    emigration of the ancient Scandinavians, may however admit of much doubt and
                    hesitation. Fiction moves from one region to another with very elastic steps,
                    and in many instances it is impossible to trace her progress.</p>
                <p>The earliest collector of Danish ballads was Anders Sörensön Vedel, chaplain to
                    the king of Denmark, and an intimate friend of the celebrated astronomer Tyge
                    Brahe. His publication bears the title of an hundred select Danish ballads, <hi
                    rend="italic">or Et hundrede vduaalde Danske Viser.</hi> Ribe, 1591, 8vo. It is
                    now a very rare book, even in Denmark; but a copious account of it is given by
                    Nyerup, in the last volume of the more recent collection of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Danske Viser.</hi> After an interval of more than a century, another clergyman,
                    Peder Syv, reprinted this collection of Vedel, and added an equal number of
                    ballads. Kiöbenhavn, 1695, 8vo. But the most extensive collection appeared under
                    the following title: <hi rend="italic">Udvalgte Danske Viser fra
                    AIiddelalderen;</hi> efter A. S. Vedels og P. Syvs trykte Uđgaver, og efter
                    haand-skrevne Samlinger, udgivne paa ny af Abrahamson, Nyerup, og Rahbek.
                    Kiöbenhavn, 1812-14, 5 Bind. 8vo. This work is accompanied with notes and
                    illustrations, and appears to us to possess no inconsiderable value. A similar
                    collection of Swedish ballads was published by Geijer and Afzelius: <hi
                    rend="italic">Svenska Folk-Visor frŭm Forηtideη</hi><hi rend="italic subscript">
                    i</hi> sam- 1ade och utgifne af Er. Gust. Geijer och Arv. Aug. Afzelius.
                    Stockholm, 1814-16, 3 del. 8vo. These volumes are accompanied with music,
                    printed in a quarto form. Of Feroese ballads there is a recent collection: <hi
                    rend="italic">Foerö-iske Qpoeder om Sigurd Fosnersbane og hans AEt,</hi> med et
                    Anhang: samlede og oversatte af Hans Christian Lyng-bye, Sognepraest i Gjesing;
                    med en Indledning af P. Ľ. Müller, Dr. og Prof, i Theol. Randers, 1822, 8vo. Dr
                    Müller, the.author of the introduction, is a learned and able writer, well known
                    as the author of more important works.</p>
                <p>Debes mentions that, at their weddings, and at Christmas, the Feroese w ere
                    accustomed to “recreate themselves with a plain dance, holding one another by
                    the hand, and singing some old champion’s ballad.”<note anchored="true"
                    place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Debes’s <hi rend="italic">Description of the
                    Islands and Inhabitants of Foeroc,</hi> Englished by Dr Sterpin, p. 273. Lonđ.
                    1676, 12mo.</p></note> These islands were peopled in the ninth century by a
                    colony of Norwegians.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"
                    ><p><hi rend="italic">Torfaei</hi> Commentatio historica de Rébus gestis
                    Foereyensium seu Faròensium, <hi rend="italic">p. 7- Havniae, 1695,
                    8vo.</hi></p></note> The language of the people, as it appears in these ballads,
                    is removed to a considerable distance from the Islandic as well as the Danish.
                    The plan of publishing a Feroese dictionary was formed about half a century ago;
                    and the English prospectus printed upon that occasion furnishes so curious and
                    entertaining a specimen of the language, that we are tempted to insert it with
                    all its peculiarities.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">“Subscription.—</hi> We are minded after many years troublesome
                    Collection to acquaint the World with the Tongue, used upon the Isles of Fero, a
                    Dialect of the old noble Tongue in former Times written and spoken in Norway,
                    Denmark, Jsland, Swede, and in a good Deal of the english Dominion. Now it
                    appears for the world translated in Latin, Danish, and conferr’d with the
                    islandsh Tongue.</p>
                <p>“If we were men of Wealth, we would not forbear to Regard the Expences of
                    printing this Dictionary as a great Trifle, because it, very likely, not will
                    exceed a good Volume in 4to; but we are poor-men. Nevertheless we hope to bring
                    it forth by Way of Subscription and for that Reason We invite hereby our
                    Neighbours, the brave and Reasonable Englishmen to Deal with us the Honour of
                    bringing this Dialect out of the Darkness, wherein it lies, and let it see the
                    Day-Liht. No-Body of our Countrymen, as we know, has thought this before.</p>
                <p>“Perhaps this moment in our Life, ’ that has been the first in Time for this
                    Purpose, will be the Last, and no body afterwards would attend it. The Price
                    will be 2 pence a Sheet and upon good Paper 3 pence.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">“N. Mohr. J. C. Svabοl'</hi></p>
                <p>The two pages which follow are divided into columns for the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Names of the Subscriptors</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Number of
                    Exemplars;</hi> but it appears that the well-meaning and pains-taking creatures
                    met with too little encouragement to proceed in their enterprise. The prospectus
                    is without a date; but we learn from Müller and Nyerup that Svabo was employed
                    in collecting Feroese ballads in the years 1781 and 1782. (<hi rend="subscript">
                    x</hi>,)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
