<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-3943-0356-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BAPTISTS (7th edition, volume 4, page 356)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tx35664">Baptism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sx86">Personality</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qk1s">Christ</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48911q68">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:827229">Baptism</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1058777">Personals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:827285">Baptists</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1102429">Russians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205669">Jordan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193193943?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BAPTISTS</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical
                    History,</hi> a denomination of Christians, distinguished from other Christians
                    by their particular opinions respecting the mode and the subjects of
                    baptism.</p>
                <p>Instead of administering the ordinance by sprinkling, they maintain that it ought
                    to be administered only by immersion. Such, they insist, is the import of the
                    word ∕3αwr∕ζω; so that a command to baptize is a command to immerse. And thus it
                    was understood by those who first administered it. John the Baptist and the
                    apostles of Christ administered it in Jordan and other rivers and places where
                    there was much water. Both the administrators and the subjects are described as
                    going down into and coming up again out of the water; and the baptized are said
                    to be buried in baptism, and to be raised again; which language could not, they
                    say, be properly adopted on supposition of the ordinance being administered in
                    any other manner than by immersion. Thus also, they affirm» it was in general
                    administered in the primitive church; thus it is now administered in the Russian
                    and Greek church; and thus it is at this day directed to be administered in the
                    church of England to all who are thought <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193193956?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-3956-0357"/> capable of
                    submitting to it in this manner. With regard to the subjects of baptism, the
                    Baptists say that this ordinance ought not to be administered to children or
                    infants at all, nor to grown up persons in general; but to adults only of a
                    certain character and description. Our Saviour’s commission to his apostles, by
                    which Christian baptism was instituted, is to go and teach all nations,
                    baptizing them; that is, say they, not to baptize all they meet with, but first
                    to instruct them, to teach all nations, or to preach the gospel to every
                    creature, and whoever receives it, him to baptize in the name of the Father, and
                    of the Son, and of the Holy Ghost. To such persons, and to such only, baptism
                    appears to have been administered by the apostles and the immediate disciples of
                    Christ. They are described as repenting of their sins, as believing in Christ,
                    and as having gladly received the word. Peter acquaints those who were converted
                    by his sermon, that without these qualifications he could not have admitted them
                    to baptism; Philip holds the same language in his discourse with the Ethiopian
                    eunuch; and Paul treats Lydia, the jailer, and others, in the same manner.
                    Without these qualifications Christians in general think it wrong to admit
                    persons to the Lord’s supper; and for the same reasons, without these
                    qualifications, or at least a profession of them, the Baptists think it wrong to
                    admit any to baptism. Wherefore they withhold it, not only from the impenitently
                    vicious and profane, and from infidels, who have no faith, but also from infants
                    and children, who have no knowledge, and are incapable of every action civil and
                    religious. They further insist that all positive institutions depend entirely
                    upon the will and declaration of the founder; wherefore, that reasoning by
                    analogy from abrogated Jewish rites is to be rejected, and the express commands
                    of Christ respecting the mode and subjects of baptism ought to be our only
                    rule.</p>
                <p>The Baptists in England form one of the denominations of Protestant dissenters.
                    They separate from the establishment for the same reasons as their brethren of
                    the other denominations do; and an additional motive is derived from their
                    particular tenets respecting baptism. The constitution of their churches, and
                    their mode of worship, is congregational or independent; and in the exercise of
                    it they are protected, in common with other dissenters, by the act of
                    toleration. Before this act they were liable to pains and penalties as
                    nonconformists, and often for their peculiar sentiments as Baptists. A
                    proclamation was in fact issued out against them, and some of them were burnt in
                    Smithfield in 1538. They bore a considerable share in the persecutions of the
                    seventeenth and preceding centuries, and, as it should seem, in those <hi
                    rend="italic">of</hi> even an earlier date; for among the Lollards and the
                    followers of Wickliffe there were several who disapproved of infant baptism, and
                    there were many of this persuasion among the Protestants and reformers abroad.
                    In Holland, Germany, and the North, they went by the names of Anabaptists and
                    Mennonites; and, in Piedmont and the south, they were found among the Albigenses
                    and Waldenses.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Baptists</hi> subsist under two denominations; the
                    Particular or Calvinistical, and the General or Arminian. The former is by far
                    the most numerous. Some of both denominations allow of <hi rend="italic">mixed
                    communion,</hi> that is, with persons who have been sprinkled in their infancy,
                    and therefore unbaptized in the view <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the Baptists.
                    Others, again, disallow it; and a few of them observe the seventh day of the
                    week as the Sabbath, apprehending the law that enjoined it not to have been
                    repealed by Christ or his <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi> P°stles. But a
                    difference of opinion respecting these and θtιer matters is not peculiar to the
                    Baptists, being common to all Christians, and to all bodies of men who think and
                    judge for themselves.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
