<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-5958-0511-03" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BED (7th edition, volume 4, page 511)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0329f">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vx06c7f">Welsh</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pg1hs5x">Gun</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ng4gw65">Gunning</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hx15r77">Sleep</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cv3f">Skins</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45d8nd6f">Skin</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0341g">Customs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:829528">Beds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829474">Bedding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1120819">Sleep</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800130">Age</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800293">Aging</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839101">Britons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193195958?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BED</label>, a convenience to stretch and compose the body
                    upon for ease, rest, or sleep, consisting generally of feathers, down, or other
                    soft material, enclosed in a ticken case. In the first ages it was universally
                    the practice for mankind to sleep upon skins of beasts. This was originally the
                    custom of the Greeks and Romans, as also of the ancięnt Britons previous to the
                    Roman invasion; and the skins thus employed were spread on the floor of their
                    apartments. But they were afterwards changed for loose rushes and heath; and in
                    process of time the Romans suggested to the central Britons the use, and the
                    introduction of agriculture supplied them with the means, of the greater
                    conveniency of straw beds. The beds of the Roman gentry at this period were
                    generally filled with feathers, and those of the inns with the soft down of
                    reeds. But for many ages the beds of the Italians had been constantly composed
                    of straw; it still formed those of the officers and soldiers present at the
                    conquest of Lancashire; and from both, it is probable, our countrymen learnt the
                    use of it. It appears, however, to have been used only by gentlemen, as the
                    common Welsh had their beds thinly stuffed with rushes as late as the end of the
                    twelfth century; and with the gentlemen it continued for many ages afterwards.
                    Straw was used in the royal chambers of England as late as the close of the
                    thirteenth century. Most of the peasants in different parts of the country sleep
                    on chaff beds at present; in the Highlands heath is also very generally employed
                    as bedding; and in France and Italy straw beds remain in general use to this
                    day.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Dining</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Bed,</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">lectus tricliniaris</hi> or <hi rend="italic">discubitorιus,</hi>
                    that on <pb break="no" facs="nls:193195971?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0704-5971-0512"/> which the ancients reclined at meals. The dining
                    or dis-cubitory beds were four or five feet in height. Three of these beds were
                    ordinarily ranged by a square table, (whence both the table and the apartment
                    where it stood were called <hi rend="italic">triclinium),</hi> in such a manner
                    that one of the sides of the table remained open and accessible to the waiters.
                    Each bed was fitted to receive three or four, rarely five persons. These beds
                    were unknown before the second Punic war; for the Romans till then had sat down
                    to eat on plain wooden benches, in imitation of the heroes of Homer, or,
                    according to Varro, after the manner of the Lacedaemonians and Cretans. But
                    Scipio Africanus first introduced a new mode, having brought from Carthage some
                    of the little beds called <hi rend="italic">punicani</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                    >archaici,</hi> which were constructed of a wood common enough, very low,
                    stuffed only with straw or hay, and covered with goats’ or sheeps’ skins, <hi
                    rend="italic">haedinis pellibus strati.</hi> In point of luxury, there was
                    really no great difference between these new beds and the ancient benches; but
                    the custom of frequent bathing, which already began to be general, by softening
                    and relaxing the body, put men on trying to rest themselves more commodiously
                    than by sitting down in an upright posture. As to the ladies, it did not seem
                    consistent with modesty for them to adopt the recumbent posture, and,
                    accordingly, they kept to the old custom during the continuance of the
                    commonwealth, and only began to use <hi rend="italic">triclinia</hi> in the
                    times of the first Caesars. The youth, again, who had not yet put on the <hi
                    rend="italic">toga virilis,</hi> were long kept to the ancient discipline, and,
                    when admitted to table, only sat on the edge of the beds of their nearest
                    relations. Never, says Suetonius, did the young Caesars, Caius and Lucius, eat
                    at the table of Augustus; they were set <hi rend="italic">in ∙ imo loco,</hi>
                    or, as Tacitus expresses it, <hi rend="italic">ad lecti fulcra.</hi> But, from
                    the greatest simplicity, the Romans by degrees carried their dining beds to the
                    most surprising magnificence. Pliny assures us it was no uncommon thing to see
                    them covered over with plates of silver, and adorned with the softest mats and
                    richest counterpanes. Lampridius, speaking of Heliogabalus, says, he had beds of
                    solid silver, <hi rend="italic">solido argento habuit lectos et tricliniares, et
                    cubiculares.</hi> We may add, that Pompey, in his third triumph, brought in beds
                    of gold. The Romans had also beds on which they studied, and beds on which the
                    dead were carried to the funeral pile.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Bed</hi><hi rend="italic">of Justice,</hi> in
                    France, under the old regime, a throne upon which the king sat when he went to
                    the parliament. The king never held a bed of justice unless for affairs that
                    concerned the state, and then all the officers of parliament were clothed in
                    scarlet robes.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Bed</hi><hi rend="italic">of the Carriage of a Great
                    Gun,</hi> a thick plank that lies under the piece, forming, as it were, the body
                    <hi rend="italic">of</hi> the carriage.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bed,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Masonry,</hi> a course or
                    range of stones. The joint of the bed is the mortar between two stones placed
                    the one over the other.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Bed,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Gardening,</hi> a square or
                    oblong piece of ground in a garden raised a little above the level of the
                    adjoining ground, and either sown or planted.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Lords of the</hi><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Bed-</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">Chamber,</hi> in the British court, are twelve noblemen who attend
                    in turn, a month each, during which time they sleep in the king’s bed-chamber,
                    and wait on him when he dines in private. Their salary is considerable; and the
                    situation, though apparently a menial one, is eagerly Sought after, even by the
                    high nobility, from the access which it gives to the person of the
                    sovereign.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
