<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-5009-0438-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BATAVIA (7th edition, volume 4, page 438)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q815225">Trade</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jh3db66">Trades</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kp7tx0f">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48c9r41n">Arabs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49p2w64d">Barrows</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980104">Islands</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1134794">Streets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845230">Canals</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:812571">Arabism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204082">Japan</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193195009?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BATAVIA</label>, a large city and sea-port on the north coast
                    of the island of Java, and the capital of all the Dutch settlements in the East.
                    It is situated on the river Jacatra, in a swampy plain, at the bottom of a bay,
                    and has long been noted for the insalubrity of its atmosphere. This bay is
                    formed by an indentation in the northern shore of Java; and it is protected from
                    the swell of the sea by fifteen or sixteen small islands, interspersed in every
                    direction across its mouth. It is of sufficient capacity to contain the whole
                    navy of England, and is perfectly secure at all seasons, the w ater being seldom
                    disturbed in any violent degree by the winds. The form of the city is an oblong
                    square, 4200 feet in length from north to south, and 3000 feet in breadth. The
                    streets are quite straight and regular, and cross each other at right angles.
                    Each street is from 114 to 204 feet broad, and has a canal in the middle, cased
                    with stone, with a low parapet on the two margins. At the distance of six feet
                    is planted a row of evergreen trees, under the shade of which are erected little
                    open pavilions of wood, surrounded with seats, on which the Dutch inhabitants,
                    in the cool of the evening, take their favourite refreshment of smoking. Beyond
                    the trees is a gravelled road from thirty to sixty feet wide, for carriages,
                    horses, cattle, and slaves, and terminated on the opposite side by a row of
                    evergreens. Batavia contains about twenty such streets, with canals in the
                    middle, over which there are about thirty stone bridges. The river Jacatra,
                    which has its rise in the Blue Mountains to the south, flows through the middle
                    of the town, and encircles it by several branches and canals connected with the
                    main stream. Numerous other streams, such as the Ankee and the Tangerang,
                    &amp;c., besides artificial canals, intersect the swampy plain of Batavia in all
                    directions, and connect the town with the surrounding country.</p>
                <p>According to Sir Stamford Raffles, in his account of Java, there are now scarcely
                    any remains of the splendour and magnificence which formerly procured for this
                    capital the proud title of the Queen of the East. “Streets,” he adds, “have been
                    pulled down, canals half filled up, forts demolished, and palaces levelled with
                    the dust.” The public buildings consist of a Lutheran and a Portuguese church, a
                    Mahommedan mosque, a Chinese temple, the stadthouse, where the supreme court of
                    justice and magistracy still assemble, the infirmary, the chamber of orphans,
                    and other institutions of less consequence. The great church of Batavia, which
                    was finished in 1760, at an expense of L.80,000, was taken down in consequence
                    of its foundation having given way, by order of General Daendels, who was
                    governor of Java after Holland was incorporated with France. The market is
                    convenient and extensive, and is well supplied with provisions of all sorts. The
                    fortifications by which the city was formerly surrounded, consisting of a wall
                    defended by bastions, were all pulled down before Batavia was captured by the
                    British in 1811. General Daendels directed the demolition of the ramparts, with
                    a view of improving the health of the city by a freer circulation of air; and
                    with the materials he built the new cantonment of Weltevreeden, about three
                    miles inland, in a higher and more healthy situation. The castle of Batavia,
                    which is on the north side of the town, next to the bay, is very spacious, and
                    contains numerous buildings and extensive warehouses, constructed with
                    prodigious labour and expense; but its situation is so unhealthy, that the
                    troops were withdrawn to another place, and it was converted into a depot for
                    naval and military stores and other articles. The town of Batavia, owing to its
                    unhealthiness, has been deserted by all the most wealthy inhabitants, who now
                    live in the environs, principally on two roads leading to Weltevreeden; the one
                    east, the other west, through Molenvliet and Ryswick. These elegant roads,
                    shaded with rows of trees, and having on each side sumptuous houses surrounded
                    with fine gardens and plantations, form the fashionable resort at Batavia. Here
                    are situated some of the public buildings of the town, namely, the grand
                    assembly-room, used by government on great occasions; also a large building,
                    which contains the treasury and all the other public offices. The environs are
                    adorned with the country residences of the opulent merchants, which extend east
                    and west, and on the south are scattered over a distance of between forty and
                    fifty miles inland.</p>
                <p>Batavia, being a great trading city, is resorted to by many different nations in
                    the East; and its population consists of a mixture of all these, as well as of
                    Europeans. The inhabitants may be divided into the following classes; namely,
                    the Dutch residents, who form buta small class, and can hardly be termed
                    European, so completely are they intermixed with Portuguese and Malay colonists;
                    the different Indian nations, originally slaves; the Moors and Arabs, an active
                    and intelligent race, principally engaged in navigation; the Javanese, who are
                    cultivators; the natives of Bali, of Celebes, Borneo, Macassar, Amboyna, and
                    Madura. The Malays are numerous; they are chiefly boatmen and navigators, and
                    profess the Mahommedan faith. The Chinese form the most numerous class in
                    Batavia. They are here, as everywhere else, ingenious, industrious, and
                    mercantile in their habits. Their sole object is to make money, in which they
                    are indefatigable. They have many of them acquired large capitals; and their
                    industry embraces the whole system of commerce, from the greatest wholesale
                    speculations to the most minute transactions in the retail trade. In their hands
                    are all the manufactories, distilleries, potteries, &amp;c.; they have large
                    coffee and sugar plantations, and gardens well stocked with all sorts of
                    vegetables; and they are the principal traders, smiths, carpenters,
                    stone-masons, shoemakers, shopkeepers, butchers, &amp;c. in the country. But
                    though they form so useful a class in Batavia, they have always been severely
                    oppressed by the tyrannical and arbitrary exactions of the Dutch government. All
                    their religious festivals, every public ceremony and popular amusement, as well
                    as every branch of industry, were subjected to taxation. They were obliged to
                    pay for a license to wear their hair in a long plaited tail, according to the
                    custom ol their country, as well as for permission to bring their greens to
                    market, and to sell their produce and manufactures in the streets. A better
                    system was introduced under the British administration of Sir Stamford Raffles;
                    but the island has since been restored to the Dutch, who have not abandoned
                    their former narrow and severe policy. The following is an estimate of the
                    population made by Barrow in 1792, from a register of the dwelling-houses m the
                    city.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193195022?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-5022-0439"/>
                <table>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> East India Company s servants of every
                            des&lt; </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 2∏p- </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> tion, with their families </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 3,300 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Burghers or free citizens, with their
                            families.. </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 5,660 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Javanese and free Malays </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 68,000 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 22,000 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 17,000 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 115,960 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> From this period the population of
                            Batavia, </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> as of other </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> districts of the country, has fallen
                            off under the tyrannical </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> administration of the Dutch; and the
                            following account </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> of the population of Batavia and its
                            environs is </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> given from </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> authentic documents by Sir Stamford
                            Raffles<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Sir
                            Stamford Raffles’s <hi rend="italic">History of Java,</hi> vol. ii.
                            Appendix, p. 10.</p></note>: </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> — </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> City of Batavia—Europeans </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 1,928 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Natives </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 6,486 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Chinese </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 11,854 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="2" role="data" rows="1"> Malays, Bugis, and other eastern
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> nations; </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 12,173 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Arabs and Moors </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 403 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> Slaves </cell>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 14,239 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row cols="1" role="data" rows="1">
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"/>
                        <cell cols="1" role="data" rows="1"> 47.083 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>The environs of Batavia he estimates to contain 218,777. Batavia is perhaps one
                    of the most unhealthy spots in the whole earth: and this is not owing altogether
                    to the climate, which is not so hot as in other tropical countries; the
                    thermometer varying in the middle of the day from 84° to 86°, though it
                    sometimes rises to 96°, and sinking during the night to 76°, and the breeze from
                    the sea regularly setting in as the day advances. It is occasioned, lsř, by the
                    situation of the town, in a marshy plain, the exhalations from which settle over
                    it in calm weather, and descend with the dews at night, or are circulated
                    through it both by the sea and the land breeze; <hi rend="italic">2dly,</hi> by
                    the stagnant water in the canals or ditches, which intersect the city in all
                    directions. These canals are a receptacle for filth of every description, and
                    having no current to carry it off, the action of a tropical sun on such a mass
                    of putrefying matter engenders the most pestilential vapours, the sure source of
                    disease. The other causes are the close plantations of trees, that prevent a
                    free circulation of air; the stagnation of the rivers from the bars of mud or
                    sand which obstruct their passage into the sca; the bad water used by the
                    inhabitants; the narrowness of their houses J the extreme filthiness of their
                    habits; and the luxury and intemperance of the richer classes. The most common
                    and the most fatal maladies are dysenteries, and putrid and inflammatory fevers,
                    which frequently prove fatal in the course of a few days, and sometimes in a few
                    hours. At Weltevreeden, not more than three miles distant, diseases are not more
                    frequent than in the healthiest parts of India.</p>
                <p>Batavia is a great commercial depot, and is resorted to by vessels from all the
                    Asiatic islands, as well as from China, the East Indies, and Europe. It's trade
                    was indeed heavily oppressed by the restrictions of the Dutch East India
                    Company, who claimed the monopoly or preemption of almost all the staple
                    articles of commerce; and who further restricted by their regulations the
                    freedom of navigation. A greater latitude was allowed under the French
                    regulations of General Daendels, though it was still sufficiently severe; and
                    when Batavia was captured by the British in 1811, the trade was set free from
                    the: <hi rend="superscript"> la</hi> ckles which had been imposed on it, and it
                    accordingly began to flourish. In 1812 the quantity of shipping that cleared out
                    from Batavia amounted to 52,375 tons; m 1813 it had increased to 64,306 tons;
                    and in 1814 to 72,718 tons.</p>
                <p>The exports from Batavia to the other islands of the archipelago, and to the
                    ports in the Malayan peninsula, are rice, salt, oil, tobacco, teak timber and
                    planks, Java cloths, brass ware, &amp;c., and European, Indian, and Chi- , nese
                    goods. The produce of the eastern islands is also collected at its ports for
                    re-exportation to India, China, and Europe; namely, gold-dust, diamonds,
                    camphor, benjamin, and other drugs; edible bird-nests, biche dc mer, rattans,
                    bees’ wax, tortoise-shell, and dyeing woods from Borneo and Sumatra; tin from
                    Banca; spices from the Moluccas; fine cloths from Celebes and Bali; and pepper
                    from Borneo. From Bengal are imported opium, drugs, and cloths; from China,
                    teas, raw silk, silk piece-goods, varnished umbrellas, coarse China ware,
                    nankeen, paper, and innumerable smaller articles for the Chinese settlers. Of
                    late, however, the Chinese have been superseded by the introduction of British
                    manufactures. A trade is also carried on with Japan, to which a ship is annually
                    sent laden with cloths, spices, elephants’ teeth, wood, tin, tortoise-shell,
                    &amp;c.; and the return is chiefly made in fine copper, China ware, lackered
                    ware, and silk goods.</p>
                <p>Batavia owes its origin to the Dutch general John Pieterson Coen, who, in 1619,
                    took the town of Jacatra by assault, destroyed it, and founded in its stead the
                    present city, which soon acquired a flourishing trade, and increased in extent
                    and importance. The Dutch enjoyed unmolested possession of this place until the
                    year 1811, when the states of Holland having been incorporated with France, a
                    British armament was sent against the Dutch settlements in Java, and to this
                    force the city of Batavia surrendered on the 8th of August. Batavia was restored
                    to the Dutch by the treaty of 1814. Long. 106. 51. E. Lat. 6. 10. S.</p>
                <p>See Stavorinus’s <hi rend="italic">Voyages to the East Indies;</hi> Barrow’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Voyage to Cochin China;</hi> Sir George Staunton’s <hi
                    rend="italic">Embassy to China;</hi> Thorn’s <hi rend="italic">Memoir of the
                    Conquest of Java;</hi> Sir Stamford Raffles’s <hi rend="italic">History of
                    Java.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(f.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
