<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-9676-0797-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BORDA, John Charles (7th edition, volume 4, page
                    797)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term ref="fast:835818">Bombings</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1047359">Order</term>
                    <term ref="fast:928067">Fluids</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1158235">Truth</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4p84454w">Wheels</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2th4x">Resultants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w38662">Fluids</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210572">Iceland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204558">Denmark</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193199676?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BORDA, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Charles</hi></label>, a
                    mathematician and nautical astronomer, celebrated for his improvements in the
                    theory of hydraulics and pneumatics, and in the construction of instruments for
                    observation. He was born at Drax, on the 4th of May 1733, and was originally
                    destined for the bar; but abandoned the pursuit of the law in favour of a
                    military life, which he considered as better calculated to afford him
                    opportunities for the cultivation of his mathematical talents, and for the
                    application of the results of his studies to practice. His acquirements in
                    science had very early attracted the attention of D’Alembert, who predicted his
                    future eminence, and warmly recommended his turning his thoughts to the
                    occupation of a place in the academy. He obtained a commission in the light
                    cavalry, and was appointed teacher of mathematics to the corps; and, in 1756, he
                    presented to the Academy of Sciences (A) <hi rend="italic">A Memoir on the Paths
                    of Bombs,</hi> which was ordered to be printed in the collection of the <hi
                    rend="italic">Savans Etrangers,</hi> but which has not excited much attention.
                    He was elected in the same year a member of the academy; and in the next he was
                    present at the battle of Hastinbeck, in the capacity of aid-de-camp to the
                    celebrated General</p>
                <p>Maĩllebois, to whom he looked up as a great master in the art of war.</p>
                <p>He was afterwards admitted into the corps of engineers, without the usual form of
                    examination into his qualifications; and being stationed at a sea-port, the
                    occurrences of the place naturally directed his attention anew to the phenomena
                    of the resistance of fluids. He published, in 1763, a detailed memoir on this
                    subject (B. <hi rend="italic">Mem. Ac. Par.</hi> 1763, p. 358), in which he
                    relates a variety of experiments, showing that the resistance of the air is
                    actually proportional to the square of the velocity, as had commonly been
                    supposed from theoretical considerations. He also determines, by other
                    experiments, the magnitude of the resistance to the motion of a sphere, and
                    proves that nothing can be more erroneous than the supposition that the
                    resistance to an oblique surface decreases as the square of the sine of the
                    angle of incidence. He also finds, that the resistance to the motion of a cube,
                    in the directions of the diagonal of its base and of one of the sides, are as 21
                    to 16, while the calculations of former theorists had made the resistance
                    greatest in the direction of the side.</p>
                <p>In 1766 he published an Essay on the discharge of fluids through the orifices of
                    vessels (C. <hi rend="italic">Mem. Ac. Par.</hi> 1766, p. 579), in which he
                    first states the objections to considering the different strata of a fluid as
                    descending in all cases very nearly in parallel directions; he examines the
                    contraction of the jet after its escape from the orifice, and determines some of
                    the effects of abrupt changes in the velocity of the fluid passing through pipes
                    or apertures of different forms.</p>
                <p>He contributed, in 1767, to the publications of the academy, an important <hi
                    rend="italic">Memoir on Water Wheels</hi> (D. p. 270), which has escaped the
                    notice of his able biographer Μ. Lacroix. He observes, in this paper, that the
                    simple hypothesis of a resistance varying as the square of the velocity, which
                    is so near the truth in common cases, where a number of particles, proportional
                    to the velocity, strikes, in a given time, upon a small exposed surface with a
                    force also proportional to the velocity, is totally inapplicable to the action
                    of a confined stream upon the floatboards of a wheel, since in this instance,
                    the number of particles concerned cannot vary materially with the velocity, the
                    whole stream being supposed to operate in all cases upon the successive
                    floatboards; so that the analogy would require us to suppose the force in this
                    case nearly proportional to the simple relative velocity; a conclusion whiclι
                    agrees remarkably well with the experiments of some practical authors.</p>
                <p>The same volume contains a continuation of Μ. Borda’s researches relating to the
                    resistance of oblique surfaces (E. <hi rend="italic">Mem. Ac. Par.</hi> 1767, p.
                    495), with a statement of experiments still more conclusively confuting the
                    received hypothesis respecting oblique impulse than his former investigations
                    had done. We also find in it an Essay on isoperimetrical problems (F. p. 551),
                    in which it is shown that Euler’s method of treating them, which had been in
                    great measure abandoned by its equally profound and candid author, in favour of
                    the more general and more elegant calculations of Lagrange, was still capable of
                    affording all the results that had been derived from the method of variations;
                    and he even pointed out some deficiencies in the first memoir of Lagrange, which
                    contained the detail of his ingenious invention. These investigations of Μ.
                    Borda afford collateral evidence of the strict truth of the demonstrations of
                    both his great predecessors; and though they have been little employed by later
                    mathematicians, yet it must be admitted to be of some importance, in enabling us
                    to appreciate the value of a new mode of calculation, to determine whether its
                    results are or are not such as might be obtained with almost equal convenience
                    by methods before in use.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193199689?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-9689-0798"/>
                <p>His memoir, inserted in the collection of the Academy for 1768 (G. <hi
                    rend="italic">Mem. Ac. Par.</hi> 1768, p. 18), is devoted exclusively to the
                    theory of pumps; and he considers especially the effect of the passage of the
                    fluid through valves and other contracted parts in diminishing the quantity of
                    the discharge. His results are derived from the principle of the preservation of
                    the living force or energy of a system of bodies, throughout all the
                    vicissitudes of its motions, which had before been employed with success by
                    Daniel Bernoulli in problems of a similar nature; but it was not until the
                    experiments of Buat had afforded sufficient grounds for the determination of the
                    friction of fluids, that cases of this kind could be submitted to exact
                    calculation.</p>
                <p>In his Essay on the curve described by cannon-balls, published among the Memoirs
                    for 1769 (H. <hi rend="italic">Mem. Ac. Par.</hi> 1769, p. 247), he has greatly
                    simplified the practical theory of projectiles, which had been treated in a
                    satisfactory though very general manner by John Bernoulli, and had been reduced
                    into a much more convenient form by Euler. Μ. Borda has substituted some
                    approximate expressions for the true value of the density of the air, and has
                    thus been enabled to integrate equations which, in their more strictly correct
                    form, had resisted the powers of Euler himself; and he has justified the
                    adoption of the formulas thus obtained by a comparison with experiment.</p>
                <p>In the mean time his talents were very actively employed in the naval service of
                    his country, which he entered in 1767, by the nomination of Μ. Praslin. The
                    time-keepers of Le Roy and Berthoud were beginning to rival those of the English
                    artists, and the French government ordered several vessels to be fitted out for
                    cruises, in order to examine the accuracy of these time-keepers. Μ. Borda was
                    appointed a lieutenant on board of the <hi rend="italic">Florc,</hi> and acted
                    jointly with Μ. Pingré as a delegate of the Academy of Sciences for the purposes
                    of the expedition. The voyage occupied about a year, and extended to the
                    Canaries, the West Indies, Newfoundland, Iceland, and Denmark. Μ. Borda had a
                    considerable share in the account which was published of the observations; and
                    the formula which he has here given for the correction of the effects of
                    refraction and parallax is considered as equally elegant and convenient. He also
                    presented to the academy a separate memoir on the results of the expedition. (I.
                    <hi rend="italic">Voyage pour éprouver les Montres de Le Poy.</hi> 4. Paris. K.
                    <hi rend="italic">Mem. Ac. Par.</hi> 1773, p. 258.) After an interval of six
                    weeks, these watches were found capable of determining the longitude within
                    about fifteen minutes of the truth.</p>
                <p>In order to supply some deficiencies in the observations made at the Canaries,
                    Borda was sent out a second time, with the <hi rend="italic">Boussole</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Espiègle;</hi> and he published, after his return (L.), a
                    very correct and highly finished map of these islands. He was soon afterwards
                    promoted to the rank of captain, and served under the Count d’Estaing as a
                    major-general, an appointment nearly similar to that of our captains of the
                    fleet. In this capacity he observed the inconvenience of too great a variety in
                    the sizes of the vessels constituting a fleet, and proposed to abolish the class
                    of fifty and of sixty-four gun ships, as too small for the line of battle, and
                    to build ships of three rates only, the lowest carrying seventy-four guns, so
                    that a smaller quantity of stores should require to be kept ready for use in the
                    dock-yards, than when ships of more various dimensions were to be refitted. In
                    1780 he had the command of the <hi rend="italic">Guerrier,</hi> and in 1781 of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Solitaire,</hi> which was taken after a gallant resistance
                    by an English squadron. He was thus compelled to pay a visit to Great Britain,
                    but was immediately set at liberty upon his parole.</p>
                <p>He proposed to the academy in this year (Μ. <hi rend="italic">Mem. Ac. Par.</hi>
                    1781), a mode of regulating elections, which was adopted by that body. Its
                    peculiarity consisted in having the names of the candidates arranged by each
                    voter in a certain order, and collecting the numbers expressing the degrees of
                    preference into separate results, so that the simple majority of voters did not
                    necessarily establish the claim of any individual, if he was placed very low in
                    the list by any considerable number of those who voted against him. But it must
                    be allowed that this mode of election is by no means wholly unobjectionable.</p>
                <p>Μ. Borda appears to have rendered an essential service to the cultivators o*f
                    practical astronomy by the introduction and improvement of the repeating circle,
                    although this instrument has probably been less employed in Great Britain than
                    elsewhere, on account of the greater perfection of those which were previously
                    in common use. It had been suggested by Mayer in 1767, that a circle with two
                    movable sights would enable us to observe a given angle a great number of times
                    in succession, and to add together the results, without any error in reading
                    them off, and thus to obtain a degree of precision equal to that of much larger
                    and better instruments of a different construction; but the proposal had been
                    little noticed until ten years afterwards, when Borda pursued the path pointed
                    out by Mayer, and trained Lenoir, then a young and unlicensed artist, to the
                    execution of the improved instrument, notwithstanding the opposition of the
                    rival opticians, and the want of encouragement from the opulent public. He
                    published in 1787 (N.) his <hi rend="italic">Description and Use of the
                    Reflecting Circle, with different Methods for Calculating the Principal
                    Observations of Nautical Astronomy;</hi> but the officers of the French navy,
                    for whom this work was intended, appear to have profited but little by his
                    instructions. His instrument was, however, much employed in the operations for
                    determining the length of the terrestrial meridian; and he himself took charge
                    of the experiments required for ascertaining the length of the pendulum, and for
                    the comparison of the different standards with each other. Hc invented some very
                    ingenious methods of overcoming the difficulties which present themselves in the
                    pursuit of these objects; but he was interrupted in his researches by the
                    horrors of the Revolution, nor did he live to see the whole of the operations
                    completed. He endeavoured, also, to promote the introduction of the new mode of
                    subdividing the circle, by the laborious computation of <hi rend="italic">Tables
                    of Logarithms</hi> (O. 4to, <hi rend="italic">Par.</hi> 1801) adapted to decimal
                    parts of the quadrant; a work in which he was assisted by Μ. Delambre. From the
                    increasing indisposition of Μ. Callet, who had undertaken to correct the proofs
                    of these tables, some very material errors had been committed in the first half
                    of the tables, and Μ. Borda thought it necessary to cancel a great number of the
                    pages; and in order to meet the expense thus entailed on him, he was obliged to
                    dispose of an estate which he had lately acquired in his native place. He was
                    also engaged, towards the close of his life, in the measurement of the force of
                    magnetism, and in the calculations of astronomical refraction. His health had
                    been threatened for several successive winters, and he died the 10th of March
                    1799.</p>
                <p>In his manners he was animated and unaffected. He avoided those who sought his
                    acquaintance merely from the vanity of being intimate with a man of talents,
                    whatever pretensions to importance they might derive from their casual relations
                    to general society. He never married; and he was too much absorbed in the
                    pursuit of science to associate with a very extensive circle even of private
                    friends. Though not a man of learning, he was not deficient in literary taste;
                    and he was, in particular, a passionate admirer of Homer. He seems to have
                    possessed a considerable share of that natural tact and sagacity which was so
                    remarkable in Newton, and which we also <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193199702?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-9702-0799"/> discover in
                    the works of Daniel Bernoulli; enabling them, like a sort of instinct, to elude
                    the insurmountable difficulties with which direct investigations are often
                    encumbered; while Euler, on the contrary, as M. Lacroix most truly observes,
                    seems to have taken pleasure in searching for matter which would give scope to
                    his analytical ingenuity, although wholly foreign to the physical investigations
                    which had first led him to the difficulties in question. It would have been
                    fortunate for the progress of science, if some of the most celebrated of Μ.
                    Borda’s countrymen had profited by his example, in studying to attain that
                    unostentatious simplicity which is the last result of the highest cultivation.
                    (Lacroix,in <hi rend="italic">Rapport des Travaux de la Société
                    Philomathique,</hi> vol. iv. 8. Par. 1800). <hi rend="smallcaps">(l.
                    l.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
