<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0704-6907-0584-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">BERKELEY, George (7th edition, volume 4, page
                    584)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1140317">Swifts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1071262">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94g8x">Religion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4th8bn4t">Religions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4st7dw9m">Popes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193196907?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">BERKELEY, <hi rend="smallcaps">George</hi></label>, the
                    celebrated bishop of Cloyne, was the eldest son of William Berkeley, Esq. of
                    Thomas-town, in the county of Kilkenny, a cadet of the family of Earl Berkeley
                    of Berkeley Castle. At eight years of age he was sent to the school of the
                    Ormond foundation at Kilkenny, from which Swift had a few years before been
                    removed to the university. Before Berkeley had attained his fourteenth year he
                    was admitted a pensioner in Trinity College, Dublin, in which, whilst bachelor
                    of arts, he obtained a fellowship. Some of his first essays as a writer were
                    published in the Spectator and Guardian, which entertaining works he adorned
                    with many pieces in favour of virtue and religion. His learning and his virtues,
                    his wit and agreeable conversation, made his friendship sought and his
                    acquaintance cultivated by many great and learned men; and amongst others by the
                    Earl of Peterborough, Dr Swift, Dr Arbuthnot, Mr Pope, and Mr Addison. The earl
                    took him as chaplain and secretary of legation into Italy; and during his
                    absence on that occasion he became senior fellow of his college, and was in 1717
                    created D. D. by diploma.</p>
                <p>Upon his return, his acquaintance among the great was considerably extended; and
                    Lord Burlington, who at Rome had conceived a high esteem for him on account of
                    his skill in architecture, obtained for him, through the Duke of Grafton, then
                    (1721) lord-lieutenant of Ireland, the king’s grant of the deanery of Down,
                    worth L.2000 per annum. Such, however, was the narrow system of politics at that
                    time prevalent in the Irish cabinet, that though his majesty had actually signed
                    the grant, the lords justices recommended <hi rend="italic">bach</hi> for this
                    preferment Swift’s Dean Daniel, celebrated for having in a state sermon styled
                    Pompey an unfortunate gentleman ;” and such was Dr Berkeley s humility and
                    mildness of temper, that he could not be prevailed upon to dispute the matter,
                    or even to expostulate on. the subject. His patron Lord Burlington procured for
                    him afterwards (1724) the deanery of Derry, the next best in Ireland to that of
                    Down; and upon this preferment the doctor resigned his fellowship.</p>
                <p>In the year 1722 his fortune received a considerable increase from an event by
                    him very unexpected. Upon his first going to London (1717), he sent one morning
                    <hi rend="subscript"> a</hi> note to Swift, desiring that they might dine
                    together that day at a tavern. The dean of St Patrick’s returned for answer,
                    that they might enjoy each other’s company at their ease where he was himself
                    engaged to dine, with the family of Mrs Esther Vanhomrigh, the celebrated
                    Vanessa"· and thither accordingly he took Mr Berkeley. Some years before her
                    death this lady removed to Ireland, and fixed her residence at Cell-bridge, a
                    pleasant village in the neighbourhood of Dublin, most probably with the view of
                    frequently enjoying the company of a man for whom she had conceived a very
                    singular attachment. But finding herself totally disappointed in that
                    expectation, she altered her intention of making the dean of St Patrick’s her
                    heir, and left the whole of her fortune, about L.8000, to be divided equally
                    between her near relation Judge Marshal of the Common Pleas in Ireland, and Dr
                    Berkeley, whom she had never seen but once in her life, and that at the distance
                    of nine years.</p>
                <p>In the interval between Dr Berkeley’s return from abroad and his preferment to
                    the deanery of Derry, his mind had been employed in conceiving a noble and
                    benevolent plan for the better supplying of the churches in our foreign
                    plantations, and for converting the savage Americans to Christianity, by
                    erecting a college in the Bermudas. To this proposal the address and abilities
                    of its author procured, after a tedious attendance on the great, an apparently
                    successful reception; for he obtained a charter for its foundation, together
                    with a parliamentary grant of L.20,000 for carrying it into execution, to which
                    were added several large subscriptions from individuals, to be paid as soon as
                    the public bounty should be received. Upon the faith of this our philosopher
                    embarked for America; where he became so generally and so justly venerated by
                    all descriptions of men, that they vied with one another who should most honour
                    him. The queen, with whom he was a favourite, had endeavoured to dissuade him
                    from this enterprise, by offering him her interest for an English bishopric; but
                    he replied, that he should prefer the headship of St Paul’s College at Bermudas
                    to the primacy of all England. From that headship he was to enjoy a revenue of
                    L.100 per annum, and was bound by his charter to resign his deanery, then worth
                    L.1100 per annum, within a year and a half after the L.20,000 should be paid by
                    government. But that sum was never paid; and after two years’ residence on Rhode
                    Island and its neighbouring continent, during which time every interest of piety
                    and virtue was near his heart and cultivated by his labours, the dean was
                    obliged to return to Europe, and abandon one of the noblest designs that had
                    ever entered into the human heart to form.</p>
                <p>In August 1728, immediately before his departure for America, he entered into
                    marriage with Anne, the eldest daughter of the Right Honourable John Forster,
                    speaker of the Irish house of commons; this lady died in 1785. In May 1734 he
                    was consecrated bishop of Cloyne, and vacated his deanery. On that occasion he
                    said to his few intimates, “I will never accept of a translation.” At Cloyne he
                    distinguished himself by pastoral vigilance, prelatical hospitality, and
                    constant residence. Throughout the whole of his clerical life he was, while his
                    health permitted, a constant and an extemporaneous preacher; nor is it known
                    that he ever reduced a single sermon to writing, except one preached before the
                    society for propagating the gospeI in foreign parts, which at their request was
                    published. He endeared himself to the people of his diocese by promoting at once
                    their temporal and their spiritual happiness. He endeavoured by all means to
                    raise a spirit of industry, and to encourage the improvement<pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193196920?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0704-6920-0585"/> of agriculture
                    in that neglected country; and it may be truly said, that never man laboured
                    more earnestly to amass a fortune or to aggrandize a family, than he did to
                    promote the best interests of mankind, considered either as citizens of earth or
                    as candidates for heaven.</p>
                <p>The earl of Chesterfield, who had never seen him but once, and that when they
                    were both young men, on being made lord-lieutenant of Ireland, sent to him a
                    most respectful offer of the then vacant see of Clogher, which was more than
                    double the value of that of Cloyne; promising at the same time his
                    recommendation to any other richer see that might be vacated during his
                    administration. But the good bishop declined the generous offer, requesting the
                    lordlieutenant not to think of him on any other vacancy, as he was resolved
                    never to quit his first bishopric for any other. In 1751, finding the
                    infirmities of age come upon him, and wishing to retire from the care of his
                    diocese to superintend the education of his son, then nominated a student of
                    Christ Church, that the revenues of the church might not be misapplied, nor the
                    interests of religion suffer by the absence of the pastor from his flock, fie
                    made great interest for leave to resign his bishopric, of which the income was
                    then not less than L.1700 per annum. Failing of success in this application, he
                    let the lands of his demesne at Cloyne on very easy terms, at the rent of L.200,
                    which he directed to be distributed annually among the poor house-keepers of
                    Cloyne, Youghall, and Aghadda, until his return.</p>
                <p>At Oxford he lived highly respected by the learned members of that great
                    university, till the hand of Providence unexpectedly deprived them of the
                    pleasure and advantage derived from his residence among them. On Sunday evening,
                    the 14th January 1753, as he was sitting in the midst of his family, and just
                    after he had concluded an extemporaneous comment on the 15th chapter of first
                    Corinthians, he was instantly translated, without a groan, from earth to heaven.
                    A polypus in the heart was the cause of his dissolution. About a minute before
                    his death he had seated himself on a couch and turned his face towards the wall;
                    and had he not ceased speaking in the middle of a sentence, his lady and his son
                    would not immediately have discovered their loss. His remains were with much
                    funeral solemnity interred at Christ Church, his friend Bishop Conybeare, then
                    dean of that cathedral, performing the last service. An elegant marble monument,
                    with a spirited inscription by the archbishop of York, marks the spot where his
                    ashes rest. As to his person, he was of the tall middle size; his countenance
                    was very handsome, and full of meaning and benignity; and his bodily strength
                    was uncommonly great, even to the last year of his life; but he was subject to
                    grievous nervous colics, in which he thought tar-water gave him more efficacious
                    relief than any other medicine. Mr Pope sums up his character in one line. After
                    mentioning some particular virtues which characterized other prelates then
                    liv-mg, he ascribes “to Berkeley every virtue under heaven.” <hi
                    rend="subscript"> t</hi> ^1he following anecdote will serve to convey an
                    impression both of his talents and character. Bishop Atterbury, having heard
                    much of Mr Berkeley, wished to see him. Accordingly he was one day introduced to
                    that prelate by the Earl of Berkeley. After some time, Mr Berkeley quitted the
                    room; on which Lord Berkeley said to the bishop, “Does my cousin answer your
                    lordship’s expectations?” The bishop, lifting up his hands in astonishment, <hi
                    rend="superscript"> r</hi> θplied, “So much understanding, so much knowledge, so
                    much innocence, and such humility, I did not think bad been the portion of any
                    but angels, till I saw this gentle- <hi rend="superscript"> n</hi><hi
                    rend="subscript"> 1</hi> * <hi rend="superscript"> an</hi> ∙ . His knowledge is
                    said to have extended even to the minutest objects, and included the arts and
                    business <hi rend="superscript"> 0 c</hi> °mmon life. Thus Dr Blackwell, in his
                    <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of</hi><hi rend="italic">the Court of Augustus,</hi>
                    having made an observation, “that the ingenious mechanics, the workers in stone
                    and metal, and improvers in trade, agriculture, and navigation, ought to be
                    searched out and conversed with no less than the professors of speculative
                    science,” adds the following eulogium on our prelate: “In this respect I would
                    with pleasure do justice to the memory of a very great though singular sort of a
                    man, Dr Berkeley, better known as a philosopher and intended founder of an
                    university in the Bermudas or Summer Islands, than as bishop of Cloyne in
                    Ireland. An inclination to carry me out on that expedition, as one of the young
                    professors on his new foundation, having brought us often together, I scarce
                    remember to have conversed with him on that art, liberal or mechanic, of which
                    he knew not more than the ordinary practitioners. With the widest views, he
                    descended into a minute detail, and grudged neither pains nor expense for the
                    means of information. He travelled through a great part of Sicily on foot;
                    clambered over the mountains and crept into the caverns, to investigate its
                    natural history, and discover the cause of its volcanoes: and I have known him
                    sit for hours in forgeries and founderies to inspect their successive
                    operations. I enter not into his peculiarities, either religious or personal;
                    but admire the extensive genius of the man, and think it a loss to the western
                    world that his noble and exalted plan of an American university was not carried
                    into execution. Many such spirits in our country would quickly make learning
                    wear another face.”</p>
                <p>He published many ingenious works, particularly An Essay towards a new Theory of
                    Vision; The Principles of Human Knowledge, the singular notions in ½+ich gave
                    rise to much controversy; Alciphron, or the Minute Philosopher, one of the most
                    elegant and learned defences of that religion which he was born to vindicate
                    both by his virtues and his ingenuity; The Analyst, in which he endeavours to
                    show that Sir Isaac Newton’s doctrine of fluxions is more incomprehensible than
                    any mystery in the Christian religion; The Querist, in which the true interests
                    of Ireland are pointed out in a very striking light; and Siris, or a Treatise on
                    Tar-Water, which, under his sanction, became for a while a very popular
                    medicine. In the Gentleman’s Magazine for January 1777, it is said that the <hi
                    rend="italic">Adventures of Signior Gaudentio di Lucca</hi> have been generally
                    attributed to Bishop Berkeley; but it is now understood that they were not the
                    offspring of his pen. The bishop never saw the work till it was put into his
                    hands by his son; and when he read it, he expressed no small contempt for the
                    style of a writer who describes his hero as a “tall, clean-made gentleman ;”
                    though he owned his fancy to be often brilliant. The adventures of Gaudentio di
                    Lucca are believed to have been written by a Romish priest, for his amusement,
                    when a prisoner in the Tower of London.</p>
                <p>Of Berkeley’s metaphysical notions, or of that idealism which he propounded with
                    the view of rooting out infidelity, and which Mr Hume afterwards employed to
                    destroy all belief, it is unnecessary to say thing in this place, as the subject
                    has been treated with surpassing ability, eloquence, and ingenuity, in the first
                    Dissertation prefixed to this work, to which, accordingly, the reader is
                    referred.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Berkeley,</hi> a market-town of the hundred of Berkeley, in
                    the county of Gloucester, 113 miles from London, on the river Little Avon, in
                    one of the richest dairy districts of England. It gives title to the ancient
                    family òf this name, whose magnificent castle here has been long celebrated in
                    English history. The inhabitants amounted in 1801 to 658, in 1811 to 716, and in
                    1821 to 836.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
