<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0713-1444-0003-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">LABRADOR (7th edition, volume 13, page 3)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1239786">America</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204310">Canada</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205290">Greenland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204270">Maine</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hq07">Esquimaux</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k06x193">Moravians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4j38kj6q">Canadians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qr4nq4d">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mw0m">Fish</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sb3x268">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4fq9qc3b">Oil</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926361">Fishes</term>
                    <term ref="fast:926650">Fishing</term>
                    <term ref="fast:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term ref="fast:933281">Founding</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1026120">Moravians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845200">Canadians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:845196">Canadianisms</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193201444?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">LABRADOR</label>, a vast region of North America, nearly of a
                    triangular shape, extending from the fiftieth to the sixty-first degree of north
                    latitude, and from fifty-six to seventyeight of west longitude. It is bounded ön
                    the south by Canada and the Gulf of St Lawrence, on the east by the Atlantic
                    Ocean, on the north by Hudson’s Straits, and on the west by Hudson’s Bay. Being
                    thus detached from the arctic lands, Labrador ought to partake in some degree of
                    the nature of the temperate cold regions; but, from causes which do not appear
                    to be very obvious, it is a country as frozen, desolate, and barren, as those to
                    the west of Hudson’s Bay. The coast along that spacious inland sea is called
                    East Main, and the climate there is peculiarly rigorous. The whole surface of
                    Labrador, indeed, is as sterile and naked as any part of the globe. The
                    prevailing features are rocks, swamps, and water; and vegetation appears as the
                    last effort of expiring naturel Small scraggy poplars, stunted firs, creeping
                    birch, and dwarf willows, thinly scattered in the southern parts, constitute the
                    whole of the trees; herbs and grass are also in sheltered places to be met with;
                    but in the most northerly parts only varieties of moss and lichens are to be
                    found. The whole of the interior, from the aspect of what has been explored, and
                    from the reports of the Esquimaux and other Indians, seems to be broken up with
                    rivers, lakes, and rocks. The geological features of the Labrador coast are as
                    follow:<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>For this account
                    of the geology of Labrador, we are indebted to ä paper by Captain II. Robinśon,
                    R. N. published in the Journal of the Royal Geographical Society of London, <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">1834.λ</hi><hi rend="subscript"> l</hi> m ülH J <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">j .</hi><hi rend="subscript smallcaps"> i</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> ,</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">∙ *</hi><hi
                    rend="superscript smallcaps"> i</hi></p></note> —The prevailing rock contiguous
                    to the sea shore is gneiss. On this, at L’Anse à Loup, the most fertile part of
                    the country, a bed of old red sandstone, about two hundred feet thick, is
                    superimposed, and extends about half a mile inland. Here also, as on every other
                    part of the coast visited by the individual from whom our information is
                    derived, the appearances of the cliffs and of the land near them, and the rolled
                    masses inland, which have evidently been exposed to the action of the sea, seem
                    to prove that the latter has considerably receded. The sandstone is generally
                    red and white in alternate strips, and presents a remarkable mural front to the
                    sea. Near the surface it was strongly marked with iron. The whole of the rock
                    was composed of white quartz and yellow felspar'; and the grains were generally
                    as fine as oatmeal, though occasionally coarser, even to the extent of half an
                    inch in diameter. Over the red sandstone was a thin stratum of red compact
                    felspar, containing vegetable impressions, and also horizontal. Above this were
                    varieties of secondary limestone arranged in parallel strata several’ feet thick
                    and full of shells. Detached masses of primitive limestone were also found; and,
                    a few miles from the shore, the secondary formations generally disappeared,
                    leaving gneiss and mica slate on the surface. North of Cape Charles, on the
                    Labrador coast, the land falls back to the westward, and the shore changes its
                    character, becoming shoal, and running off in flats; whereas to the southward it
                    is bold and abrupt. The prevailing rock, however, is still gneiss, containing
                    numerous veins of granite, from a few inches to many feet in thickness, the
                    constitüent parts being mica, quartz, and felspar. The diameter and dip of the
                    gneiss rock is here, as elsewhere on the coast, to the northwest, and at an
                    angle of nearly 65°. It is coarse and dark, hornblende taking the place of mica,
                    and frequently very light-grayish felspar forming the chief constituent. Where
                    this occurs, the face of the hill has a remarkably spotted appearance. On one of
                    the islands which here skirt the coast, a large bed of primitive greenstone was
                    found, forming a range of hills resting on the gneiss, and appearing to have the
                    same direction. On the western part of these islands also the gneiss gives place
                    to mica slate, this commencing beyond the above-mentioned range of greenstone,
                    which appears to mark the line of demarcation between them. The mica slate then
                    predominates through all the islands and shores examined to the westward of this
                    point, viz. to the Mealy Mountains, in Sandwich Bay, a distance of about
                    thirty-five miles. In some places crystals of garnet are very abundant in it,
                    and in others considerable beds of granite were found, of a confused appearance,
                    and in which quartz and felspar predominated. The Mealy Mountains are the
                    highest land on this coast, and were computed to be about 1484 feet in height,
                    covered nearly to the top with wood, notwithstanding the severity of the
                    climate. They are of mica slate, with a dark, finegrained formation of the same,
                    resembling basalt, at their base. The general rock is coarse-grained. At the
                    foot of these mountains were also found beds ’eight and ten feet thick, and
                    large.rolled masses of a remarkable conglomerate rock, of which the basis was
                    composed of grains of mica, quartz, and felspar; and the imbedded masses were
                    large rounded pebbles of quartz, mica slaté, felspar, hornblende, granite, and
                    grieiss. The whole was very hard, and elicited sparks of fire nndér the stroke
                    of the hammer. The imbedded fragn⅛ents were all water-worn.</p>
                <p>The general aspect of different parts of the Labrador coast has been described by
                    the Moravian missionaries, from whom we learn that NullatarIok Bay, iń 59° north
                    latitude, is surrounded by high mountains, which are covered with moss, alder,
                    birch, and various shrubs and plants, the valleys in July being grassy and
                    enamelled with a great variety of flowers. The rocks are slaty, easily splitting
                    into plates of from four to eight feet square. At Nachvâk Bay the sea was clear
                    oficė in the middle of July, and the magnificent mountains around afforded to
                    the missionaries a most enchanting prospect. Oppernavik, lying between the
                    sixtieth and sixty-first degrees of north latitude, iš not far distant from Cape
                    Chudleigh, where the coast, which was hitherto north, now trends to the
                    south-south-west, embosoming a‘ spacious expanse of water called Ungava Bay. The
                    river Kàn-gertluksoak, in latitude 58. 57. north, is about 140 miles
                    south-south-west of Cape Chuđleigb. The <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> estuary
                    of the Koksoak lies in 58. 36. north latitude, at the distance of about 650
                    miles from the Moravian station Okk <hi rend="superscript"> i</hi> ak, and is as
                    broad as the Thames at Gravesend. Up the river there is a bay surrounded on all
                    sides by gently rising ground, well wooded with trees of moderate size. <hi
                    rend="superscript"> 1</hi> For about half a mile a fine slope extends, bounded
                    on each extremity by a hill. The Moravians describe the land as level and dry,
                    watered by rivulets issuing from the <pb break="no"
                    facs="nls:193201457?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0713-1457-0004"/> woods, in
                    which were found various European plants and flowers, different kinds of shrubs,
                    such as junipers, currants, and the like, and grass and trees in abundance. The
                    missionaries were informed that, further west, no wood grows along the coast.
                    The soil at L’Anse à Loup is rich, and it is much the most eligible part of
                    Labrador for settlers. Corn will not ripen, but serves for green food; and
                    potatoes, cabbages, lettuce, spinach, and early Dutch turnips, do well. There is
                    generally much rain on the whole coast, but now the temperature would appear to
                    be more equable than it was some fifty years ago, if we may trust to the
                    correctness of the reports of navigators. The current always sets to the
                    southward along the coast. The tides rise six feet to the northward, and about
                    four to the southward. The prevailing winds are from west-south-west to
                    north-west. There is less fog than farther south; and the Straits of Belleisle,
                    which separate Newfoundland from Labrador and thb continent of America, are
                    never frozen over.</p>
                <p>On the coast of Labrador the winter is extremely severe, the thermometer often
                    falling thirty degrees below the freezing point; and although the houses of the
                    Moravian missionaries are heated by large cast-iron stoves, the windows and
                    walls are all the winter covered with ice, and the bed-clothes freeze to the
                    walls. Rum is frozen in the air as rapidly as water, and rectified spirits soon
                    become thick like oil. From December to June the sea is completely frozen over;
                    and so intense is the cold during the winter months, that travelling is
                    sometimes attended with the most painful consequences. The summer months, again,
                    are extremelyhot along the coast, the thermometer rising to eighty-six degrees
                    of Fahrenheit, when swarms of musquitoes infest the air. The climate, however,
                    is not insalubrious; and, notwithstanding all its disadvantages, Labrador is of
                    considerable importance to Great Britain. No country is better provided with
                    large, convenient, and safe harbours, or supplied with better water; and vast
                    multitudes of all those kinds of fish common to the arctic seas abound on the
                    coast. Herrings are very fine and plentiful in August, but there is no weather
                    to cure any kind of fish after the 10th of September. The rivers are frequented
                    by salmon and sea trout; and pike, barbel, eels, river trout, and the like, are
                    likewise found in them. On the numerous islands which are scattered along the
                    east coast, multitudes of eider-ducks and other water-fowl breed. Those of large
                    size have deer, foxes, and hares, upon them. On the continent the wild animals
                    are principally bears, wolves, foxes, and otters; beavers and deer are not
                    numerous, but their furs are remarkably close and beautiful. The birds of the
                    country are the white-tailed eagle, falcons, hawks, and owls of various kinds;
                    raven, white grouse, ptarmigan, spruce-game, whistling curlew, gray plover,
                    various kinds of sand-pipers and other waders; geese, ducks of various sorts,
                    shags, gulls, divers, and some few species of small birds. During the short
                    summer, insects are very numerous, especially in swampy places. In winter they
                    exist in a state of torpidity, from which they are aroused by the solar heat or
                    artificial warmth. The phenomenon of the aurora borealis is uncommonly brilliant
                    in this region, and exercises a very marked influence over the compass.</p>
                <p>The exports of Labrador consist of the products of the country, fish, oil, and
                    fur. During the fishing season, from 280 to 300 schooners proceed from
                    Newfoundland to the different fishing stations on the coast, where about 20,000
                    British subjects are employed for the season. About one third of these vessels
                    make two voyages, loaded with dry fish, back to Newfoundland, during the summer;
                    and several merchant vessels proceed from Labrador with their cargoes direct to
                    Europe, leaving generally full cargoes for the fishing vessels to carry to
                    Newfoundland. A considerable part of the fish of the second voyage is in a green
                    or pickled state, and dried afterwards at Newfoundland. Quebec sends eight or
                    nine vessels to the coast, manned with eighty or one hundred fishermen. Part of
                    the fish caught by them is sent to Europe, and the remainder is carried to
                    Quebec; besides which, they carry annually about L.6000 worth of furs, oil, and
                    salmon to Canada. From one hundred to one hundred and twenty vessels come from
                    Nova Scotia and New Brunswick. The principal part of their cargoes goes home in
                    a green state. From 16,000 to 18,000 seals are taken at Labrador in the
                    beginning of winter and spring. They are of a very large size, and the winter
                    residents on the coast are said to feast and fatten on their flesh, which, when
                    young, they account excellent eating. About 4000 of these seals are killed by
                    the Esquimaux. The whole number caught produce about 350 tons of oil, the value
                    of which may be about L.8000. One third of the resident inhabitants are British
                    servants, who take charge of the property left, and likewise employ themselves,
                    in the spring and fall, catching seals. The other two thirds live constantly at
                    Labrador, and act in the capacity of furriers and seal catchers on their own
                    account, but chiefly as the former during the winter; in summer all are engaged
                    in the fisheries. Half of these individuals are Jerseymen and Canadians, most of
                    whom have families. There are six or seven English houses, and four or five
                    Jersey houses, established at Labrador, unconnected with Newfoundland, who
                    export their oil and fish directly to Europe. The quantity exported to the
                    Mediterranean in 1830 was about</p>
                <p>50,000 quintals cod fish, at 10s L.25,000</p>
                <p>900 tierces salmon, at 60s 2,700</p>
                <p>To England, about 200 tons cod oil 4,000</p>
                <p>200 do. seal do 4,500</p>
                <p>Furs 3,000</p>
                <p>L.39,200</p>
                <p>By Newfoundland houses, 20,000 quintals cod fish, at I0s 10,000</p>
                <p>300 tierces salmon, at 60s 900</p>
                <p>Total direct export from Labrador L.50,100</p>
                <p>Produce sent direct to Newfoundland from Labrador:</p>
                <p>24,000 quintals cod fish, 9s. best quality 10,800</p>
                <p>300,000 quintals cod fish 127,500</p>
                <p>1500 tuns cod oil, at L.18 27,000</p>
                <p>Salmon, &amp;c 3,000</p>
                <p>Fish, &amp;c. sent to Canada, about 10,000</p>
                <p>Ditto carried to Nova Scotia and New Brunswick, should be in value at least
                    50,000</p>
                <p>Estimated value of the produce of Labrador, exclusive of what the Moravians send
                    to London<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>These
                    statements are made at the most depressed prices, and not at the average prices,
                    which would increase the gross value to L.312,400. The Americans of the United
                    States had, in 1829, about 500 vessels and 15,000 men employed on the coast, and
                    their “catch amounted to 1,100,000 quintals oí fish, and about 3000 tuns of oil;
                    value altogether, about L.610,000.</p></note> L.278,400</p>
                <p>The Labrador fishery has, since 1814, increased more than sixfold, principally in
                    consequence of our fishermen<pb break="no" facs="nls:193201470?mode=fullsize"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0713-1470-0005"/> being driven from the grounds now occupied by the
                    French.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>M <hi
                    rend="superscript"> c</hi> Gregor ’ s <hi rend="italic">British America,</hi>
                    vol. i. p. 209; to which work we are indebted for the above facts relative to
                    the trade of L‰&gt;- brador.</p></note></p>
                <p>This vast country, equal in square miles to France, Spain, and Germany, has not a
                    resident population exceeding 4000 inhabitants, including the natives and
                    Moravians. The latter, an excellent and truly Christian people, have several
                    settlements on this stern, inhospitable shore; and nothing but the purest spirit
                    of religion and philanthropy could induce them to remain, and zealously labour
                    to enlighten the miserable and disgusting native population. The principal
                    station is at Nain, on the north shore, where a ship annually arrives from
                    London in July, laden with provisions and other necessaries. At Nain there are
                    four missionaries, at Okkak three missionaries, at Hebron five missionaries, and
                    at Hopedale four missionaries. The total number of brethren is twenty-nine; and
                    there are 895 Esquimaux converts to Christianity, of whom about 320 are
                    communicants. These Moravians appear to have come from Greenland about the
                    middle of the last century, in the prosecution of their pious undertaking to
                    enlighten the heathen. Their habits and mode of life are simple and quiet,
                    corresponding to their isolated condition. Their trade is wholly with the
                    Esquimaux, with whom they barter coarse cloths, powder, shot, guns, and
                    edge-tools, for furs, oils, and other articles, the produce of the country. The
                    Esquimaux, the most filthy and disgusting tribe yet discovered on the shores of
                    America, are thinly scattered along the coast of Labrador. The greatest number
                    of them in any one place appears to be at Invutoke Inlet, or Esquimaux Bay, on
                    the Atlantic coast of Labrador, where there are about two hundred and fifty.
                    (For a description of the Esquimaux, see the article <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Greenland).</hi> The Canadians and others residing at Labrador employ these
                    people in catching fish, and the like. Labrador belongs to the government of
                    Newfoundland. During summer there is a court held, from which appeals are made
                    to the supreme court of St John’s. An armed vessel visits, and continues
                    generally along the coast, during the greater part of the fishing season. <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">(r. r. r.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
