<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0797-0722-02" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAMBALUC (9th edition, volume 4, page 722)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>267 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bg2hh25">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49g5gh4j">Names</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47s7ht9n">Walls</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qm4p">Emperors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b44f1mm3n">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b49c6s277">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4vm42z9s">Jesuits</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2tc9j">Franciscans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1025421">Mongols</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881747">Courts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859599">Christianity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:859760">Christians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:916820">Europeans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800130">Age</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800293">Aging</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1032344">Names</term>
                    <term ref="fast:938950">Gates</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206073">China</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n797/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAMBALUC</label> is the name by which, under sundry
                    modifications, the royal city of the Great Khan became known to Europe during
                    the Middle Ages, that city being in fact the same that we now know as Peking.
                    The word itself represents the Mongol <hi rend="italic">Kaan-Baligh,</hi> “the
                    city of the khan,” or emperor, the title by which Peking continues, more or
                    less, to be known to the Mongols and other northern Asiatics.</p>
                <p>A city occupying approximately the same site had been the capital of one of the
                    principalities into which China was divided some centuries before the Christian
                    era; and during the reigns of the two Tartar dynasties that immediately preceded
                    the Mongols in Northern China, viz., that of the Khitans, and of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Kin</hi> or “Golden” khans, it had been one of their royal
                    residences. Under the names of Yenking, which it received from the Khitan, and
                    of Chungtu, which it had from the Kin, it holds a conspicuous place in the wars
                    of Chinghiz Khan against the latter dynasty. He captured it in 1215, but it was
                    not till 1264 that it was adopted as the imperial residence in lieu of Kara
                    Korum in the Mongol steppes, by his grandson Kublaï. The latter selected a
                    position a few hundred yards to the N.E. of the old city of Chungtu or Yenking,
                    where he founded the new city of <hi rend="italic">Ta-tu</hi> (“great capital
                    ”), called by the Mongols <hi rend="italic">Tαidu</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >Daitu,</hi> but also <hi rend="italic">Kaaη-bηligh</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >;</hi> and from this time dates the use of the latter name as applied to
                    this site.</p>
                <p>The new city formed a rectangle, enclosed by a colossal mud-rampart, the longer
                    sides of which ran north and south. These were each about 5½ English miles in
                    length, the shorter sides 3⅜, so that the circuit was upwards of 18 miles. The
                    palace of the khan, with its gardens and lake, itself formed an inner inclosure
                    fronting the south. There were eleven city gates, viz., three on the south side,
                    always the formal front with the Tartars, and two on each of the other sides;
                    and the streets ran wide and straight from gate to gate (except, of course,
                    where interrupted by the palace-walls), forming an oblong chess-board plan.</p>
                <p>Tatu continued to be the residence of the emperors till the fall of the Mongol
                    power (1368). The native dynasty (Ming) which supplanted them established their
                    residence at <hi rend="italic">Nan-king</hi><hi rend="italic">(“</hi>
                    South-Court ”), but this proved so inconvenient that the second sovereign of the
                    dynasty reoccupied Tatu, giving it then, for the first time, the name of <hi
                        rend="italic">Pe-king</hi> (“North-Court ”). This was the name in common use
                    when the Jesuits entered China towards the end of the 16th century, and began to
                    send home accurate information about China. But it is not so now; the names in
                    ordinary use being <hi rend="italic">Kiηg-eheηg</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >King-tu,</hi> both signifying “capital.” The restoration of Cambaluc was
                    commenced in 1409. The size of the city was diminished by the retrenchment of
                    nearly one-third at the northern end, which brought the enceinte more nearly to
                    a square form. And this constitutes the modern (so-called) “Tartar city” of
                    Peking, the south front of which is identical with the south front of the city
                    of Kublaï. The walls were completed in 1437. Population gathered about the
                    southern front, probably using the material of the old city of Yenking, and the
                    excrescence so formed was, in 1544, enclosed by a wall, and called the “outer
                    city.” It is the same that is usually called by Europeans “the Chinese city.”
                    The ruins of the retrenched northern portion of Kublaï’s great rampart are still
                    prominent along their whole extent, so that there is no room for question as to
                    the position or true dimensions of the Cambaluc of the Middle Ages; and it is
                    most probable, indeed it is almost a necessity, that the present palace stands
                    on the lines of Kublaï’s palace, <pb break="no"
                        facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n798/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0798-0723"/> The city, under the name of Cambaluc, was
                    constituted into an archiépiscopal see by Pope Clement V. in 1307, in favour of
                    the missionary Franciscan John of Montecorvino; but though some successors were
                    nominated it seems probable that no second metropolitan ever actually occupied
                    the seat.</p>
                <p>Maps of the 16th and 17th centuries often show Cambaluc in an imaginary region to
                    the north of China, a part of the misconception that has prevailed regarding
                    Cathay (see <hi rend="smallcaps">China).</hi> The name is often in popular
                    literature written Cambaïu, and is by Longfellow accented in verse <hi
                        rend="italic">Cámbalú.</hi> But this spelling originates in an accidental
                    error in Ramusio’s Italian version, which, till lately, was the chief channel
                    through which Marco Polo’s book was popularly known. The original (French) MSS.
                    all agree with the etymology in calling it Cambaluc, which should be accented
                        <hi rend="italic">Cărnbaluc.</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">(h. y.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
