<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0832-0755-01" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAMPBELL, Thomas (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    755)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>267 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795b2n">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0kz00">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4639kc77">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4pc2td33">Goldsmithing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659k3h">Goldsmiths</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ns0m53j">Polishing</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4804xp4n">Polishes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:960068">Hope</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944605">Goldsmiths</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1068347">Poles</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821688">Authors</term>
                    <term ref="fast:821653">Authority</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1067778">Poets</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206891">Poland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n832/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAMPBELL, <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi></label>
                    (1777-1844). This distinguished poet was a cadet of the respectable family of
                    Campbell of Kirnan, in Argyllshire. Owing to the straitened circumstances of his
                    father, who had settled in Glasgow and been unfortunate in business, young
                    Campbell was obliged, while attending college, to have recourse to private
                    teaching as a tutor. Notwithstanding the amount of additional labour thus
                    entailed, he made rapid progress in his studies, and attained considerable
                    distinction at the university over which it was his fortune, in after years, to
                    preside. He very early gave proofs of his aptitude for literary composition,
                    especially in the department of poetry; and so strong was his addiction to these
                    pursuits, that he could not bring himself seriously to adopt the choice of a
                    profession. From private tuition, which is at best an irksome drudgery, he
                    recoiled after a short trial. Neither law, physic, nor divinity had any
                    attractions for him; nor is it probable that he ever would have risen to
                    eminence in a regular profession, owing to a constitutional sensitiveness almost
                    morbid, and a want of resolute energy. We are told by his friend and biographer
                    Dr Beattie that “the imaginative faculty had been so unremittingly cultivated
                    that circumstances, trifling in themselves, had acquired undue influence over
                    his mind, and been rendered formidable by an exaggeration of which he was at the
                    moment unconscious. Hence various difficulties, which industry might have
                    overcome, assumed to his eye the appearance of insurmountable obstacles. Without
                    resolution to persevere, or philosophy to submit to the force of necessity, he
                    drew from everything around him, with morbid ingenuity, some melancholy presage
                    of the future. He was dissatisfied with himself, chilled by the world’s neglect,
                    and greatly hurt by the apathy of friends who had extolled his merits, but left
                    him to pine in obscurity.” Campbell was not a man who could have successfully
                    struggled with the world. Fortunately for him, his genius was such as to ensure
                    an early recognition.</p>
                <p>We find him at the age of twenty in Edinburgh, attending lectures at the
                    university, soliciting employment from the booksellers, and not unknown to a
                    circle of young men then resident in the Scottish metropolis, whose names have
                    become historical. Among those were Walter Scott, Henry Brougham, Francis
                    Jeffrey, Dr Thomas Brown, John Leyden, and James Grahame, the author of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Sabbath.</hi> He also became acquainted with Dr Robert
                    Anderson, editor of a collection of the British poets, a man of extreme
                    enthusiasm and kindliness of disposition, who early appreciated the remarkable
                    powers of Campbell, and encouraged him to proceed in his literary career. In
                    1799 his poem, <hi rend="italic">The Pleasures of Hope,</hi> was published.</p>
                <p>Probably there is no parallel instance of literary success so instantaneously
                    achieved by a first effort; nor was that owing to novelty of design on the part
                    of the auth∙r, or the caprice of the public. For considerably more than half a
                    century the poem has maintained, nay, increased its popularity. During that time
                    the public has adopted and abandoned many favourites—names once famous and in
                    every mouth have gradually become forgotten and unregarded—poetical works of
                    greater pretension, which were once considered as masterpieces of genius and
                    inspiration, have fallen into neglect; but this poem by the boy Campbell remains
                    a universal favourite. It is not much to say that it is, without any exception,
                    the finest didactic poem in the English language. Even those who are not
                    admirers of didactic poetry are forced to admit its charm; and the uttermost
                    objection that criticism can make appears to be a certain vagueness, which,
                    after all, is inseparable from the nature of the subject and the necessary plan
                    of the composition. The delicacy of the thoughts, the beauty of the imagery, the
                    occasional power of pathos, the extraordinary felicity of the language, and the
                    wonderful harmony of the versification, distinguish the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pleasures of Hope</hi> from any poem which has been written before or
                    since, and entitle it to a very high place as an original work of genius. It is
                    as original and characteristic of its author as is the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Deserted Village</hi> of Goldsmith, with which it has been frequently, but
                    surely improperly compared. Goldsmith’s poem affects us by its simplicity and
                    truth. Campbell’s, it must be owned, is much more florid and ornamented; but how
                    exquisite is the taste of the ornament!</p>
                <p>The literary and the private histories of an author are inseparable. In order to
                    comprehend the one we must have recourse to the other. The first success of
                    Campbell brought him fame, but not fortune. He had disposed of the copyright of
                    the <hi rend="italic">Pleasures of Hope,</hi> by his original bargain with the
                    publishers, for a sum certainly moderate, which, however, probably exceeded his
                    expectations at the time. He was, moreover, very kindly treated, for he received
                    a considerable unstipulated allowance for each new edition, which circumstance
                    ought to have deterred him from uttering certain diatribes against “the trade,”
                    in which he was afterwards rather prone to indulge. The fact is that he did not
                    know how to make use of his success. Instead of availing himself of the
                    reputation which he had so worthily and decisively won, and applying himself to
                    a new effort, he went abroad without any determinate aim; was perfectly.
                    wretched on the Continent, where he had no friends, and was sorely embarrassed
                    for want of means; and began to write fugitive poetry for the London journals.
                    On his return to Britain he had ample opportunity of bettering his condition.
                    With a name such as his, a moderate amount of exertion would have secured him
                    not only a competence but comparative affluence; but indolence, perhaps the
                    result of timidity, had grown upon him. Campbell never could adapt himself even
                    to the profession of literature, which, precarious though it be, is not without
                    its prizes. In that profession, as in all others, the requisites for success are
                    steadiness, punctuality, and perseverance; but Campbell possessed none of them.
                    The publishers were ready, and offered to give him lucrative employment, nor was
                    he at all backward in accepting their offers; but when the period for
                    performance arrived he had literally done nothing. In extraordinary contrast to
                    him stands Scott, who seemed simply to will in order to conceive and execute.
                    Campbell had many bright conceptions, but he could not apply himself to the
                    work. Of course he lost repute with the men who alone can intervene between an
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n833/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0833-0756"/> author and the public, and “the fathers of
                    the Row” became chary of offering him engagements. Some idea of the extent of
                    his habitual indolence may be formed from the fact, that the publication of his
                        <hi rend="italic">Specimens of the British Poets</hi> did not take place
                    until thirteen years after the work was undertaken!</p>
                <p>In the meantime Campbell married; and his prospects were of the darkest, when, in
                    1805, he received a Government pension of £200. He was then in great distress,
                    and even that aid, material as it was, failed to extricate him. It was probably
                    fortunate for his fame that such was the case, for in 1809 he published his poem
                    of <hi rend="italic">Gertrude of Wyoming,</hi> to which were attached the most
                    celebrated of his grand and powerful lyrics.</p>
                <p>Among Campbell’s lengthier poems <hi rend="italic">Gertrude of Wyoming</hi> must
                    hold the second place. He designed it for a poem of action, but he has failed to
                    give it that interest and vivacity which a poem of action requires. There is in
                    it too decided a predominance of the sentimental vein, and an extreme degree of
                    elaboration, which, in poetry as in painting, is hurtful to the general effect.
                    There is great truth in the following criticism, which occurs in a letter from
                    Jeffrey to the author:—“Your timidity or fastidiousness, or some other knavish
                    quality, will not let you give your conceptions glowing, and bold, and powerful,
                    as they present themselves; but you must chasten, and refine, and soften them,
                    forsooth, till half their nature and grandeur is chiselled away from them.
                    Believe me, the world will never know how truly you are a great and original
                    poet till you venture to cast before it some of the rough pearls of your fancy.”
                    In spite of these defects, <hi rend="italic">Gertrude</hi> was considered at the
                    time as a work in every way worthy of the poet’s previous reputation; and it
                    will ever be admired by that numerous class of readers who are more fascinated
                    by the beauties of expression than by high inventive power and vigorous
                    execution.</p>
                <p>The soundness of the above criticism, proceeding from an eminent literary
                    authority whose whole leanings were rather towards than against fastidiousness
                    in composition, is demonstrated by the universal admiration accorded to
                    Campbell’s lyrical pieces. One or two of these, in particular <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lochicl</hi> ’ <hi rend="italic">s Warning</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Hohenlinden,</hi> are to be referred to an earlier period than the
                    composition of <hi rend="italic">Gertrude</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> but there
                    are others of a later date which show how much power remained in the man when he
                    chose to exert it freely. There are few lyrics in the English language to be
                    placed in comparison with the <hi rend="italic">Mariners of England</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">The Battle of the Baltic</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and his
                    exquisite poem of <hi rend="italic">O’Connor’s Child,</hi> which has not unaptly
                    been termed the diamond of his casket of gems, is greatly superior in pathos and
                    passion to his more elaborate compositions. All these, and others scarcely
                    inferior to them, seem to have been struck off at a heat, and to have escaped
                    that chiselling process to which Jeffrey so pointedly referred.</p>
                <p>Campbell was now settled at Sydenham in England, and his circumstances were
                    materially improved. His home was a happy one; the society in which he moved was
                    of the most refined and intellectual character; and he enjoyed the personal
                    friendship of many of his distinguished contemporaries. Ample leisure was
                    afforded him to carry into effect any of the cherished schemes of his literary
                    ambition; but his indolence and inherent want of resolution again interfered.
                    His most noteworthy exertion for years appears to have been the preparation of a
                    short course of lectures on poetry, which he delivered with great <hi
                        rend="italic">éclat</hi> at the Royal Institution in London and elsewhere.
                    It appears that at one time it was proposed by his friends, and especially by
                    Sir Walter Scott, that he should become a candidate for the occupancy of a
                    literary chair in the University of Edinburgh; but he shrank from the idea of
                    undertaking so serious a labour as is involved in the preparation of a thorough
                    academical course. In 1820 he accepted the editorship of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >New Monthly Magazine,</hi> and acted in that capacity for a considerable
                    period, until he resigned it to take charge of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Metropolitan.</hi> His connection with periodical literature may have been
                    advantageous in a pecuniary point of view, but did not tend materially to
                    enhance his reputation. His was not the pen of the ready writer; and it must
                    ever be regretted that he was induced to bestow so much attention upon merely
                    ephemeral literature, to the sacrifice of the nobler aims which were expected
                    from his acknowledged genius. In 1824 he published his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Thxodric,</hi> a poem which, in spite of some fine passages, was generally
                    considered as a failure. With <hi rend="italic">Theodric</hi> his poetical
                    career may be said to have closed. At times he put forth short poems of various
                    degrees of merit, but none of them were equal to the grand lyrics already
                    treasured in the memory of his countrymen. It seemed as if a large portion of
                    the old virtue had departed from him; and his last published poem, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Pilgrim of Glencoe,</hi> showed hardly any marks of his former
                    accomplishment and power.</p>
                <p>In fact it appeared that the rich mine of poetry had been worked out. Without
                    actually adopting that conclusion, we may observe that Campbell had latterly
                    occupied himself most zealously with matters which were apart from his earlier
                    pursuits. In the first place, he took an active share in the Institution of the
                    London University, and it was mainly through his exertions that it was saved
                    from becoming a mere sectarian college. Shortly afterwards, in 1826, he was
                    elected Lord Rector of the University of Glasgow, an event which he considered
                    as the crowning honour of his life, and which certainly was a mark of
                    distinction of which any man might have been proud. He did not accept the office
                    as a mere sinecure, but applied himself to discharge the actual duties (which,
                    through the negligence of former rectors, had been allowed to fall into
                    abeyance) with a zeal and energy which made entire conquest of the hearts of his
                    youthful constituents. In 1831, the year in which the gallant struggle of the
                    Poles for their independence was terminated by entire defeat, Campbell, who in
                    his earliest poem had referred in such beautiful language to the shameful
                    partition of Poland, more than revived his youthful enthusiasm for her cause. He
                    had watched with an anxiety almost bordering on fanaticism the progress of the
                    patriotic movement; and the news of the capture of Warsaw by the Russians
                    affected him as if it had been the deepest of personal calamities. “His heart,”
                    says his biographer, “was in the subject of Poland; he could neither write nor
                    speak upon any other with common patience; and if a word was dropt in company
                    that did not harmonize with his feelings, he was very apt to consider it as a
                    personal offence.” In one of his own letters he says, “I know that my zeal for
                    Poland has put me half mad.” And again, “It is still all that I can do to
                    support a tolerable cheerfulness before these kind hospitable people, for Poland
                    preys on my heart night and day. It is sometimes a relief to me to weep in
                    secret, and I do weep long and bitterly.” Nor did he show his sympathy by words
                    alone, but by resolute and continued action. He was the founder of the
                    association in London of the Friends of Poland, which not only served to
                    maintain the strong interest felt by the British people for the Polish cause,
                    but was the means of providing assistance and giving employment to large numbers
                    of the unfortunate exiles who were driven to seek refuge in this country. Never,
                    till his dying day, did he relax his exertions in their behalf; and many an
                    unhappy wanderer, who, but for unexpected aid, might have perished in the
                    streets of a foreign city, had reason to bless the name of Thomas Campbell.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n834/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0834-0757"/>
                <p>The remainder of his life presents few features of interest. Domestic calamity
                    had overtaken him. His wife, whom he loved affectionately, had been taken from
                    him—of his two sons, one died in infancy, and the other was afflicted by an
                    incurable malady. His own health became impaired. He gradually withdrew from
                    public life, and died at Boulogne on 15th July 1844, at the age of sixty-seven.
                    His last hours were soothed by the affectionate care of his relatives and
                    friends; nor did his countrymen forget the poet in his death, for his remains
                    were solemnly interred in Westminster Abbey, with the honours of a public
                    funeral.</p>
                <p>Few poets of reputation, whose span has been extended nearly to the threescore
                    and ten allotted years, have written so little as Campbell: at the same time it
                    must be confessed that there are fewer still whose works are likely to be prized
                    by posterity in the like proportion with his. If we throw out of consideration
                    altogether <hi rend="italic">Thsodric,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> though some
                    might demur to such an excision,—if we overlook the <hi rend="italic">Pilgrim of
                        Glencoe,</hi> and weed from his lyrical garden such plants as have little
                    charm either from their colour or their fragrance, there will still remain a
                    mass of poetry familiar to the ear and the heart, such as hardly any other
                    writer of this century has been able to produce. We may regret that Campbell was
                    not more diligent in the cultivation of his poetical genius, that he did not
                    apply himself more sedulously in his earlier years to some serious effort, and
                    that he allowed other pursuits and designs to interfere with his peculiar
                    calling. But who can venture to say what success might have attended his efforts
                    had he acted otherwise than he did? <hi rend="italic">We</hi> blame the poet for
                    apparent indolence, not reflecting that inspiration is not to be commanded at
                    will. It is not only possible but easy for the man who is practised in
                    versification to write a certain given number of lines within a certain
                    specified time; but genuine poetry never was and never will be the product of
                    Egyptian taskwork. It cannot be produced to order—it must be spontaneous; and
                    its quality must depend entirely upon the mood of mind under which it is com
                    posed. The greater part of the poetry or rather the verse of Southey, a
                    considerable portion of that of Scott, and a vast deal of that of Wordsworth,
                    was not conceived or written under the poetic impulse. On such occasions these
                    celebrated men were writing verse, as they might have written prose, without
                    enthusiasm or anything like the feeling of passion; and although their ordinary
                    thoughts were far higher, bolder, and more subtle than those of the million,
                    they still were not attempting to rise beyond their ordinary intellectual level.
                    One can see at a glance when they were inspired, and when they were merely
                    versifying. Of the poets who adorned the first half of the present century,
                    Coleridge and Campbell were conspicuous for their abstinence in writing except
                    under the influence of real emotion. Of the former it may be said that he has
                    hardly penned a line of mere mechanical verse; the latter did not do so until
                    his inspiration seemed to have abandoned him. Undoubtedly, however,—to have
                    recourse to a hackneyed, though by no means an unmeaning phrase,—it is the duty
                    of the poet to woo the muse, not to wait for her courtship. He must seek for the
                    waters of Castaly, not tarry till they are conveyed to him; and it is in this
                    respect probably that Campbell principally erred. He did not sufficiently
                    endeavour to awake his genius; he was too much a dreamer, and may at times have
                    lost his opportunity from the sheer weight of indolence. And yet, considering
                    the value of the legacy he has left, we have no reason to complain. Critics may
                    dispute regarding the comparative merits of his longer works; and, as they
                    incline towards didactic or narrative poetry, may prefer the one composition to
                    the other. Both are entitled to high praise and honour, but it is on his lyrics
                    that the future reputation of Campbell must principally rest. They have taken
                    their place, never to be disturbed, in the popular heart; and, until the
                    language in which they are written perishes, they are certain to endure. (w. <hi
                        rend="smallcaps">e. a.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
