<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0818-0741-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAMERON, John</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 741</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:944037">God</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1058072">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:844604">Calvinists</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1079920">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:814833">Arminians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:814830">Arminianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:844591">Calvinism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1219920">England</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4028pn8z">Synods</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4bk16r27">Protestantism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4sq8qh7s">Arminianism</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4nz80q31">Arminians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44b2x59s">Calvinism</term>
                    <term n="4" ref="lcsh1910:b4348gn83">Mind</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4gf0n262">Periodicals</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n818/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAMERON, <hi rend="smallcaps">John</hi></label> (1579-1623),
                    a learned theologian, was born at Glasgow about 1579, and received his early
                    education in his native city. After having taught Greek in the university for
                    twelve months, he removed to Bordeaux, where he was soon appointed a regent in
                    the College of Bergerac. He did not remain long at Bordeaux, but accepted the
                    offer of a chair of philosophy at Sedan, where he passed two years. He then
                    returned to Bordeaux, and in the beginning of 1604 he was nominated one of the
                    students of divinity who were maintained at the expense of the church, and who
                    for the period of four years were at liberty to prosecute their studies in any
                    Protestant seminary. During this period he acted as tutor to the two sons of
                    Calignon, chancellor of Navarre. They spent one year at Paris, and two at
                    Geneva, whence they removed to Heidelberg, where they remained nearly twelve
                    months. In this university, on the 4th of April 1608, he gave a public proof of
                    his ability by maintaining a series of theses, <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">triplici</hi><hi rend="italic">Dei cum</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >Homine</hi><hi rend="italic">Foedere,</hi> which were printed among his works.
                    The same year he was recalled to Bordeaux, where he was appointed the colleague
                    of Dr Primrose; and when Gomarus was removed to Leyden, Cameron, iu 1618, was
                    appointed professor of divinity at Saumur, the principal seminary of the French
                    Protestants.</p>
                <p>In 1620 the progress of the civil troubles in France obliged Cameron to seek
                    refuge for himself and family in England. For a short time he read private
                    lectures on divinity in London; and in 1622 the king appointed him principal of
                    the university of Glasgow in the room of Robert Boyd, who had been removed from
                    his office in consequence of his adherence to Presbyterianism. His successor
                    appears to have been more favourably inclined to Episcopacy,—a circumstance that
                    may have tended to diminish the cordiality of his reception in his native city.
                    Here he also taught divinity with great reputation, but he resigned his office
                    in less than a year. Calderwood says that “Cameron was so misliked by the people
                    that he was forced to quit his place soon afterwards.”</p>
                <p>He returned to France, and fixed his residence at Saumur; and after an interval
                    of a year he was appointed professor of divinity at Montauban. The country was
                    still torn by civil and religious dissensions; and as Cameron maintained the
                    doctrine of passive obedience, he excited the indignation of the more strenuous
                    adherents of his own party. He withdrew to the neighbouring town of Moissac; but
                    he soon returned to Montauban, and a few days afterwards he died at the age of
                    about forty-six. Cameron left by his first wife several children, whose
                    maintenance was undertaken by the Protestant churches in France. All his works
                    were published after his death.</p>
                <p>His name has furnished a designation to a party of Calvinists in France, who
                    asserted that the will of man is only determined by the practical judgment of
                    the mind; that the cause of men’s doing good or evil proceeds from the knowledge
                    which God infuses into them; and that God does not move the will physically, but
                    only morally, by virtue of its dependence on the judgment of the mind. This
                    peculiar doctrine of grace and free-will was adopted by Amyraut, Cappel,
                    Bochart, Daillé, and others of the more learned among the Reformed ministers,
                    who judged Calvin’s doctrines on these points too harsh. The Cameronites are
                    moderate Calvinists, and approach to the opinion of the Arminians. They are also
                    called <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n819/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0819-0742"/> Univerealists, as holding the universal reference
                    of Christ’s death, and sometimes Amyraldists. The rigid adherents to the Synod
                    of Dort accused them of Pelagianism, and even of Manicheism, and the controversy
                    between the parties was carried on with great zeal <hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">yet</hi> the whole question between them was only, whether the wiU
                    of man is determined by the immediate action of God upon it, or by the
                    intervention of a knowledge which God impresses on the mind. The Synod of Dort
                    had laid down the position that God not only illuminates the understanding, but
                    gives motion to the will by making an internal change therein; whereas Cameron
                    admitted only the illumination by which the mind is morally moved, and attempted
                    to explain the decision of the Synod of Dort so as to make the two opinions
                    consistent.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
