<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0718-0647-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAITHNESS</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 647</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="11" ref="fasttopic:865801">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:952579">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:829042">Bays</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1039481">Norwegians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:850410">Celts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:1019272">Mey</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="11" ref="lcsh1910:b4862bd3v">Coasts</term>
                    <term n="6" ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86n9w">Head</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs8z">Norwegians</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4j09w45x">Celts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4r20rx5q">Presbyterianism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1206715">Scotland</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n718/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAITHNESS</label>, the most northern county of the Scottish
                    mainland, bounded W. and S. by Sutherlandshire, and E. and N. by the Northern
                    Ocean, is situated between 58° 8' and 58° 40' N. lat., 3° 0' and 3° 55' W.
                    long., and has an extreme length of 53 miles, an extreme breadth of 33, a coast
                    line of 105 miles, and an area of 455,708 acres or 712 square miles. The form of
                    Caithness resembles an irregular triangle, having as its greatest side the line
                    of coast on the S.E., stretching from the Ord of Caithness to Duncansby Head.
                    The surface of the county generally is flat and tame, consisting for the most
                    part of barren moors, and being almost entirely destitute of trees. It presents
                    a gradual slope from the north and east upwards to the ridge of hills on the
                    west and south, which separates it from Sutherlandshire, and on the southern
                    boundary, where it is bifurcated, attains considerable elevation. Thé one
                    branch, called the Maiden Paps, contains the peak of Morven, 2334 above the
                    level of the sea; the other, continuing in the line of the main ridge, juts into
                    the sea, and terminates in the huge granitic precipice of the Ord. In the centre
                    of the county, hemmed in by the hills on the western boundary, the ridge of the
                    Maiden Paps, and the sea, is a large undulating plain comprising nearly
                    four-fifths of the whole extent. On its southern side it is broken up by several
                    detached hills, and in the interior contains a considerable number of small
                    lakes. The most depressed part of the county lies in the peninsula formed in the
                    northeast corner by the indentation of Dunnet Bay and Sinclair Bay. The more
                    elevated portion presents a light sandy soil, which admits of considerable
                    cultivation, but the low grounds are covered with extensive morasses, producing
                    only heath and rough grass.</p>
                <p>The geological formation consists chiefly of sandstone, sandstone flag, and
                    occasionally limestone; but granite and gneiss are also found in the west. On
                    the east Caithness presents a precipitous coast, with scarcely a creek in which
                    a vessel, even of small size, can find shelter. On the northern coast, where the
                    Pentland Firth separates it from the Orkney islands, stand at the distance of 13
                    miles from each other the two bold headlands of Duncansby Head on the north-east
                    and Dunnet Head on the north-west. The latter, the most northern point of
                    Scotland, is situated in 58° 40' N. lat. and 3° 21' W. long., and is crowned by
                    a lighthouse, with a fixed light, built on the rock 346 feet above the level of
                    the sea; while the former is marked by the white steeple of Cannisby on the
                    west. The navigation of the Pentland Firth is attended with considerable danger,
                    from the strength and eddies of the current. Off the island of Stroma, which is
                    separated from the mainland by a strait three miles broad, is a small vortex
                    called the Swalchie; while nearer the shore are the “Merry Men of Mey,” a group
                    of breakers caused by eddies between projecting headlands. On the east coast, in
                    addition to the harbour of Wick, erected in 1831, at a cost of above £40,000,
                    and since improved at further expense, there is a small harbour at Sarclett and
                    another at Staxigoe, a small pier at Clyth and another at Lybster. On the
                    northern coast Scrabster roads in Thurso Bay afford tolerably good anchorage,
                    while at Thurso and Sandside Bay are commodious harbours for larger vessels.</p>
                <p>The climate of Caithness is variable, but not unhealthy; and though the winter
                    storms fall with great severity on the unsheltered coast, yet from its proximity
                    to a large expanse of sea the cold is not intense and snow seldom lies many days
                    continuously. In winter and spring the northern shore is subject to frequent and
                    disastrous gales from the N. and N.W. The waters of Forss, Thurso, and Wick, are
                    the principal streams which traverse the county, but none of them are of any
                    particular importance. The largest lochs are those of Watten and Cathel; there
                    are numerous small ones well stocked with trout.</p>
                <p>A great change has been effected in the agricultural position of Caithness,
                    chiefly by the late James Traill, Esq. of Ratter. The farms along the coast are
                    still mostly in the hands of small farmers, who cultivate the soil only during
                    the intervals of the fishing-season; but inland, in the more elevated districts,
                    and along the banks of the principal streams, the land is let out into large
                    farms, with leases long enough to encourage the holder to improve the soil and
                    practise a rotation of crops. The average extent of land held by each occupier,
                    in 1874, was 39 acres, much larger than the average in Sutherlandshire, which
                    only amounted to 10 acres in the same year. In the pasturage ground, black
                    cattle and sheep, chiefly of the Leicester and Cheviot breeds, are reared for
                    the southern markets; and, independently of the weekly corn-markets at Thurso
                    and Wick, the rapidity of communication with the south is opening up a valuable
                    market for the produce of the dairy and farmyard.</p>
                <p>The principal crops raised are oats, beans, potatoes, and turnips; wheat can be
                    grown only where draining has been carried to considerable perfection. In 1874
                    there were only 87 acres in wheat, 1895 in barley, 70 in rye, and 27 in peas;
                    while oats occupied 33,071 acres, turnips 14,045, and potatoes 2190. In the same
                    year there were 21,567 <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n719/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0719-0648"/> acres in permanent pasture, and 6222 in temporary
                    grass, while only 440 were covered with wood. The number of cattle of all kinds
                    in the county was 22,616, sheep 108,829, horses 4969, and pigs 1789. But the
                    great source of profit to the inhabitants is to be found in the fisheries of
                    cod, ling, lobsters, and herring, which abound all around the coast. The most
                    important is the herring-fishery, though it has considerably lessened in value
                    during the last twenty or thirty years. Beginning about the end of July the
                    season lasts for about six weeks, the centre of operations being at Wick and the
                    surrounding districts. The number of fishermen employed in 1874 was 4304; and
                    the value of boats, nets, lines, &lt;fcc., for the same year, was estimated at
                    £112,270. Besides those more immediately engaged in manning the boats, the
                    fisheries give employment to a large number of coopers, curers, packers, and
                    others. The salmon-fisheries on the coast and at the mouths of rivers were
                    formerly very productive, and are still let at high prices. At intervals along
                    the coast are valuable quarries of freestone and slate, and of excellent flag
                    for pavements; but the county is far from rich in other minerals. Slight traces
                    of lead and iron have been found in the mountainous districts; and indications
                    of coal, or rather of bituminous shale, have been noticed at Cannisby. The only
                    article of manufacture is woollen cloth. The Highland Railway, opened in 1873,
                    enters the county from Sutherlandshire, and curves through the centre to Wick,
                    passing Altnabreac, Scotscalder, Halkirk, Georgemas, Bower, Watten, and
                    Bilbster; while a branch line runs from the Georgemas junction to Thurso.</p>
                <p>The early history of Caithness may, to some extent, be traced in the various
                    character of the remains and the diversity of its local nomenclature. Picts’
                    houses, Norwegian names, and Danish mounds attest that the Celts were
                    successively displaced by these different tribes; and the number and strength of
                    its fortified keeps leave us to infer that its annals present the usual record
                    of feuds, assaults, and reprisals. Circles of erect stones, as at Steinster Loch
                    and Bower, and the ruins of Romanist chapels and places of pilgrimage in almost
                    every district, illustrate the changes which have come over its ecclesiastical
                    condition. The most important remains are those of Bucholie Castle, Girnigo
                    Castle, and the tower of Keiss; and on the S.E. coast the castles of Clyth,
                    Swiney, Forss, Latheron, Knockinnan, Berridale, Achastle, and Dunbeath,—of which
                    the last is romantically situated on one of the detached pillars of sandstone
                    rock that are frequent along the Caithness coast. About six miles from Thurso
                    stand the ruins of Braal Castle, the residence of the ancient bishops of
                    Caithness, and on the shores of the Pentland is situated the mythical site of
                    John o’ Groats’ House. The total number of landowners in 1872-3 was 1030,—among
                    the most important being the duke of Portland, with 81,605 acres; Sir John
                    Sinclair of Tollemache, with 78,053; Mrs Thomson Sinclair of Fenswick, with
                    57,757; Sir Robert Anstruther of Balcaskie in Fife, with 36,597; and the earl of
                    Caithness, with 14,460.</p>
                <p>Caithness is divided into ten civil and twelve <hi rend="italic">quoad sacra</hi>
                    parishes, and contains twelve churches and two chapels of ease belonging to the
                    Establishment (in four of which there is service in Gaelic); seventeen belonging
                    to the Free Church (in seven of which there is service in Gaelic); one United
                    Presbyterian, and one Roman Catholic at Wick.</p>
                <p>The county returns one member to the imperial parliament. The parliamentary
                    constituency in 1875—76 was 1172. The principal towns are Wick and Thurso; the
                    most important villages are Broadhaven, Castletown, Louisburgh, Sarclett, and
                    Staxigoe. The population in 1831 was 34,529; in 1841, 36,343; in 1851, 38,709;
                    and in 1871, 39,992. In the last year the males numbered 18,937, and the females
                    21,055; and there were in the county at the same date 7474 inhabited houses, 203
                    vacant, and 431 building.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
