<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0753-0682-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CALENDER</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 682</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="9" ref="fasttopic:979089">Iron</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1052348">Paper</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:848395">Caste</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:848476">Casts</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1075837">Press</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:962708">Huguenots</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:934209">French</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:844258">Calico</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="9" ref="lcsh1910:b4n00zz70">Iron</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4r785w31">Paper</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cn1s">Caste</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4hd7nt71">Casting</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4m61br13">Casts</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4086371g">Huguenots</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n753/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CALENDER</label>, a mechanical engine employed for dressing
                    and finishing cloths and various descriptions of fabrics, preparatory to sending
                    them into the market. It is also used by calico-printers to prepare the surface
                    of their cloths for the operations of printing. The first object of calendering
                    is to produce in the cloth as perfect extension and smoothness of surface as can
                    be attained,—so that no wrinkle or doubled folding may remain in it. The second
                    end attained by the calendering of cloth is the compression of the yarn or
                    threads of which the texture is composed, which in some degree divests them of
                    their cylindrical shape, and reduces them to a degree of flatness, which, by
                    bringing them more closely into contact with each other, gives to the fabric a
                    greater appearance of closeness and strength than it would otherwise possess.
                    The operation of the calender also improves the superficial appearance, by
                    flattening down all knots, lumps, and other imperfections, from which no
                    material from which cloth is fabricated can ever be entirely freed during the
                    previous processes of spinning and weaving. And, thirdly, in certain fabrics it
                    is desirable that cloth should receive, by means of friction, an additional
                    lustre or polish, which is distinguished by the appellation of glazing. For the
                    accomplishment of these objects the agencies on which the calenderer has to rely
                    are moisture, heat, pressure, and friction, and these he variously combines to
                    produce many different effects.</p>
                <p>The term calender, which really means only the chief mechanical engine employed,
                    gives the general name to the finishing establishments where all the varied
                    operations of cloth-lapping are carried on; and it is as usual to say that goods
                    are <hi rend="italic">packed</hi> as that goods are <hi rend="italic"
                    >dressed</hi> at a calender. The common domestic smoothing-iron may be regarded
                    as a form of calendering utensil; as is also the old-fashioned domestic mangle,
                    which consists of a cylinder applied to a plane, upon which it is rolled
                    backward and forward, until some degree of smoothness is produced by this
                    reciprocating motion. . A form of mangle, consisting of an enormously heavy
                    cylinder, which is worked forwards and backwards over a plane surface, is still
                    used in calendering establishments for the finishing of very heavy linens and
                    similar goods.</p>
                <p>The smoothing calender completes the substitution of cylindrical for plane
                    surfaces, all the parts which operate upon the cloth being of that form. This
                    ingenious engine, which was introduced into Britain from Flanders and Holland
                    during the persecution of the Huguenots, has, since its introduction and
                    adoption, undergone no very material or important alteration or improvement in
                    point of theoretical principle; nor, until the extension of the cotton
                    manufacture had introduced a general spirit of mechanical improvement, were any
                    great advances made in the practical applications of it .</p>
                <p>Calenders are constructed with from two to five rollers or cylinders, technically
                    termed “bowls,”—three or five-bowl calenders being most frequently employed. The
                    materials of which these cylinders are made are wood, compressed paper, and
                    metal, such as chilled cast-iron, brass, or copper. They are variously arranged
                    in. relation to each other, and as mechanical arrangements are required—1st, for
                    varying pressure; 2d, for applying heat within a metal bowl from steam, hot
                    iron, or burn ing gas; and 3d, for varying the rate of motion of a pair of the
                    bowls so as to produce friction—the gearing of a calender is somewhat complex.
                    Commonly a three-bowl calender has an upper and under cylinder of paper, the
                    central one being of metal, and in such an implement either two pieces may pass
                    through at the same time, or one piece may receive two pressures. An ordinary
                    five-bowl calender has the first, third, and fifth cylinders of paper, the
                    intermediate being of metal, and here four successive pressures may be given.
                    Fig. 1, Plate XXXII., is an elevation of a five-roller calender for finishing
                    cloth. A, A are two paper rollers, of 20 inches diameter each. B, B are two
                    cast-iron cylinders, externally turned until perfectly smooth; their diameter is
                    8 inches, allowing the substance of iron to be 2 inches, and leaving a
                    perforation of 4 inches diameter. C is a paper roller of 14 inches diameter; D,
                    D is the framing of cast-iron for containing the bushes in which the journals of
                    the rollers revolve; E, E are two levers by which the rollers are firmly pressed
                    together while the cloth is passing through.</p>
                <p>Fig. 2 is an end view of the same calender, with the wheels for glazing cloth.
                    The wheel on the upper cylinder is 10 inches diameter, the wheel on the under
                    cylinder is 13 inches diameter; they are connected by the wheel F, which
                    communicates the speed of the upper cylinder, so that the wheel on the under
                    cylinder being nearly one-third of an inch more in diameter, the difference of
                    their motions retards the centre paper roller, by which means the upper cylinder
                    passes over the cloth one-third faster than the cloth passes through the
                    calender, and polishes it in consequence.</p>
                <p>The construction of paper or pasteboard rollers for calenders is a process of
                    great interest and importance. The frequent heating and cooling to which the
                    apparatus is subject necessarily produces warping and splitting in wooden bowls,
                    which are thereby rendered useless, but the substitution of paper afforded a
                    radical cure for these defects as well as a collateral advantage arising from
                    its being susceptible of a much higher degree of superficial polish, which is
                    always transferred to the cloth. In the construction of paper cylinders an axis
                    or journal of malleable iron and two circular plates of cast-iron of the same
                    diameter as the cylinder to be made are, in the first place, provided. A plate
                    is secured on one end of the journal. The entire space between the two iron
                    plates is then to be filled with circular pieces of paper or pasteboard,
                    exceeding by about 1 inch in diameter the iron plates, and having each a
                    correspondent perforation, through which the iron journal passes. A cylinder is
                    thus formed, the substance of which is of paper locked together by plates of
                    iron at the extremities, and susceptible of immense compression which it
                    receives in a hydraulic press. After undergoing this preparation, the cylinder
                    is exposed to strong heat in a confined apartment in which the paper contracts
                    and becomes loose. It is again put into the press, more sheets of paper are
                    added, and this process goes on till the cylinder has gradually acquired the
                    requisite compression. It is then re-exposed to the ordinary temperature of the
                    atmosphere, and by its re-expansion presents a body almost remarkably compact,
                    its specific gravity in this state being greater than even that of silver.</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n756/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0756-0683"/>
                <p>The only operation now required is that of turning its superficies until
                    correctly cylindrical; and this is a work of immense labour and patience.</p>
                <p>For dressing muslins, gauzes, lawns, and other goods of a light kind, a smaller
                    species of calender is employed. It Consists of only three cylinders of equal
                    diameter (generally about 6 inches), and is easily moved by a common winch or
                    handle. The middle cylinder is iron, and the others are of wood or pasteboard.
                    All the cylinders are of equal diameter, and are moved with equal velocities by
                    means of small wheels. This machine is always used in a cold state.</p>
                <p>By means of the calender, also, is produced the waved or watered surface, known
                    as <hi rend="italic">moire</hi> among the French, and best seen in the silk
                    textures called moire antique, and in woollen moreens. The effect is produced in
                    a variety of ways, the principal method employed consisting of passing two webs
                    laid above each other through the calender at the same time. The threads of the
                    web not running perfectly parallel to each other are at some places
                    superimposed, and at other points they fit into alternate spaces, —the result
                    being that at the places where the threads press directly on each other a higher
                    gloss is produced, which gives the watered appearance to the texture. Watering
                    is also effected on a single thickness of material by moving the web to the
                    right and left as it enters the calender, and thus varying the direction in
                    which it travels over a bowl on which there are a series of engraved lines
                    running in a parallel direction. Embossed patterns, or imitations of the grain
                    of leather, &amp;c., for bookbinders’ cloth, are produced by means of a calender
                    having a bowl of brass or other metal on which the pattern is engraved. When a
                    paper cylinder is used along with an embossing cylinder, the paper must be
                    turned into such exact proportion to the embossed bowl that it will repeat the
                    pattern accurately on its circumference, so that the depressions on the one bowl
                    always fit accurately into the elevations on the other. For many purposes a
                    covering of leather, felt, or lead is used for the cylinder which works against
                    that on which the pattern is engraved.</p>
                <p>Goods after passing through the calender are folded, either by machinery or on
                    long pins by hand-working into a variety of forms according to their nature and
                    destination, and when so folded they are submitted to a very powerful
                    compression either in a screw-press or in an hydraulic press.</p>
                <p>Fig. 3, Plate XXXII., is a perspective view of an hydraulic press. A is the
                    piston, 8 inches diameter, working in the cylinder B, and kept water-tight by
                    passing through a collar of leather; D, a cast-iron plate raised by the piston
                    A, between which and the entablature E, E the goods to be pressed are laid <hi
                    rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">C,</hi> C, C, C, four malleable iron
                    columns, 2∣ inches diameter, having screwed ends, with nuts, by which the
                    entablature and the base F, F are firmly connected together; G, a cistern for
                    holding water to supply the two force-pumps H and I, the largest of which has a
                    piston 1½ inch diameter, and the other one of ½ inch diameter, which is used to
                    give the highest pressure"; K, K, weights to balance the pump-handles which fit
                    into the sockets at <hi rend="italic">I, I.</hi> The pistons of the force-pumps
                    are made water-tight by collars of leather, kept in their place by the screwed
                    pieces <hi rend="italic">m</hi> and <hi rend="italic">n.</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >e, e,</hi><hi rend="italic">e</hi> is a pipe communicating with the pumps and
                    the large cylinder B; there is a stopcock at/, which shuts this communication
                    when required.</p>
                <p>Fig. 4 is an enlarged view of the force-pump piston, to show the method of
                    keeping the rod parallel.</p>
                <p>An illustration of a glazing calender as used by bleachers and calico-printers,
                    with further details as to finishing processes, will be found under <hi
                    rend="smallcaps">Bleaching.</hi> See also <hi rend="smallcaps"
                    >Calico-Printing.</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
