<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0837-0760-05" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAMPHOR</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 760</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4z02zf6b">Malays</term>
                    <term n="18" ref="lcsh1910:b4bn9x413">Camphor</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hm52s7v">Production</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4319s24m">Acids</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41c1tg27">Wood</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="18" ref="fasttopic:844918">Camphor</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:795828">Acids</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1179191">Wood</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:980104">Islands</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1243192">Borneo</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fastgeo:1206073">China</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1204082">Japan</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n837/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAMPHOR</label> is a colourless translucent body, having a
                    tough waxy structure, with a specific gravity about equal to that of water,
                    melting at 347° Fahr, and boiling at 400°. It volatilizes readily at ordinary
                    temperatures, <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n838/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0838-0761"/> giving off that peculiarly pungent aromatic odour
                    which is characteristic of the substance. It is very slightly soluble in water,
                    to which it communicates its warm camphoraceous taste; but it dissolves with
                    facility in alcohol, ether, fixed and volatile oils, naphtha, &amp;c. In its
                    chemical constitution it is analogous to the solid stearoptines deposited by
                    many essential oils, especially such as are derived from labiate plants. By
                    submitting it to the action of oxidizing agents camphor, C <hi rend="subscript">
                    10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> O, is transformed into camphoric acid, C
                    <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 16</hi> O <hi
                    rend="subscript"> 4</hi>, and if the oxidation is continued it becomes
                    camphretic acid, C <hi rend="subscript"> 10</hi> H <hi rend="subscript"> 14</hi>
                    O <hi rend="subscript"> 7</hi>.</p>
                <p>The greater part of the camphor of Western commerce is obtained by distillation
                    from the wood of a tree, <hi rend="italic">(Jamphora</hi><hi rend="italic"
                    >officinarum,</hi> belonging to the Natural Order <hi rend="italic"
                    >Lauraceoe.</hi> It is produced most largely in the Island of Formosa, the area
                    of production being a narrow belt of debateable land separating the Chinese
                    settlement from the territory held of the aboriginal inhabitants of the island.
                    The preparation of the product is consequently attended with considerable
                    danger, owing to the mutual jealousies and encroachments of the natives and the
                    Chinese. The crude and primitive process of distillation is thus described by Mr
                    E. C. Taintor in his; <hi rend="italic">Trade Report of Tamsui,</hi> 1869 :—“A
                    long wooden trough, frequently hollowed out from the trunk of a tree, is fixed
                    over a furnace and protected by a coating of clay. Water is poured into it, and
                    a board perforated with numerous small holes is luted over it. Over these holes
                    the chips [of the camphor-wood] are placed and covered with earthenware pots.
                    Heat being applied in the furnace, the steam passes through the chips, carrying
                    with it the camphor, which condenses in the form of minute white crystals in the
                    upper part of the pots.” It is collected and stored iu vats to await
                    exportation, during which time it gives out from 3 to 4 per cent, of
                    uncrystallizable camphor oil of a yellowish colour, which has been suggested for
                    use in medicine and the arts in the same way as spirits of turpentine. In
                    addition to the supplies obtained from Formosa, a considerable quantity of
                    camphor is now shipped from Japan. Japanese unrefined camphor is of a lighter
                    colour than that obtained from Formosa, and commands a higher price in the
                    market. Crude camphor is submitted to a process of refining by sublimation from
                    a small quantity of sand, charcoal, iron-filings, or lime. The operation is
                    conducted in glass vessels of peculiar form, to the upper part of which the
                    sublimate adheres. It requires to be conducted with great care on account of the
                    peculiarly inflammable nature of the product, and the heat must be carefully
                    regulated to produce a solid compact cake.</p>
                <p>Borneo camphor, or Barus camphor, is a variety differing entirely in its source,
                    being the produce of <hi rend="italic">Drydbalanops Camphora,</hi> and also
                    somewhat removed in its chemical constitution aud physical properties from the
                    ordinary variety. It is obtained in its concrete form in fissures in old trees,
                    which are cut down and split up in search of it. The tree is a native of the
                    Malay peninsula, and is found chiefly in certain parts of Borneo and Sumatra.
                    Borneo camphor is extravagantly prized by the Chinese, who readily pay one
                    hundred times more for this variety than for ordinary camphor.</p>
                <p>A third variety of camphor, scarcely known beyond China, but there called Ngai
                    camphor, has been ascertained by the late Mr D. Hanbury to be the product, in
                    part at least, of <hi rend="italic">Blumea balsamifera.</hi> In chemical
                    composition it is the same as Borneo camphor, but differs from it iu respect of
                    odour, greater hardness, and higher volatility. In China it occupies in respect
                    of value an intermediate place between ordinary and Borneo camphor.</p>
                <p>Camphor is extensively employed in medicine both internally and externally as a
                    stimulant, but its chief medicinal use is in the preparation of liniments, into
                    the composition of many of which it enters. It has a vulgar reputation as a
                    prophylactic, on which account it is in great demand during serious epidemics.
                    It possesses properties invaluable to naturalists and others for keeping furs,
                    skins, and other animal substances free from moths; and it similarly preserves
                    cabinets of insects from attack. A very large quantity of camphor is consumed in
                    India, and generally throughout the East.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
