<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0904-0714-0643-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb09_v1.1">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAIRNES, John Elliott</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">9th edition, volume 4, page 643</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.1">Version 1.1 <date when="2025">2025</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>486 MB; 17,775 XML files</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2025">2025</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                            Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                            >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                            sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                            ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                            Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                            when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                            type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                            <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="12" ref="fasttopic:880656">Cost</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1018631">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:915437">Essays</term>
                    <term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1198491">Essay</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:978902">Irish</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:821510">Australians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205427">Ireland</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4s17sw59">Essays</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fz4p">Irish</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4cz32806">Fall</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b44m91b3s">Gold</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b47m04609">Power</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b4cc0tw1v">Cost</term>
                    <term n="12" ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q67d">Costs</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b49882p6v">Methodism</term>
                    <term n="7" ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change status="public" when="2025-08-15" who="#pml">v1.1. Isolates one entry;
                    corrects "B.c." and variants; replaces "bom" with "born", removed 783 instances
                    of extra space before semicolon. Separates metadata in <gi>teiHeader</gi> into
                    two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
                <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL
                    finished</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n714/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAIRNES, <hi rend="smallcaps">John Elliott</hi></label>, a
                    distinguished political economist, was born at Drogheda in 1824, and died on the
                    8th July 1875. After leaving school he spent some years in the counting-house of
                    his father, who was an extensive brewer. His tastes, however, lay altogether in
                    the direction of study, and he was permitted to enter Trinity College, Dublin.
                    He took the degree of B.A. in 1848, and six years later commenced as Μ. A. After
                    passing through the curriculum of arts he engaged in the study of law and was
                    called to the Irish bar. But he does not appear to have felt any very strong
                    inclination for the legal profession, and during some years he occupied himself
                    to a large extent with contributions to the daily press, treating of the social
                    and economical questions that affected Ireland. The subject to which at this
                    time he devoted most attention was political economy, which he studied with
                    great thoroughness and care. While residing in Dublin he made the acquaintance
                    of Archbishop Whately, who conceived a very high respect for his character and
                    abilities. In 1856 a vacancy occurred in the chair of Political Economy at
                    Dublin founded by Whately, and Cairnes received the appointment. In accordance
                    with the regulations of the foundation, the lectures of his first year’s course
                    were published. The book appeared in 1857, with the title <hi rend="italic"
                    >Character and Logical Method of Political Economy,</hi> and did not, perhaps,
                    receive so much attention as it deserved. It follows up and expands J. S. Mill’s
                    treatment in the <hi rend="italic">Essays on some Unsettled Questions in
                    Political Economy,</hi> and forms a most admirable introduction to the study of
                    economics as a science. In it the author’s peculiar powers of thought and
                    expression are displayed to the best advantage. Logical exactness, precision of
                    language, and firm grasp of the true nature of economic facts, are the qualities
                    characteristic of this as of all his other works. If the book had done nothing
                    more, it would still have conferred inestimable benefit on political economists
                    by its clear exposition of the true nature and meaning of the ambiguous term
                    law. To the view of the province and method of political economy expounded in
                    this early work the author always remained true, and several of his later
                    essays, such as those on <hi rend="italic">Political Economy and Land, Political
                    Economy and LaissezrFaire,</hi> are but reiterations of the same doctrine.</p>
                <p>His next contribution to economical science was a series of articles on the gold
                    question, published partly in <hi rend="italic">Fraser’s Magazine,</hi> in which
                    the probable consequences of the increased supply of gold attendant on the
                    Australian and Californian gold discoveries are analyzed with great skill and
                    ability. The general conclusions arrived at in these papers with regard to the
                    effects of the depreciation of gold—that finished manufactures would be on the
                    average least altered in price; that raw produce, particularly the portion
                    derived from the animal kingdom, would be most seriously affected; and that, on
                    the whole, the section of the population most nearly concerned in the movement
                    would be the class of labourers or artisans—are highly interesting, and have
                    been confirmed to a remarkable extent by recent statistical researches. The
                    further inferences drawn as to the international results likely to follow on the
                    introduction into the several currencies of so large a mass of gold have not
                    been borne out to the same extent. The facts were too complex to admit of
                    accurate prediction. The articles attracted much attention at the time, and were
                    highly commended by the most competent judges. A critical article on Μ.
                    Chevalier’s work <hi rend="italic">On the Probable Fall in the Value of
                    Gold,</hi> which appeared in the <hi rend="italic">Edinburgh Review</hi> for
                    July 1860, may be regarded as the sequel to these papers.</p>
                <p>In 1861 Cairnes was appointed to the professorship of political economy and
                    jurisprudence in Queen’s College, Galway, and in the following year he published
                    his admirable work <hi rend="italic">The Slave Power,</hi> one of the finest
                    specimens of applied economical philosophy. The inherent disadvantages of the
                    employment of slave labour are exposed with great fulness and ability, and the
                    conclusions arrived at have taken their place among the recognized doctrines of
                    political economy. To a very large extent the opinions expressed by Cairnes as
                    to the probable issue of the war in America were verified by the actual course
                    of events.</p>
                <p>During the remainder of his residence at Galway Professor Cairnes published
                    nothing beyond some fragments and pamphlets, mainly upon Irish questions in
                    which he was deeply interested. The most valuable of these papers are the series
                    devoted to the consideration of university education in Ireland. His health, at
                    no time very good, was still further weakened in 1865 by a fall from his horse,
                    which inflicted severe injury on one of his legs. He was ever afterwards
                    incapacitated from active exertion, and was constantly liable to have his work
                    interfered with by attacks of illness. In 1866 he was appointed professor of
                    political economy in University College, London. He was compelled to spend the
                    session 1868-69 in Italy, but on his return continued to lecture till 1872.
                    During his last session he conducted a mixed class, ladies being admitted to his
                    lectures. His health soon rendered it impossible for him to discharge his public
                    duties; he resigned his post in 1872, and retired with the honorary title of
                    Emeritus Professor of Political Economy. In 1873 his own university conferred on
                    him the degree of LL.D.</p>
                <p>The last years of his life were spent in the collection and publication of some
                    scattered papers contributed to various reviews and magazines, and in the
                    preparation of his most extensive and important work. The <hi rend="italic"
                    >Political Essays,</hi> published in 1873, comprise all the papers relating to
                    Ireland and its university system, together with some other articles of a
                    somewhat similar nature. The <hi rend="italic">Essays in Political Economy,
                    Theoretical and Applied,</hi> which appeared in the same year, contain the
                    essays towards a solution of the gold question, brought up to date and tested by
                    comparison with statistics of prices. Among the other articles in the volume the
                    more important are the criticisms on Bastiat and Comte, and the Essays on <hi
                    rend="italic">Political Economy and Land,</hi> and on <hi rend="italic"
                    >Political Economy and Laissez-Faire,</hi> which have been referred to above. In
                    1874 appeared his largest work, <hi rend="italic">Some Leading Principles of
                    Political Economy, newly Expounded,</hi> which is beyond doubt a <pb break="no"
                    facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n715/mode/1up"
                    xml:id="kp-eb0904-0715-0644"/> worthy successor to the great treatises of Smith,
                    Malthus, Ricardo, and Μ ill. It does not expound a completed system of political
                    economy; many important doctrines are left untouched; and in general the
                    treatment of problems is not such as would be suited for a systematic manual.
                    The work is essentially a commentary on some of the principal doctrines of the
                    English school of economists, such as value, cost of production, wages, labour
                    and capital, and international values, and is replete with keen criticism and
                    lucid illustration. While in fundamental harmony with Mill, especially as
                    regards the general conception of the science, Cairnes differs from him to a
                    greater or less extent on nearly all the cardinal doctrines, subjects his
                    opinions to a searching examination, and generally succeeds in giving to the
                    truth that is common to both a firmer basis and a more precise statement The
                    last labour to which he devoted himself was a republication of his first work on
                    the <hi rend="italic">Logical Method of Political Economy,</hi> which had long
                    been out of print. The second edition appeared tn April, a few months before the
                    author’s untimely death.</p>
                <p>Taken as a whole the works of Cairnes form the most important contribution to
                    economical science made by the English school since the publication of J. S.
                    Mill’s <hi rend="italic">Principles.</hi> As has been already pointed out, they
                    possess especial value by reason of the writer’s firmgraspof thenature, method,
                    and limits of the science he is engaged in expounding It is not possible to
                    indicate more than generally the special advances in economic doctrine effected
                    by him, but the following points may be noted as establishing for him a claim to
                    a place alongside of Ricardo and Mill :—(1.) His exposition of the province and
                    method of political economy. He never suffers it to be forgotten that political
                    economy is a <hi rend="italic">science,</hi> and consequently that its results
                    are entirely neutral with respect to social facts or systems. It has simply to
                    trace the necessary connections among the phenomena of wealth, and dictates no
                    rules for practice. Further, he is distinctly opposed both to those who would
                    treat political economy as an integral part of social philosophy, and to those
                    who have attempted to express economic facts in quantitative formulae, and to
                    make economy a branch of applied mathematics. According to him political economy
                    is a mixed science, its field being partly mental, partly physical. It may be
                    called a positive science, because its premises are facts, but it is
                    hypothetical in so far as the laws it lays down are only approximately true, <hi
                    rend="italic">i.e.,</hi> are only valid in the absence of counteracting
                    agencies. From this view of the nature of the science, it follows at once that
                    the method to be pursued must be that called by Mill the Physical or Concrete
                    Deductive, which starts from certain known causes, investigates their
                    consequences, and verifies or tests the result by comparison with facts of
                    experience. It may, perhaps, be thought that Cairnes gives too little attention
                    to the effects of the organism of society on economic facts, and that he is
                    disposed to overlook what have recently been called by Mr Bagehot the postulates
                    of political economy. (2.) His analysis of cost of production in its relation to
                    value. According to Mill, the universal elements in cost of production are the
                    wages of labour and the profits of capital. To this theory Cairnes objects that
                    wages, being <hi rend="italic">remuneration,</hi> can in no sense be considered
                    as <hi rend="italic">cost,</hi> and could only have come to be regarded as cost
                    in consequence of the whole problem being treated from the point of view of the
                    capitalist, to whom, no doubt, the wages paid represent cost. The real elements
                    of cost of production he looks upon as labour, abstinence, and risk, the second
                    of these falling mainly, though not necessarily, upon the capitalist. In this
                    analysis he to a considerable extent follows and improves upon Senior, who had
                    previously defined cost of production as the sum of the labour and abstinence
                    necessary to production. (3.) His exposition of the natural or social limit to
                    free competition, and of its bearing on the theory of value. He points out that
                    in any organized society there can hardly be the ready transference of capital
                    from one employment to another, which is the indispensable condition of free
                    competition; while class distinctions render it impossible for labour to
                    transfer itself readily to new occupations. Society may thus be regarded as
                    consisting of a series of non-competing industrial groups, with free competition
                    among the members of any one group or class. Now the only condition under which
                    cost of production will regulate value is perfect competition. It follows that
                    the normal value of commodities—the value which gives to the producers the
                    average and usual remuneration—will depend upon cost of production only when the
                    exchange is confined to the members of one class, among whom there is free
                    competition. In exchange between classes, or noncompeting industrial groups, the
                    normal value is simply a case of international value, and depends upon
                    reciprocal demand, that is to say, is such as will satisfy the equation of
                    demand. This theory is a substantial contribution to economical science, and
                    throws great light upon the general problem of value. At the same time, it may
                    be thought that Cairnes has overlooked a point brought forward prominently by
                    Senior, who also had called attention to the bearing of competition on the
                    relation between cost of production and value. The cost to the producer fixes
                    the limit below which the price cannot fall without the supply being affected;
                    but it is the desire of the consumer—i.e., what he is willing to give up rather
                    than be compelled to produce the commodity for himself—that fixes the maximum
                    value of the article. To treat the whole problem of natural or normal value from
                    the point of view of the producer is to give but a one-sided theory of the
                    facts. (4.) His defence of the wages fund doctrine. This doctrine, expounded by
                    Mill in his <hi rend="italic">Principles,</hi> has not been universally accepted
                    even by British economists, and has recently been assailed with great vigour by
                    Thornton and F. D. Longe. In consequence of these attacks it has been
                    relinquished by Mill, but Caírnes still undertakes to defend it. He certainly
                    succeeds in removing from the theory much that has tended to obscure its real
                    meaning, and in placing it in its very best aspect. He has also shown the sense
                    in which, when treating the problem of wages, we must refer to some fund devoted
                    to the payment of wages, and has pointed out the conditions under which the
                    wages fund may increase or decrease. But he has not, it seems to us, been
                    successful in showing that the theory is fruitful, or gives any satisfactory
                    explanation of the many complicated questions connected with the varying rates
                    of wages.</p>
                <p>These points, of course, do not comprehend all or nearly all that Cairnes has
                    handled in his peculiarly fresh and attractive manner. <hi rend="italic">The
                    Leading Principles,</hi> for instance, contain admirable discussions on trades
                    unions and protection, together with a clear analysis of the difficult theory of
                    international trade and value, in which there is much that is both novel and
                    valuable, while numerous minor topics are treated throughout the volume. The <hi
                    rend="italic">Logical Method</hi> contains the best exposition and defence known
                    to us of Ricardo’s theory of rent; and the <hi rend="italic">Essays</hi> contain
                    what is probably the most complete and successful criticism of Bastiat’s
                    economic doctrines. <hi rend="smallcaps">(r. ad.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
