<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0904-0801-0726-03" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">CAMBRIDGE, County of (9th edition, volume 4, page
                    726)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 9th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2023"
                    >2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>267 MB; 17,772 XML files in 47 folders </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://tu-plogan.github.io/index.html"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/12465694" xml:id="mn">Baynes, T.
                                Spencer (Thomas Spencer), <date from="1823" to="1887"
                                    >1823-1887</date></persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Ninth Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="25" unit="vol">25 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Charles Scribner's Sons</publisher>
                        <authority>Authorized reprint from Edinburgh plates</authority>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1875" to="1889">1875-1889</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="ia-uc"><title>Encyclopaedia Britannica: a dictionary of arts,
                                sciences, and general literature</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/">Internet Archive</orgName><orgName
                                    ref="https://archive.org/details/cdl">University of California
                                    Libraries, California Digital Library</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2006</date><idno type="OCLC">592355607</idno><idno
                                type="ark">13960/t0ks6j612</idno><availability>
                                <p>Internet Archive: NOT_IN_COPYRIGHT</p>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <desc>Alternate images of the same print editions were substituted when the
                        primary source had unusable images for those pages.</desc>
                    <bibl xml:id="um-ht">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Michigan: vol. 14, pp. 34-35; vol. 15, pp. 170-171.</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for future entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding uses the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in Libraries
                            Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike-through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s53t">Normans</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bc3t08d">Dykes</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zw18v1m">War</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4h98zp4v">Wars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4086351k">Larks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4bz61762">Leveling</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996970">Levellers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:996964">Leveling</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1035721">Nene</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:899678">Dutch</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1039127">Normans</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1207649">Wales</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-28" who="#pml">v.1 published</change>
            <change status="public" when="2023-02-27" who="#pml">v.1 teiHeader XSL finished</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n801/mode/1up" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">CAMBRIDGE, <hi rend="smallcaps">County of</hi></label>, one
                    of the smaller English counties, belonging to the South Midland division of
                    England, is about 45 miles in length and 30 in breadth. It comprises 17
                    hundreds, and the boroughs of Cambridge and Wisbeach. There are in the county,
                    which is embraced within the diocese of Ely, 172 parishes and townships, besides
                    parts of parishes. It contains, according to the census of 1871, 524,926 statute
                    acres. It is divided by the old course of the River Ouse into Cambridge proper
                    and the <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n802/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0802-0727"/> Isle of Ely. Until the year 1857 the Isle of
                    Ely was practically a county palatine, like the county palatine of Chester and
                    the bishopric of Durham, a distinct enclosure within the county. The liberty of
                    the Isle of Ely has its court of quarter sessions, a separate commission of the
                    peace, and its own county rate. The county, which is purely agricultural, and
                    for the most part arable, presents a vast land expanse, with little that is
                    picturesque and with no claims to fine scenery, but imposing to the summer
                    tourist by the frequent pollarded watercourses, the heavy crops of grain, and
                    the immense dome of sky.</p>
                <p>Cambridgeshire evidently once formed part of the country of the Iceni. The
                    Icenhilde, always a British way, and never a via strata, was most probably
                    derived from the same root. The country is rich in Roman roads and other
                    remains, and some of the Roman roads were doubtless formed on old British
                    tracks. (For the ancient roads consult Professor Babington’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Monographs</hi> Cambridgeshire became a dependency of the kingdom of East
                    Anglia. It was included in the Danelagh, though how far it was colonized by
                    Northmen is uncertain. According to Henry of Huntingdon, in the war against the
                    Danes, when the English fled the men of Cambridgeshire resisted most manfully.
                    During the period of the Conquest, the siege and capture of the Isle of Ely is
                    the most remarkable event; the sea country was the last that yielded to the
                    Conqueror, and the half-legendary Hereward is the last English hero of the
                    conflict. In the time of Stephen, in the time of John, and in the time of the
                    Barons’ War in the reign of Henry III., the Isle of Ely emerges repeatedly into
                    notice. The splendid foundations of Etheldreda and her sister, with the rising
                    colleges of the university of Cambridge, drew pilgrims to the district from all
                    parts of the country. In the Civil War Cambridgeshire belonged to the associated
                    counties, and had no actual share in the conflict. Cromwell possessed a
                    considerable estate in the Isle of Ely, and lived in the rectory house of Ely
                    till elected member for Cambridge. He became governor of Ely, and his son Henry
                    died in the neighbourhood (Carlyle’s <hi rend="italic">Cromwell).</hi> King
                    Charles, after his seizure at Ξoldenby, was brought to Childerly near Cambridge,
                    and was taken thence to Newmarket, near which the Parliamentary army was
                    encamped under Fairfax and Cromwell.</p>
                <p>The drainage of the Cambridgeshire fens forms one of the most remarkable chapters
                    of the industrial history of the country. All the northern portion of the
                    county, at the junction of the counties of Lincoln, Huntingdon, Cambridge, and
                    Norfolk, is part of the vast district known as the Great Level of the Fens. A
                    large province of 680,000 acres of the richest land in England has been
                    reclaimed from the sea and preserved by continual watchfulness, as completely as
                    is the case in the opposite kingdom of Holland. The great works which have
                    reclaimed the land were mainly due to Cornelius Vermuyden, the Dutchman,
                    knighted by Charles I., and the Dutch and Flemings he employed, and in more
                    recent times to James Rennie, the eminent engineer. The chief promoters were
                    five successive earls of Bedford, who have given their name to the great Bedford
                    Level. From the earliest times, however, there had been conflicts between the
                    encroaching waters and the inhabitants of the invaded shores. The Romans, who
                    left few great works unattempted, reclaimed much of the rich silt and soil
                    deposited on the shores of the Wash, and constructed the immense drainage work
                    known as the Carr (Fen) Dyke. They also carried causeways over the fen country.
                    Much of the Roman work seems to have lapsed into the “great dismal swamp,”
                    caused by the silting up of the outfalls of rivers, and the mingling of the
                    tides with the upland waters. The submerged territory seems originally to have
                    been rich meadow and forest land, and it receives the river deposits of soil
                    from eight counties, the causes of the great and abiding fertility. All this
                    region then formed an immense estuary, the Wash, or rather a large lake,
                    communicating by shifting channels with the sea. The more elevated grounds were
                    called islands, whose isolation sometimes invited the founders of religious
                    edifices, and sometimes those without the pale of the law. The whole country
                    from Cambridge to Lincoln was a morass abounding with fish and fowl, and all the
                    scattered habitations of the fenmen were liable to be swept away by sudden
                    storms.</p>
                <p>The monasteries and the bishops of Ely did good work in the reclamation of lands.
                    Morton’s Learn was a canal made by Bishop Morton of forty miles from
                    Peterborough to the sea, which drained the North Level. After the dissolution of
                    the monasteries the work fell into abeyance until renewed by Cornelius
                    Vermuyden. The fenmen vehemently opposed his plans, and Oliver Cromwell, the
                    member for Cambridge, put himself at their head and succeeded in stopping all
                    the operations. When he became protector, however, he sanctioned Vermuyden’s
                    plans, and Scotch prisoners taken at Dunbar, and Dutch prisoners taken by Blake
                    in his victory over Van Tromp, were employed as the workers. Much valuable land
                    was reclaimed, and the fen country altogether improved. There remained, however,
                    very much to be done. Vermuyden’s system was exclusively Dutch; and while
                    perfectly suited to Holland it did not meet all the necessities of East Anglia.
                    He confined his attention almost exclusively to the inland draining and
                    embankments, and did not provide sufficient out-let for the waters themselves
                    into the sea. So late as 1810 there were districts in which people reaped their
                    harvest, and gathered their orchard fruits, and went to church, in boats. Rennie
                    pointed out the true scientific principle that a thorough drainage could only be
                    effected by cutting down the outfalls to low water at spring tides, and so
                    facilitating the escape of the waters. He projected a great system of drainage
                    and provided a more effectual outfall of the Ouse into the Wash. His work was
                    improved and extended by Telford.</p>
                <p>Throughout the present century great improvements of all kinds have been carried
                    on. The surplus waters were formerly pumped into the rivers and canals by
                    windmills; but this could not be counted on as an invariable force, and
                    steam-mills are generally substituted. Dykes, causeways, sluices, and drains
                    were now cut in every direction. All the rivers of Cambridgeshire which formerly
                    found their outlet at Wisbeach, before the channel was choked up, now mainly by
                    cuts and straightenings, have forsaken their old beds and are poured into the
                    sea by artificial streams, like the Bedford rivers into the German Ocean.</p>
                <p>It will be interesting to enumerate the original courses of the streams; it is
                    not always easy to decipher the natural channels. The chief rivers are the Nene
                    and the Ouse, with its tributary streams. The Nene on arriving at Peterborough
                    turned to the right, and making a circuit of several meres passed by March to
                    Wisbeach. It is now made to flow into three channels. One arm is the Cats-water
                    or Shire Drain, which meets Morton Learn and flows into the Wash; the second arm
                    is Whittlesey Dyke, or the old Nene river; the third is Morton’s Learn. The
                    Great Ouse enters the Fens near Earith, where it formerly forked; one branch
                    ultimately joined the Nene; the other branch was called the West Water, and
                    ultimately joined the main channel of the Nene. Both the channels are now nearly
                    closed to the waters of the Ouse, and are carried by the Bedford rivers in a
                    direct line to Denver, where they meet the channel of the Little Ouse, and só
                        <pb break="no" facs="ia:encyclopediabrit04newyrich/page/n803/mode/1up"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0904-0803-0728"/> roach the sea at King’s Lynn. The Cam or
                    Granta, formed :»y the junction of some small Essex streams, flows N.N.E. from
                    Cambridge, changing its name to Ouse three miles from Ely, but instead of
                    flowing into the sea at Wisbeach is carried on to Denver, and thence to the sea
                    at Lynn. The Lark for seven miles separates Cambridgeshire from Suffolk, and the
                    Linnet, a feeder of the Lark, also serves as a boundary stream for another
                    stretch of seven miles.</p>
                <p>All the northern part of Cambridgeshire, the fen country, is covered with
                    alluvial deposits resting on a bed of clay of great but unknown thickness. These
                    are called the Kimmeridge and Oxford clays, the Oxford clay lying below the
                    Kimmeridge. There is no break of continuity between them; they are only
                    distinguished by the embodied fossils above the clay. There is a deposit of peat
                    of variable thickness, but generally very deep. South and east the Fens are
                    bordered by a narrow belt of Kimmeridge clay, beyond which is a strip of lower
                    and then of upper greensand; and beyond this, in the southern division of the
                    country, we have the chalk. In the fen country there are great masses of gravel,
                    sand, and drift-clay. “We can trace the rise of the fen lands through the
                    deposits of landfloods, and the growth of fuel-bogs” (Professor Sedgwick).
                    Besides these regular formations and deposits Cambridgeshire contains much
                    diluvial deposit, not to be accounted for by land-floods or tides and currents,
                    but belonging to the glacial period. The uplands or so-called “highlands” of
                    Cambridgeshire are level, but broken by low chalk hills in the neighbourhood of
                    Essex and Suffolk. The chalk is in two divisions,—upper with flints, lower
                    without flints. At the foot of the hills the lower bed of chalk has been
                    extensively quarried, and much elaborate· sculpture in Ely Cathedral has been
                    formed of it. The thin upper greensand below the lower chalk rests on gault.
                    This formation everywhere constitutes the northern border of the chalk, and in
                    the western portion of the country forms rich, well-wooded soil. The gault is
                    the blue brick earth of Cambridge, and has a thickness of 150 feet. Professor
                    Sedgwick has given a careful account of the fossils found in these formations,
                    and there is an ample collection of examples in the Woodwardian Museum. In deep
                    diggings in the fen lands, and in excavations for buildings in Cambridge gravel,
                    remains are discovered of the wolf, bear, horse, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >bos</hi><hi rend="italic">primigenius.</hi> Diluvial beds of loam mixed
                    with fragments of chalk extend into the parts of Cambridgeshire adjacent to
                    Essex and Suffolk. Along the irregular line separating Cambridgeshire from these
                    counties the iron-sand which underlies the gault rises to the surface. It forms
                    excellent garden ground, and is rich in fragments of mineralized wood (Conybeare
                    and Phillip’s <hi rend="italic">Geology of England and Wales).</hi>
                    Cambridgeshire is one of the chief corn-producing counties. A part of the county
                    near the south-west border was formerly called the Dairies; and large dairy
                    farms are still found producing cheese very similar to the best Stilton. The
                    census of 1871 returned 25 per cent, of the male population as agricultural
                    labourers, farmservants, and shepherds. Although the county is entirely
                    agricultural, mainly arable, with some wheat and pasture crops, many busy trades
                    are also carried on,—brewing and malting, brick-making, lime-burning. There is a
                    great deal of boat-building, and there are many seamen employed on the navigable
                    cuts. The climate of the county is generally healthy, but it would be premature
                    to say that ague is altogether banished from the fen country.</p>
                <p>Some reference has already been made to the British and Roman antiquities. There
                    are some remains of Roman camps; a few only of Norman castles. In the southern
                    part of the county are four great dykes. They once formed the boundary between
                    East Anglia and Mercia; each extended from fen land to wooded country, crossing
                    the open intervening space. The chief of these fosses was the Devil’s Ditch;
                    another was the Fleam or Balsham Dyke; the others were the ditches of Breat and
                    Bran. All these were most probably of British origin. The county of Cambridge is
                    rich in churches, especially in Ely and Cambridge and their neighbourhoods. We
                    have abundant examples of Pre-Norman, Norman, Early English, Decorated,
                    Perpendicular. At Ely there are some valuable monastic remains. The famous Abbey
                    of Thorney is only represented by various foundations, and a fragment of the
                    abbey church, which has been worked into the present parish church. Of domestic
                    architecture there are very slight.remains in one or two manor houses, and some
                    remains of the Episcopal palace at Downham. The modern architectural efforts may
                    well compete with those of any former age.</p>
                <p>Though Cambridge is the county town, Ely is the one city of Cambridgeshire. It
                    derived its name from the abundance of the eels which were found there. It was
                    situated on the largest of the islands that rose above the level of the Fens,
                    which in winter were surrounded by water, and were only accessible by certain
                    passes or gates. (See <hi rend="smallcaps">Ely.)</hi> The other Cambridgeshire
                    towns are soon enumerated. Wisbeach (beach of the Ouse) is a large and
                    prosperous town, next in size and population to Cambridge. The navigable River
                    Nene intersects the town and makes it a port. The main export is grain; the main
                    import is Baltic timber. The Wisbeach canal gives water communication in many
                    directions. Newmarket has a somewhat peculiar reputation, and is called the
                    metropolis of the turf. The race course is four miles in length, of elastic
                    turf; some hundred horses may be seen exercising on the Downs. There are seven
                    race meetings in the year. This and the neighbouring town of Royston, on the
                    borders of Hertfordshire, have been often frequented by royalty; many houses are
                    inhabited by patrons of the turf. Our literature abounds with references to
                    Newmarket, which, truth to say, are as a rule of an unflattering description.
                    Wimpole Park, Lord Hardwicke’s place, is the principal seat in the county, and
                    the fine park has some of the best timber in the country. Wimpole is celebrated
                    for its pictures, and there is a good library. The principal other proprietors
                    are the dukes of Bedford and Rutland and Mr Childers. Doddington was till
                    recently the richest living in England, but the revenues are now spread over
                    seven rectories. The village of Babra-han is celebrated as the first place in
                    England where water irrigation was introduced, and also for the breed of
                    Southdown sheep which bears the name. Whittlesea Mere is the most remarkable of
                    the modern reclamation; there abundant crops are raised where boating and
                    fishing were carried on within living memory. Whittlesea West is still covered
                    with water many months in the year, when there is abundance of waterfowl. The
                    ancient town of March should be noticed, also Chatteris, Thorney, Johan,
                    formerly famous for their abbeys. The town of Thorney was greatly improved and
                    beautified by a former duke of Bedford. In 1875 the county was under the
                    ownership of 6497 proprietors of one acre and upwards, and of 6677 proprietors
                    of less than one acre. For parliamentary purposes the two divisions of the shire
                    and isle form one district, returning three members to parliament. The
                    population of the county in 1861, as compared with 1851, exhibited a decrease of
                    5 per cent., but in 1871 an improvement was manifested to the extent of 6 per
                    cent. The rate of progress is slow, and it is hardly likely to be accelerated,
                    By the census of 1871 the population consisted of 186,906 persons,—of whom
                    92,115 were males, and 94,791 females. <hi rend="smallcaps">(f.</hi> A.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
