<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="kp-eb0718-2424-0773-01" xml:lang="en"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.1"><title level="a" type="main">QUALITY</title><title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 18, page 773</title><editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282" role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor><respStmt><orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName><resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName><resp>metadata development</resp></respStmt><respStmt><persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName><resp>data management</resp></respStmt><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National Endowment
                        for the Humanities</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of Museum
                        and Library Services</orgName></funder><funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder><sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci">Drexel
                        University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition n="3.1">Version 3.1<date when="2025">2025</date></edition></editionStmt><extent>416 MB; 21,118 XML files </extent><publicationStmt><publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher><availability status="free"><p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence></availability><date when="2025">2025</date></publicationStmt><seriesStmt><title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title><editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor></seriesStmt><sourceDesc><biblFull xml:lang="en"><titleStmt><title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title><editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor></titleStmt><editionStmt><edition>Seventh Edition</edition></editionStmt><extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent><publicationStmt><publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher><pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace><date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838">National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability><p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence></availability></bibl></sourceDesc></biblFull><listBibl><head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head><bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl><bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl></listBibl></sourceDesc></fileDesc><encodingDesc><editorialDecl><ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic"><item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            "TEI in Libraries Guidelines."</item><item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item><item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item><item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is
                            not captured dependably and the results should not be relied
                            upon.</item><item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas.
                            The uncorrected results remain in the text.</item><item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                            <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                            <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles
                            are ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item></list></ab><correction method="markup" status="low"><p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p><p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p><p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p></correction><normalization method="silent"><p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p></normalization><punctuation marks="some"><p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p><p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p></punctuation><quotation marks="some"><p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p></quotation><hyphenation eol="hard"><p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p></hyphenation><segmentation><p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p><p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p></segmentation></editorialDecl><tagsDecl><namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage></namespace></tagsDecl><projectDesc><p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p><p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p></projectDesc><samplingDecl><p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p></samplingDecl><listPrefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)" replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)" replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p></prefixDef><prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)" replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1"><p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p></prefixDef></listPrefixDef></encodingDesc><profileDesc><textClass default="false"><keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/"><term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1140317">Swifts</term><term n="1" ref="fasttopic:839044">British</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1091272">Reason</term><term n="8" ref="fasttopic:1091282">Reasoning</term><term n="7" ref="fasttopic:1015978">Men</term><term n="5" ref="fasttopic:1121907">Snow</term><term n="4" ref="fasttopic:884853">Cube</term></keywords><keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/"><term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b4vd6p635">Swifts</term><term n="10" ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86m8z">Man</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b4zg6gc5h">Reason</term><term n="8" ref="lcsh1910:b46688j6x">Reasoning</term><term n="5" ref="lcsh1910:b4mc8rn70">Snow</term><term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hh6c946">Sphere</term></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc status="published"><listChange><change n="3.1" status="public" when="2025-06-05" who="#pml">v3.1. Isolates two
                    additional entries; restores <gi>label</gi> tags to 6 entries; makes minor
                    corrections throughout.</change><change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change><change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change><change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change></listChange></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><body><div facs="nls:193542424" type="entry"><p><label type="entry">QUALITY</label> is a word which, as used in philosophical
                    disquisitions, cannot be explained by any periphrasis. That which is expressed
                    by it must be brought into the immediate view of the senses or intellect, and
                    the name properly applied, or he who is a stranger to the .word will never be
                    made to comprehend its meaning. Aristotle, who treated it as a general
                    conception, second in order amongst the ten predicaments or categories, gives
                    several characters of it; but though they are all in some respects just, no man
                    could from them, without other assistance, learn what quality is.</p><p>When a man comprehends, by means of his senses and intellect, what it is that the
                    word <hi rend="italic">quality</hi> denotes, he will indeed perceive that the
                    first of these characters is applicable to some qualities and not to others;
                    that the second is more applicable to quantity than to quality; and that, it is
                    only the third which can with propriety be considered as <hi rend="subscript">
                    1</hi> the general characteristic of this predicament. Thus, when we have
                    learned by our sense of sight that whiteness is a quality of snow, and blackness
                    of coal; and, by means of observation and reflection, that wisdom is a quality
                    of one man, and folly of another; we must admit that the sensible quality of the
                    snow is contrary to that of the coal, and that the intellectual quality of
                    wisdom is contrary to that of folly. There is, however, no contrariety between
                    wisdom and whiteness or blackness, nor between hardness or softness and any
                    particular colour; for sensible and intellectual qualities can never be
                    compared, and it is not easy, if indeed it be possible, to make a comparison
                    between qualities perceptible only by different senses. Nay, amongst qualities
                    perceptible by the same sense, we often meet with a difference where there is no
                    contrariety; for though the figure of a cube is different from that of a sphere,
                    and the figure of a square from that of a circle, the sphere is not contrary to
                    the cube, nor the circle to the square.</p><p>His second characteristic of this genus is still less proper than the first. It
                    is indeed true that some qualities admit of intension and remission; for snow is
                    whiter than paper, and one woman is handsomer than another; but of the species
                    of quality called figure we cannot predicate either more or less. A crown-piece
                    may have as much of the circular quality in it as the plane of the equator, and
                    a musket-bullet as much of the spherical quality as the orb of the sun. It is
                    indeed a property of all quantity to admit of intension and remission; and
                    therefore this ought to have been given as the character, not of the second, but
                    of the third category.</p><p>That it is only from a comparison of their qualities that things are denominated
                    like or unlike, or that one thing cannot resemble another but in some quality,
                    is indeed a just ohservation. We know nothing directly except qualities sensible
                    and intellectual (see <hi rend="smallcaps">Metaphysics)</hi>; and as these have
                    no resemblance to each other, we conclude that body or matter, the subject of
                    the former, is a being unlike mind, the subject of the latter. Even of bodies
                    themselves we can say that one is like or unlike another only by virtue of their
                    qualities. A ball of ivory resembles a ball of snow in its figure and colour,
                    but not in its coldness or hardness; a ball of lead may resemble a ball of snow
                    in its figure and coldness, but not in its colour; and a cube of ivory resembles
                    not a ball of lead either in figure, colour, or coldness. The mind of a brute
                    resembles that of a man in its powers of sensation and perception, but does not
                    resemble it in the powers of volition and reasoning; or at least the
                    resemblance, in this latter instance, is very slight. All bodies resemble one
                    another in being solid and extended, and all minds in being more or less active.
                    Likeness or unlikeness, therefore, is the universal characteristic of the
                    category <hi rend="italic">quality.</hi></p><p>Aristotle has other speculations respecting quality which are worthy of notice.
                    He distinguishes between qualities which are essential and those which are
                    accidental, between qualities which are natural and those which are acquired;
                    and he speaks of the qualities of capacity and those of completion. Extension
                    and figure in general are qualities essential to all bodies; but a particular
                    extension, such as an inch or an ell, and a particular figure, such as a cube or
                    a sphere, are qualities accidental to bodies. Amongst the natural qualities of
                    glass it is one to transmit objects of vision; but to enlarge these objects is
                    an adventitious or acquired quality. The same quality may be natural in one
                    substance, as attraction in the magnet; and acquired in <pb break="no" facs="nls:193542437" xml:id="kp-eb0718-2437-0774"/>another, as the
                    same attraction in the magnetic bar. Docility may be called a quality natural to
                    the mind of man, science an acquired one. To understand what he means by
                    qualities of capacity and completion, it may be sufficient to observe, that
                    every piece of iron has the qualities of a razor in capacity, because it may be
                    converted into steel, and formed into a razor; and when it is so formed, it has,
                    in the language of this sage, the quality of a razor in completion. Amongst the
                    qualities of capacity and completion, the most important, and what may lead to
                    interesting speculations, is the reasoning faculty of man. A capacity of
                    reasoning is essential to the human mind; but the completion of this capacity or
                    actual reasoning is not, otherwise infants and persons asleep would be excluded
                    from the human species.</p><p>Mr Locke has puzzled his readers with a question respecting the species of an
                    idiot or a changeling, w horn he pronounces to be something between a man and a
                    brute.<note anchored="true" place="bottom" type="authorial"><p>Book iv. chap. 4,
                    § 13, &amp;c.</p></note> It is not often that we feel ourselves inclined to
                    regret Locke’s ignorance of Aristotle’s distinctions; but we cannot help
                    thinking, that had the British philosopher attended to the Stagyrite’s account
                    of qualities in capacity and qualities in completion, this perplexing question
                    would never have been started. It is justly observed in the Essay upon Human
                    Understanding, that of real essences we know nothing, but that every man selects
                    a certain number of qualities which he has always perceived united in certain
                    beings, and, forming these into one complex conception, gives to this conception
                    a specific name, which he applies to every being in which he finds those
                    qualities united. This is undoubtedly the process of the mind in forming genera
                    and species; and as the excellent author refuses the name of man to the
                    changeling, it is obvious that the complex conception, to which he gives that
                    name, must imply rationality, or the actual exercise of reason. But this
                    limitation will exclude many beings from the species man, whom Mr Locke
                    certainly considered as men and women. Not to mention infants and persons in
                    sound sleep, how shall we class those who, after having lived thirty or forty
                    years in the full exercise of reason, have been suddenly or by degrees deprived
                    of it by some disorder in the brain?</p><p>From Marlborough’s eyes the streams of dotage flow, And Swift expires a driveller
                    and a show.</p><p>But were the hero and the wit in those deplorable circumstances excluded from the
                    human species, and classed between men and brutes? No, surely; they were both
                    acknowledged to be men, because they were known to have the quality of reason in
                    what Aristotle would have called capacity. Their dotage and drivelling
                    originated from some disorder in their bodies, probably in the region of the
                    brain; and Locke himself contends that no defect in body is sufficient to
                    degrade a person from the rank of manhood. Again, lunatics have the exercise of
                    reason, except at new and full moon. Are these unhappy beings sometimes men and
                    sometimes a species by themselves between men and brutes?</p><p>It appears, therefore, that not the actual exercise of reason, but reason in
                    capacity, ought to be included in the complex conception to which we give the
                    specific name of man, as some of the greatest men that ever lived have been
                    during parts of their lives deprived of the power of actual reasoning. This,
                    however, it will be said, does not remove the difficulty; for the occasional
                    exercise of reason in lunatics, and the great exertions of it in such men as
                    Swift and Marlborough, show that they had it in capacity at all times; whereas
                    we have no evidence that changelings have even a capacity of reasoning at any
                    time, since they never do a rational action, nor ever utter a sentence to the
                    purpose. That we have no direct and positive evidence of the minds of
                    changelings being capable of reasoning, were they supplied with proper organs,
                    must be granted; but the probabilities of their being so are many and great. We
                    know by experience that the actual exercise of reason may be interrupted by an
                    occasional and accidental pressure on the brain; and therefore we cannot doubt
                    but that if this pressure were rendered permanent by any wrong configuration of
                    the skull given to it in the womb, or in the act of being born into the world,
                    an infant, with a mind capable of reasoning by means of proper organs, would by
                    this accident be rendered, throughout the whole of life, an idiot or changeling.
                    That idiotism is caused by such accidents, and is not the quality of an inferior
                    mind occasionally given to a human body, will at∙least seem probable from the
                    íòllowing considerations. ,</p><p>It does not appear that an animal body can live and move except whilst it is
                    actuated by some mind. Whence, then, does the unborn infant derive its mind? It
                    must be either immediately from God, or <hi rend="italic">ex traduce</hi> from
                    its parents; but if the mind of man be immaterial, it cannot be <hi rend="italic">ex traduce.</hi> Now, as idiots are very few in number when
                    compared with the rational part of the human species, and as God in the
                    government of this world acts not by partial but by general laws, we must
                    conclude that the law which he has established respecting the union of mind and
                    matter is, that human bodies shall be animated with minds endowed with a
                    capacity of reasoning, and that those who never exert this capacity are
                    prevented by some such accident as we have assigned.</p></div></body></text></TEI>