<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-0368-0043-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ABRUZZO</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94m4s">Sea</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48w3845p">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4028pc5x">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4rb6w237">Running</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94c35">Extents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4r49gb4d">Church</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47d2q898">Churches</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1110395">Seas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:878993">Corn</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1124682">Soils</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1025853">Months</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1101348">Running</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1100116">Romans</term>
                    <term ref="fast:860364">Church</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193030368?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">ABRUZZO</label>, one of the four provinces into
                    which the continental part of the kingdom of Naples, or of the two Sicilies, was
                    formerly divided, but now the name given to three out of the 17 provinces of the
                    later division of that country. It is, with altered boundaries, now
                    distinguished as Abruzzo Ulteriore First, Abruzzo Ulteriore Second, and Abruzzo
                    Citeriore.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Abruzzo</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Ulteriore</hi>
                    First, is a maritime province on tlιe Adriatic Sea,»which is its boundary
                    towards the northcast. On the north-west the Papal dominions bound it, on the
                    south-east Abruzzo Citeriore, and on the southwest Abruzzo Ulteriore Second. The
                    western part of the province is very mountainous; the highest crest of the
                    Appcnines divides it from Abruzzo Ulteriore Second, and extends towards the sea.
                    The district on the sea-coast is flat, but everywhere else hilly. The valleys
                    between the hills possess a rich soil, well watered by rivulets and brooks in
                    the winter and spring, but which are generally dried up in the summer months.
                    These streams either run into the Pescara, which bounds the province towards
                    Abruzzo Citeriore, or into the Tronto, which is the boundary on the Papal
                    frontier. The extent of the province is 1140 square miles, or 730,600 English
                    acres. The cultivation is badly conducted, and many districts are almost left in
                    a state of natural wildness. The art of irrigation is not understood, nor
                    embankment of the rivers practised, so that the best of the land is often
                    rendered useless. There are owners of two or three hundred acres of land, who
                    scarcely raise sufficient food for their families; and yet the soil, when
                    tolerably managed, will yield 12 grains of wheat for one. The corn most
                    cultivated and preferred is maize. Hemp and flax are raised, but, like corn,
                    merely sufficient for the home supply. Olives, almonds, figs, grapes, and
                    chesnuts, are abundant, as is wood for construction and fuel. The number of
                    inhabitants is 157,339, according to the late census. They are a hardy, bold,
                    idle, and superstitious, race. The most industrious of them stroll yearly into
                    the territories of the Church to work at harvest and in making charcoal, and
                    return home in winter with their wages. The province is divided into two
                    districts, Teramo and Civita di Penne. The city of Teramo is the capital of the
                    province.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Abruzzo</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Ulteriore</hi>
                    Second, a province in the continental division of the kingdom of Naples. It is
                    an inland district, bounded on the north by the Papal States, on the north-east
                    by Abruzzo Ulteriore First, on the south-east by Abruzzo Citeriore, on the south
                    by the province Terra di Lavora, and on the west by the States of the Church,
                    The extent is 2210 square miles, or 1,414,400 acres. The whole province is
                    nearly covered with mountains of various heights, one of which, the Grand Casso
                    ďltalia, near Aquila, is the loftiest peak of the Appenines. There are no
                    plains; but among these mountains some beautiful and fruitful valleys have been
                    formed by the various streams that run through them. None of the rivers are
                    navigable, but all of them have abundance of water, except in the hottest of the
                    summer months. The largest frcsh lake of the kingdom is that of Cellano, 14
                    miles long, and 9 broad, surrounded with hills. A canal, built by the Romans to
                    carry off the surplus water, has been long neglected and stopped up, but is now
                    in course of being cleaned and opened. The air is generally temperate, and the
                    sirocco is never felt. The cultivation just suffices to provide sufficient corn
                    for the inhabitants, who, when the maize is dear, make out thcir subsistence by
                    the help of chesnuts. Olives and vines rarely bring their fruit to full
                    ripeness. Some flax and hemp are raised, and a vast quantity of saffron, which
                    is generally preferred to all other. The sheep produce fine wool when the flocks
                    migrate,.and the flesh is good. The cows·, yield good butter and cheese, which
                    form the chief articles of exportation to the neighbouring provinces. The
                    inhabitants amount to 249,600. Like all mountaineers, they are a strong and
                    active race, and frugal in their habits. The manufactures are insignificant,
                    consisting of some little woollen and linen cloth, some paper, pottery, and
                    wood-warc; but not sufficient of any for the demand of the territory, which is
                    supplied by the exchange of almonds, figs, saffron, wool, butter, and cheese.
                    The chief city is Aquila.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Abruzzo</hi><hi rend="smallcaps">Citeriore,</hi> a
                    province in the kingdom of Naples. It is bounded on the north-west by Abruzzo
                    Ulteriore First, on the north-east by the Adriatic Sea, on the south-west by the
                    province Molise, and on the west by that of Abruzzo Ulteriore Second. This
                    province is less hilly than the other two Abruzzos, but the Appenines are
                    extended through the south-west part. They, however, gradually decline in
                    height, and extend themselves in wide plains of sand and pebbles. The rivers <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193030381?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-0381-0044"
                    />all run to the Adriatic, and are very deficient in water during the summer
                    months. Agriculture is in a very backward state, and the soil is rather
                    ungrateful when ' labour is bestowed upon it; and the inhabitants prefer the
                    chase and the fishery to it. The corn is sufficient for the population, who grow
                    and consume much more maize and rice than wheat or barley. On the coast some oil
                    and some silk are produced, which, with wine, form the chief export articles.
                    Hemp, flax, liquorice, almonds, and figs, are grown for home consumption. The
                    cattle are more neglected than in the other Abruzzos, though there is excellent
                    pasture both for sheep and cows. There are, however, abundance of swine, goats,
                    and asses. The manufactures are very insignificant. All the exchange of
                    commodities is carried on by land; for though the province has an extensive
                    frontier to the sea, it has no harbour or secure anchoring places. The extent is
                    1920 square miles, or 1,228,800 acres. The inhabitants are 222,730. There is but
                    one decent road through the province. The capital is Civita di Chieti, formerly
                    called Teti.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
