<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-6543-0518-02" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALLAN, David</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1206715">Scotland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kk94k2c">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4w669c71">Views</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mr95">Art</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45q4rn8c">Mark</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4dz0341g">Customs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1050530">Painters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1166896">Views</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1048190">Originality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1133959">Stools</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1115813">Shepherds</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1126696">Sons</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193036543?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">ALLAN, <hi rend="smallcaps">David</hi></label>, a
                    Scotish historical painter of considerable eelebrity, was born at Alloa, on the
                    13th February 1744. At a very early age he showed sueh marks of genius as
                    attracted the notice of some gentlemen living in the neighbourhood. In a remote
                    part of the eountry, and deprived of the ordinary means of indulging his
                    propensity to drawing, he betook himself, when a boy, to sueh implements and
                    materials as he could readily procure; and the meehanical skill and taste whieh,
                    in particular, he displayed in using his knife, have been mentioned as
                    remarkable for his years. Mr Stewart, then collector of the Customs at Alloa,
                    having mentioned these proofs of natural talent to Mr Foulis the printer, who
                    some time before had instituted an aeademy in Glasgow for painting and
                    engraving, he invited young Allan to study under his care. Here he remained
                    about seven years, studying the elementary principles of his art; and, by the
                    proficiency whieh he attained, justified the opinion of his talents whieh had
                    procured him admission to that ill-fated seminary. But although the publie taste
                    for the fine arts, whieh then existed in Scotland, was so feeble as to leave his
                    preceptor without support, whieh his liberal and spirited efforts justly
                    elaimed, Allan, on leaving the aeademy, had the good fortune to gain the
                    patronage of individuals whose generosity enabled him to proseeute his views,
                    and to improve his taste, by studying the works of art abroad. At the joint
                    expense of several persons of fortune, particularly Lord Catheart and Mr
                    Abererombie of Tullibody, he was enabled to go to Italy; and at Rome he devoted
                    himself with great zeal to his profession. Here he remained for no less a period
                    than sixteen years, during which time his subsistence ehiefly depended on the
                    copies whieh he made from the most celebrated pictures of the aneient masters.
                    Among the original works which he then painted, there was one which does the
                    highest credit to his talents, and whieh gained for him the gold'medal given by
                    the Academy of St Luke, in the year 1773, for the best specimen of historical
                    composition. This picture represents the <hi rend="italic">Origin of
                        Painting,</hi> and is well known by the excellent engraving of it by Cunego.
                    His design of the <hi rend="italic">Calabrian Shepherds</hi> is also a
                    composition of great merit; and his four views of the Carnivals at Rome, etehed
                    by Paul Sandby, are said likewise to have been very sueeessful.</p>
                <p part="N">On his return to his native country, he took up his residence in
                    Edinburgh, and soon after, on the death of Alexander Runciman, in 1786, was
                    appointed director and master of the aeademy established by the Board of
                    Trustees for Manufactures in Scotland. There he executed a great variety of
                    works, of various degrees of merit; but perhaps none sueh as might have been
                    expected from the author of the <hi rend="italic">Origin of Painting.</hi>
                    Those, indeed, by whieh he is most known, are of a east altogether different,
                    being remarkable for the eomie humour whieh they display. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Scotch Wedding,</hi> the <hi rend="italic">Highland Dance,</hi> the <hi
                        rend="italic">Repentance Stool,</hi> with his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Illustrations of the Gentle Shepherd,</hi> are all of this elass, and so
                    generally known, from his own spirited etchings in aqua-tinta, as to need no
                    description. Of his graver compositions, the <hi rend="italic">Prodigal
                        Son,</hi> in possession of Lord Catheart, and his <hi rend="italic">Hercules
                        and</hi><hi rend="italic">Omphale,</hi> in the possession of Mr Erskine of
                    Mar, are regarded as works of great merit.</p>
                <p part="N">As an artist, Mr Allan possessed much facility of invention, with a keen
                    discernment of those evanescent eireumstanees in the outward form whieh mark the
                    different shades of passion and affeetion in the mind. With the talent of
                    artfully arranging the various parts of a crowded and bustling seene, sueh as
                    appears in some of his eomic produetions, he possessed that feeling for
                    simplicity which gives to his graver compositions a classical and antique air of
                    eleganee∙ In his drawing he was often hasty and ineorreet. He executed a great
                    variety of etchings and drawings in water eolours, which are valuable, on
                    aeeount of their excellent humour, and the great knowledge of national character
                    whieh they express. We do not know that Allan left any pupil who has followed
                    his particular line in painting; but among those who received from him the
                    rudiments of art while he continued master of the aeademy, we may name the late
                    Mr Hugh W. Williams, whose genius, however, directed him to a different eourse,
                    whieh conducted him to high and merited distinction as a landscape painter.</p>
                <p part="N">Mr Allan is remembered and spoken of as an excellent private character.
                    He died at Edinburgh on the 6th of August 1796, in the 53d year of his age.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Allan,</hi> a river of Perthshire, in Scotland,
                    which passes by Dunblane, and falls into the Forth near Stirling.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
