<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-0862-0081-17" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ACCELERATION</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="fast:914456">Equality</term>
                    <term ref="fast:993678">Law</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1151043">Time</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b43f4kq7b">Descents</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47659j0m">Descent</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4319s59c">Foot</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1240375">Moon</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193030862?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">ACCELERATION</label>, in <hi rend="italic">Natural
                        Philosophy,</hi> denotes generally an increase of motion or velocity, and is
                    chiefly applied to the motion of such bodies as go on, not with a uniform
                    motion, but one which becomes continually quicker and quicker as they advance. A
                    body, for example, rolling down a hill proceeds slowly at first, but gradually
                    increases as it descends, until at last it acquires a velocity and momentum
                    which bears down every thingbefore it. The same thing takes place when a body is
                    dropped, and allowed to fall freely in the air; although the acceleration is
                    here less observable, on account of the great rapidity of the descent. The
                    earth, in its annual motion round the sun, is subject to a continued
                    acceleration from the apogee to the perigee, while from thence again it suffers
                    a similar retardation. Many other examples occur of such acceleration; but the
                    most interesting is the <hi rend="smallcaps">Acceleration of Falling
                        Bodies.</hi> That such an acceleration does take place, is obvious from many
                    circumstances, particularly the increasing momentum which a body acquires in
                    proportion to the height of its descent But it was only by considering the cause
                    of the descent that the true law of the acceleration was determined. This great
                    discovery we owe to the genius of Galileo. Various theories had been framed by
                    philosophers to account for the accelerated descent of falling bodies, but all
                    of them inconclusive and visionary. Some, for instance, ascribed it to the
                    weight of the pure air above increasing as the body descended. The followers of
                    Gassendi pretended that there are continually issuing out of the earth certain
                    attractive corpuscles directed in an infinite number of rays; those, say they,
                    ascend and then descend in such a manner, that the nearer a body approaches to
                    the earth’s centre, the more of these attractive rays press upon it, in
                    consequence of which its motion becomes accelerated. The Cartesians again
                    ascribed the effect to the reiterated impulses of their <hi rend="italic"
                        >materia</hi><hi rend="italic">subtilis</hi> acting continually on falling
                    bodies, and propelling them downwards. It appears now incredible how such dreams
                    could have been gravely proposed by men having the reputation of philosophers.
                    Galileo, however, on considering the subject attentively, and applying the
                    powerful aids of geometry and mathematics, soon discovered that the true cause
                    was simply the continued action of the moving force of gravity. This force,
                    Galileo reasoned, must operate continually on the body, not only at the moment
                    of starting, but also during every moment of its descent. And as the body
                    retains and accumulates all these impressions according to the great and
                    original law of moving bodies, no wonder that its motion should become
                    continually accelerated: for, suppose that gravity were to act only at certain
                    small intervals, each second for instance, and suppose that at first it
                    communicates such a motion to the body as causes it to descend, say ten feet in
                    the first second; the body could not stop here even though gravity were ceasing
                    altogether to act on it: retaining the original impression, it would still go on
                    moving uniformly at the rate of ten feet every second of its descent; but at the
                    end of the first second, gravity <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193030875?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-0875-0082"/>again acts
                    on it and communicates a second impression, by virtue of which it would descend
                    ten feet during the second interval, in addition to the ten feet arising from
                    the original impulse; so that on the whole it descends 20 feet in the second
                    interval. In the same manner, during the third interval it would descend 30
                    feet, and during the fourth 40, and so on; the space described in each second
                    thus increasing regularly with the increase of the time.</p>
                <p part="N">Hence Galileo deduced the fundamental law of acceleration in falling
                    bodies, that the <hi rend="italic">Velocity,</hi> which in every case is just
                    the space described in each second or other fixed interval, <hi rend="italic"
                        >increases in exact proportion to the whole time of descent;</hi> so that
                    whatever be the velocity at the end of the first second, then at the end of any
                    number of seconds the velocity would just be as many times greater,—a law from
                    which he easily deduced all the others regarding the descent of falling bodies,
                    which are of so much importance in mechanical inquiries. The most remarkable is
                    that which regards the <hi rend="italic">Space</hi><note anchored="true"
                        place="bottom" type="authorial"><p part="N">This phrase, we may remark,
                            probably from Galileo’s geometrical illustration, haá been rather
                            atìkwardlý Introduced in tħese discussions, and in a way which tends to
                            produce a little obscurity. Space generally includes the idea of
                            extension, in at least two dimensions, both length and breadth; whereas
                            it is here employed to denote merely the lineal extent, the length of
                            the track deshibed by the moving body,</p></note> described, or the
                    total amount of the descent in a given time. This Galileo deduced very elegantly
                    from a simple geometrical consideration. In every case of a body moving
                    uniformly without acceleration, the space described in any given time must be
                    proportional to the time, and must be found by multiplying the time by the
                    velocity: it may be represented, therefore, by a simple diagram. Let A B, for
                    instance, denote by its length the velocity of the body, or the number of feet
                    described by it in a second, and CD the time or number of seconds during which
                    it is in motion; then, if we construct a rectangle <hi rend="italic">a</hi> E,
                    of which one of the sides, <hi rend="italic">a b,</hi> is equal to A B, and the
                    other, <hi rend="italic">c d,</hi> equal to C D, this rectangle, that is, the
                    number of square feet in it, will denote the space, that is, the number of
                    lineal feet described during the· whole period. Let us now apply this principle
                    to the case of a body moving with an accelerated velocity, and let AB, CD, EF,
                    &amp;c. denote the velocities at the end of certain equal intervals of time, of
                    which let each be denoted by <hi rend="italic">l m</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi>
                    and suppose also, that during each of these intervals the motion is uniform, and
                    is only accelerated by a sort of start which takes place at the end of each:
                    then, if we construct a rectangle <hi rend="italic">a l b,</hi> of which <hi
                        rend="italic">a b</hi> is equal to A B, the velocity at the end of the first
                    interval, and <hi rend="italic">α l</hi> equal to <hi rend="italic">l m</hi> the
                    first interval, this rectangle will denote the space described during that
                    interval. Continue now the line <hi rend="italic">a l</hi> to <hi rend="italic"
                        >m,</hi> making <hi rend="italic">l m</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">α I = I rn,</hi> and continue also <hi rend="italic">I c</hi>
                    to <hi rend="italic">d,</hi> so that <hi rend="italic">l d</hi> may be equal to
                    D C, the velocity during the second interval, and complete the rectangle <hi
                        rend="italic">dime,</hi> this will denote the space described in the second
                    interval; and, in the same manner, each of the succeeding rectangles in
                    descending will denote the space described in the succeeding interval, so that
                    the total amount of the descent will be denoted by the sum of all the rectangles
                    together, or by the compound figure which they form. But what is the nature of
                    this figure? It is evidently, as appears more clearly by taking out the parallel
                    lines, triangular, only that the longest side presents a serrated outline. What
                    is the cause of this? It is clearly owing to the supposition we have made of the
                    motion continuing uniform during the intervals, and then increasing by starts;
                    instead of growing continually, as it really does. Suppose then that we shorten
                    the intervals one-half, for instance, and double their number, we shall then be
                    much nearer the truth; but the inequalities in the hypothenuse of the triangle
                    are now greatly reduced; and the more we thus diminish the intervals, and
                    increase their number, the more nearly does it approach to a straight line, In
                    the extreme case, therefore, where there are in reality no intervals, but where
                    the velocity goes on continually increasing, neither will there be any
                    inequalities in the outline; the figure will be really a triangle: and while the
                    vertical side A B denotes the time of descent, and the horizontal B C the
                    velocity, the area of the triangle will denote in square measure the space
                    descended in the given time. But the areas of similar triangles are in every
                    case proportional to the squares of their corresponding sides; that is, the area
                    ABC is to A D E as the square of A B or B C is to the square of A D or D E.
                    Hence in general it follows, that the <hi rend="italic">spaces</hi> described in
                    any given time or times are always <hi rend="italic">proportional to the squares
                        of these times,</hi> and also to the <hi rend="italic">squares of the
                        velocities at the end of such times.</hi> Thus, if a body describes 16 feet
                    during the first second of its descent, it will, during the next, descend 4
                    times as much, or 64; during the third 9 times, or 144 feet; during the fourth
                    16 times, or 256, and so on.</p>
                <p part="N">Such, then, is the great law of acceleration in regard to the spaces
                    described. It is easily deducible also from numerical or algebraical
                    considerations. Let the velocity, for example, at the end of any given time,
                    such as a second, be denoted by 1; then in the second, third, and fourth, it
                    will be 2, 3, 4, &amp;c. But the space described at the end of any time is
                    evidently equal to the time multiplied by the mean velocity; that is, the
                    velocity at the half-interval. During the first second, therefore, the space
                    described wifi be ⅛, during the second f, during the third f, during the fourth
                    ½, and so on; adding these successively, the whole space from the beginning at
                    the end of each interval will be ½, ½, ∣, <hi rend="superscript"> 1</hi> J <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi>, &amp;c., being each proportional to the square
                    of the time. Algebraically again, if we suppose gravity to act only at the end
                    of successive intervals, and the motion to continue uniform during these, then
                    the spaces described will form an arithmetical progression, such as <hi
                        rend="italic">α,</hi> 2 <hi rend="italic">a,</hi> 3 <hi rend="italic"
                        >a,</hi> 4 α, 5 α, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c. ... n a,</hi> and the wħble
                    space will be the sum of this series, or <hi rend="italic">α + η a</hi> χ .
                    =</p>
                <p part="N">2 <pb break="no" facs="nls:193030888?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0702-0888-0083"/>n <hi rend="superscript"> 2</hi> + n × -.
                    Suppose now the intervals diminished 2</p>
                <p part="N">in extent and increased in number indefinitely, they will bear no sort
                    of proportion to <hi rend="italic">n-</hi>: the second term of the above sum
                    therefore maybe neglected, and ultimately the whole space will be proportional
                    to n <hi rend="superscript"> a</hi>, the square of the time. In every view,
                    then, this great, law is established; and when we come to try it experimentally,
                    which is done by means of Atwood’s machine, it is confirmed by the nicest
                    observation; every falling body describing in the first second 16⅛ feet, and in
                    every other a space proportional to the time. See <hi rend="italic">Atwooďs</hi>
                    Machine, <hi rend="smallcaps">Dynamics, Mechanics, &amp;c.</hi> (c.)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Acceleration,</hi> in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Astronomy,</hi> is applied in various ways, and to different objects. Thus,
                    the <hi rend="italic">Acceleration pf the Fixed Stars</hi> denotes that apparent
                    increase of motion or velocity by which night after night they arrive sooner and
                    sooner upon the meridian than before. A star which passes the meridian to-night
                    at 10 o’clock, for instance, will to-morrow night arrive at it 3' 56" sooner, or
                    at 56' 4" past nine, and so on each succeeding evening; thus anticipating
                    continually the mętion of the sun, which regulates the length of the day. A star
                    which passes the meridian to-day with the sun, will to-morrow pass 3' 56"
                    sooner; so that it appears to revolve with a quicker or accelerated motion. It
                    is in reality the sun, however, moving continually backwards among the stars
                    which causes in them this apparent acceleration.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Acceleration of the Planets</hi> denotes that
                    accelerated motion with which they all, as well as the earth, advance from the
                    perigee to the apogee of their orbits. This acceleration is most readily
                    observed by comparing the successive diurnal motions of the planet in its orbit.
                    When the actual diurnal motion exceeds the mean diurnal motion, the planet is
                    accelerated; and, on the other hand, when it falls short of it, it is retarded,
                    as takes place between the apogee and perigee.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Acceleration of the Moon</hi> is a remarkable increase
                    which lias been discovered in the moon’s motion in her orbit, which has been
                    going on increasing from age to age by a gradation so imperceptible, that it was
                    only discovered or suspected by Dr Halley, on comparing the ancient eclipses
                    observed at Babylon and others with those of his own time. The quantity of this
                    acceleration was afterwards determined by Mr Dunthorne from more accurate data
                    regarding the longitudes of Alexandria and Babylon, and from the most authentic
                    eclipse of which any good account remains, observed at Babylon in the year 721
                    before Christ. The beginning of this eclipse, as observed at that time, was
                    about an hour and three quarters sooner than he found it would have been by
                    computation; and hence he found the mean acceleration, or what has since bçen
                    termed the moon’s secular equation, about 10" of a degree each century.
                    According to Laplace, it amounts to 11∙135". This remarkable fact had long
                    excited the attention of astronomers; as, along with several others of the same
                    kind among the heavenly bodies, it seemed to betray imperfection; exhibiting
                    inequalities which were continually increasing, instead of correcting themselves
                    or being somehow compensated by that admirable design which prevailed in every
                    other part of the system. At last, however, it was discovered, by the
                    application of a refined analysis, that these inequalities were not perpetual;
                    that they actually terminate in the lapse of ages, and again return in the
                    opposite direction, thus preserving entire the harmony of the celestial motions.
                    This fine discovery, which observation alone could never have disclosed, we owe
                    to the genius of Laplace. See <hi rend="smallcaps">Astronomy</hi> in this work;
                    also <hi rend="italic">Phil. Trails.</hi> No. 204, 218, and vol. xlvi. 1749,</p>
                <p part="N">1750, 1777; <hi rend="italic">Mem. de ľAcad. Par.</hi> 1757, 1763, 1786;
                        <hi rend="italic">Mem. de l'Acad. Berlin,</hi> 1773, 1782; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Connoissances des Temps,</hi> 1779, 1782, 1790; Newton’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Principia,</hi> second edition; Say’s <hi rend="italic">Astronomy</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi> Vince's <hi rend="italic">Astronomy</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">;</hi><hi rend="italic">Astronomie,</hi> par Lalande, &amp;c.
                    (c.)</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic smallcaps"> Acceleration</hi><hi rend="italic">of
                        Bodies on inclined Planes.</hi> The same • general law obtains here as in
                    bodies falling perpendicularly: the effect of the plane is to make the motion
                    slower; but the inclination being everywhere equal, the retardation arising
                    therefrom will proceed equally in all parts, at the beginning and the ending òf
                    the motion.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
