<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-8441-0664-07" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AMONTONS (Guillaume)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4k649s3x">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ff3kz95">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jd4pp0f">Air</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m0441w">Friction</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4js9hb31">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zp3w744">Progress</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41j9785q">Success</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795344">Accountants</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795379">Accounting</term>
                    <term ref="fast:795510">Accounts</term>
                    <term ref="fast:802066">Air</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1136568">Subjectivity</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1027064">Motion</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1078723">Progress</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1137041">Success</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193038441?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">AMONTONS <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >(Guillaume)</hi></label>, a celebrated French experimental philosopher, was
                    the son of an advocate, who had left his native province of Normandy, and
                    established himself at Paris, where the subject of this memoir was born in 1663.
                    The exertions of genius frequently take a particular direction from accidental
                    circumstances. A severe illness, with which Amontons was afflicted in his early
                    youth, had the effect of rendering him almost entirely deaf, aņd consequently of
                    secluding him in a great measure from the ordinary commerce and amusements of
                    society. Being compelled by this accident to depend for his enjoyments on the
                    resources of his own mind, he began to take great pleasure in the construction
                    of machines of various kinds, and in the study of the laws of mechanics; a path
                    of inquiry which he pursued through life with unremitting ardour and
                    distinguished success. One of the first objects which engaged his attention was
                    the discovery of the perpetual motion. His attempts, though necessarily
                    unsuccessful, were productive of greater advantage to him than they have usually
                    been to those who have pursued that vain chimera; for in the course of his
                    reflections on the subject he became convinced, that, in order to make any
                    progress in mechanics, it is necessary to be acquainted with certain principles,
                    the knowledge of which can only be acquired through the medium of geometry. He
                    therefore assiduously applied himself to the study of this latter science, and
                    his progress in it prepared the way for his future mechanical discoveries. He is
                    said to have derived so much pleasure from the uninterrupted pursuit of these
                    interesting speculations, that he refused to employ any remedy for his deafness,
                    lest he should be diverted from them by an increased facility of intercourse
                    with the world; resembling in this respect, says Fontenelle, the ancient sage
                    who put out his eyes that he might enjoy his philosophic meditations without
                    distraction.</p>
                <p part="N">Amontons directed his views in a particular manner to the improvement of
                    instruments employed in physical experiments; a subject which requires the
                    finest applications of mechanical principles, and which till that time had not
                    met with a due share of attention. In 1687, before he had attained his 24th
                    year, he presented to the Academy of Sciences an hygrometer of his own
                    invention, which was received with approbation by that learned body. In 1695 he
                    published the only work which he has given to the world. . It was dedicated to
                    the academy, and entitled <hi rend="italic">Pemarques</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >et</hi><hi rend="italic">Experiences Physiques</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >sur</hi><hi rend="italic">la Construction ďnn</hi><hi rend="italic">nouvel
                        Clepsydre, sur les Baromètres, les Thermomètres, et les Hygromètres.</hi>
                    After Huygens’ beautiful application of the pendulum to the regulation of the
                    motion of clocks, any attempt to revive the clepsydra, an incommodious
                    instrument, and not susceptible of much accuracy, might seem to subject its
                    author to the imputation of not sufficiently appreciating the great importance
                    of a discovery which has so completely changed the face of astronomical science;
                    but the object of Amontons was to produce an instrument capable of measuring
                    time on board ship, in circumstances where the motion of the vessel rendered
                    such timekeepers as were then known useless. The machine which he constructed is
                    said to have been extremely ingenious, and probably differed entirely from those
                    of the ancients, among whom the clepsydra was in common use.</p>
                <p part="N">In 1669 Amontons was admitted into the Academy of Sciences, the memoirs
                    of which he enriched with many important contributions. The first paper which he
                    presented after his admission was one on the theory <hi rend="italic">of
                        Friction,</hi> a subject then involved in great obscurity, and on which his
                    inquiries tended to throw considerable light. After that appeared, in
                    succession, an Account of a New Thermometer, and of numerous Experiments made
                    with the Barometer, relative to the Nature and Properties of Air,—a detailed
                    account of all which is given in the history of the academy. By his countrymen
                    he is generally regarded as the inventor of the telegraph; and he had the honour
                    of exhibiting the methods by which he proposed to accomplish the object in view,
                    before some members of the royal family. It appears, however, from a paper read
                    by Dr Hooke to the Royal Society in 1684, that that ingenious philosopher had
                    brought the telegraph, in theory at least, to a state of far greater maturity
                    than Amontons, and nearly 20 years earlier. The experiments of the latter were
                    made about the year 1702. It maybe regarded as a curious fact in the history of
                    inventions, that although the great importance of telegraphic communication is
                    obvious, and the method of accomplishing it was clearly explained by Hooke, and
                    its practicability demonstrated by Amontons, it continued to be regarded as a
                    mere yew <hi rend="italic">d’esprit,</hi> and was not regularly applied to
                    useful purposes till nearly a century afterwards, at the time of the French
                    Revolution.</p>
                <p part="N">Although most of the instruments invented by Amontons have been
                    superseded by others more accurate and convenient, yet they contributed to give
                    a greater precision than had been attained before his time, to experiments and
                    physical investigations, and consequently to accelerate the progress of
                    experimental philosophy, which from that period began to make rapid advances. He
                    possessed a singular talent for contriving and conducting experiments, and
                    showed great address in obviating or eluding the difficulties which, even in the
                    hands of the most skilful and <pb break="no" facs="nls:193038454?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0702-8454-0665"/>! expert, so frequently occur to prevent their
                    success. His industryand activity promised still more important services <hi
                        rend="subscript"> z</hi> to science, when, to the great regret of his
                    contemporaries, he was suddenly cut off by inflammation, at the age of 42 years.
                    His manners are represented to have been simple and unostentatious, his
                    character candid and frank, entirely free from affectation or pretension of any
                    sort; and he lived in comparative obscurity, because, as his eulogist
                    ingeniously observes, he was unacquainted with the arts of the courtier, and
                    knew no other means of acquiring reputation or fortune, than those of real merit
                    and useful services to mankind. See his <hi rend="italic">Eloge</hi> by
                    Fontenelle, (s.)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
