<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-3046-0249-13" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">AGRA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:839044">British</term>
                    <term ref="fast:833378">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="fast:969307">Indians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:806511">Alvars</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1098312">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1171139">Water</term>
                    <term ref="fast:970275">Indigo</term>
                    <term ref="fast:880858">Cotton</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4wh2dg8p">Rivers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4513v11w">Water</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ms3k440">Indigo</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4jw86q1x">Cotton</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42804z62">Bishops</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4599z60x">Hindoos</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4zk55m05">Indians</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1210276">India</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193033046?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">AGRA</label>, a province of Hindostan, chiefly
                    situated between the 25th and 28th degrees of N. lat. On the north it is bounded
                    by the province of Delhi, on the south by that of Malwah, on the east by the
                    provinces of Oude and Allahabad, and on the west by that of Ajmeer. It is
                    estimated to be 250 miles in length, and in average breadth to be 180. The
                    following are the principal geographical and political divisions:—1. Agra
                    district; 2. the Doab; 3. the district of Etaweh; 4. the Furruckabad district;
                    5. Cal-pee, Gohud, and Gualior; 6. the Bhurtpoor territories; 7. Alvar or
                    Machery; 8. the Alighur district.</p>
                <p part="N">This province has an unequal surface. To the north-east of the Jumna the
                    country is flat and open, and rather bare of trees; but to the south of the
                    Chumbul, and also towards the western frontier, it rises into hills, and is
                    interspersed with jungle. Owing to the elevation of the ground, it has for the
                    greater part of the year a temperate climate. In summer, while the hot winds
                    prevail, it is intensely hot, and the climate is unhealthful, especially among
                    the hills. But these winds do not continue for any length of time; and in the
                    winter months it is actually cold, especially during the night. The province is
                    indifferently watered. The chief rivers are the Jumna, the Chumbul, and the
                    Ganges, besides other streams of inferior note. Except in the vicinity of the
                    large rivers, water is scarce for the purposes of irrigation. Rice, which
                    requires an abundant supply of moisture, is not cultivated. The soil is
                    particularly adapted to the cultivation of indigo, cotton, and sugar, the
                    production of which is annually increasing in the country under the jurisdiction
                    of the British: in that which is still subject to the native chiefs, agriculture
                    is in a backward state. There are no remarkable mineral productions in the
                    province of Agra. The animals differ in no respect from those found in other
                    parts of Hindostan; and the breed of horses is much esteemed. The principal
                    article manufactured is coarse cotton cloth; but no great quantity is exported.
                    The most fertile part of the province is the Doab, or the territory included
                    between the Ganges and the Jumna, which exports indigo, sugar, and cotton. The
                    country to the north-west of Agra, which is under the dominion of the native
                    chiefs, being scantily supplied with water, is of a very inferior quality, and
                    comparatively unproductive. This province is not nearly so populous as Bengal,
                    Jaupore, and the more flourishing parts of the British territory. It does not
                    contain above six millions of inhabitants, of whom the greater proportion live
                    under the British jurisdiction; the remainder under Scindia and others of the
                    native princes. The chief towns, besides Agra, the capital, are Alvar or Aloor,
                    the capital of a native rajah; Bhurtpoor, one of the strongest fortresses in
                    India, which the British carried by storm in 1826; Deeg, another strong
                    fortress; Mathura, Kanoje, Etaweh, Gualior, Gohud, Calpee, Narwar, and
                    Furruckabad. The natives are in general a robust and handsome race of people,
                    and consist of a mixture of Hindoos and Mahometans. The Hindoo religion and
                    language are predominant, although the country has been subject to the
                    Mahometans since the thirteenth century.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="smallcaps">Agra,</hi> the capital of the preceding province,
                    is situated on the south-west side of the Jumna, from the banks of which it
                    extends upward in a vast semicircle. It is a large, old, and ruinous city, with
                    little to attract attention beyond that picturesque confusion of houses,
                    balconies, and projecting roofs, common to all Indian towns. The houses consist
                    of several stories, and the streets are so narrow as scarcely to admit a
                    palanquin. The greater part of this once flourishing city is now a heap of
                    ruins, and uninhabited. It is still, however, estimated to contain 60,000
                    inhabitants; and as its commerce improves, which it is likely to do, from the
                    facilities which it affords to the trade of <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193033059?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-3059-0250"/>western
                    Hindostan, its population is likely to increase also. Since 1818, indeed, in
                    consequence of the tranquillity of the neighbouring province of llajpootana or
                    Ajmeer, the produce of the customs has continued progressively to increase. It
                    has a fort, which is very large and ancient, and is surrounded with high walls
                    and towers of red stone, of the hardness and colour of jasper, which command
                    some noble views of the city, its neighbourhood, and the windings of the Jumna.
                    The fort has a ditch of great depth, and a double rampart, the inner one being
                    of an enormous height, with bastions at regular distances. Agra is famed for
                    some beautiful edifices, the most remarkable of which is the Jage-mahal, a tomb
                    erected by the emperor Shah Jehan, to the memory of Begum Novr-jehan, his
                    beloved wife. Bishop Heber mentions, that after all he had heard of this
                    celebrated mausoleum, its beauty rather exceeded than fell short of his
                    expectations. It is of white marble, and is placed on an elevated terrace of
                    white and yellow marble, with four tall minarets of the same material rising at
                    each of its angles. The interior, containing a central hall, in which are the
                    tombs of the emperor and his wife, is remarkable for its exquisite finish; the
                    pavement being laid with alternate squares of marble, and the walls, screens,
                    and tombs, crowned with flowers and inscriptions executed in beautiful Mosaic of
                    cornelian, lapis lazuli, and jasper. The general effect of the whole is solemn
                    and impressive rather than gaudy. There is a tomb erected to another of the
                    emperors, now used as a court of justice, which is a splendid edifice. Agra
                    contains, besides, a beautiful mosque of white marble, carved with exquisite
                    simplicity and elegance, and the palace, built by Acbar chiefly of the same
                    material, and now used as warehouses, offices, and lodging-rooms for the
                    garrison. At Secundra, a ruinous village about six miles from Agra, is the
                    magnificent tomb of the emperor Acbar, which, Bishop Heber remarks, is the most
                    splendid building in its way that he had seen in India.</p>
                <p part="N">Agra was greatly enlarged and embellished by Acbar, who made it his
                    capital. The city, which was under the rule of Scindia, surrendered to the
                    British army under Lord Lake in 1803. It was soon after made the scat of the
                    civil establishment for the collection of the revenue and the administration of
                    justice. The fortifications have been lately strengthened and improved. 137
                    miles travelling distance from Delhi. Long. 77. 53. E. Lat. 27. 11. N. <hi
                        rend="italic">(Narrative of a Journey through the Upper Provinces of India,
                        from Calcutta to Rσmbay,</hi> 1824, 1825; by Reginald Heber, D. D. Bishop of
                    Calcutta.— <hi rend="italic">A Geographical, Statistical, and Historical
                        Description of Hindostan and the adjacent Countries;</hi> by Walter
                    Hamilton, Esq. 1820.) (<hi rend="subscript"> F</hi>.) <hi rend="superscript">
                        n</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
