<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-5204-0415-06" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ALFIERI, Victor</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r48v">Passions</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b45m62623">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4n58cs1k">Manners</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ws8hn48">Mothers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4xd0r400">Memoirs</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b40k26h3v">Lombards</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4d795c7h">Republicanism</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1239717">Alps</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1205401">Switzerland</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204537">Sweden</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204303">Spain</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1204597">Virginia</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1737291">Italianization</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:947546">Greeks</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                    <term ref="fast:881352">Countesses</term>
                    <term ref="fast:897468">Drama</term>
                    <term ref="fast:964412">Husbands</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193035204?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">ALFIERI, <hi rend="smallcaps">Victor</hi></label>,
                    chiefly celebrated as the author who raised the Italian tragic drama from its
                    previous state of degradation, was born on the 17th January 1749, at the town of
                    Asti, in Piedmont. He lost his father in early infancy; but he continued to
                    reside with his mother, who married a second time, till his tenth year, when he
                    was placed at the academy of Turin. After he had passed a twelvemonth at the
                    academy, he went on a short visit to a relation who dwelt at Coni; and during
                    his stay there he made his first poetical attempt, in a sonnet chiefly borrowed
                    from lines in Ariosto and Metastasio, the only poets he had at that time read.
                    When thirteen years of age, he was induced to commence the study of civil and
                    canonical law; but the attempt only served to disgust him with every species of
                    application, and to increase his relish for the perusal of French romances.</p>
                <p part="N">By the death of his uncle, who had hitherto taken some charge of his
                    education and conduct, he was left, at the age of fourteen, to enjoy without
                    control his vast paternal inheritance, augmented by the recent accession of his
                    uncle’s fortune. He now began to attend the ridingschool, where he acquired that
                    rage for horses and equestrian exercise which continued to be one of his
                    strongest passions till the close of his existence.</p>
                <p part="N">After some time spent in alternate fits of extravagant dissipation and
                    ill-directed study, he was seized with a <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193035217?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-5217-0416"/>deśire of
                    travelling; and having obtained permission from the king, he departed, in 1766,
                    under the care of an English preceptor. Restless and unquiet, he posted with the
                    utmost rapidity through the towns of Italy; and his improvement was such as was
                    to be expected from his mode of travelling and his previous habits. Dissatisfied
                    with himself, he felt as little relish for spectacles or entertainments as for
                    literature; and was as little amused by the gaiety of a carnival at Naples, as
                    he was impressed by the remains of antiquity at Rome,· or the exhibitions of
                    modern art at Florence and Bologna. This indifference and insensibility did not,
                    however, arise from defect of talent or the ∙natural powers of taste, but from
                    the want of some serious passion, or some ennobling or praiseworthy pursuit.
                    Hoping to find in foreign countries some relief from the 'tedium and <hi
                        rend="italic">ennui</hi> with which he was oppressed, and being anxious to
                    become acquainted with the French theatre, he proceeded to Paris; but his
                    feelings were only those of disgust or indifference for the dramas which he saw
                    represented in that capital. He seems, indeed, to have been completely
                    dissatisfied with every thing he witnessed in France, and contracted a dislike
                    to its people, which his intercourse in future years rather contributed to
                    augment than diminish. In Holland he became deeply enamoured of a married lady,
                    who returned his attachment, but who was soon obliged to accompany her husband
                    to Switzerland. Alfieri, whose feelings were of the most impetuous description,
                    was in despair at this separation, and returned to his own country in the utmost
                    anguish and despondency of mind. While under this depression of spirits, he was
                    induced to seek alleviation from works of literature; and the perusal of
                    Plutarch’s Lives, which he read with profound emotion, inspired him with an
                    enthusiastic passion for freedom and independence. Under the influence of this
                    rage for liberty he recommenced his travels; and his only gratification, in the
                    absence of freedom among the Continental States, appears to have been derived
                    from contemplating the wild and sterile regions of the north of Sweden, where
                    gloomy forests, lakes, and precipices conspired to excite those sublime and
                    melancholy ideas which were congenial to his disposition. Human manners and
                    human institutions he seems invariably to have surveyed with an eye of passion
                    or prejudice, instead of viewing them with the calmness of a philosopher, who
                    meditates how they may be rectified, or what lessons may be drawn from them. In
                    every country his soul felt as if confined by the bonds of society: he
                    everywhere panted for something more free in governments, more elevated in
                    sentiment, more devoted in love, and more perfect in friendship. In search of
                    this ideal world, he posted through various countries, more with the rapidity of
                    a courier than of one who travels for amusement or instruction. During a journey
                    to London, he engaged in an intrigue with a married lady of high rank; and
                    having been detected, the publicity of a rencounter with the injured husband,
                    and of a divorce, which followed, united to the knowledge he now acquired of the
                    infamous character of the woman, to whom he was ardently attached, rendered it
                    expedient and desirable for him to quit England. He then visited Spain and
                    Portugal, where he became acquainted witlι the Abbé Caluso, who remained through
                    life the most attached and estimable friend he ever possessed. In 1772 Alfieri
                    returned to Turin, where he again became enamoured of a lady, whom he loved with
                    his usual ardour, and who seems to have been as undeserving of a sincere
                    attachment as those he had hitherto adored. In the course of a long attendance
                    on his mistress, during a malady with which she was afflicted, he one day wrote
                    a dialogue, or scene of a drama, which he left at -this lady’s house. About a
                    year after, on a difference taking place between them, this piece was returned
                    to him. Having then retouched and extended it t <hi rend="subscript"> 0</hi>
                    five acts, it was performed at Turin in 1775, under the title of <hi
                        rend="italic">Cleopatra,</hi> whose amours had always been a favourite
                    subject with Italian dramatists.</p>
                <p part="N">From this moment Alfieri was seized with an immeasurable thirst of
                    theatrical fame, and the remainder of his life was devoted to its attainment.
                    His first two tragedies, <hi rend="italic">Filippo</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Polinice,</hi> were originally written in French prose; and when he came to
                    versify them in Italian, he found that, from his Lombard origin, and long
                    intercourse with foreigners, he expressed himself with feebleness and
                    inaccuracy. Accordingly, with the view of improving his Italian style, he went
                    to Tuscany, and, during an alternate residence at Florence and Sienna, he
                    completed his <hi rend="italic">Filip, po</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Poliηice,</hi> and conceived the plan of various other dramas. While thus
                    employed, he became acquainted with the countess of Albany, who then resided
                    with her husband at Florence. For her he formed an attachment which, if less
                    violent than his former loves, appears to have been more permanent. With this
                    motive to remain at Florence, he could not endure the chains by which his vast
                    possessions bound him to Piedmont. He therefore resigned his whole property to
                    his sister, the countess Cumiana, reserving an annuity, which scarcely amounted
                    to a half of his original revenues. At this period the countess of Albany, urged
                    by the ill treatment she received from her husband, sought refuge in Rome, where
                    she at length received permission from the pope to live apart from her
                    tormentor. Alfieri followed the countess to that capital, where he completed
                    fourteen tragedies, four of which were now for the first time printed at
                    Sienna.</p>
                <p part="N">At length, however, it was thought proper, that, by leaving Rome, he
                    should remove the aspersions which had been thrown on the object of his
                    affections. During the year 1783, he therefore travelled through different
                    states of Italy, and published six additional tragedies. The interests of his
                    love and literary glory had not diminished his rage for horses, which seems to
                    have been at least the third passion of his soul. He came to England solely for
                    the purpose of purchasing a number of these animals, which he brought with him
                    to Italy. On his return he learned that the countess of Albany had gone to
                    Colmar in Alsace, where he joined her, and resided with her under the same roof
                    during the rest of his life. They chiefly passed their time between Alsace and
                    Paris, but at length took up their abode entirely in that metropolis. While
                    here, Alfieri made arrangements with Didot for an edition of his tragedies; but
                    was soon after forced to quit Paris by the storms of the Revolution. He
                    recrossed the Alps with the countess, and finally settled at Florence. The last
                    ten years of his life, which he spent in that city, seem to have been the
                    happiest of his existence. During that long period his tranquillity was only
                    interrupted by the entrance of the revolutionary armies into Florence m 1799.
                    Though an enemy of kings, the aristocratic feelings of Alfieri rendered him also
                    a decided foe to the principles and leaders of the French Revolution; and he
                    rejected, with the utmost contempt, those advances which were made with a view
                    to bring him over to their cause.. The concluding years of his life were
                    laudably employed in the study of Greek literature, and in perfecting a series
                    of comedies. His assiduous labour on this object, which he pursued with his
                    characteristic impetuosity, exhausted his strength, and brought on a malady, for
                    which he would not adopt the prescriptions of his physicians, but obstinate y
                    persisted in employing remedies of his own. Under this regimen his disorder
                    rapidly increased, and at length ter∙</p>
                <pb break="no" facs="nls:193035230?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-5230-0417"/>
                <p part="N">minated his life on the 8th October 1803, in the fifty-fifth year of his
                    age.</p>
                <p part="N">The character of Alfieri may be best appreciated from the portrait which
                    he has drawn of himself in his own <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of his Life.</hi>
                    He was evidently of an irritable, impetuous, and almost ungovernable temper.
                    Pride, which .seems to have been a ruling sentiment, may account for many
                    apparent inconsistencies of his character. While it made him abhor kings,
                    because superior to himself, it led him to detest those republicans who, by too
                    near an approach, contaminated aristocratic dignity; and it induced him, while
                    yet undistinguished himself, and panting for literary fame, to decline a
                    proffered introduction to Metastasio and Rousseau. But as all his bad qualities
                    were greatly softened by the cultivation of literature, it may be presumed, that
                    a better education, and an earlier employment of his faculties, would have
                    rendered him a much more perfect character. His application to study gradually
                    tranquillized his temper and softened his manners, leaving him at the same time
                    in perfect possession of those good qualities which he had inherited from
                    nature,—a warm and disinterested attachment to his family and friends, united to
                    a generosity, vigour, and elevation of character, which rendered him not
                    unworthy to embody in his dramas the actions and sentiments of Grecian
                    heroes.</p>
                <p part="N">To these dramas Alfieri is chiefly indebted for the high reputation to
                    which he has attained. Before his time the Italian language, so harmonious in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Sonnets</hi> of Petrarch, and so energetic in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Commedia</hi> of Dante, had been invariably languid and
                    prosaic in dramatic dialogue. The pedantic and inanimate tragedies of the
                    sixteenth century were followed, during the iron age of Italian literature, by
                    dramas, of which extravagance in the sentiments, and improbability in the
                    action, were the chief characteristics. The prodigious success of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Merope</hi> of Maffei, which appeared in the commencement of
                    the last century, may be attributed more to a comparison with such productions,
                    than to intrinsic merit. In this degradation of tragic taste, the appearance of
                    the tragedies of Alfieri was perhaps the most important literary event that had
                    occurred in Italy during the eighteenth century. On these tragedies it is
                    difficult to pronounce a judgment, as the taste and system of the author
                    underwent considerable change and modification during the intervals which
                    elapsed between the three periods of their publication. An excessive harshness
                    of style, an asperity of sentiment, and total want of poetical ornament, are the
                    characteristics of his first four tragedies, <hi rend="italic">Filippo,
                        Polinice, Antigone,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Virginia.</hi> These faults
                    were in some measure corrected in the six tragedies which he gave to the world
                    some years after, and in those which he published along with <hi rend="italic"
                        >Saul,</hi> the drama which enjoyed the greatest success of all his
                    productions; a popularity which may be partly attributed to the severe and
                    unadorned manner of Alfieri being well adapted to the patriarchal simplicity of
                    the age in which the scene of the tragedy is placed. But though there be a
                    considerable difference in his dramas, there are certain observations applicable
                    to them all. None of the plots are of his own invention. They are founded either
                    on mythological fable or history; most of them had been previously treated by
                    the Greek dramatists, or by Seneca. <hi rend="italic">Ros-mιιηdα,</hi> the only
                    one which could be supposed of his own contrivance, and which is certainly the
                    least happy effusion oí his genius, is partly founded on the eighteenth novel of
                    the third part of Bandello, and partly on Prevost s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Mémoires</hi><hi rend="italic">d</hi><hi rend="italic superscript">
                        ,</hi><hi rend="italic">un Homme</hi><hi rend="italic">de Qualité.</hi> But
                    whatever subjects he chooses, his dramas are always formed on the Grecian model,
                    and breathe a freedom and independence worthy of an Athenian poet. Indeed, his
                        <hi rend="italic">Agide</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Bruto</hi> may rather be
                    considered oratorical declamations and dialogues on liberty, than tragedies. The
                    unities of time and place are not so scrupulously observed in his as in the
                    ancient dramas; but he has rigidly adhered to a unity of action and interest. He
                    occupies his scene with one great action and one ruling passion, and removes
                    from it every accessary event or feeling. In this excessive zeal for the
                    observance of unity, he seems to have forgotten that its charm consists in
                    producing a common relation between multiplied feelings, and not in the bare
                    exhibition of one, divested of those various accompaniments which give harmony
                    to the whole. Consistently with that austere and simple manner which he
                    considered the chief excellence of dramatic composition, he excluded from his
                    scene all <hi rend="italic">coups de theatre,</hi> all philosophical
                    reflections, and that highly ornamented versification which had been so
                    assiduously cultivated by his predecessors. In his anxiety, however, to avoid
                    all superfluous ornament, he has stripped his dramas of the embellishments of
                    imagination; and for the harmony and flow of poetical language he has
                    substituted, even in his best performances, a style which, though correct and
                    pure, is generally harsh, elaborate, and abrupt; often strained into unnatural
                    energy, or condensed into factitious conciseness. The chief excellence of
                    Alfieri consists in powerful delineation of dramatic character. In his Philip
                    II. he has represented, almost with the masterly touches of Tacitus, the sombre
                    character, the dark mysterious counsels, the <hi rend="italic">suspensa</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">semper</hi><hi rend="italic">et</hi><hi rend="italic">obscura
                        verba,</hi> of the modern Tiberius. In <hi rend="italic">Polinice,</hi> the
                    characters of the rival brothers are beautifully contrasted; in <hi
                        rend="italic">Maria Stuarda,</hi> that unfortunate queen is represented
                    unsuspicious, impatient of contradiction, and violent in her attachments. In <hi
                        rend="italic">Mirra,</hi> the character of <hi rend="italic">Ciniro</hi> is
                    perfect as a father and king, and <hi rend="italic">Cecri</hi> is a model of the
                    virtues of a wife and mother. In the representation of that species of mental
                    alienation where the judgment has perished, but traces of character still
                    remain, he is peculiarly happy. The insanity of Saul is skilfully managed; and
                    the horrid joy of Orestes in killing Egisthus rises finely and naturally to
                    madness, in finding that, at the same time, he had inadvertently slain his
                    mother.</p>
                <p part="N">Whatever mav be the merits or defects of Alfieri, he may be considered
                    as the founder of a new school in the Italian drama. His country hailed him as
                    her sole tragic poet; and his successors in the same path of literature have
                    regarded his bold, austere, and rapid manner, as the genuine model of tragic
                    composition.</p>
                <p part="N">Besides his tragedies, Alfieri published during his life many sonnets,
                    five odes on American independence, and the poem of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Etruria,</hi> founded on the assassination of Alexander I. duke of
                    Florence. Of his prose works, the most distinguished for animation and eloquence
                    is the <hi rend="italic">Panegyric on Trajan,</hi> composed in a transport of
                    indignation at the supposed feebleness of Plinys eulogium. The two books,
                    entitled <hi rend="italic">La Tirannide</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Essays on
                        Literature and Government,</hi> are remarkable for elegance and vigour of
                    style, but are too evidently imitations of the manner of Machiavel. His <hi
                        rend="italic">Antigallican·,</hi> which was written at the same time with
                    his <hi rend="italic">Defence of Louis XVI.,</hi> comprehends an historical and
                    satirical view of the French Revolution. The posthumous works of Alfieri consist
                    of satires, six political comedies, and the <hi rend="italic">Memoirs of
                        his</hi><hi rend="italic">Life</hi><hi rend="italic">—Ά</hi> work which will
                    always be read with interest, in spite of the cold and languid gravity with
                    which he delineates the most interesting adventures and the strongest passions
                    of his agitated life. See <hi rend="italic">Mem. di</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Vit.</hi><hi rend="italic">Alflen;</hi> Sismondi <hi rend="italic">de la
                        Lit. du Midi</hi><hi rend="italic">de l'Europe;</hi> Walker s <hi
                        rend="italic">Memoir on Italian Tragedy</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Giorn. de Pisa,</hi> tom. lvm. <hi rend="smallcaps"
                        >(q.)</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193035243?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0702-5243-0418"/></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
