<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0702-8558-0673-08" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">ANA</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                        role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                            <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                            University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                            Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                        Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                        Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                        University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                        >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp;
                    Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="2.0">Version 2.0 <date when="2023">2023</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>365 MB; 21,026 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                        Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                        target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2023">2023</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                                Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                                [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                                    ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                                    >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date
                                when="2019">2019</date><idno type="DOI"
                                >https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                                <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                                <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY
                                    4.0 </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                            <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                        <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the
                            TEI in Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                        <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                            omitted.</item>
                        <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                        <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                            subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                            bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                        (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"
                    />https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which
                    consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                            of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:808411">Anas</term>
                    <term ref="fast:934209">French</term>
                    <term ref="fast:830184">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="fast:910709">English</term>
                    <term ref="fast:980750">Italians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1180188">Work</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1198505">Life</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1015978">Men</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1182566">Year</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1219920">England</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1754964">Rome</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x05xc2x">Ana</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4v11vw02">Work</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b42j68511">Life</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4b27pq8k">Numbers</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4kh0f02c">Death</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4s46hf7s">Talking</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4gm81p0j">Bells</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48p5vb0p">Caesars</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b48g8fh7d">Greeks</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0 XSL updated</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:193038558?mode=fullsize" org="uniform" part="N" sample="complete"
                type="entry">
                <p part="N"><label type="entry">ANA</label>, a Latin plural termination,
                    appropriated to various collections of the observations and criticisms of <pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193038571?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-8571-0674"
                    />674 ANA.</p>
                <p part="N">Ana. eminent characters delivered in conversation and recorded by their
                    friends, or discovered among their papers after their decease. Though the term
                    Ana is but of modern origin, the species of composition to which it has been
                    applied is not of such recent date as some persons have imagined. It appears,
                    from D’Herbeloťs <hi rend="italic">Bibliothèque Orientale,</hi> that, since the
                    earliest periods, the eastern nations have been in the habit of preserving the
                    maxims of their sages. From them this practice passed to the Greeks and Romans.
                    Plato and Xenophon treasured up and recorded the sayings of their master
                    Socrates. From their example Arrian, in the concluding books of his <hi
                        rend="italic">Enchiridion,</hi> which have not descended to posterity,
                    collected the casual observations which had dropped from Epictetus. The numerous
                    apophthegms seattered in Plutarch, Diogenes Laertius, and other writers, evince
                    that it had been customary in Greece to preserve the ideas delivered by
                    illustrious characters. It appears that Julius Caesar compiled a book of
                    apophthegms, in which he related the <hi rend="italic">bon-mots</hi> of Cicero;
                    and Quintilian informs us, that a freedman of that celebrated wit and orator
                    composed three books of a work entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Jocis Ciceronis.</hi> We are told by Suetonius, that Caius
                    Melissus, originally the slave, but afterwards the freedman and librarian, of
                    Maecenas, collected the sayings of his master; and Aulus Gelliuś has filled his
                        <hi rend="italic">Noctes</hi><hi rend="italic">Atticae</hi> with anecdotes
                    which he heard from those distinguished characters whose society he frequented
                    in Rome. Were the books compiled by the freedmen of Cicero and Maecenas now
                    extant, they might be entitled Ana; and it is certainly to be regretted that we
                    possess no authentic record of the conversational remarks or hints which dropped
                    from the sages, orators, or statesmen of Greece and Rome. How interesting would
                    be a <hi rend="italic">Colloquia Mensalia</hi> of Atticus or Caesar!</p>
                <p part="N">But though vestiges of this species of composition may be traced in the
                    classical ages, it is only in modern times that it has attained to full
                    popularity and perfection. Literary anecdotes, critical reflections, and
                    historical incidents, came to be mingled with the detail of <hi rend="italic"
                        >bon-mots</hi> and ludicrous tales; so that instruction and entertainment
                    were agreeably blended. The term Ana seems to have been applied to such
                    collections as far back as the beginning of the fifteenth century. Thus,
                    Francesco Barbaro, in a letter to Poggio, says, that the information and
                    anecdotes which Poggio and Barthelemi Monteρolitiano had picked up during a
                    literary excursion through Germany, will be called <hi rend="italic">Ana:</hi>
                    “Quemadmodum mala ab Appio e Claudia gente <hi rend="italic">Appiana,</hi> et
                    pira a Mallio <hi rend="italic">Malliana</hi> cognominata sunt, sic haec
                    literarum quae vestra ope et opera Germania in Italiam deferetur, aliquando et
                        <hi rend="italic">Pog-giana</hi> et <hi rend="italic">Montepolitiana</hi>
                    vocabuntur.”</p>
                <p part="N">Poggio Bracciolini, to whom this letter is addressed, and to whom the
                    world is indebted for the preservation of so many classical remains, is the
                    first eminent person of modern times whose jests and opinions have been
                    transmitted to posterity. Poggio was secretary to five successive popes. During
                    the pontificate of Martin V., who was chosen in 1417, Poggio and other members
                    of the Roman chancery were in the habit of assembling in a common hall adjoining
                    the Vatican, in order to converse freely on all subjects. Being more studious of
                    wit than of truth, they termed this apartment <hi rend="italic">Buggiale,</hi> a
                    word signifying a place of recreation where tales are related, and which Poggio
                    himself interprets <hi rend="italic">Mendaciorum Officina.</hi> At these
                    meetings Poggio and his friends discussed the news and scandal of the day, and
                    communicated to each other entertaining anecdotes; they attacked what they did
                    not approve, and they approved of little; they also indulged in the utmost
                    latitude of satiric remark, dealing out their <hi rend="smallcaps">a∣,</hi>
                    sarcasms with such impartiality, that they did not spare ''-*~ k even the pope
                    and cardinals. The pointed jests and hu- ' morous stories which occurred in
                    these unrestrained conversations were collected by Poggio, and formed the chief
                    materials of his <hi rend="italic">Facetiae,</hi> first printed, according to De
                    Bure, in 1470. This celebrated collection, which forms a principal part of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Poggiana,</hi> is chiefly valuable as recording
                    interesting anecdotes of eminent men of the fourteenth and fifteenth centuries.
                    It also contains a number of quibbles or <hi rend="italic">jeux-de-τηots,</hi>
                    and a still greater number of idle and licentious stories. Many of these,
                    however, are not original, some of them being taken from ancient authors, and a
                    still greater number from the <hi rend="italic">Fabliaux</hi> of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Trοu∙ veurs.</hi> Thus, the <hi rend="italic">Fabliau</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">La Culotte</hi><hi rend="italic">des Cordeliers</hi> is the
                        <hi rend="italic">Braccae Divi Francisci</hi> of Poggio; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Meunier dΛleus</hi> is Poggio’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Quinque Ova</hi><hi rend="italic">; Du Vilain et de sa Femme</hi> is his
                        <hi rend="italic">Mulier Demersa;</hi><hi rend="italic">and Du Pre</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Tondu</hi> is the <hi rend="italic">Pertinacia Muliebris</hi>
                    of the <hi rend="italic">Facetiae.</hi> On the other hand, Poggio has suggested
                    much to succeeding writers. Hans Carvel’s <hi rend="italic">Bing</hi> is his <hi
                        rend="italic">Visio</hi><hi rend="italic">Francisci Filelfi</hi><hi
                        rend="italic smallcaps"> ĵ</hi> and Fontaine’s fables, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Le</hi><hi rend="italic">Charlatan,</hi><hi rend="italic">Le Coq et le
                        Renard,</hi> and that of the <hi rend="italic">ĩVolf and Fox pleading before
                        the Ape,</hi> are from stories originally related by Poggio. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Facetiae</hi> forms, upon the whole, the most amusing and
                    interesting part of the Į <hi rend="italic">Poggiaηa</hi> printed at Amsterdam
                    in 1720; but this collec-Poggι a. tion also comprehends some further anecdotes
                    of his life, and a few scattered maxims extracted from his graver
                    compositions.</p>
                <p part="N">Though Poggio was the first person whose remarks and <hi rend="italic"
                        >bon-mots</hi> were collected under the name of Ana, the ŵo- <hi
                        rend="superscript"> 1</hi><hi rend="italic">ligerana,</hi> which contains
                    the opinions of Joseph Scaliger, was the first work <hi rend="italic"
                        >published</hi> under that appellation; and, accordingly, may be regarded as
                    having led the way to that class of publications.</p>
                <p part="N">There are two collections called Scaligerana—a <hi rend="italic"
                        >ρrirnα</hi> Scali; and <hi rend="italic">secunda</hi> Scaligerana. The
                    first was compiled bya <hi rend="superscript"> ana</hi> ∙ physician named
                    Francis Vertun ien, Sieur de Lavau, who attended the family of the Messieurs
                    Chateigner, in whose house Joseph Scaliger resided. He, in consequence, had
                    frequent opportunities of meeting that celebrated critic, and was in the custom
                    of committing to paper the learned or ingenious observations which dropped from
                    him in the course of conversation; to which he occasionally added remarks of his
                    own. This collection, which was chiefly Latin, remained in manuscript many years
                    after the death of the compiler. It was at length purchased by Μ. de Sigogne,
                    who published it in 1669, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Prima</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">Scaligerana,</hi><hi rend="italic">nusquam antehac edita;</hi>
                    bestowing upon it the title <hi rend="italic">prima,</hi> in order to preserve
                    its claim of priority over another Scaligerana which had been published three
                    years before, but had been more recently compiled. This second work, known by
                    the name of <hi rend="italic">Secunda</hi><hi rend="italic">Scaligerana,</hi>
                    was collected by two brothers of the name of Vassau, who went to complete their
                    studies at the university of Ley den, of which Scaliger was at that time one of
                    the professors. Being particularly recommended to Scaliger, they were received
                    in his house, and daily enjoyed his conversation; in the course of which, he
                    gave them much information concerning various topics of history and criticism.
                    The Vassans immediately wrote down what they had heard, and soon made up a large
                    manuscript volume, in which, however, there was neither connection nor
                    arrangement of any description. In this state the manuscript was delivered by
                    one of the Vassans, on his retirement to a monastery, to Μ. de Puy; and after
                    passing through various hands, it came into the possession of Μ. Daillé, who for
                    his own use arranged in alphabetical order the articles which it con-taineđ<pb
                        break="no" facs="nls:193038584?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-8584-0675"
                    />. Isaac Vossius having come to Paris on a visit to Μ. 'DaiΠe, obtained the
                    loan of the manuscript, which he transcribed, and afterwards published at the
                    Hague, under the title of <hi rend="italic">Scaligerana,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >sive Excerpta</hi><hi rend="italic">ex ore Josephi Scαligeri.</hi> This
                    edition was full of inaccuracies and blunders; but a more correct impression was
                    afterwards published by Μ. Daillé, with a preface complaining of the use that
                    Vossius had made of the manuscript, which he declares was never intended for
                    publication, and was not of a nature to be given to the world. Indeed most
                    literary men in that age conceived that the <hi rend="italic">Scaligerana,</hi>
                    particularly the <hi rend="italic">second,</hi> detracted considerably from the
                    reputation of the great scholar whose sentiments they recorded. They are full of
                    mistakes and contradictions; and Baylė has remarked, that the Vassans attribute
                    to him observations which it is almost impossible he could have uttered. Joseph
                    Scaliger, with more extensive erudition, but less genius than his father Julius
                    Caesar Scaliger, had inherited his ridiculous vanity and dogmatical spirit. He
                    wished it to be thought that he knew every thing, and that his opinions were
                    infallible. Conversing with two young students of a university, of which he
                    formed the principal ornament, he would probably be but little cautious in the
                    opinions he expressed, as his literary errors could not be detected or exposed.
                    Unfortunately the blind admiration of his pupils led them to regard even his
                    most absurd opinions as the responses of an oracle, and his most unmerited
                    censures as just condemnations. The <hi rend="italic">Scaligerana,</hi>
                    accordingly, contains many falsehoods, with much unworthy personal abuse, of the
                    most distinguished characters of the age. Thus, he calls Cardinal Bellarmin a
                    mere atheist <hi rend="italic">{plane atheus),</hi> and compares the duke of
                    Sully to Sejanus. Indeed Μ. Daillé, in his preface to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Secunda</hi><hi rend="italic">Scaligerana,</hi> confesses that it contains
                    “multa futilia, scurrilia, obscoena; quaedam manifeste falsa. Ubique de se
                    suisque magnifice, ne dicam thrasonice, loquitur; laudum parcus, conviciorum
                    largus, in omnes contumeliosissime invehitur: denique, neminem sibi de manibus
                    elabi patitur,, cujus non errata, vitia, nae-vos etiam levissimos, acerrime
                    insectetur, et plusquam cynica licentia arrodat.”</p>
                <p part="N">In imitation of the <hi rend="italic">Scaligerana,</hi> a prodigious
                    number of similar works appeared in France towards the end cf the seventeenth
                    and beginning of the eighteenth century. At first these collections were
                    confined to what had fallen from eminent men in conversation; but they were
                    afterwards made to embrace fragments found among their papers, and even passages
                    extracted from their works and epistolary correspondence. Of those which merely
                    record the conversations of eminent men, the best known, the fullest, and most
                    valuable, is the <hi rend="italic">Meηαgiana.</hi> Menage was a person of good
                    sense, of various and extensive information, and of a most communicative
                    disposition. He lived during the greater part of his life in the best society.
                    An assembly of literary characters met, during a long period of time, at his
                    house every Wednesday; and, during his latter years, he daily received persons
                    of that description. Much of his time was thus spent in conversation; and those
                    of his friends who habitually enjoyed it were at pains to record his opinions,
                    which were generally founded on a correct taste and judgment, and were always
                    delivered in a manner the most interesting and lively. A collection of his oral
                    opinions was published in 1693, soon after his death; and this collection, which
                    was entitled <hi rend="italic">Meηagiaηa,</hi> was afterwards corrected and
                    enlarged by Μ. la Monnoye, in an edition published by him in 1715. Among the
                    most curious articles in the <hi rend="italic">Menagiana</hi> may be numbered
                    the dissertation on <hi rend="italic">Le Moyen de Parvenir,</hi> a work
                    attributed to Beroalde de Verreville; that on <hi rend="italic">Le Songe de
                        Poliphile;</hi> as also a letter of La Monnoye on the existence of a book
                    supposed to have been entitled <hi rend="italic">De</hi><hi rend="italic">Tribus
                        Impostoribus,</hi> concerning which there has been much discussion and
                    controversy.</p>
                <p part="N">The <hi rend="italic">Pcτroniana,</hi> which exhibits the opinions of
                    Cardinal Perron, was composed from his familiar conversation by Μ. de Puy, and
                    published by Vossius, by the same contrivance which put him in possession of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Scaligerana.</hi> Some parts of this collection are useful
                    in illustrating the literary and ecclesiastical history of the age in which
                    Perron lived; but it also contains many puerile, imprudent, and absurd remarks,
                    which it is generally supposed he never uttered, and many of which were proved
                    by Μ. Chevreau (<hi rend="italic">Chevroeana)</hi> to have been the
                    interpolations of his friends. Some of his assertions,—as that Luther denied the
                    immortality of the soul, and that every English peasant drinks from a silver
                    goblet,—are evidently false. Nor can much reliance be placed on the judgment or
                    taste of an author who has elsewhere declared that a page of Quintus Curtius is
                    worth thirty of Tacitus, and that, next to Quintus Curtius, Florus is the
                    greatest Roman historian. The <hi rend="italic">Thuana,</hi> or observations of
                    the president De Thou, have usually been published along with the <hi
                        rend="italic">Perroηiana.</hi> This collection is not extensive, and by no
                    means of such value as might have been expected from a man so able and
                    distinguished.</p>
                <p part="N">The <hi rend="italic">Valcsiana</hi> is a collection of the literary
                    opinions of the historiographer Adrian Valois, published by his son. Μ. Valois
                    was a great student of history, and the <hi rend="italic">Valesi-ana,</hi>
                    accordingly, comprehends many valuable historical observations, particularly on
                    the works of Du Cange.</p>
                <p part="N">The <hi rend="italic">Eureteriana</hi> contains the <hi rend="italic"
                        >bon-mots</hi> of Μ. Furetiere, of the French academy, the stories which he
                    was in the habit of telling, and a number of anecdotes and remarks found among
                    his papers after his decease. This production, however, consists chiefly of
                    short stories, and comprehends but few thoughts, opinions, or criticisms on
                    books. Furctiere, it is well known, had a violent quarrel with the French
                    Academy, of which he was a member, concerning his <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire
                        Universel de la Langue Françoise.</hi> Having published a preliminary
                    discourse, the further printing was interdicted by the French Academy, which
                    accused him of purloining materials they had amassed for a similar work. This
                    controversy subsisted during the rest of the life of Furctiere, who spent his
                    concluding years in writing and publishing libels on his associates. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Eureteriana,</hi> accordingly, is replete with allusions to a
                    subject with which his thoughts were so completely engrossed: in particular we
                    find there the plan and outline of an allegorical and burlesque poem, entitled
                        <hi rend="italic">Les Couches de l'Academic</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> in
                    which he has satirized different members of the academy, especially Μ.
                    Charpentier, one of his bitterest foes, whom he has designated by the name of
                        <hi rend="italic">Marmentier.</hi></p>
                <p part="N">The <hi rend="italic">Chevraeana,</hi> so called from Μ. Chevreau,
                    exhibits more research than most works of a similar description, and is probably
                    more accurate, as it was published during the life of the author, and revised by
                    himself. Among other interesting articles, it contains a learned and ingenious
                    commentary on the works of Malherbe, to whom the French language and poetry were
                    highly indebted for the perfection to which they attained.</p>
                <p part="N"><hi rend="italic">Parrhasiana</hi> is the work of Jean le Clerc, a
                    professor of Amsterdam, who bestowed this appellation on his miscellaneous
                    productions with the view of discussing various topics of philosophy and
                    politics with more freedom than he could have employed under his own name. This
                    work is not of the light and unconnected description of <pb break="no"
                        facs="nls:193038597?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0702-8597-0676"/>most of the
                    Ana whieh have been above enumerated, as it contains much learned philological
                    disquisition, and a long dissertation on poetry and eloquence. In the first
                    volume there is a list of his published works, and a bitter reply to all those
                    who had censured them.</p>
                <p part="N">The <hi rend="italic">Huetiana,</hi> whieh has always held a
                    distinguished plaee among the Ana, contains the detached thoughts and criticisms
                    of Huet, bishop of Avranches, whieh he himself committed to writing during his
                    life. This author was well fitted to produce a valuable work in this department
                    of literature. He enjoyed the friendship of a number of distinguished
                    characters, and his reading was various and extensive. This collection, however,
                    was not begun by him till he was far advanced in life. Huet was born in 1630,
                    and in 1712 he was attacked by a malady which impaired his memory, and rendered
                    him incapable of the sustained attention necessary for the completion of a long
                    or laborious work. In this situation he employed himself during the concluding
                    years of his life in throwing his detached observations on paper. These were
                    published by the Abbé d’Olivet the year after his death, under the name of <hi
                        rend="italic">Huetiana,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> a work which is not,
                    like some other Ana, a succession of <hi rend="italic">bon-mots</hi> or
                    anecdotes, but forms a series of thoughts and criticisms on various topies of
                    morals, philosophy, and literature, and also comprehends pretty long
                    dissertations on the origin of rhyme, the comparative merit of the ancients and
                    moderns, with similar topics. One of the most instructive discussions to a
                    scholar, in this collection, is that on the Latinization of names and surnames;
                    in whieh he points out and criticises the different modes of this process. His
                    eritieal judgments on Montaigne, Rochefoucauld, and Taeitus, seem also well
                    founded; and if some of his opinions in matters of taste betray singular or
                    defective feelings, there are others whieh appear equally just and refined. But
                    were there no other literary memorials of the bishop of Avranehes, he certainly
                    would not derive high reputation from the <hi rend="italic">Huetiana.</hi>
                    D’Alembert has treated this collection with contempt; and has selected some
                    articles to show the bishop’s incompetent judgment and frivolous taste. It may
                    be suspected, indeed, from the circumstances in which the articles contained in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Huetiana</hi> were composed, that they do not always
                    display that correct judgment which distinguishes many of the other works of
                    this learned writer.</p>
                <p part="N">The <hi rend="italic">Casauboniana</hi> presents us with the
                    miscellaneous observations, chiefly philological, of the celebrated Isaac
                    Casaubon. During the eourse of a long life, that eminent commentator was in the
                    daily practice of committing to paper any thing remarkable which he heard in
                    conversation with his friends, especially if it bore on the studies in which he
                    was engaged. He also made diurnal annotations on the works he was employed in
                    reading, with which he connected his judgments concerning the author and his
                    writings. This compilation, whieh was styled <hi rend="italic">Ephemerides,</hi>
                    together with his <hi rend="italic">Adversaria,</hi> and materials amassed for a
                    refutation of the <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical Annals of Earonius,</hi>
                    came, at his death, into the possession of his son Merie Casaubon, who
                    bequeathed the whole to the Bodleian library at Oxford. These were shown to
                    Christopher Wolfius during a visit whieh he paid to that university; and having
                    been transcribed by him, were published under the title of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Casauboniana.</hi> This collection consists of opinions concerning various
                    eminent writers, illustrations of passages in Scripture, and philological
                    observations and animadversions on the first thirty-four years of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Annals of Baronius.</hi> The materials and information which
                    it contains are probably more accurate than is usually the case in works of the
                    same description, as they were not communicatëd in Casual conversation, and
                    reported by others, but were daily committed to writing by Casaubon himself,
                    while the works from which they were derived remained fresh in his
                    recollection.</p>
                <p part="N">Besides the above, a great many works, under the title of Ana, appeared
                    in Franee about the same period. Thus, the opinions and conversation of
                    Charpentier, Colomesius, and St Evremond, were recorded in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Carpeηteriαηα, Colomesiana,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">St
                        Evremoniana</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and those of Segrais in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Segraisiana,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> a collection formed
                    by a person stationed behind the tapestry in a house where Segrais was
                    accustomed to visit, and of which Voltaire has declared, “que de tous les Ana
                    e’est eelui qui merite le plus d’être mis au rang des mensonges imprimés, et
                    surtout des mensonges insipides.” The Ana, indeed, from the popularity which
                    they now enjoyed, were compiled in sueh numbers, and with so little care, that
                    they beeanιe almost proverbial for inaeeuraey. About the middle of the
                    eighteenth century they were sometimes made the vehicles of political squibs, as
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Maupeouana,</hi> and of heretical opinions, as in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Longueruana.</hi> Thus the evil naturally began to eure
                    itself, and by a re-action, which is very general in regard to all productions
                    of literature, the Freneh Ana sunk in publie esteem as much below their
                    intrinsic value as they had formerly been exalted above it.</p>
                <p part="N">Although these conectĩons have been ehiefly formed from the oral
                    opinions of eminent men on the Continent, particularly in France, England has
                    also produced one or two examples of this species of composition, whieh are not
                    altogether undeserving of attention. Of these, perhaps the most eurious is the
                        <hi rend="italic">Walpolianα,</hi> which is a transcript of the literary
                    conversation of Horace Walpole. That multifarious author was distinguished for
                    his resources of aneedote, wit, and judicious remark, as well as for his
                    epistolary qualifications. From his father, Sir Robert Walpole, he had learned
                    many anecdotes concerning the political characters who figured during the period
                    of his administration. He was himself personally acquainted with all the eminent
                    literary characters of his own day in England; and his repeated visits to Paris,
                    and constant correspondence with friends in that capital, supplied him with the
                    most interesting information with regard to Franee. A great part of his life was
                    devoted to conversation. While residing at Strawberry-hill, he generally rose
                    from table about five o’clock, and taking his place on his drawing-room sofa, to
                    which his gout in a great measure confined him, he passed the time, till two
                    o’clock in the morning, in miscellaneous chit-ehat, full of singular anecdotes,
                    strokes of wit, and aeute observations. As he possessed, and was daily
                    eommunieating, such stores of instruction and amusement, it was suggested to him
                    that he ought to form a collection of these anecdotes and observations. This he
                    declined, but he furnished the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Walpoliana</hi>
                    with many anecdotes in his own handr writing. After his death, several specimens
                    of this miscellany were published in the <hi rend="italic">Monthly
                        Magazine·,</hi> and being afterwards enlarged by anecdotes retained in the
                    memory of the editor, or communicated by others, were published in two volumes,
                    under the title of <hi rend="italic">Wαlροliαnα,</hi> Most other works which, in
                    this country, have been published under the name of <hi rend="italic">Ana,</hi>
                    as <hi rend="italic">Eaconiana, Atterbury-ana,</hi> are rather extracts from the
                    writings and correspondence of eminent men, than memorials of their
                    conversation.</p>
                <p part="N">There are some works whieh, though they do not bear the title, belong
                    more strictly to the elass of Ana than many of those eolleetions which are known
                    under that appellation. Such are the <hi rend="italic">Mélange</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">d’</hi><hi rend="italic">Histoire et</hi><hi rend="italic">de
                        Littcrαr</hi><pb break="no" facs="nls:193038610?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0702-8610-0677"/><hi rend="italic">ture,</hi> published under
                    the name of <hi rend="italic">Vigneul Marυille</hi><hi rend="italic">;</hi> and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Locorum Communium Collectanea,</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >ex</hi><hi rend="italic">Lectionibus</hi><hi rend="italic">Philippi
                        Melanchthonis,</hi><hi rend="italic">—</hi> a work which was published as
                    far back as the sixteenth century, and has. obtained considerable reputation on
                    account of its theological learning, and the information it communicates
                    concerning the early state of the reformed church. But of those productions
                    which belong to the class, though they do not bear the name, of Ana, the most
                    celebrated are the <hi rend="italic">Colloquia Mensalia</hi> of Luther, and
                    Selden’s <hi rend="italic">Table-Talk,</hi> both of which merit particular
                    notice. The first, which comprehends the conversation of Luther with his friends
                    and coadjutors in the great work of the Reformation, was first published in
                    1566. Captain Henry Bell, who translated it into English in the time of the
                    Commonwealth, informs us that, at the instigation of the pope, the emperor of
                    Germany had promulgated an edict commanding the works of Luther to be destroyed.
                    It was for some time supposed that all the copies of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Colloquia Mensalia</hi> had been burned in consequence of this order; but
                    at length, in 1626, a German called Van Sparr, having occasion to build on the
                    old foundation of a house in which his grandfather dwelt when the imperial edict
                    was issued, he found lying in a deep hole, and wrapped up in a linen cloth, a
                    printed copy of the <hi rend="italic">Colloquia Mensalia.</hi> Captain Bell
                    having formerly become acquainted with Van Sparr during a long residence in
                    Germany, his friend transmitted the work to him in England, where he executed a
                    translation of it; an undertaking to which he pretends that he was urged by the
                    vision of an old man with a long white beard, arrayed in white, who spoke these
                    words: “Sirrah, will you not take time to translate that book ?” The
                    -extraordinary book translated by Bell, at the instance of this vision, is said
                    to have been originally collected by Dr Anthony Lauterbach, “out of the holy
                    mouth of Luther ;” and was afterwards digested into common-places by Dr John
                    Aurifaber. It chiefly contains observations and discussions on idolatry,
                    auricular confession, mass, excommunication, clerical jurisdiction, general
                    councils, and all the points agitated by the reformed church in those early
                    periods. With such topics there is intermixed many diatribes against Antichrist
                    and the Cardinals, and much sarcasm on popish miracles and relics. Occasionally,
                    however, it must be confessed that our great reformer expresses a belief in
                    superstitions fully as wild and monstrous as those which he derides, and which
                    he was called to overthrow. Thus, he asserted that he was repeatedly kept from
                    sleep by the devil cracking nuts in his chamber; and he affirmed that there was
                    a child at Dessau, which had been substituted by the arch-fiend instead of one
                    he had stolen away, and which child Luther earnestly advised the prince of
                    Anhalt to throw into the river Moldaw.</p>
                <p part="N">If the collection of Selden’s apophthegms and sayings, entitled <hi
                        rend="italic">Table-Talk,</hi> be regarded of good authority, we shall find
                    in it a more genuine and undisguised expression of the sentiments of that
                    eminent man, than in his more studied productions. This work was published,
                    after the death of Selden, by Richard Milward, his amanuensis, who, in his
                    dedication to Selden’s executors, affirms that, for twenty years, he enjoyed the
                    opportunity of daily hearing his discourse, during which long period he made it
                    his practice, from time to time, faithfully to commit to writing “the excellent
                    things that usually fell from him.” Dr Wilkins, in his introductory discourse to
                    the Works of Selden, has attempted to throw discredit on the genuineness of this
                    compilation, asserting that it contains many things derogatory from Selden’s
                    erudition, and foreign from his manners and principles. It is not improbable,
                    indeed, that the memory of the amanuensis may have occasionally failed him, and
                    that he may have recorded sayings which inadvertently escaped his master in the
                    heat of conversation, and such as he probably would not have deliberately
                    maintained. But, on the whole, the work has completely an air of genuineness;
                    and although the familiarity of his illustrations and parallels may appear to
                    clash with the idea formed of so great a scholar, they are characteristic of a
                    man who had been conversant with scenes of common life, no less than the
                    speculations of the closet. That such was the usual manner of Selden’s
                    conversation, the editor of the <hi rend="italic">Table-Talk</hi> recalls to the
                    recollection of those friends of his patron to whom the work is dedicated; and
                    this appeal forms a presumption of his veracity. The <hi rend="italic"
                        >Table-Talk</hi> contains many curious facts and opinions concerning the
                    political and ecclesiastical history of the interesting period during which
                    Selden lived, and in the important events of which he bore a considerable share.
                    To judge from this work, Selden had great contempt for the theologians of his
                    day; and seems to have been of opinion that the state should invariably keep a
                    rein on the church. He was partial to the Episcopal form of worship; but was
                    evidently not very strict in doctrinal points, as appears from what he is
                    reported to have said on the subject of <hi rend="italic">heresy.</hi> In his
                    political opinions he seems to have entertained a high respect for the
                    sacredness of the social contract; and he justified the resistance to the
                    Stewarts, on the ground that they had infringed and violated this compact
                    between prince and people. Besides religious and political opinions, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Table-Talk</hi> contains much of a lighter description; in
                    consequence of which, Selden has been accused of showing more laxness, in point
                    of moral principle, than might have been expected from so grave and respectable
                    a character. Many of those sentiments, however, which have been considered
                    objectionable, may have been merely advanced as plausible deductions from
                    principles assumed for the sake of argument. But whatever difference of opinion
                    may exist with regard to the matter of the <hi rend="italic">Table-Talk,</hi>
                    the manner in which the sentiments are there expressed must be universally
                    admitted to be perspicuous and agreeable. The style of Selden, in most of the
                    works published under his own care, is harsh and obscure; but Clarendon, who
                    differed from him so widely in political opinions, acknowledges that he was “a
                    clear discourser, and that he possessed the faculty of making difficult things
                    easy, and presenting them clearly to the understanding.” Accordingly, this
                    talent for elucidation shines chiefly in his <hi rend="italic">Table-Talk,</hi>
                    which is filled with the stores of his extensive reading, delivered without any
                    pretensions to that order and method, the want of which has been attributed to
                    his other productions.</p>
                <p part="N">It thus appears that, although the compilations designated by the name
                    of Ana belong more particularly to France, they have not been wholly unknown in
                    this country. In their <hi rend="italic">Motti e Burle,</hi> and sometimes in
                    their novels, the Italians also have recorded the witticisms of their
                    distinguished poets and artists. The novels of Sacchetti are full of repartees
                    attributed to Dante and the painters Giotto and Buffalmacco. Almost every
                    Italian biographical work of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, like
                    Boswell’s <hi rend="italic">Life of Johnson,</hi> records at great length the
                    conversational remarks of the individual whose life is detailed. Thus, Manso has
                    dedicated one of the books of his life of Torquato Tasso to an account of the
                    wise and witty sayings of that illustrious poet, who, towards the close of his
                    days, had become the intimate friend of his biographer. The conversation of the
                    poet, however, was neither gay nor brilliant. One of the characters in
                        Goldoni<pb break="no" facs="nls:193038623?mode=fullsize"
                        xml:id="kp-eb0702-8623-0678"/>’s drama of Torquato Tasso thus contrasts his
                    writings and conversation:</p>
                <lg part="N">
                    <l part="N"> Ammiro il suo talento, gradisco i carmi suoi; </l>
                    <l part="N"> Ma piacer non trovo a conversar con lui. </l>
                </lg>
                <p part="N">It also unfortunately happens that the greater part of the sayings
                    recorded by Manso may be found in the Apophthegms of Erasmus, which were
                    published before the birth of Tasso. Indeed Manso seems to have been aware of
                    the want of originality in the <hi rend="italic">bon-mots</hi> of his friend;
                    for, after mentioning one, he says, “questo motto fu da alcuni ad <hi
                        rend="italic">Epiteto</hi> attribuito.” It was usual, indeed, among the
                    biographers of those times to pillage Xenophon or Plutarch for good things to
                    put into the mouths of their heroes; a practice from which Machiavel could not
                    abstain in his short account of the illiterate soldier Cas-truccio Castracani.
                    In those ages of pedantry, however, it is not improbable that many sayings of
                    the old philosophers might have been repeated as their own by the learned men of
                    the times; and that the Italian <hi rend="italic">literati</hi> might
                    occasionally attempt to make their hearers merry with the jests of Socrates or
                    Diogenes. The genius and character of the people rendered any collection of this
                    nature less agreeable than the Ana of the neighbouring nation. In Italy, gravity
                    was numbered among the virtues, and, in the eulogy of an illustrious man, is
                    always mentioned as one of his most commendable qualities. There seems, in that
                    country, to have been no medium between the most fantastic buffoonery and a
                    certain tragic solemnity. The Italians wanted that “mobility of imagination,”
                    that facility, rapidity, abandonment, and gaiety, which seems almost peculiar to
                    the French, and forms the chief charm of social intercourse, as well as of those
                    works in which it is represented; though, no doubt, when reduced into writing,
                    much of its grace and spirit must evaporate and disappear.</p>
                <p part="N">The existence of similar causes, and perhaps in a stronger degree,
                    prevented the popularity of Ana among the Spaniards; though they too have
                    related the jests and opinions of the duke d’Ossuna, and of some others. Indeed,
                    whatever may be the genius or disposition of a people, traces of this mode of
                    composition may in some shape or other be discovered among them.</p>
                <p part="N">When presented in their most perfect form, which is that of the French
                    Ana, these collections are certainly entertaining from their variety, and
                    curious, as presenting a lively image of the distinguished 'characters whose
                    sentiments they record. If men reason more correctly on paper, they usually
                    display their feelings and convictions with more truth in unpremeditated
                    conversation. Few are so cautious or hypocritical that they do not sometimes
                    drop the mask in the society of their friends, and express what they think or
                    feel, when they no longer entertain apprehensions that their sentiments will be
                    communicated to the vulgar. In general, however, the Ana should rather be
                    regarded as affording a notion of the spirit and turn of thinking of those whose
                    conversation they detail, than as authorities for particular opinions. A spirit
                    of contradiction, a wish to display ingenuity, to astonish by paradoxes, or even
                    to support conversation, may often lead men to maintain opinions in colloquial
                    intercourse which they perhaps never seriously held, or at least would be ready
                    to disclaim on mature consideration. It also unfortunately happens that, in many
                    of the Ana, those who collected the conversations which they presented to the
                    world interpolated their own opinions; which, of course, greatly diminishes
                    their authority as characteristical records. It has also been objected to this
                    species of composition, that every subject is treated superficially; but it
                    should be recollected that the Ana do not profess to contain profound
                    dissertations; and in fact no one consults them with the view of being deeply
                    informed on any topic. A better founded objection is, that many subjects are
                    treated, not merely superficially, but inaccurately. Such compositions are
                    liable to a double risk of error; first, of the person who delivers opinions in
                    the heat of discourse, or relates anecdotes from vague recollection; and,
                    secondly, of the person who records them, who must be liable to mistake what he
                    has only heard in the course of conversation. From these causes, and from their
                    wide and general circulation, many of the most current literary errors may be
                    traced to the Ana. When read, however, with discrimination, they may prove
                    highly useful in illustrating various points of literary history, as they
                    certainly contain a great deal which is not to be found in the formal
                    compositions of the learned.</p>
                <p part="N">Wolfius has given a histbry of the <hi rend="smallcaps">Ana</hi> in a
                    preliminary discourse to his edition of the <hi rend="italic">Casaubσniana,</hi>
                    published in 1710. In the <hi rend="italic">Repertoire de Bibliographies
                        Speciales,</hi><hi rend="italic">Curieuses, et Instructives,</hi> by
                    Peignot, there is a <hi rend="italic">Notice</hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >Bibliographique</hi> of these collections; but many of the books there
                    enumerated consist of mere extracts from the writings of popular authors, and do
                    not, therefore, belong to that class of literary works described in the
                    preceding article. <hi rend="smallcaps">(q.)</hi></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
