<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-9023-0166-01" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v3.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NEW HAVEN</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable
                    transcription</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">7th edition, volume 16, page 166</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="3.0">Version 3.0<date when="2024">2024</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>464 MB; 21,116 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2024">2024</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol">21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <ab><list rend="bulleted" type="basic">
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the "TEI
                        in Libraries Guidelines."</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Print page headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>OCR successfully reproduced simple tables, but complex tabular data is not
                        captured dependably and the results should not be relied upon.</item>
                    <item>OCR was not able to successfully reproduce math and chemical formulas. The
                        uncorrected results remain in the text.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: <val>italic</val>,
                        <val>smallcaps</val>, <val>strikethrough</val>, <val>subscript</val>,
                        <val>superscript</val>, <val>underline</val>. The following print styles are
                        ignored: bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        Some OCR errors have been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        indicated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                    <p>Some volumes of the print edition substituted "c" for "e" letters across
                        multiple pages. These are silently corrected.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                    <p>Ordinal numbers, such as 1st, 2ndly, etc., are inconsistently italicized in
                        the printed text; they are normalized as roman throughout.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are silently removed.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections, but their inclusion is largely
                        aspirational.</p>
                </segmentation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered <gi>div</gi> tags are used throughout.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze using
                    machine-learning methods.</p>
                <p>Subject keywords are added to <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each entry; they were
                    generated by the HIVE2 automated vocabulary server, created by the Metadata
                    Research Center at Drexel University (<link
                    target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>This release reproduces the text matter for all entries. It does not include
                    images, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1, which consists of
                    "Dissertations" rather than entries. The reproduction of tables and formulae is
                    unreliable. </p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fastgeo" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fastgeo:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Geographical subject heading
                        schema derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fasttopic" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fasttopic:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) Topical subject heading schema
                        derived from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues of the
                        Library of Congress</hi>, 2 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:1136041">Students</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="fasttopic:852215">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1099409">Rocks</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:931268">Foot</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:1155984">Trees</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="fasttopic:910709">English</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807480">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807485">Americanization</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:807488">Americans</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fasttopic:875214">Congregationalists</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw6r">East</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4hq3s746">Towns</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4sj19s90">Students</term>
                    <term n="3" ref="lcsh1910:b4z892g7x">Chapels</term>
                    <term n="2" ref="lcsh1910:b41j9770v">State</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4vh5ch72">Americanisms</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4mw28p24">Scotch</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="lcsh1910:b4g15t99g">Almanacs</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term n="3" ref="fastgeo:1205688">Connecticut</term>
                    <term n="1" ref="fastgeo:1239786">America</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <listChange>
                <change n="3.0" status="public" when="2024-12-06" who="#pml">v3.0. Includes
                    significant corrections to the OCR text, predominantly in cases of confusing "c"
                    and "e." Isolates 90 entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior
                    entries in v1 and v2. Normalizes ordinal numbers. Separates metadata in
                    <gi>teiHeader</gi> into two separate facets: FAST Topical and FAST Geographical.
                    Moves commas following <gi>pb</gi> in the text to preceding it and removes extra
                    space around the <gi>pb</gi> tag. Where a word is hyphenated at a <gi>pb</gi>,
                    the end fragment is now joined to the start fragment, making a machine-readable
                    word.</change>
                <change n="2.0" status="public" when="2023-10-11" who="#pml">v2.0. Isolates 42
                    entries that were mistakenly included at the end of prior entries in v1. Removes
                    <att>xml:id</att> from the <gi>div</gi> for the entry and adds it to the
                    <gi>TEI</gi> tag. Adds schema link to all files.</change>
                <change n="1.0" status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v1.0. Initial
                    release.</change>
            </listChange>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194559023" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NEW HAVEN</label>, a city of Connecticut, one of the United
                    States of North America. It lies round the head of a bay, which stretches
                    inwards about four miles from Long Island Sound, seventy-six miles north-east
                    from New York, and stands on a large and beautiful plain, which is bordered on
                    the north partly by eminences called East and West Rock, presenting bold and
                    almost perpendicular columns of bare trap rock from three to four hundred feet
                    in height. Upon the eastern and western sides the city is skirted by small
                    rivers, and extends from east to west three miles, being about two miles in
                    width. It is regularly laid out, and consists of two parts, the old and the new
                    town. The former was originally laid out in one large square, and is divided
                    into several smaller squares. The central square is intersected by a very fine
                    street, in which three handsome churches have been erected; and it also contains
                    a new state-house, built after the model of the Parthenon, and ranking with the
                    best American buildings. The public square and the principal streets are
                    ornamented with trees; and a great part of the dwelling-houses have gardens
                    filled with fruit trees, which give to the city a rural and delightful
                    appearance. New Haven contains eight or nine places of public worship,
                    Congregationalists and Episcopalians being the most numerous sects. There is a
                    jail, an almshouse, a custom-house, a museum, two banks, two insurance offices,
                    an institution for popular lectures, and a number of printing offices, from
                    which five or six newspapers and a few other periodicals are issued. Yale
                    College consists of ten buildings; four halls one hundred feet by forty, and
                    four stories in height, containing thirty-two rooms each for students, a chapel,
                    a medical college, a laboratory, and other necessary apartments. According to
                    the American Almanac for 1837, the state of this institution was as
                    follows:—Instructors, twenty-seven; alumni,4485; ministers, 1297; students, 413;
                    volumes in the college libraries, 10,500; and volumes in the students’
                    libraries, 15,000. The philosophical and chemical apparatus are good, and the
                    cabinet of minerals is the most valuable in the United States. In connection
                    with this establishment there are theological, medical, and law schools; and the
                    place is celebrated for the number of its boarding schools, there being seldom
                    fewer than one thousand persons who come hither from abroad for the purpose of
                    education. The harbour of New Haven is well defended from winds, but is shallow,
                    and gradually filling up with mud; an evil which has been remedied in part by
                    the construction of a wharf, about a mile in length, extending into the harbour.
                    The maritime commerce of this city is greater than that of any other place in
                    Connecticut, and it owns a considerable amount of shipping. Both the foreign and
                    the coasting trade are extensive, and packets and steam-boats ply regularly
                    between New Haven and New York. It was first settled by the English in the year
                    1638, and, as the capital of the colony of New Haven, continued distinct from
                    that of Connecticut till the year 1665. The legislature of the state meets
                    alternately here and at Hartford. The population in 1820 amounted to 7147, in
                    1830 to 10,678, and in 1837 to about 13,000. Long. 72. 57. W. Lat. 4L 18. N.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Newhaven,</hi> a town of the county <hi rend="italic"
                    >of</hi> Sussex, and the hundred of Holmstrough, sixty miles distant from
                    London. It stands at the mouth of the river Ouse, and is the port of Lewes,
                    where the custom-house is established. It was formerly a place of more
                    importance than at present; but the harbour has been neglected, and nearly
                    choked up by sand. It is sometimes called Meeching. The population amounted in
                    1801 to 584, in 1811 to 755, in 1821 to 927, and in 1831 to 904.</p>
                <p><hi rend="smallcaps">Newhaven,</hi> an ancient and considerable fishing village,
                    situated on the Frith of Forth, less than two miles north from Edinburgh, and
                    one mile west from Leith. The village is formed by a street running contiguous
                    with the shore, with several back lanes, and in appearance it has nothing to
                    recommend it to attention. It possesses a low-water pier, which affords shelter
                    to the fishing boats of the station, and accommodation to the ferry and other
                    steamers in the taking up and landing of their passengers and goods. A handsome
                    chapel has lately been erected at the west end of the village, and forms a
                    subsidiary place of worship, or chapel of ease, to North Leith church. The
                    inhabitants are a most industrious race, both sexes being busily employed, the
                    men in procuring the fish, and the females in carrying them to the market. The
                    oyster-bank is valuable, and yields fish of excellent quality. Were it turned to
                    its proper account, it would yield a far greater amount of revenue to the
                    proprietors. At the west end of the village there has been erected within these
                    few years a considerable suburb, called Trinity, consisting chiefly of houses
                    built in the villa style, and cottages for sea-bathing quarters. There is a
                    chain-pier here, built by Captain Brown, from which steamers for various
                    quarters hourly depart. A bill passed last session (1836-37) for constructing a
                    harbour here, in order to accommodate the large class of steamers plying between
                    the English and Scotch capitals. At Granton, about a mile farther west, a
                    harbour is considerably advanced for the same purpose. There is no municipal
                    government in Newhaven, the superiors of the place being the town-council of
                    Edinburgh, who purchased it in the year 1511, with all the privileges and rights
                    with which James IV. had endowed it. Along with Leith, Portobello, Musselburgh,
                    and Fisherrow, it returns a member to Parliament.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
