<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-model  href="https://TU-plogan.github.io/code/odd/tei_kp1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xml:id="kp-eb0716-9842-0229-04" xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt xml:id="eb07_v1.0">
                <title level="a" type="main">NIMROD (7th edition, volume 16, page 229)</title>
                <title level="m" type="main">Encyclopaedia Britannica, 7th edition</title>
                <title level="m" type="sub">A machine-readable transcription</title>
                <editor>Edited by <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2362-8282"
                    role="editor" xml:id="pml">Peter Melville Logan</persName></editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <orgName xml:id="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project Staff,
                        <affiliation>Temple University</affiliation></orgName>
                    <resp>OCR transcription and data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName ref="https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7819-5360" xml:id="jg">Jane
                        Greenberg, <affiliation>Metadata Research Center, Drexel
                        University</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>metadata development</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName xml:id="dk">Don Kretz, <affiliation>Distributed
                        Proofreading</affiliation></persName>
                    <resp>data management</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/137796012" xml:id="neh">National
                    Endowment for the Humanities</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/121974598" xml:id="imls">Institute of
                    Museum and Library Services</orgName></funder>
                <funder><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/127396206" xml:id="tu">Temple
                    University</orgName></funder>
                <sponsor><orgName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/3653147665869560670009" xml:id="cci"
                    >Drexel University, College of Computing &amp; Informatics</orgName></sponsor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition n="1.0">Version 1.0, initial release <date when="2022"
                    >2022</date></edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>411 MB; 20,984 XML files </extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher corresp="kp"><orgName corresp="kp">Nineteenth-Century Knowledge
                    Project</orgName><email>nckp@temple.edu</email><link
                    target="https://github.com/TU-plogan/KnowledgeProject"/></publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</p>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"> CC BY 4.0
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <date when="2020">2022</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="s">Encyclopaedia Britannica: A machine-readable text
                    transcription</title>
                <editor corresp="pml">Peter Melville Logan</editor>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull xml:lang="en">
                    <titleStmt>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Britannica</title>
                        <editor><persName ref="http://viaf.org/viaf/79392506" xml:id="mn">Napier,
                            Macvey, 1776-1847</persName></editor>
                    </titleStmt>
                    <editionStmt>
                        <edition>Seventh Edition</edition>
                    </editionStmt>
                    <extent><measure quantity="21" unit="vol"> 21 volumes</measure></extent>
                    <publicationStmt>
                        <publisher>Adam and Charles Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                        <date from="1830" to="1842">1830-1842</date>
                    </publicationStmt>
                    <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl xml:id="NLS"><title>Seventh edition - Encyclopaedia Britannica
                            [190218838]</title><publisher><orgName
                            ref="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/190218838"
                            >National Library of Scotland</orgName></publisher><date when="2019"
                            >2019</date><idno type="DOI">https://doi.org/10.34812/cg4r-dn40</idno><availability>
                            <p>National Library of Scotland License: CC BY 4.0</p>
                            <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC BY 4.0
                            </licence>
                            </availability></bibl>
                    </sourceDesc>
                </biblFull>
                <listBibl>
                    <head>Alternate image sources for this edition:</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UW-HT">Hathi Trust, from print source at the University of
                        Wisconsin: vol. 9, pp. 29, 31, 32, 36, 37, 39, 41, 48, 50-55, 57, 59, 62,
                        63, 66, 67, 69-71, 76, 88; vol. 19 (all).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UCH-HT">Hathi Trust, from print souce at the University of
                        Chicago: vol. 10, pp. 7-10; vols. 20, 21 (all).</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction method="markup" status="low">
                    <p>This electronic text file was created by optical character recognition (OCR).
                        OCR errors have not been corrected.</p>
                    <p>Illegible text in the original is indicated using <gi>unclear</gi> or
                        <gi>gap</gi>, as appropriate. If corrected, the reference source is
                        incidated with <gi>supplied</gi>.</p>
                </correction>
                <normalization method="silent">
                    <p>Original spelling is preserved. When noticed, obvious misspellings are
                        combined with the correct spelling as <gi>choice</gi> in the TEI. Ligatures
                        are reproduced as multiple letters. Original footnote and marginal note
                        sigla are replaced with sequential numbers for each entry.</p>
                </normalization>
                <punctuation marks="some">
                    <p>Extra space around punctuation marks is removed.</p>
                </punctuation>
                <quotation marks="some">
                    <p>Quotation marks are retained as content in the text. Redundant open quotation
                        marks at the start of lines inside block quotes are silently removed.</p>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation eol="hard">
                    <p>Soft hyphens are removed silently.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="entry"</tag> element divides the text into individual
                        entries.</p>
                    <p>The <tag>div type="section"</tag> and <tag>div type="subsection"</tag>
                        elements are reserved for entry subsections.</p>
                </segmentation>
                <ab><list>
                    <item>Encoding has been done using the recommendations for Level 3 of the TEI in
                        Libraries Guidelines.</item>
                    <item>Individual entries and page-breaks are encoded, but column breaks are
                        omitted.</item>
                    <item>Running headers and side descriptions are not included.</item>
                    <item>Some font formatting is preserved: italic, small caps, strike through,
                        subscript, superscript, underline. The following formatting is ignored:
                        bold, font size, typeface.</item>
                    </list></ab>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi="div">Unnumbered divs used.</tagUsage>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>All text was encoded for the Nineteenth-Century Knowledge Project to provide a
                    machine-readable edition of the Encyclopedia Britannica to analyze.</p>
                <p>Subject-level metadata was added to each entry using the HIVE automated
                    vocabulary server created by the Metadata Research Center at Drexel University
                    (<link target="https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu"/>https://hive2.cci.drexel.edu).</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The first release is a reproduction of text matter for all entries. It does not
                    include images, tables, formulae, front- or back-matter. It omits volume 1,
                    which consists of "Dissertations" rather than entries.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
            <listPrefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="fast" matchPattern="(\d+)"
                    replacementPattern="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>fast:</code> point to terms in the OCLC FAST
                        (Faceted Application of Subject Terminology) subject heading schema derived
                        from the Library of Congress Subject Headings (LCSH).</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="lcsh1910" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://n2t.net/ark:/99152/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>lcsh1910:</code> point to subject terms in the
                        volume <hi rend="italic">Subject Headings Used in the Dictionary Catalogues
                        of the Library of Congress</hi>, 7 vols., Library of Congress, 1910.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ht" matchPattern="([\w\-\.;=\&#34;&amp;]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ht:</code> point to page images in the Hathi
                        Trust.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="ia" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://archive.org/details/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>ia:</code> point to page images in the Internet
                        Archive.</p>
                </prefixDef>
                <prefixDef ident="nls" matchPattern="([\w?\=]+)"
                    replacementPattern="https://digital.nls.uk/encyclopaedia-britannica/archive/$1">
                    <p>URIs with the prefix <code>nls:</code> point to page images in the National
                        Library of Scotland.</p>
                </prefixDef>
            </listPrefixDef>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass default="false">
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:964151">Hunters</term>
                    <term ref="fast:1150276">Thoughtfulness</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944037">God</term>
                    <term ref="fast:944223">Gods</term>
                    <term ref="fast:800130">Age</term>
                    <term ref="fast:950737">Ham</term>
                    <term ref="fast:903991">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:819237">Assyrians</term>
                    <term ref="fast:983135">Jews</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="https://id.cci.drexel.edu/">
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4ft8ds25">Ham</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4tt4fw77">Egyptians</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5zh77">Mahommedanism</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4x34mt4n">Jews</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b41v5bf9q">God</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4df6k36b">Earth</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b47m04774">Representation</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4q814s63">Beasts</term>
                    <term ref="lcsh1910:b4qn5z99h">Age</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="http://id.worldcat.org/fast/">
                    <term ref="fast:1208757">Syria</term>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc status="published">
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-30" who="#pml">RNG schema v.1 completed. </change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-28" who="#pml">v.1 XSL finished</change>
            <change status="public" when="2022-11-18" who="#pml">RNG schema draft</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div facs="nls:194559842?mode=fullsize" type="entry">
                <p><label type="entry">NIMROD</label>, the sixth son of Cush, and to all appearance
                    much younger than any of his brothers, since Moses mentions the sons of Raamah,
                    his fourth brother, before he speaks of him. What the sacred historian says of
                    him is short; and yet he says more than of any other of the posterity of Noah,
                    till he comes to Abraham. He tells us that “Nimrod began to be a mighty one in
                    the earth ;” that he was “a mighty hunter before the Lord,” even to a proverb;
                    and that “the beginning of his kingdom was Babel, and Erech, and Accad, and
                    Calneh, in the land of Shinar.”</p>
                <p>From this account Nimrod is supposed to have been a man of extraordinary strength
                    and valour. Some represent him as a giant; all consider him as a great warrior.
                    It is generally thought that by the words “a mighty hunter,” is to be understood
                    that he was a great tyrant; but some of the rabbin interpret these words
                    favourably, thinking that Nimrod was qualified by peculiar dexterity and
                    strength for the chase, and that he offered to God the game which he caught; and
                    several of the moderns are also of opinion that this passage is not to be
                    understood of his tyrannical oppressions, or his hunting of men, but only of
                    beasts. It must be owned that the phrase “before the Lord” may be taken in a
                    favourable sense, and as a commendation of his good qualities; but the
                    generality of expositors and commentators understand it otherwise.</p>
                <p>Hunting must have been one of the most useful employments in the times
                    immediately after the dispersion, when all countries were overrun with wild
                    beasts, of which it was necessary that they should be cleared, to render them
                    habitable; and therefore nothing seemed more proper to procure a man esteem and
                    honour in those ages than his being an expert hunter. By that exercise, we are
                    told, the ancient Persians qualified their kings for war and government; and
                    hunting is still, in many countries, considered as part of a royal
                    education.</p>
                <p>There is nothing in the short history of Nimrod that carries the least air of
                    reproach, excepting his name, which signifies a <hi rend="italic">rebel;</hi>
                    and that is the circumstance wdιich seems to have occasioned the injurious
                    opinions which have been entertained respecting him in all ages. Commentators,
                    being in general prepossessed in favour of the opinion that the curse of Noah
                    fell upon the posterity of Ham, and finding this prince stigmatised by such a
                    name, have interpreted every passage relating to him to his disadvantage<pb
                    break="no" facs="nls:194559855?mode=fullsize" xml:id="kp-eb0716-9855-0230"/>.
                    They represent him as a rebel against God, in persuading the descendants of Noah
                    to disobey the divine command to disperse, and in setting them on to build the
                    tower of Babel, with an impious design of scaling heaven. They brand him as an
                    ambitious usurper and an insolent oppressor, and make him the author of the
                    adoration of fire and idolatrous worship, as well as the first persecutor on the
                    score of religion. On the other hand, some account him a virtuous prince, who,
                    far from advising the building of Babel, left the country, and went into
                    Assyria, because he would not give his consent to that extravagant project.</p>
                <p>Nimrod is generally thought to have been the first king after the Deluge, though
                    some authors, supposing a plantation or dispersion prior to that of Babel, have
                    thought that there were kings in several countries before his time. Mizraim is
                    conceived, by many who contend for the antiquity of the Egyptian monarchy, to
                    have begun his reign much earlier than Nimrod; and others, from the uniformity
                    of the languages which were spoken in Assyria, Babylonia, Syria, and Canaan,
                    affirm that those countries must have been peopled before the confusion of
                    tongues.</p>
                <p>The four cities which Moses gave to Nimrod constituted a large kingdom in those
                    early times, when few kings had more than one; only it must be observed, that
                    possessions might at first have been large, and afterwards divided into several
                    parcels; and Nimrod being the leader of a nation, we may suppose that his
                    subjects were settled within those limits. Whether he became possessed of those
                    cities by conquest or otherwise, does not appear. It is most probable he did not
                    build Babel, all the posterity of Noah seeming to have been equally concerned in
                    that affair; nor does it appear that he built the other three cities, although
                    the founding of them, and many more, besides other works, are attributed to him
                    by some authors. It may also seem a little strange that Nimrod should have been
                    preferred to the regal dignity, and enjoyed the most cultivated part of the
                    earth then known, rather than any other of the elder chiefs or heads of nations,
                    even of the branch of Ham. Perhaps it was conferred on him for his dexterity in
                    hunting, or it may be that he did not assume the title of king till after the
                    death of his father Cush, who might have been settled there before him, and left
                    him the sovereignty; but we incline to think that he seized Shinarfrom the
                    descendants of Shem, driving out Ashur, who went from thence and founded
                    Nineveh, and other cities in Assyria.</p>
                <p>The Scripture does not inform us when Nimrod began his reign. Some date it before
                    the dispersion; but such a conjecture does not seem to suit with the Mosaical
                    history; for before the dispersion we read of no city but Babel, nor could there
                    well be more whilst all mankind were yet in a body together. But when Nimrod
                    assumed the regal title there seems to have been other cities, and this shows
                    that he must have done so a considerable time after the dispersion. The learned
                    writers of the Universal History place the beginning of his reign thirty years
                    after that event, and in all likelihood it should be placed rather later than
                    earlier.</p>
                <p>Authors have taken a great deal of trouble to find Nimrod in profane history.
                    Some have imagined him to be the same with Belus, the founder of the Babylonian
                    empire; and others take him to be Ninus, the first Assyrian monarch. Some
                    believe him to have been Evechous, the first Chaldaean king after the Deluge;
                    and others perceive a great resemblance between him and Bacchus, both in actions
                    and in name. Some of the Mahommedan writers suppose Nimrod to have been
                    identical with Zohak, a Persian king of the first dynasty; whilst others contend
                    for his being Kay Kaus, the second king of the second race; and some of the Jews
                    say that he is the same with Amraphel, the king of Shinar, mentioned by Moses.
                    But there is no certainty in these conjectures, nor have we any knowledge of his
                    immediate successors.</p>
                <p>The Scripture mentions nothing respecting the death of Nimrod. Some of the rabbin
                    pretend that he was slain by Esau, whom they make his contemporary. There is a
                    tradition that he was killed by the fall of the tower of Babel, when that
                    structure was overthrown by tempestuous winds. But others say, that when he led
                    an army against Abraham, God sent a squadron of gnats, which destroyed most of
                    them, and particularly Nimrod, whose brain was pierced by one of those
                    insects.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
